<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="9266">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 09, 2023</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT05701709</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>SHR-A2102-I-102</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT05701709</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Phase I Study of SHR-A2102 in Patients With Advanced Solid Tumors</brief_title>
  <official_title>An Open-Label, Single-Arm, Multi-Center Phase I Clinical Study to Evaluate the Safety, Tolerability, Efficacy and Pharmacokinetics of SHR-A2102 in Patients With Advanced Solid Tumors</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Shanghai Hengrui Pharmaceutical Co., Ltd.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Shanghai Hengrui Pharmaceutical Co., Ltd.</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The study was designed to evaluate the efficacy, safety, and pharmacokinetics of SHR2102 in&#xD;
      patients with advanced solid tumors. The objective of this study was to determine the&#xD;
      dose-limiting toxicity, maximum tolerance and recommended dose of SHR-A2102 in phase II&#xD;
      study.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">April 6, 2023</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">August 31, 2025</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">August 31, 2025</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>N/A</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>SHR-A2102 single arm</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of participants with adverse events</measure>
    <time_frame>24 months</time_frame>
    <description>Adverse events are assessed by CTCAE v5.0</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Maximum tolerated dose (MTD)</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>MTD is defined as the maximum dose within the first 3 weeks of multiple dosing that does not exceed the proportion of subjects who develop DLT as specified in the protocol's BOIN design.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Recommended Phase 2 dose (RP2D)</measure>
    <time_frame>24 months</time_frame>
    <description>RP2D will be determined based on the available data for toxicity and PK.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Dose Limiting Toxicity (DLT)</measure>
    <time_frame>3 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Adverse events that occurred during the DLT observation period (the first period of study administration, a total of 21 days) that were determined to be related to the study drug (see protocol for details).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Peak plasma concentration (Cmax)</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Area under the plasma concentration versus time curve (AUC）</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>T1/2 (Half-life)</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>The time required for the plasma concentration of a drug to be reduced by 50%</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Immunogenicity: Number of subjects with anti-SHR-A2102 antibody (ADA), incidence, occurrence time, duration, etc</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Objective response rate (ORR)</measure>
    <time_frame>24 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>duration of response (DoR)</measure>
    <time_frame>24 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>disease control rate (DCR)</measure>
    <time_frame>24 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>progression-free survival (PFS)</measure>
    <time_frame>24 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>overall survival (OS)</measure>
    <time_frame>24 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">200</enrollment>
  <condition>Advanced Solid Tumors</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>SHR-A2102</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>SHR-A2102</intervention_name>
    <description>SHR-A2102 was given intravenously. Patients may continue to use SHR-A2102 until disease progression or unacceptable toxicity occurs.</description>
    <arm_group_label>SHR-A2102</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:&#xD;
&#xD;
          1. Able and willing to provide a written informed consent;&#xD;
&#xD;
          2. Age ≥18 years old, gender unlimited;&#xD;
&#xD;
          3. The physical status score of the Eastern Tumor Cooperative Group (ECOG) was 0 ~ 1;&#xD;
&#xD;
          4. Life expectancy Predicted survival ≥3 months;&#xD;
&#xD;
          5. Histologically or cytologically confirmed advanced or metastatic malignant tumor;&#xD;
             Patients with advanced solid tumors confirmed by pathology who have failed or been&#xD;
             intolerant to standard treatment, have no standard treatment or refuse standard&#xD;
             treatment;&#xD;
&#xD;
          6. There is at least one measurable lesion that meets the RECIST 1.1 criteria.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Exclusion Criteria:&#xD;
&#xD;
          1. Plan to receive any other antitumor therapy during this trial;&#xD;
&#xD;
          2. Receiving other investigational drugs or treatments that are not on the market within&#xD;
             4 weeks prior to the initial administration of the study drug;&#xD;
&#xD;
          3. Received antitumor therapy such as chemotherapy, radiotherapy, biotherapy, targeted&#xD;
             therapy, or immunotherapy within 4 weeks prior to first administration of the study&#xD;
             drug (nitrosourea or mitomycin C within 6 weeks prior to first administration; Oral&#xD;
             fluorouracil within 2 weeks prior to initial first administration); Palliative&#xD;
             radiotherapy or local therapy within 2 weeks before first administration use of the&#xD;
             study drug;&#xD;
&#xD;
          4. Had major surgery other than diagnosis or biopsy within 4 weeks prior to the study's&#xD;
             initial dosing;&#xD;
&#xD;
          5. Treatment with CYP3A4, CYP2D6, P-gp or BCRP booster or inducer is less than 5 drug&#xD;
             half-life from the date of first administration;&#xD;
&#xD;
          6. According to NCI-CTCAE v5.0, adverse events caused by previous antitumor therapy did&#xD;
             not recover to ≤ grade 1 (except hair loss; In the judgment of the investigator, after&#xD;
             consultation with the sponsor, some tolerable chronic grade 2 toxicity may be&#xD;
             excluded);&#xD;
&#xD;
          7. Inadequately treated central nervous system (CNS) metastases, or the presence of&#xD;
             uncontrolled or symptomatic active CNS metastases, may be characterized by the&#xD;
             presence of clinical symptoms, cerebral edema, spinal cord compression, cancerous&#xD;
             meningitis, pia meningeal disease, and/or rapid progression. Patients with CNS&#xD;
             metastases that have been adequately treated and whose neurological symptoms return to&#xD;
             baseline at least 4 weeks prior to randomization (except for residual signs or&#xD;
             symptoms associated with CNS treatment) may be enrolled. In addition, subjects must&#xD;
             either stop corticosteroids or receive prednisone (or an equivalent dose of another&#xD;
             corticosteroid) at least 4 weeks prior to randomization;&#xD;
&#xD;
          8. Any other malignancies, excluding cured basal cell carcinoma of the skin and carcinoma&#xD;
             in situ of the cervix, etc. within 5 years prior to initial administration;&#xD;
&#xD;
          9. A history of clinically significant lung disease (such as interstitial pneumonia,&#xD;
             radiation pneumonia, pulmonary fibrosis) or chest imaging during screening suggests&#xD;
             any such disease;&#xD;
&#xD;
         10. Severe infections that require intravenous antibiotic, antiviral or antifungal&#xD;
             control;&#xD;
&#xD;
         11. Active HBV or HCV infection (HBsAg positive and viral copy number ≥2000 IU/mL, HCV&#xD;
             antibody positive and HCV RNA higher than the lower limit of detection method);&#xD;
&#xD;
         12. History of immunodeficiency (including HIV positive, other acquired or congenital&#xD;
             immunodeficiency diseases) or organ transplantation;&#xD;
&#xD;
         13. Concomitant diseases (such as severe diabetes, thyroid disease, and psychosis) or any&#xD;
             other conditions that, in the investigator's judgment, seriously endanger the&#xD;
             patient's safety or affect the patient's ability to complete the study.&#xD;
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Fei Luo</last_name>
    <phone>+0518-81220121</phone>
    <email>fei.luo@hengrui.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Shanghai Chest Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Shanghai</city>
        <state>Shanghai</state>
        <zip>200030</zip>
        <country>China</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Hua Zhong</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>China</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>January 2023</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>January 18, 2023</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 18, 2023</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">January 27, 2023</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 28, 2023</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 28, 2023</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 31, 2023</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

