<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="9934">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 09, 2023</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT05687162</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>1253</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT05687162</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>SSIs for Mental Health and Loneliness</brief_title>
  <official_title>Brief Internet Interventions to Support Mental Health</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of California, Irvine</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Jacobs Foundation</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of California, Irvine</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This project includes three studies that explore the effectiveness of brief internet&#xD;
      interventions for mental health and loneliness.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Study 1: The goal of this clinical trial is to examine if a brief online single-session&#xD;
      intervention (SSI) adapted from an evidence-based internet cognitive behavioral therapy can&#xD;
      reduce feelings of loneliness in people aged 16 and older who struggle with loneliness. The&#xD;
      main question it aims to answer is if a brief SSI is sufficient to meaningfully reduce&#xD;
      loneliness compared to an active control. Researchers will test these questions by comparing&#xD;
      change in loneliness after 8 weeks between participants randomly assigned to either 1) a&#xD;
      30-minute online SSI for loneliness or 2) a 3-session online intervention for loneliness or&#xD;
      3) an active control SSI.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Study 2: The goal of this clinical trial is to examine if an SSI for psychological distress&#xD;
      that uses popular online content as its primary form of intervention content can reduce&#xD;
      feelings of psychological distress in people aged 16 and older who struggle with&#xD;
      psychological distress. The main questions it aims to answer are 1) if curated popular online&#xD;
      content can be more effective in supporting people struggling with psychological distress&#xD;
      than researcher-created content and 2) if curated popular online content can be more&#xD;
      effective in supporting people struggling with psychological distress than un-curated&#xD;
      self-selected popular online content. Researchers will test these questions by comparing&#xD;
      change in distress after 8 weeks between participants randomly assigned to either 1)&#xD;
      25-minute popular online content-based SSI for distress or 2) an effective 25-minute online&#xD;
      SSI for distress with evidence-based researcher-created content or 3) online help-seeking as&#xD;
      usual.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Study 3: The goal of this clinical trial is to examine if an SSI for loneliness that uses&#xD;
      popular online content as its primary form of intervention content can reduce feelings of&#xD;
      loneliness in people aged 16 and older who struggle with loneliness. The main questions it&#xD;
      aims to answer are 1) if curated popular online content can be more effective in supporting&#xD;
      people struggling with loneliness than researcher-created content, 2) if curated popular&#xD;
      online content can be more effective in supporting people struggling with psychological&#xD;
      distress than an active control, and 3) replicating the comparison in study 1, if a brief SSI&#xD;
      is sufficient to meaningfully reduce loneliness compared to an active control. The study will&#xD;
      test these questions by comparing change in loneliness after 8 weeks between participants&#xD;
      randomly assigned to either 1) a 25-minute popular online content-based SSI for loneliness or&#xD;
      2) a 25-minute online SSI for loneliness with evidence-based researcher-created content or 3)&#xD;
      an active control SSI.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Study 1: Severe loneliness is globally prevalent and is strongly associated with impaired&#xD;
      mental and physical well-being, making it a significant public health issue. Evidence-based&#xD;
      interventions for loneliness reach a small subset of people who might benefit from them, so&#xD;
      identifying new strategies for addressing loneliness at scale should be a high priority.&#xD;
      Online single-session interventions (SSIs) have demonstrated particular promise to offer&#xD;
      efficient and highly-scalable support to diverse populations.&#xD;
&#xD;
      The study will test if an internet-mediated self-guided SSI can produce lasting improvements&#xD;
      in loneliness. The investigators adapted a 9-week online loneliness intervention into a&#xD;
      3-week 3-session version and a single-session 30-minute SSI version. The investigators will&#xD;
      randomly assign participants to complete the 3-week version, the SSI version, or a control&#xD;
      SSI.&#xD;
&#xD;
      The investigators will collect self-report measures at baseline, directly after the&#xD;
      intervention, and 4 and 8 weeks after baseline. The investigators will also measure&#xD;
      participant engagement with the intervention using self-report and behavioral measures. The&#xD;
      investigators will recruit teens and adults (16+) for the study via social media.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Study 2: SSIs for mental health have shown promise for delivering efficient support to&#xD;
      diverse populations. Despite their brevity, existing SSIs still struggle to engage users.&#xD;
&#xD;
      This study will explore using a broad range of mental health-relevant popular online content&#xD;
      (eg, psychology lectures on YouTube, Instagram posts from self-care influencers, and blog&#xD;
      posts written by people who struggle with mood disorders) in SSIs. Although it is often not&#xD;
      evidence-based, popular online content may be more appealing and tailored to particular&#xD;
      audiences than the researcher-created intervention content typically used in evidence-based&#xD;
      SSIs.&#xD;
&#xD;
      In this study, researchers will examine the effectiveness of this content for addressing&#xD;
      psychological distress. Researchers will conduct an experiment to compare a popular online&#xD;
      content-based SSI to one that has already demonstrated efficacy and to online help seeking as&#xD;
      usual to identify whether such content is useful within an SSI context. Researchers will&#xD;
      measure change in psychological distress from baseline to 4-week and 8-week follow-ups.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Study 3: In this study, researchers aim to replicate and extend studies 1 and 2 to further&#xD;
      evaluate the potential of an SSI for loneliness and the utility of popular online content as&#xD;
      a mental health intervention.&#xD;
&#xD;
      In this study, researchers will examine the effectiveness of popular online content for&#xD;
      addressing loneliness. Researchers will conduct an experiment to compare a popular online&#xD;
      content-based SSI for loneliness to another online SSI for loneliness with researcher-created&#xD;
      content and to an active control SSI. Researchers will measure change in loneliness from&#xD;
      baseline to 4-week and 8-week follow-ups.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">December 4, 2022</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">October 30, 2023</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">September 1, 2023</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>In each study, participants will be randomly assigned to complete one of three online programs, assessing DVs at baseline and 4 and 8 weeks later.&#xD;
Note that each study has 3 arms, so in total 9 arms are included in this project.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double (Participant, Investigator)</masking>
    <masking_description>Participants will not be informed which condition they were assigned to or what the other conditions involve. The investigators will not interact with participants or see which condition they are in during the intervention.</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in UCLA Loneliness Scale Version 3 at 8 weeks</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 8-week follow-up</time_frame>
    <description>A 20-item measure of trait loneliness. Range 20-80 with higher scores indicated more severe loneliness. Included in studies 1 and 2b</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in UCLA Loneliness Scale Version 3 at 4 weeks</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 4-week follow-up</time_frame>
    <description>A 20-item measure of trait loneliness. Range 20-80 with higher scores indicated more severe loneliness. Included in studies 1 and 3</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Depression Anxiety and Stress Scale - 9-item total score at 8 weeks</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 8-week follow-up</time_frame>
    <description>A brief scale with subscales measuring depression, anxiety, and stress. Range 0-27 with higher scores indicating greater symptom severity. Included in all studies.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Depression Anxiety and Stress Scale - 9-item total score at 4 weeks</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 4-week follow-up</time_frame>
    <description>A brief scale with subscales measuring depression, anxiety, and stress. Range 0-27 with higher scores indicating greater symptom severity. Included in all studies.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in 3-item Mini Social Phobia Inventory at 8 weeks</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 8-week follow-up</time_frame>
    <description>A brief measure of social anxiety. Range 0-12 with higher scores indicating greater symptom severity. Included in studies 1 and 3</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in 3-item Mini Social Phobia Inventory at 4 weeks</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 4-week follow-up</time_frame>
    <description>A brief measure of social anxiety. Range 0-12 with higher scores indicating greater symptom severity. Included in studies 1 and 3</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Short form of the General Self-Efficacy Scale at 8 weeks</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 8-week follow-up</time_frame>
    <description>A 6-item measure of general self-efficacy. Range 6-24 with higher scores indicating greater self-efficacy. Included in all studies.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Short form of the General Self-Efficacy Scale at 4 weeks</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 4-week follow-up</time_frame>
    <description>A 6-item measure of general self-efficacy. Range 6-24 with higher scores indicating greater self-efficacy. Included in all studies.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Short form of the General Self-Efficacy Scale immediately post-intervention</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, immediately post-intervention (roughly 30 minutes after beginning study for single-session conditions, and roughly 2 weeks after beginning study for 3-week iCBT condition)</time_frame>
    <description>A 6-item measure of general self-efficacy. Range 6-24 with higher scores indicating greater self-efficacy. Included in all studies.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Beck Hopelessness Scale - 4-item at 8 weeks</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 8-week follow-up</time_frame>
    <description>A brief version of a hopelessness measure. Range 4-12 with higher scores indicating more hopelessness. Included in all studies.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Beck Hopelessness Scale - 4-item at 4 weeks</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 4-week follow-up</time_frame>
    <description>A brief version of a hopelessness measure. Range 4-12 with higher scores indicating more hopelessness. Included in all studies.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Beck Hopelessness Scale - 4-item immediately post-intervention</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, immediately post-intervention (roughly 30 minutes after beginning study for single-session conditions, and roughly 2 weeks after beginning study for 3-week iCBT condition)</time_frame>
    <description>A brief version of a hopelessness measure. Range 4-12 with higher scores indicating greater hopelessness. Included in all studies.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Frequency of actions and thoughts scale at 8 weeks</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 8-week follow-up</time_frame>
    <description>A 12-item measure of adaptive thoughts and behaviors, improvement in which might be a target of cognitive behavioral therapy. Range 0-48 with higher scores indicating greater frequency of adaptive thoughts and behaviors. Included in all studies.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Frequency of actions and thoughts scale at 4 weeks</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 4-week follow-up</time_frame>
    <description>A 12-item measure of adaptive thoughts and behaviors, improvement in which might be a target of cognitive behavioral therapy. Range 0-48 with higher scores indicating greater frequency of adaptive thoughts and behaviors. Included in all studies.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Program Feedback Scale</measure>
    <time_frame>immediately post-intervention (roughly 30 minutes after beginning study for single-session conditions, and roughly 2 weeks after beginning study for 3-week iCBT condition)</time_frame>
    <description>A 7-item measure of engagement with and acceptability of SSIs. Range 7-35 with higher scores indicating greater engagement with and acceptability of the SSI. Included in all studies.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Credibility and Expectancy Questionnaire</measure>
    <time_frame>immediately post-intervention (roughly 30 minutes after beginning study for single-session conditions, and roughly 2 weeks after beginning study for 3-week iCBT condition)</time_frame>
    <description>A 6-item measure of user-perceived intervention appeal and efficacy. Range 6-54 with higher scores indicating higher user-perceived intervention appeal and efficacy. Included in all studies.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Insight experience</measure>
    <time_frame>immediately post-intervention (roughly 30 minutes after beginning study for single-session conditions, and roughly 2 weeks after beginning study for 3-week iCBT condition)</time_frame>
    <description>A 1-item measure of whether one experienced an insight moment as a result of the program. Range 0-1 with 1 indicating presence of an insight experience and 0 indicating a lack of insight experience. Included in all studies.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Star rating</measure>
    <time_frame>immediately post-intervention (roughly 30 minutes after beginning study for single-session conditions, and roughly 2 weeks after beginning study for 3-week iCBT condition)</time_frame>
    <description>A rating of program quality, from 1-5 stars with more stars indicating greater quality. Included in all studies.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in PROMIS Meaning and Purpose in Life - 4-item at 4 weeks</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 4-week follow-up</time_frame>
    <description>a 4-item measure of meaning and purpose in life. Range 4-20 with higher scores indicating a greater sense of meaning and purpose. Included in studies 2 and 3.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in PROMIS Meaning and Purpose in Life - 4-item at 8 weeks</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 8-week follow-up</time_frame>
    <description>a 4-item measure of meaning and purpose in life. Range 4-20 with higher scores indicating a greater sense of meaning and purpose. Included in studies 2 and 3.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>9</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">4000</enrollment>
  <condition>Loneliness</condition>
  <condition>Mental Health Issue</condition>
  <condition>Distress, Emotional</condition>
  <condition>Depression</condition>
  <condition>Anxiety</condition>
  <condition>Stress</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>(Study 1) 3-week Loneliness Program</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>The second and third sessions are completed in the second and third week, respectively, after beginning the study.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>(Study 1) Single-session loneliness program</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>(Study 1) Single-session active control program</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>(Study 2) Popular online content-based single-session intervention for distress</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>(Study 2) Researcher-created single-session intervention for distress</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>(Study 2) Online help-seeking as usual</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>(Study 3) Popular online content-based single-session intervention for loneliness</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>(Study 3) Researcher-created single-session intervention for loneliness</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>(Study 3) Single-session active control program</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Overcoming Loneliness three-week intervention</intervention_name>
    <description>A self-guided online loneliness intervention with three 10-20 minute sessions. The intervention content draws heavily from Internet Cognitive Behavioral Therapy for Loneliness and follows the form of single-session mental health interventions.</description>
    <arm_group_label>(Study 1) 3-week Loneliness Program</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Overcoming Loneliness single-session intervention</intervention_name>
    <description>The Overcoming Loneliness Three-Week Intervention condensed into a single-session intervention lasting 20-30 minutes.</description>
    <arm_group_label>(Study 1) Single-session loneliness program</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>(Study 3) Researcher-created single-session intervention for loneliness</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Single-session &quot;Sharing Feelings&quot; program</intervention_name>
    <description>A self-guided online supportive therapy intervention with a single 20-30 minute session intended to encourage users to share feelings with close others. Slightly modified from the &quot;Sharing Feelings&quot; intervention</description>
    <arm_group_label>(Study 1) Single-session active control program</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>(Study 3) Single-session active control program</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>The Blu Surfer program: a popular online content-based intervention for psychological distress</intervention_name>
    <description>The Blu Surfer Program is a 25-minute SSI the research team developed centered on popular online content relevant to mental health. In the SSI, the user is first asked to select the kinds of support they would like to view. Next, the user is asked to explore a library of annotated popular online content (filtered by their desired kinds of content) and to select the content they find personally valuable. Finally, the SSI provides the user an annotated list of the content they selected. Users can keep this list to draw from, build on, or share later on as they wish.</description>
    <arm_group_label>(Study 2) Popular online content-based single-session intervention for distress</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>The Action Brings Change (ABC) Program (TEAM Lab version)</intervention_name>
    <description>The ABC project is a 20-30-minute SSI for teens based on behavioral activation. It was found to be efficacious for reducing depression, anxiety, hopelessness, and self-hate and increasing perceived control and agency in youth (link to SSI: https://osf.io/ch2tg/, license: http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/). The researchers modified the phrasing in the intervention to make it more relevant to both teens and adults, as the original was designed for only teens.</description>
    <arm_group_label>(Study 2) Researcher-created single-session intervention for distress</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Online help-seeking as usual</intervention_name>
    <description>This intervention, created by the present research team, aims to emulate how one might find support on their own using the internet. In this condition, participants are asked to browse the internet for 25 minutes to find popular online content relevant to their personal struggles and create an annotated list of links to the content they find useful. The intervention is similar to a &quot;self-study&quot; condition, which found self-study and a video intervention equally increased mental health knowledge. The survey platform provides text entry boxes to help each participant create their guide and then provides a text version of their guide for them to keep.</description>
    <arm_group_label>(Study 2) Online help-seeking as usual</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>The Lonely Blu Surfer program: a popular online content-based intervention for loneliness</intervention_name>
    <description>The Lonely Blu Surfer Program is a 25-minute SSI the research team developed centered on popular online content relevant to loneliness. In the SSI, the user is first asked to select the kinds of support they would like to view. Next, the user is asked to explore a library of annotated popular online content (filtered by their desired kinds of content) and to select the content they find personally valuable. Finally, the SSI provides the user an annotated list of the content they selected. Users can keep this list to draw from, build on, or share later on as they wish.</description>
    <arm_group_label>(Study 3) Popular online content-based single-session intervention for loneliness</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Be fluent in English&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Be 16 years old +&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Have internet access and a computer, smartphone, or tablet&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  To be compensated for participation and be included in the main analysis, participants&#xD;
             in studies 1 and 2 must meet criteria for &quot;struggling with loneliness&quot; (ie, a score on&#xD;
             the 3-item loneliness screen of at least 6, and indicating that one's loneliness is&#xD;
             causing one distress). Otherwise, participants can still participate in the study on a&#xD;
             volunteer basis.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  To be compensated for participation and be included in the main analysis, participants&#xD;
             in study 3 must meet criteria for &quot;struggling with distress&quot; (ie, a score on either&#xD;
             the depression or anxiety subscale greater than or equal to 3 (range 0-6), as these&#xD;
             scores are suggestive of a depressive or anxiety disorder.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Exclusion Criteria:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Having completed the study in the past&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Failing both of the attention checks in the baseline measures.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Spending less than 3 minutes completing the study introduction and baseline measures&#xD;
             (ie, were very likely bots)&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Indicating, at the end of the study, that one did not complete the study seriously and&#xD;
             that one's data should not be included in analyses.&#xD;
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>16 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Stephen M Schueller, Ph.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of California, Irvine</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Benjamin T Kaveladze, M.A.</last_name>
    <phone>(310) 984-9318</phone>
    <email>bkavelad@uci.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Stephen M Schueller, Ph.D.</last_name>
    <phone>(949) 824-3850</phone>
    <email>s.schueller@uci.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Online (based at UC Irvine)</name>
      <address>
        <city>Irvine</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>92697</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Benjamin T Kaveladze, MA</last_name>
      <phone>310-984-9318</phone>
      <email>bkavelad@uci.edu</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Cacioppo JT, Cacioppo S. The growing problem of loneliness. Lancet. 2018 Feb 3;391(10119):426. doi: 10.1016/S0140-6736(18)30142-9. No abstract available.</citation>
    <PMID>29407030</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hickin N, Kall A, Shafran R, Sutcliffe S, Manzotti G, Langan D. The effectiveness of psychological interventions for loneliness: A systematic review and meta-analysis. Clin Psychol Rev. 2021 Aug;88:102066. doi: 10.1016/j.cpr.2021.102066. Epub 2021 Jul 18.</citation>
    <PMID>34339939</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Masi CM, Chen HY, Hawkley LC, Cacioppo JT. A meta-analysis of interventions to reduce loneliness. Pers Soc Psychol Rev. 2011 Aug;15(3):219-66. doi: 10.1177/1088868310377394. Epub 2010 Aug 17.</citation>
    <PMID>20716644</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kall A, Backlund U, Shafran R, Andersson G. Lonesome no more? A two-year follow-up of internet-administered cognitive behavioral therapy for loneliness. Internet Interv. 2020 Jan 17;19:100301. doi: 10.1016/j.invent.2019.100301. eCollection 2020 Mar.</citation>
    <PMID>32071885</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Yamaguchi S, Ojio Y, Ando S, Bernick P, Ohta K, Watanabe KI, Thornicroft G, Shiozawa T, Koike S. Long-term effects of filmed social contact or internet-based self-study on mental health-related stigma: a 2-year follow-up of a randomised controlled trial. Soc Psychiatry Psychiatr Epidemiol. 2019 Jan;54(1):33-42. doi: 10.1007/s00127-018-1609-8. Epub 2018 Oct 12.</citation>
    <PMID>30315333</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Rizvi SL, Finkelstein J, Wacha-Montes A, Yeager AL, Ruork AK, Yin Q, Kellerman J, Kim JS, Stern M, Oshin LA, Kleiman EM. Randomized clinical trial of a brief, scalable intervention for mental health sequelae in college students during the COVID-19 pandemic. Behav Res Ther. 2022 Feb;149:104015. doi: 10.1016/j.brat.2021.104015. Epub 2021 Dec 21.</citation>
    <PMID>34958980</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Murphy ST, Frank LB, Chatterjee JS, Baezconde-Garbanati L. Narrative versus Non-narrative: The Role of Identification, Transportation and Emotion in Reducing Health Disparities. J Commun. 2013 Feb;63(1):10.1111/jcom.12007. doi: 10.1111/jcom.12007.</citation>
    <PMID>24347679</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kroenke K, Spitzer RL, Williams JB, Lowe B. An ultra-brief screening scale for anxiety and depression: the PHQ-4. Psychosomatics. 2009 Nov-Dec;50(6):613-21. doi: 10.1176/appi.psy.50.6.613.</citation>
    <PMID>19996233</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>April 2023</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>November 29, 2022</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 5, 2023</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">January 18, 2023</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 20, 2023</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 20, 2023</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">April 24, 2023</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of California, Irvine</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Stephen Matthew Schueller</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Associate Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Depression</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Yes</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>De-identified participant data will be shared, including all measures. Participants' responses to open text response questions within the program will not be shared for the sake of privacy.</ipd_description>
    <ipd_info_type>Study Protocol</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_info_type>Statistical Analysis Plan (SAP)</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_info_type>Informed Consent Form (ICF)</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_info_type>Analytic Code</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_time_frame>The data will be available as soon as it is cleaned and de-identified and it will remain publicly available as long as possible.</ipd_time_frame>
    <ipd_access_criteria>The data will be available to the public via an online dataset on the Open Science Framework (osf.io)</ipd_access_criteria>
  </patient_data>
  <provided_document_section>
    <provided_document>
      <document_type>Study Protocol and Statistical Analysis Plan</document_type>
      <document_has_protocol>Yes</document_has_protocol>
      <document_has_icf>No</document_has_icf>
      <document_has_sap>Yes</document_has_sap>
      <document_date>April 6, 2023</document_date>
      <document_url>https://ClinicalTrials.gov/ProvidedDocs/62/NCT05687162/Prot_SAP_001.pdf</document_url>
    </provided_document>
  </provided_document_section>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

