<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="9358">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 09, 2023</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT05699668</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>PREMA-OCTA</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT05699668</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Preterm Infants REtinalMicrovascular Alterations by Means of OCT Angiography</brief_title>
  <acronym>PREMA-OCTA</acronym>
  <official_title>Preterm Infants REtinalMicrovascular Alterations by Means of OCT Angiography</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Centre Hospitalier Intercommunal Creteil</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Centre Hospitalier Intercommunal Creteil</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Retinal vascularization in humans develops between the 16th and 36th week of amenorrhea,&#xD;
      centrifugally from the papilla. In case of premature birth, the immature retinal periphery is&#xD;
      at risk of ischemic damage due to lack of vascular development.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Prematurity is often associated with respiratory fragility. It often requires ventilatory&#xD;
      assistance in the form of oxygen therapy, invasive (oro-tracheal intubation) or non-invasive,&#xD;
      which leads to reflex arteriolar vasoconstriction aggravating the ischemia already present.&#xD;
      One may wonder if there are subclinical retinal vascular changes, detectable on Tomographie&#xD;
      par Cohérence Optique-Angiography (, that could explain the greater risk of amblyopia and&#xD;
      optical correction observed. Tomographie par Cohérence Optique-Angiography is a fast growing&#xD;
      technique in retinal vascular pathologies: it is a simple, fast, reliable, non-invasive,&#xD;
      injection-free examination, which allows to study in high resolution the retinal&#xD;
      vascularization, with a distinct analysis of the retinal plexuses and the choriocapillaris&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Retinal vascularization in humans develops between the 16th and 36th week of amenorrhea,&#xD;
      centrifugally from the papilla. In case of premature birth, the immature retinal periphery is&#xD;
      at risk of ischemia due to lack of vascular development. This lack of perfusion in the&#xD;
      retinal periphery leads to abnormal secretion of pro-angiogenic factors, promoting the&#xD;
      appearance of abnormal neovessels, which can be complicated by intravitreal hemorrhage and&#xD;
      tractional retinal detachment, permanently altering vision.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Conversely, it is known that in premature infants, there is a smaller central avascular zone&#xD;
      compared to full-term infants. This area of the retina, where 90% of the cones are&#xD;
      concentrated, must be free of vascular structures to allow optimal vision.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Prematurity is often associated with respiratory fragility. It often requires ventilatory&#xD;
      support in the form of oxygen therapy, invasive (oro-tracheal intubation) or non-invasive,&#xD;
      which causes reflex arteriolar vasoconstriction, aggravating the ischemia already present in&#xD;
      the periphery.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Clinically, after birth, ocular disorders are more frequently found in preterm infants:&#xD;
      amblyopia and contrast vision disorders, ametropia, strabismus and optic nerve anomalies.&#xD;
&#xD;
      It is questionable whether there are subclinical retinal vascular changes, detectable on&#xD;
      Tomographie par Cohérence Optique-Angiography, associated with clinical differences.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Indeed, Angiography-Tomographie par Cohérence Optique allows detection of changes in foveolar&#xD;
      and peripapillary retinal microvascularization more sensitively than dilated fundus&#xD;
      examination (detection of subclinical microvascular abnormalities), as has been demonstrated&#xD;
      for many retinal pathologies; it thus participates in the diagnosis, monitoring, evaluation&#xD;
      of therapeutic response and prognosis of many retinal Angiography Tomographie par Cohérence&#xD;
      Optique is rapidly expanding in retinal vascular pathologies: it is a simple, rapid,&#xD;
      reliable, noninvasive, and injection-free examination that allows high-resolution study of&#xD;
      the retinal vasculature, with a distinct analysis of the retinal plexuses and the&#xD;
      choriocapillaris.&#xD;
&#xD;
      It would also be interesting to investigate whether there is a correlation between the&#xD;
      child's neonatal parameters, the retinal vascular changes on Angiography -Tomographie par&#xD;
      Cohérence Optique, and the elements of the clinical examination (vision and refraction). If&#xD;
      such a correlation is found, it would allow a targeted and personalized visual screening of&#xD;
      the subjects identified as most at risk, with a stratification of the ocular risk according&#xD;
      to the neonatal history and the OCT-A measurements.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Finally, this study would provide a better understanding of the development of the retina&#xD;
      during the neonatal period, the factors that may influence it, and the mechanisms potentially&#xD;
      responsible for the observed disorders.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">March 15, 2023</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 31, 2023</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">July 31, 2023</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Premature infants born at a term ≤28 weeks of amenorrhea, without bronchopulmonary dysplasia (BPD), whether or not followed at CHIC Premature infants born at a term ≤28 weeks of amenorrhea, with bronchopulmonary dysplasia (BPD) and followed or not at CHIC Patients in the control group (without prematurity without BPD) selected at a scheduled routine ophthalmology consultation at CHIC, born at a term ≥ 38SA</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Other</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>To show a difference on vascular density in OCT-A (%), between preterm children (born ≤ 28 SA) and control children (born &gt; 38SA).</measure>
    <time_frame>1day</time_frame>
    <description>Macular and peripapillary vascular densities (%):on OCT-A images at the superficial and deep capillary plexus in the control and preterm groups</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>To demonstrate differences in clinical parameters (visual acuity, spherical equivalent) between premature children (born ≤ 28 SA) and control children (born &gt; 38SA)</measure>
    <time_frame>1 day</time_frame>
    <description>Collection of clinical parameters</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>To demonstrate differences in OCT-A parameters (fractal dimension), between premature children (born ≤ 28 SA) and control children (born &gt; 38SA)</measure>
    <time_frame>1 day</time_frame>
    <description>Collection of clinical parameters</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>To demonstrate a correlation between neonatal history (term, birth weight, duration of oxygen therapy, ventilation mode, presence or absence of BPD), clinical parameters (visual acuity, spherical equivalent), and OCT-A parameters.</measure>
    <time_frame>1 day</time_frame>
    <description>Collection of neonatal history</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>To demonstrate differences in OCT-A parameters (central avascular zone area (mm2), between premature children (born ≤ 28 SA) and control children (born &gt; 38SA)</measure>
    <time_frame>1 day</time_frame>
    <description>Collection of OCT angiography parameters</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">56</enrollment>
  <condition>Premature With Dysplasia Bronchopulmonary</condition>
  <condition>Premature Without Dysplasia Bronchopulmonary</condition>
  <condition>Controls Born at Term</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>older premature children born at a term ≤28 weeks of amenorrhea without dysplasia bronchopulmonary</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>OCT Angiography</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>older premature children born at a term ≤28 weeks of amenorrhea with dysplasia bronchopulmonary</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>OCT Angiography</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>patients in the control group without prematurity without BPD</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>OCT Angiography</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>OCT Angiography</intervention_name>
    <description>2 views per eye (one centered on the fovea, one centered on the optic nerve), in 6x6 mm, using the OCT-A Plexelite®.&#xD;
Acquisition time per image: about 10 seconds.</description>
    <arm_group_label>older premature children born at a term ≤28 weeks of amenorrhea with dysplasia bronchopulmonary</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>older premature children born at a term ≤28 weeks of amenorrhea without dysplasia bronchopulmonary</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>patients in the control group without prematurity without BPD</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:&#xD;
&#xD;
        Premature group:&#xD;
&#xD;
        - Any child aged 5 to 15 years born before or at 28 SA (with or without BPD), followed or&#xD;
        not at the Creteil's hospital intercommunal&#xD;
&#xD;
        Control group:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Any child aged 5 to 15 years born ≥ 38SA, consulting ophthalmology at the Creteil 's&#xD;
             hospital intercommunal.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Acceptance to participate in the protocol&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Child living near the Creteil's intercommunal hospital&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Affiliated to a social security system&#xD;
&#xD;
        Exclusion Criteria: all groups&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Neurobehavioral disorder or psychomotor delay that does not allow the examination to&#xD;
             be performed&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Presence of a POR with zone I involvement or having received IVT of anti-VEGF (as it&#xD;
             may directly modify the OCT-A parameters)&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Pre-existing retinal pathology: macular scarring of any etiology, retinal vascular&#xD;
             alterations such as sickle cell disease, diabetes.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Pre-existing optic nerve pathologies: glaucoma, coloboma, tumors.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Chronic respiratory pathologies other than BPD (i.e. not associated with prematurity):&#xD;
             cystic fibrosis, DDB...&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  General pathology unrelated to prematurity that may have a retinal impact: e.g.&#xD;
             respiratory diseases other than BPD&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Participation in an interventional study in ophthalmology&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  A history of hyperthermic convulsions in infants or epilepsy, which contraindicates&#xD;
             the use of eye drops.&#xD;
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>5 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>15 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Camille JUNG</last_name>
    <phone>00157022268</phone>
    <email>camille.jung@chicreteil.fr</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Cyndie Nilusmas</last_name>
    <email>cyndie.nilusmas@chicreteil.fr</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <verification_date>July 2022</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>December 14, 2022</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 16, 2023</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">January 26, 2023</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 13, 2023</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 13, 2023</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">February 15, 2023</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Premature Birth</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

