<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="9716">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 09, 2023</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT05691803</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>UMEPA01</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT05691803</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Understanding Motivation Towards Exercise to Enhance Physical Activity on Prescription Adherence - Feasibility Study</brief_title>
  <acronym>UMEPA-F</acronym>
  <official_title>Understanding Motivation Towards Exercise to Enhance Physical Activity on Prescription Adherence - Feasibility Study</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Umeå University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Umeå University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The goal of this clinical trial is to explore feasibility and evaluate methods to investigate&#xD;
      changes in physical activity, function and psychometrics in relation to an exercise&#xD;
      intervention in physically inactive middle-aged men and women. The main questions it aims to&#xD;
      answer are:&#xD;
&#xD;
        -  Is the exercise intervention feasible regarding retention and user experience?&#xD;
&#xD;
        -  Is the evaluation methods on physical activity, function and psychometrics suitable for&#xD;
           the present study?&#xD;
&#xD;
        -  Is there an intervention effect in physical activity, function and psychometrics at&#xD;
           three and six month post baseline?&#xD;
&#xD;
        -  Can barriers and facilitators towards increased physical activity be identified in the&#xD;
           two groups of the study?&#xD;
&#xD;
      All participants will first receive standard care for physically inactive patients, i.e.&#xD;
      Physical activity on Prescription (PaP), followed by allocation to an exercise intervention&#xD;
      (EI) group. The EI group will be offered an additional exercise intervention for 12 weeks&#xD;
      consisting of 1-2 training sessions per week of a combination of aerobic and resistance&#xD;
      training at a private fitness center.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Feasibility of the exercise intervention will be evaluated based on retention rates and user&#xD;
      experience.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Additionally, researchers will assess physical activity, function and psychometrics in the EI&#xD;
      group at three and six months to evaluate the suitability of the chosen methods and to get&#xD;
      preliminary data on the intervention effect. Finally, interviews with the participants in the&#xD;
      control and EI groups will be performed at the end of the study in order to explore barriers&#xD;
      and facilitators towards increased physical activity in formally inactive patients.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Edit after registration of the study: Due to a lower number of recruited participants than&#xD;
      expected (20 instead of the anticipated 30), the protocol was updated by removing the control&#xD;
      group that would initially consist of 10 participants. The remaining 20 participants were all&#xD;
      allocated to the exercise intervention group to assess feasibility of the intervention.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">February 3, 2023</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">September 29, 2023</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">September 29, 2023</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>N/A</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>A one arm intervention study with allocation to usual care (Physical activty on Prescription) + an exercise intervention.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Adherence to the exercise intervention</measure>
    <time_frame>Documented continuously during the 12 week intervention period</time_frame>
    <description>Number of completed training sessions in the exercise intervention group</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Retention rate</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months post baseline</time_frame>
    <description>The proportion of participants starting the intervention that completes outcome assessment in either group</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Time spent in moderate and vigorous physical activity</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 3 months and 6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Objectively measured physical activity, measured with an accelerometer for 7 consecutive days. Raw data are then recalculated to minutes spent in different intensity zones and finally minutes in moderate and vigorous physical activity are calculated.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Daily step-count</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 3 months and 6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Objectively measured physical activity, measured with an accelerometer for 7 consecutive days is used to collect step-count which is presented as steps taken per day.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Cardio-respiratory capacity</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 3 months and 6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Ekblom-Bak cycle ergometer test will be used to assess cardio-respiratory fitness.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Upper limb strength</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 3 months and 6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Hand grip strength om the non dominant hand is measured with a hand dynamometer to the nearest kg. Three consecutive trials is performed in a seated position with the elbow held at a 90 degree angle and the highest value is recorded. A higher value indicate higher upper limb strength.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Lower limb muscle strength</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 3 months and 6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Five repetition sit to stand test. From a seated position, the participant is instructed to stand up and then sit down again for a total of five times. The total time of five repetition sit to stand cycles is then recorded in seconds with a stopwatch. A lower total time indicate higher lower limb muscle strength.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Health related quality of life</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 3 months and 6 months</time_frame>
    <description>RAND-36 health survey will be used (RAND is not an acronym but the name of a research corporation). The RAND-36 survey contains 36 questions belonging to eight health concepts that can be further categorized into two summary scores; physical and mental health. The answers from the survey is re-coded into points in where higher points indicate better perceived health. The points, ranging from 0 to 100, are then presented for the different concepts, the two summary scores and the overall score for the 36 questions.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Self-reported exercise and physical activity</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 3 months and 6 months</time_frame>
    <description>One question regarding exercise and one question regarding every day physical activity in a typical week. The question regarding exercise comprises 6 answer alternatives ranging from 0 min to more than 120 min per week. The question regarding every day physical activity comprises 7 answer alternatives raging from 0 min to more than 300 min per week. The questions are produced by the Swedish National Board of Health and Welfare.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Motivational stages of self-determination for exercise</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 3 months and 6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Behavioral Regulation in Exercise Questionnaire-2 (BREQ-2) will be used. The questionnaire contains 19 questions, belonging to one of the five categories Amotivation, External regulation, Introjected regulation, Identified regulation and Intrinsic regulation. The scale assesses where a person is on the continuum of self-determination in where higher, positive scores indicate greater relative autonomy; lower, negative scores indicate more controlled regulation.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Confidence in one's own ability to exercise</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 3 months and 6 months</time_frame>
    <description>The Swedish Exercise Self-Efficacy Scale (ESES-S) will be used. The questionnaire comprises 10 questions on exercise self-efficacy, each with four answer alternatives. The composite score ranges from 10 to 40 and a higher score indicate a higher precised self-efficacy towards exercise.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Basic psychological needs connected to physical activity satisfaction</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months and 6 months</time_frame>
    <description>The Basic Psychological Needs in Exercise Scale (BPNES) will be used. This questionnaire contains 12 questions related to one of three basic psychological needs; Autonomy, Competence and Relatedness in the exercise domain. Answers are given on a five point Likert scale and results are presented for the individual needs and as a collective, global need. The maximal score for each question is 5 and the minimal score is 1. Mean values for each need is presented together with a mean score of all 12 questions. A higher score indicate a higher need fulfillment.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Feasibility of the exercise intervention</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months</time_frame>
    <description>Semi-structured qualitative individual interviews will be conducted with the exercise intervention group to explore the user experience of the participants</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Exploring barriers and facilitators towards physical activity</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Semi-structured qualitative individual interviews will be conducted in both groups</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">20</enrollment>
  <condition>Physical Inactivity</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Exercise intervention</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants are prescribed a Physical activity on Prescription (PaP) which means that they will have a motivational interview with a physiotherapist regarding increased physical activity. The physiotherapist will then prescribe a individualized PaP with the goal to increase weekly physical activity that the participant are instructed to adhere to for the remainder of the study. A follow-up session is also included after 12 weeks.&#xD;
Participants are invited to a 12 week exercise intervention at a private fitness center after they have received their PaP. The exercise, including a variety of aerobic and resistance training, is performed in a group setting starting with one session per week for the first three weeks and then two sessions per week for week 4-12. A follow-up session is also included after 12 weeks.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Exercise intervention</intervention_name>
    <description>The 6 month intervention consists of usual care (PaP) plus an initial 12 weeks of instructor led exercise (described below) followed by a 12 week period in where the participant will have to conduct their physical activity on their own.&#xD;
Exercise intervention:&#xD;
Participants are invited to a 12 week exercise intervention at a private fitness center after they have received their PaP. The exercise, including a variety of aerobic and resistance training, is performed in a group setting starting with one session per week for the first three weeks and then two sessions per week for week 4-12. A follow-up session is also included after 12 weeks in where a physiotherapist contact the participant and discuss how they will adhere to their Physical activity on prescription.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Exercise intervention</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Physically inactive persons as defined as not meeting the current recommendations of&#xD;
             at least 150 minutes of moderate to vigorous physical activity per week. This&#xD;
             criterion is self-assessed by potential participants.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Age 40-60 years&#xD;
&#xD;
        Exclusion Criteria:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Physical disability that affects the ability to perform the exercise intervention.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Heart failure or severe degenerative disease, e.g. malignant cancer, multiple&#xD;
             sclerosis etc.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Myocardial infarction or stroke during the last 12 months.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Heart conditions including angina pectoris that is worsened with exercise.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Neuromuscular, musculoskeletal, or rheumatic conditions that is worsened with&#xD;
             exercise.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Hypertension grade III, i.e. systolic blood pressure above 180 mmHg and/or diastolic&#xD;
             blood pressure over 110 mmHg.&#xD;
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>40 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>60 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Umeå University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Umeå</city>
        <state>Västerbotten</state>
        <zip>SE-90187</zip>
        <country>Sweden</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Sweden</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2023</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>December 21, 2022</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 10, 2023</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">January 20, 2023</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 17, 2023</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 17, 2023</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 18, 2023</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Umeå University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Andreas Hult</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Associate Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Physical inactivity</keyword>
  <keyword>Exercise Referral Scheme</keyword>
  <keyword>Physical activity on Prescription</keyword>
  <keyword>Exercise intervention</keyword>
  <keyword>Feasibility study</keyword>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>Sharing of individual data is not in accordance with the ethical permission granted from the Swedish ethics review authority.</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

