<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="9323">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 09, 2023</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT05700461</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>22-492</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT05700461</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Drug Screening Using Novel IMD in Renal Cell Carcinoma</brief_title>
  <official_title>Pilot Study of an Implantable Microdevice for in Situ Evaluation of Drug Response in Renal Cell Carcinoma</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Wenxin Xu</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Dana-Farber Cancer Institute</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This research is being done to study the safety and feasibility of implanting and retrieving&#xD;
      a microdevice that releases microdoses of 19 specific drugs or drug combinations as a&#xD;
      possible tool to evaluate the effectiveness of several cancer drugs against metastatic renal&#xD;
      cell carcinoma (RCC).&#xD;
&#xD;
      The name of the intervention(s) involved in this study are:&#xD;
&#xD;
        -  Implantable Microdevice (IMD)&#xD;
&#xD;
        -  Surgery (excision of tumor)&#xD;
&#xD;
        -  Drugs used in this study will only include drugs already used as standard of care for&#xD;
           the treatment of metastatic renal cell carcinoma (RCC)&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This Pilot research is being done to study the safety and feasibility of implanting and&#xD;
      retrieving a microdevice that releases microdoses of 19 specific drugs or drug combinations&#xD;
      as a possible tool to evaluate the effectiveness of several cancer drugs against metastatic&#xD;
      renal cell carcinoma (RCC). The drugs participants receive will include medications currently&#xD;
      used as standard-of-care treatment for metastatic RCC as well as medications currently&#xD;
      approved in other cancer types that are under investigation for treatment of RCC.&#xD;
&#xD;
        -  This study involves planting 1 to 6 microdevices, each small enough to fit inside the&#xD;
           tip of a needle, into a tumor. The microdevices will release microdoses of cancer drugs&#xD;
           via passive diffusion. The drugs will only penetrate the local tumor tissues.&#xD;
&#xD;
        -  After approximately 3 days, the microdevices and small regions of surrounding tissues&#xD;
           will be removed and analyzed.&#xD;
&#xD;
      The research study procedures include screening for eligibility, study imaging and&#xD;
      evaluations, blood collections, tumor biopsies, and follow up visits.&#xD;
&#xD;
      The U.S. Food and Drug Administration (FDA) has not approved the microdevice as a treatment&#xD;
      for any disease.&#xD;
&#xD;
      The drugs being used have been FDA-approved for the treatment of cancers.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Participation in this research study is expected to last up to 4 months.&#xD;
&#xD;
      It is expected that about 5 people will take part in this research study.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">July 2023</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">October 2, 2025</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">October 2, 2023</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>N/A</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of Patients with Safe Microdevice Procedure</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 45 days</time_frame>
    <description>Defined by any grade 3-5 adverse event (AE) associated with microdevice placement or retrieval (attribution possible or higher) based on CTCAEv5.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of Patients with Feasible Microdevice Procedure</measure>
    <time_frame>72 hours</time_frame>
    <description>Defined as technical success of microdevice placement and microdevice retrieval from the surgery specimen plus having sufficient amount and quality of tissue for histopathology analysis and interpretation of at least 50% of the microdevice reservoirs.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">5</enrollment>
  <condition>Renal Cell Carcinoma</condition>
  <condition>Metastatic Renal Cell Carcinoma</condition>
  <condition>Kidney Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Implantable microdevice (IMD) + Biopsy + Standard of Care Treatment</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants with confirmed or suspected metastatic Renal Cell Carcinoma (RCC) and who are candidates for standard of care metastatectomy or debulking/consolidative nephrectomy will be selected for study participation and will undergo study procedures as outlined:&#xD;
Placement of 1-6 microdevice(s) 72 +/- 24 hours prior to scheduled, standard of care surgery. The number of microdevices implanted into a tumor will be made on a case-by-case basis based on tumor and participant factors before and during the procedure.&#xD;
At the time of standard of care surgery, surgical removal of microdevice(s) along with surrounding tumor tissue.&#xD;
Monitoring for safety endpoints during inpatient stay and at a follow-up clinic visit.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Combination Product</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Implantable Microdevice (IMD)</intervention_name>
    <description>Small, implantable device with 20 microreservoirs for drug and drug combinations, via needle, percutaneously, and guided by interventional radiologic techniques.&#xD;
Drugs include all or a subset of the following: Cabozantinib, Pazopanib, Lenvatinib, Axitinib, Ipilimumab, Nivolumab, Pembrolizumab, Carboplatin, Paclitaxel, Abemaciclib, Gemcitabine, Everolimus, Belzutifan, Cabozantinib + nivolumab, Cabozantinib + belzutifan, Ipilimumab + nivolumab, Lenvatinib + pembrolizumab, Lenvatinib + everolimus, Abemaciclib + belzutifan, and Tivozanib.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Implantable microdevice (IMD) + Biopsy + Standard of Care Treatment</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Patients must have the ability to understand and the willingness to sign a written&#xD;
             informed consent document.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Participants must have confirmed or suspected metastatic renal cell carcinoma, and&#xD;
             must be planned for either nephrectomy or metastatectomy as part of their clinical&#xD;
             care. The lesion planned for excision must be at least 1cm in size.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Participants must be 18 years of age or older.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Participants must be evaluated by a medical oncologist who will determine the&#xD;
             clinically appropriate treatment strategy based on clinical history and extent of&#xD;
             disease.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Patients must be deemed medically stable to undergo both percutaneous procedures and&#xD;
             standard-of-care surgical procedures.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Participants will undergo laboratory testing within 30 days prior to the procedure (or&#xD;
             within 72 hours if there has been a change in the clinical status since the initial&#xD;
             blood draw). Patients must have absolute neutrophil count ≥1,000/mcL, platelets&#xD;
             ≥50,000/mcL, PT (INR) 1.5 and PTT &lt;1.5x control.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Participants must have undergone CT or MRI that assesses the extent of disease and&#xD;
             allows the research team to assess for study eligibility. This will have been done as&#xD;
             part of the standard-of-care.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  The participant's case must be reviewed by representatives of interventional radiology&#xD;
             and the appropriate surgical subspecialty to assess the following factors:&#xD;
&#xD;
               -  Patient is clinically stable to undergo microdevice implantation and surgical&#xD;
                  procedures&#xD;
&#xD;
               -  Patient has sufficient volume of disease to allow implantation of the microdevice&#xD;
&#xD;
               -  Patient has a lesion for which the microdevice is a) amenable to percutaneous&#xD;
                  placement, and b) amenable to removal at the time of surgery&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Patients must be willing to undergo research-related genetic sequencing (somatic and&#xD;
             germline) and data management, including the deposition of de-identified genetic&#xD;
             sequencing data in NIH central data repositories.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Exclusion Criteria:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Uncontrolled intercurrent illness including, but not limited to, ongoing or active&#xD;
             infection, symptomatic congestive heart failure, unstable angina pectoris, unstable&#xD;
             cardiac arrhythmia, or psychiatric illness/social situations that would limit the&#xD;
             safety of a biopsy and/or surgery.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Uncorrectable bleeding or coagulation disorder known to cause increased risk with&#xD;
             surgical or biopsy procedures (detailed below).&#xD;
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Wenxin Xu, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Dana-Farber Cancer Institute</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Wenxin Xu, MD</last_name>
    <phone>617-632-6534</phone>
    <email>Wenxin_Xu1@dfci.harvard.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Dana-Farber Cancer Institute</name>
      <address>
        <city>Boston</city>
        <state>Massachusetts</state>
        <zip>02215</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Wenxin Xu, MD</last_name>
      <phone>617-632-6534</phone>
      <email>Wenxin_Xu1@dfci.harvard.edu</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>January 2023</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>January 17, 2023</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 17, 2023</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">January 26, 2023</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 17, 2023</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 17, 2023</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">January 26, 2023</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor-Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Dana-Farber Cancer Institute</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Wenxin Xu</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Principal Investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Renal Cell Carcinoma</keyword>
  <keyword>Metastatic Renal Cell Carcinoma</keyword>
  <keyword>Kidney Cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>Suspected Renal Cell Carcinoma</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Carcinoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Carcinoma, Renal Cell</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Kidney Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Yes</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>The Dana-Farber / Harvard Cancer Center encourages and supports the responsible and ethical sharing of data from clinical trials. De-identified participant data from the final research dataset used in the published manuscript may only be shared under the terms of a Data Use Agreement. Requests may be directed to: [contact information for Sponsor Investigator or designee]. The protocol and statistical analysis plan will be made available on Clinicaltrials.gov only as required by federal regulation or as a condition of awards and agreements supporting the research.</ipd_description>
    <ipd_info_type>Study Protocol</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_info_type>Statistical Analysis Plan (SAP)</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_info_type>Informed Consent Form (ICF)</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_time_frame>Data can be shared no earlier than 1 year following the date of publication.</ipd_time_frame>
    <ipd_access_criteria>Contact the Partners Innovations team at http://www.partners.org/innovation.</ipd_access_criteria>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

