<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="9470">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 09, 2023</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT05697094</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>119431</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT05697094</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Impact of Meditation on Reducing Stress in Glaucoma Patients During COVID-19 Pandemic</brief_title>
  <official_title>Impact of Meditation on Reducing Stress in Glaucoma Patients During COVID-19 Pandemic: An Electronic Pilot Feasibility Study</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Lawson Health Research Institute</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Lawson Health Research Institute</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Visually impaired seniors are susceptible to having lower Quality of Life (QOL)1-4. The&#xD;
      current situation-specific stressors including the fear of contracting COVID-19, prolonged&#xD;
      periods of self-isolation, reduced mobility, greater dependence on caregivers or family&#xD;
      members, reduced or no social interactions, inability to visit clinics for non-emergency&#xD;
      treatments and surgeries, and financial uncertainty may further deteriorate the QOL of&#xD;
      seniors with eye diseases. In this study, patients with moderate glaucoma aged 65 and above&#xD;
      will be randomized to Art of Meditation (AOM) plus Treatment as usual (TAU) or TAU alone to&#xD;
      assess the changes in Health-related quality of life (HRQoL). Patients in the AOM group will&#xD;
      be taught a meditation technique by trained instructors while the patients in the TAU group&#xD;
      continue to receive standard of care. It is hypothesized that it's feasible to assess the&#xD;
      effects of AOM in a sample of glaucoma patients during COVID-19 pandemic, and that glaucoma&#xD;
      patients will experience enhanced QOL, reduced depression and anxiety, and improved sleep&#xD;
      quality by participating in the AOM intervention.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">May 1, 2023</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">April 30, 2024</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">April 30, 2024</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Supportive Care</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Participant)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in health-related quality of life (HRQoL)</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 0, week 4</time_frame>
    <description>HRQoL is an essential measure of quality of life related to health; it helps physician identify hidden morbidity in clinical care as well as improves patient-physician communications. HRQoL will be measured using time trade-off questionnaire.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Visual Function Score</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 0, week 4</time_frame>
    <description>Visual Function score will be measured using Visual Function Questionnaire (VFQ-25).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Depression</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 0, week 4</time_frame>
    <description>Depression is a feeling of severe despondency and dejection. Depression will be measured using the Center for Epidemiological Studies - Depression (CES-D) score.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Anxiety</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 0, week 4</time_frame>
    <description>Anxiety will be measured using Hospital Anxiety and Depression Scale - Anxiety (HADS-A) subscale</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Sleep quality</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 0, week 4</time_frame>
    <description>Sleep quality as measured using the Pittsburgh Sleep Quality Index (PSQI) scores.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">50</enrollment>
  <condition>Glaucoma</condition>
  <condition>Depression</condition>
  <condition>Anxiety</condition>
  <condition>Sleep Disorder</condition>
  <condition>Quality of Life</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Art of Meditation</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Art of Meditation (AOM) is a type of meditation that helps quiet the mind and induces physiological and mental relaxation whilst the eyes are shut. It utilizes a specific sound value (mantra) to draw attention inward and permit the mind to experience a restful but alert state of consciousness. Participants will receive three weekly online instructions (90 minutes each) by trained instructors in addition to standard care.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment as Usual</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>The usual standard of care for patients with glaucoma includes starting them on first line of drugs. Participants will be initiated and maintained on appropriate dosages of such medications as part of standard of care. The usual standard of care also includes an ophthalmic examination measuring best-corrected Snellen VA and pinhole acuities and a follow-up visit once a year.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Art of Meditation</intervention_name>
    <description>Art of Meditation (AOM) is a type of meditation that helps quiet the mind and induces physiological and mental relaxation whilst the eyes are shut. It utilizes a specific sound value (mantra) to draw attention inward and permit the mind to experience a restful but alert state of consciousness.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Art of Meditation</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Sahaj Samadhi Meditation</other_name>
    <other_name>Automatic Self-Transcending Meditation</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria&#xD;
&#xD;
          1. Patients diagnosed with glaucoma by an experienced ophthalmologist.&#xD;
&#xD;
          2. Patients aged 65 and above.&#xD;
&#xD;
          3. Be able to provide valid informed consent to participate in the research study.&#xD;
&#xD;
          4. Being able to read and understand English.&#xD;
&#xD;
          5. Having no significant self-reported or physician-diagnosed mental health disorder.&#xD;
&#xD;
          6. Access to technology to participate in virtual AOM sessions.&#xD;
&#xD;
          7. Able to sit comfortably for 90 minutes without any major pain or discomfort, hear well&#xD;
             enough to follow verbal instructions when the eyes are closed, and be in good general&#xD;
             physical health.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Exclusion Criteria&#xD;
&#xD;
          1. Inability to provide a valid informed consent.&#xD;
&#xD;
          2. Significant communication barriers or lack of English proficiency that prevents&#xD;
             participants from completing the questionnaires.&#xD;
&#xD;
          3. Severe depression as confirmed by a CES-D ≥ 24.&#xD;
&#xD;
          4. Having a lifetime diagnosis of self-reported other serious mental disorders, including&#xD;
             bipolar I or II disorder, primary psychotic disorder (schizophrenia, schizoaffective&#xD;
             disorder, schizophreniform disorder, delusional disorder).&#xD;
&#xD;
          5. Self-reported substance abuse or dependence within the past 3 months.&#xD;
&#xD;
          6. Having an acutely unstable medical illnesses, including delirium or acute&#xD;
             cerebrovascular or cardiovascular events within the last 6 months.&#xD;
&#xD;
          7. Having irreversible vision loss that prevents one from completing the questionnaires.&#xD;
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>65 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Monali Malvankar, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>5196858500</phone>
    <phone_ext>61288</phone_ext>
    <email>monali.malvankar@schulich.uwo.ca</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>St. Joseph's Hospital, Ivey Eye Institute</name>
      <address>
        <city>London</city>
        <state>Ontario</state>
        <zip>N6G0H8</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Canada</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Atreya CE, Kubo A, Borno HT, Rosenthal B, Campanella M, Rettger JP, Joseph G, Allen IE, Venook AP, Altschuler A, Dhruva A. Being Present: A single-arm feasibility study of audio-based mindfulness meditation for colorectal cancer patients and caregivers. PLoS One. 2018 Jul 23;13(7):e0199423. doi: 10.1371/journal.pone.0199423. eCollection 2018.</citation>
    <PMID>30036361</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Yunesian M, Aslani A, Vash JH, Yazdi AB. Effects of Transcendental Meditation on mental health: a before-after study. Clin Pract Epidemiol Ment Health. 2008 Nov 1;4:25. doi: 10.1186/1745-0179-4-25.</citation>
    <PMID>18976496</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>January 2023</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>June 25, 2021</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 20, 2023</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">January 25, 2023</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 20, 2023</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 20, 2023</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">January 25, 2023</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Health-related quality of life</keyword>
  <keyword>Glaucoma</keyword>
  <keyword>COVID-19</keyword>
  <keyword>Meditation</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>COVID-19</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Sleep Wake Disorders</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Glaucoma</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>De-identified individual participant data (IPD) collected in this study will not be available to other researchers (e.g., outside the primary research group). Since the primary research group has the necessary expertise to analyze the data and do not need any outside help.</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

