<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="9747">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 09, 2023</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT05691140</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>13902</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT05691140</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Prevention of Postpartum Anxiety in High-Risk Women</brief_title>
  <official_title>Prevention of Postpartum Anxiety in High-Risk Women: A Proof-of-Concept Randomized Clinical Trial</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>St. Joseph's Healthcare Hamilton</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>St. Joseph's Healthcare Hamilton</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The primary aim of this study is to evaluate whether a CBT group designed to target IU&#xD;
      (CBT-IU) in pregnant women with heightened levels of IU, prevents postpartum anxiety. The&#xD;
      investigators hypothesize that women with clinically significant IU during pregnancy will&#xD;
      exhibit both significant reductions in IU, as well as a decrease in anxiety symptoms&#xD;
      postpartum, compared to a treatment as usual control group. The secondary aim of this study&#xD;
      is to evaluate whether CBT-IU significantly improves and/or prevents depression symptoms,&#xD;
      worry symptom severity, and difficulties with emotion regulation. The investigators&#xD;
      hypothesize that CBT-IU will lead to significant improvements in symptom severity compared to&#xD;
      the treatment as usual control group.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Anxiety disorders are a serious mental health concern, affecting as many as 15-24% of women&#xD;
      during the perinatal period. Despite the high prevalence of anxiety during the perinatal&#xD;
      period and its associated impact, fewer than 15% of women receive treatment often due to&#xD;
      difficulties in timely and accurate symptom detection. Our group conducted a longitudinal&#xD;
      study that investigated the psychosocial and biological risk factors of postpartum anxiety&#xD;
      worsening in a sample of high-risk pregnant women with pre-existing anxiety and depressive&#xD;
      disorders. In this study, intolerance of uncertainty (IU) was identified as the strongest&#xD;
      predictor. IU is a cardinal trait of anxiety and has been implicated in predicting treatment&#xD;
      response in non-perinatal populations. However, despite the relevance of IU in anxiety&#xD;
      disorders, our study was the first to assess IU in the perinatal population. As improving&#xD;
      symptom detection through identification of significant risk factors, such as IU, can aid in&#xD;
      the development of preventative and treatment measures, our group recently validated the&#xD;
      Intolerance of Uncertainty Scale (IUS) in a perinatal population for the detection of anxiety&#xD;
      disorders. In this study of 198 perinatal women, the IUS demonstrated excellent internal&#xD;
      consistency and an optimal clinical cut-off score of 64 or greater was established, yielding&#xD;
      a sensitivity of 89%. The IUS also demonstrated very good positive (79%) and negative (80%)&#xD;
      predictive values. These findings suggest that the IUS represents a clinically useful&#xD;
      screening tool to be used as an aid for the early and accurate detection of anxiety disorders&#xD;
      during the perinatal period. Cognitive Behavioural Therapy (CBT) is considered a first-line&#xD;
      treatment for perinatal anxiety disorders and CBT programs targeting IU have revealed&#xD;
      promising findings in non-perinatal populations.It is therefore imperative to investigate&#xD;
      whether a treatment program specifically designed to target IU during pregnancy can prevent&#xD;
      postpartum anxiety.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">October 1, 2022</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">October 1, 2024</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">October 1, 2024</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of participants with principal anxiety disorder (as per DSM-5)</measure>
    <time_frame>6-12 weeks postpartum</time_frame>
    <description>Postpartum anxiety prevention will be defined as whether participants meet provisional DSM-5 diagnostic criteria for an anxiety disorder at the post-treatment assessments.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">30</enrollment>
  <condition>Postpartum Anxiety</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Cognitive Behavioural Therapy</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment as Usual</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Cognitive Behavioural Therapy</intervention_name>
    <description>Cognitive Behavioural Therapy targeting Intolerance of Uncertainty</description>
    <arm_group_label>Cognitive Behavioural Therapy</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Pregnant women (up to 30 weeks pregnant to allow for completion of the CBT-IU protocol&#xD;
             before child delivery)&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  18 years or older&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Baseline score of ≥64 on the IUS (Furtado et al., 2021)&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  No psychotropic medication or, if taking medication, no change in dose or type for a&#xD;
             minimum of 6 weeks prior to baseline&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  No concurrent psychological treatment&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Fluent in English and able to consent for treatment&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Located in Ontario, Canada&#xD;
&#xD;
        Exclusion Criteria:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  A current diagnosed DSM-5 anxiety disorder, as assessed by the Mini International&#xD;
             Neuropsychiatric Interview (version 7.0.2)&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Active suicidal ideation&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Current psychosis or substance use disorder&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  For those enrolled on a stable dosage of a psychotropic medication, if a change in&#xD;
             medication is required during the psychological therapy trial, the participant will&#xD;
             continue with the therapy but will be excluded from the analysis.&#xD;
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Sheryl M Green, PhD, CPsych</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>St. Joseph's Healthcare Hamilton</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Melissa Furtado, MSc, PhD (candidate)</last_name>
    <phone>905-522-1155</phone>
    <phone_ext>36369</phone_ext>
    <email>mfurtado@stjoes.ca</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Sheryl M. Green, PhD, CPsych</last_name>
    <phone>905-522-1155</phone>
    <phone_ext>33672</phone_ext>
    <email>sgreen@stjoes.ca</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>St. Joseph's Healthcare Hamilton</name>
      <address>
        <city>Hamilton</city>
        <state>Ontario</state>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Sheryl M Green, PhD, CPsych</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Canada</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Dennis CL, Falah-Hassani K, Shiri R. Prevalence of antenatal and postnatal anxiety: systematic review and meta-analysis. Br J Psychiatry. 2017 May;210(5):315-323. doi: 10.1192/bjp.bp.116.187179. Epub 2017 Mar 16.</citation>
    <PMID>28302701</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Furtado M, Frey BN, Green SM. Validation of the intolerance of uncertainty scale as a screening tool for perinatal anxiety. BMC Pregnancy Childbirth. 2021 Dec 14;21(1):829. doi: 10.1186/s12884-021-04296-1.</citation>
    <PMID>34903196</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Smith MV, Shao L, Howell H, Wang H, Poschman K, Yonkers KA. Success of mental health referral among pregnant and postpartum women with psychiatric distress. Gen Hosp Psychiatry. 2009 Mar-Apr;31(2):155-62. doi: 10.1016/j.genhosppsych.2008.10.002. Epub 2008 Dec 3.</citation>
    <PMID>19269536</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Furtado M, Van Lieshout RJ, Van Ameringen M, Green SM, Frey BN. Biological and psychosocial predictors of anxiety worsening in the postpartum period: A longitudinal study. J Affect Disord. 2019 May 1;250:218-225. doi: 10.1016/j.jad.2019.02.064. Epub 2019 Mar 1.</citation>
    <PMID>30870771</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Dugas MJ, Ladouceur R. Treatment of GAD. Targeting intolerance of uncertainty in two types of worry. Behav Modif. 2000 Oct;24(5):635-57. doi: 10.1177/0145445500245002.</citation>
    <PMID>11036732</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>van der Heiden C, Muris P, van der Molen HT. Randomized controlled trial on the effectiveness of metacognitive therapy and intolerance-of-uncertainty therapy for generalized anxiety disorder. Behav Res Ther. 2012 Feb;50(2):100-9. doi: 10.1016/j.brat.2011.12.005. Epub 2011 Dec 21.</citation>
    <PMID>22222208</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>April 2023</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>January 10, 2023</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 10, 2023</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">January 19, 2023</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 11, 2023</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 11, 2023</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">April 14, 2023</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>St. Joseph's Healthcare Hamilton</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Sheryl Green</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Clinical Psychologist, Principal Investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Anxiety Disorders</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

