<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="9248">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 09, 2023</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT05702021</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>STU00217287</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>P50DA054072</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT05702021</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Implementing Contingency Management for Stimulant Use in Specialty Addiction Treatment Organizations</brief_title>
  <acronym>MIMIC2</acronym>
  <official_title>Implementing Contingency Management for Stimulant Use in Specialty Addiction Treatment Organizations (Center for Dissemination and Implementation Science at Stanford, Research Component #2)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Northwestern University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Institute on Drug Abuse (NIDA)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Stanford University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Ohio State University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Northwestern University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Stimulants constitute a new and deadly fourth wave of the opioid epidemic. Contingency&#xD;
      management is the most effective intervention for stimulant use and is an evidence-based&#xD;
      adjunct to medication for opioid use disorder. Yet, uptake of contingency management in&#xD;
      opioid treatment programs that provide medication for opioid use disorder remains low; in&#xD;
      fact, access to contingency management is arguably one of the greatest research-to-practice&#xD;
      gaps in the addiction treatment services field. The goal of this study is to conduct a type&#xD;
      III hybrid effectiveness-implementation trial to evaluate a multi-level implementation&#xD;
      strategy, the Science of Service Laboratory, to install contingency management for stimulant&#xD;
      use in opioid treatment programs. The Science of Service Laboratory has three core&#xD;
      components: didactic training, performance feedback, and external facilitation.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Utilizing a stepped wedge design, a regional cohort of 10 public sector opioid treatment&#xD;
      programs will be randomized to receive Science of Service Laboratory at five distinct time&#xD;
      points. At six intervals, each of the 10 opioid treatment programs will provide de-identified&#xD;
      electronic medical record data from all available patient charts on contingency management&#xD;
      delivery and patient outcomes. Staff from each opioid treatment program will provide feedback&#xD;
      on contextual determinants influencing implementation. This study will rigorously evaluate&#xD;
      whether a multi-level implementation strategy developed by one of the longest-standing&#xD;
      national intermediary purveyor organizations-the SAMHSA Technology Transfer Centers, will&#xD;
      improve both implementation and patient outcomes.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Stimulant use among persons with opioid use disorder is associated with an array of serious&#xD;
      consequences. Among those with opioid use disorder, stimulant use has been associated with&#xD;
      more persistent opioid use; higher risk of HIV infection; higher levels of family, medical,&#xD;
      legal, and vocational problems; and increased risk of fatal overdose. Contingency management&#xD;
      is an evidence-based intervention for stimulant use and an evidence-based adjunct to&#xD;
      medication for opioid use disorders. Medication for opioid use disorder is the first-line,&#xD;
      evidence-based treatment for opioid use disorder, but does not specifically reduce stimulant&#xD;
      use, and there are not yet efficacious medications for stimulant addiction. Moreover,&#xD;
      individuals who continue to use stimulants while receiving medication for opioid use disorder&#xD;
      have worse treatment response in terms of both retention and abstinence from opioids.&#xD;
      Contingency management targets stimulant use via reinforcing incentives for attaining&#xD;
      abstinence. Despite an abundance of research evidence, contingency management uptake in&#xD;
      opioid treatment programs remains low due to barriers at both the provider- and&#xD;
      organizational-levels. Effectively addressing the contingency management evidence-to-practice&#xD;
      gap could advance both the field of implementation science and the quality of care in&#xD;
      specialty addiction treatment settings. This project evaluates a multi-level implementation&#xD;
      strategy, the Science to Service Laboratory, to install contingency management for stimulant&#xD;
      use in opioid treatment programs. The Science of Service Laboratory employs three core&#xD;
      components: didactic training; performance feedback; and external facilitation.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Utilizing a fully powered type III hybrid effectiveness-implementation trial with a stepped&#xD;
      wedge design, we will randomize a cohort of 10 public sector opioid treatment programs in New&#xD;
      England to receive the Science of Service Laboratory at five time points. Data collection&#xD;
      will leverage multiple sources. At six intervals, each of the 10 opioid treatment programs&#xD;
      will extract de-identified electronic medical record data on contingency management&#xD;
      implementation and patient outcomes. In addition, opioid treatment program staff will report&#xD;
      on contextual determinants of implementation. Results will evaluate whether a multi-level&#xD;
      implementation strategy initially developed by one of the longest-standing intermediary&#xD;
      purveyor organizations (SAMHSA Technology Transfer Centers), will improve implementation and&#xD;
      patient outcomes. In addition, the project will ensure equitable service provision to&#xD;
      diverse, high-risk patients while advancing implementation science via specification and&#xD;
      evaluation of contextual determinants.&#xD;
&#xD;
      The Specific Aims and corresponding hypotheses are:&#xD;
&#xD;
      Specific Aim 1: To test the effectiveness of the Science of Service Laboratory on&#xD;
      implementation outcomes, including contingency management Reach, Adoption, and&#xD;
      Implementation.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Specific Aim 2: To test the effectiveness of the Science of Service Laboratory on patient&#xD;
      outcomes, including: Stimulant Abstinence and Treatment Retention.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">April 1, 2023</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">August 1, 2027</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">April 1, 2027</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Crossover Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Stepped-wedge trial</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Health Services Research</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
    <masking_description>Outcomes will be exported from electronic medical records. Data analysts will not know who was receiving the intervention at what time point.</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in percent of patients receiving contingency management from pre-implementation to post-implementation</measure>
    <time_frame>10 months</time_frame>
    <description>This is an implementation outcome capturing Reach and is extracted from electronic medical records. This is a patient-level measure of the change in the percent of newly inducted patients with a history of stimulant use who are documented as having received 1 or more contingency management sessions from pre-implementation to post-implementation.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in percent of counselors delivering contingency management from pre-implementation to post-implementation</measure>
    <time_frame>10 months</time_frame>
    <description>This is an implementation outcome capturing Adoption and is extracted from electronic medical records. This is a provider-level measure of the change in percent of counselors at each program who are documented as having delivered 1 or more contingency management sessions from pre-implementation to post-implementation.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in the percent of toxicology screens negative for stimulants</measure>
    <time_frame>10 months</time_frame>
    <description>This is a patient-level outcome measuring Stimulant Abstinence and is extracted from electronic medical records. This measures the change in percent of toxicology screens that are negative for stimulants from pre-implementation to post-implementation.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in number of contingency management sessions</measure>
    <time_frame>10 months</time_frame>
    <description>This is a patient-level outcome measuring Contingency Management Treatment Retention and is extracted from electronic medical records. This measures the change in the number of contingency management sessions received per patient from pre-implementation to post-implementation.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">76</enrollment>
  <condition>Stimulant Use (Diagnosis)</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Science of Service Laboratory implementation strategy</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>The Science of Service Laboratory implementation strategy consists of: didactic training (contingency management workshops; monthly contingency management coaching calls), performance feedback (practice sessions and electronic medical record feedback); and facilitation (monthly facilitation calls).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Stepped wedge comparator</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>Our hybrid trial uses a unidirectional crossover stepped wedge design. All sites cross over in the same direction from usual care to intervention. All sites therefore act as their own comparison prior to the sequential roll-out of the implementation strategy.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Science to Service Laboratory</intervention_name>
    <description>The Science of Service Laboratory implementation strategy consists of: didactic training (contingency management workshops; monthly contingency management coaching calls), performance feedback (practice sessions and electronic medical record feedback); and facilitation (monthly facilitation calls).</description>
    <arm_group_label>Science of Service Laboratory implementation strategy</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        -  Opioid Treatment Program Counselors:&#xD;
&#xD;
               -  Inclusion criteria: 1) provide ongoing psychosocial support to medication for&#xD;
                  opioid use disorder patients (e.g., intake sessions, individual counseling,&#xD;
                  and/or group counseling sessions), and 2) have an active caseload&#xD;
&#xD;
               -  Exclusion criteria: Younger than 18 years of age, unable to provide informed&#xD;
                  consent&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Persons on Medication for Opioid Use Disorder [Not recruited, via electronic medical&#xD;
             records only]&#xD;
&#xD;
               -  Inclusion criteria: must be newly initiated on medication for opioid use&#xD;
                  disorders (within the past 30 days) and have concurrent stimulant use (indicated&#xD;
                  by self-report of past 30-day stimulant use or positive toxicology screen within&#xD;
                  30 days).&#xD;
&#xD;
               -  Exclusion criteria: Younger than 18 years of age, Does not have electronic&#xD;
                  medical records&#xD;
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Sara Becker</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Northwestern University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Executive Administrator</last_name>
    <phone>800-862-2181</phone>
    <email>darcie.boiano@rootcenter.org</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Chief Medical Officer</last_name>
    <phone>800-862-2181</phone>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Root Center for Advanced Recovery- Bristol Clinic</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bristol</city>
        <state>Connecticut</state>
        <zip>06010</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Research Coordinator</last_name>
      <phone>800-862-2181</phone>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Root Center for Advanced Recovery: Doctors Clinic</name>
      <address>
        <city>Hartford</city>
        <state>Connecticut</state>
        <zip>06106</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Research Coordinator</last_name>
      <phone>800-862-2181</phone>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Root Center for Advanced Recovery: Henderson/Johnson Clinic</name>
      <address>
        <city>Hartford</city>
        <state>Connecticut</state>
        <zip>06120</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Research Coordinator</last_name>
      <phone>800-862-2181</phone>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Root Center for Advanced Recovery: Manchester</name>
      <address>
        <city>Manchester</city>
        <state>Connecticut</state>
        <zip>06040</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Gabrielle Research Coordinator</last_name>
      <phone>800-862-2181</phone>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Root Center for Advanced Recovery: Middletown Clinic</name>
      <address>
        <city>Middletown</city>
        <state>Connecticut</state>
        <zip>06457</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Research Coordinator</last_name>
      <phone>800-862-2181</phone>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Root Center for Advanced Recovery: New Britain</name>
      <address>
        <city>New Britain</city>
        <state>Connecticut</state>
        <zip>06051</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Research Coordinator</last_name>
      <phone>800-862-2181</phone>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Root Center for Advanced Recovery: New London Clinic</name>
      <address>
        <city>New London</city>
        <state>Connecticut</state>
        <zip>06320</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Research Coordinator</last_name>
      <phone>800-862-2181</phone>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Root Center for Advanced Recovery: Norwich Clinic</name>
      <address>
        <city>Norwich</city>
        <state>Connecticut</state>
        <zip>06360</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Research Coordinator</last_name>
      <phone>800-862-2181</phone>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Root Center for Advanced Recovery: Torrington Clinic</name>
      <address>
        <city>Torrington</city>
        <state>Connecticut</state>
        <zip>06790</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Research Coordinator</last_name>
      <phone>800-862-2181</phone>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Root Center for Advanced Recovery: Willimantic Clinic</name>
      <address>
        <city>Willimantic</city>
        <state>Connecticut</state>
        <zip>06226</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Research Coordinator</last_name>
      <phone>800-862-2181</phone>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>February 2023</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>January 11, 2023</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 26, 2023</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">January 27, 2023</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 21, 2023</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 21, 2023</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">February 22, 2023</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Northwestern University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Sara Becker</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Alice Hamilton Professor of Psychiatry</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Stimulants</keyword>
  <keyword>Contingency management</keyword>
  <keyword>Opioid Use Disorder</keyword>
  <keyword>Implementation science</keyword>
  <keyword>Behavior change</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Disease</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Behavior, Addictive</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Yes</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>This study protocol is embedded within a Center of Excellence funded by the National Institute on Drug Abuse. In coordination with other center project components, the study protocol and statistical analysis plan for primary outcomes will be submitted for publication to either an addiction (e.g., Addiction, Journal of Substance Abuse Treatment) or implementation science (e.g., Implementation Science, Implementation Science: Research and Practice) journal. Additional data (analytic code, participant-level data) can be requested from the Principal Investigator. Analysis files will be constructed from the electronic data and will be stripped of identifying information. Specifically, participants will be identified with a numeric identifier that is not related to any element of their personal identifying information. No names, addresses, telephone numbers, email addresses, medical record numbers, etc. will be retained in the de-identified files.</ipd_description>
    <ipd_info_type>Study Protocol</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_info_type>Statistical Analysis Plan (SAP)</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_time_frame>Protocol will be submitted for publication in coordination with other project components, with a target submission date in 2023. Analytic code and participant-level data will be made ready for distribution within 12 months of study completion.</ipd_time_frame>
    <ipd_access_criteria>Data will only be shared with external investigators when a data use agreement (DUA) is executed between Northwestern University and the requester's institution. The DUA will specify the requested data elements (each of which must be justified), the specific research question, the timeline for the project, and schedule for data destruction.</ipd_access_criteria>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

