<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="9782">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 09, 2023</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT05690295</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>DFP22-0020</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT05690295</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Resistance-type Exercise Training in Postmenopausal Women Survivors of Breast Cancer</brief_title>
  <acronym>MUSCLE-CLIM</acronym>
  <official_title>Comparison of the Effects of Prolonged Resistance-type Exercise Training Between Healthy Postmenopausal Women Versus Postmenopausal Women Survivors of Breast Cancer</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Universidad de La Frontera</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Universidad de La Frontera</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Background: In postmenopausal women, an alteration in body composition occurs as a&#xD;
      consequence of the secretion of low levels of serum estrogens by the ovaries. Observing an&#xD;
      increase in abdominal and mammary fat mass and a decrease in skeletal muscle mass, which is&#xD;
      also accompanied by loss of muscle strength and physical function, which leads early to a&#xD;
      sarcopenia.&#xD;
&#xD;
      On the other hand, the increase in estrogen production by adipose tissue has been associated&#xD;
      with an increased risk of breast cancer during menopause because the mammary parenchyma is&#xD;
      particularly sensitive to this type of estrogen. For this reason, Hormone Therapy (Aromatase&#xD;
      Inhibitors and Tamoxifen) is prescribed in women with estrogen receptor-positive breast&#xD;
      cancer. Antineoplastic treatments (Chemotherapy and Hormonal Therapy) have contributed to&#xD;
      non-metastatic breast cancer currently presenting a high survival rate, not without adverse&#xD;
      effects associated with the course of the disease, age and antineoplastic treatment,&#xD;
      affecting various systems, but particularly skeletal muscle mass.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Therefore, resistance exercise training has been proposed as an effective intervention&#xD;
      strategy to increase muscle mass and strength in different populations. However, the level of&#xD;
      muscle response to this type of training in postmenopausal women survivors of breast cancer&#xD;
      with and without hormone treatment (Aromatase Inhibitors and Tamoxifen) is unknown.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Hypothesis: The increase in skeletal muscle mass after 12 weeks of progressive&#xD;
      resistance-type exercise training is less in postmenopausal breast cancer survivors compared&#xD;
      to healthy women of the same age range.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Postmenopausal breast cancer survivors without hormonal therapy will have greater gains in&#xD;
      skeletal muscle mass compared to breast cancer survivors with Hormone Therapy (Aromatase&#xD;
      Inhibitors or Tamoxifen) of the same age range after 12 weeks of progressive resistance-type&#xD;
      exercise training.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Goals: The primary aim of this study is to compare the effects of a 12-week progressive&#xD;
      resistance-type exercise training on muscle mass (whole body muscle mass) in healthy&#xD;
      postmenopausal women versus postmenopausal women survivors of breast cancer with and without&#xD;
      Hormone Therapy (Aromatase Inhibitors and Tamoxifen).&#xD;
&#xD;
      Specific goals Determine whether resistance-type exercise training can increase muscle&#xD;
      strength and quality of life in healthy postmenopausal women versus postmenopausal women&#xD;
      survivors of breast cancer with and without Hormone Therapy (Aromatase Inhibitors and&#xD;
      Tamoxifen).&#xD;
&#xD;
      Identify whether circulating biochemical markers are up- or down-regulated in in healthy&#xD;
      postmenopausal women versus postmenopausal women survivors of breast cancer with and without&#xD;
      Hormone Therapy (Aromatase Inhibitors and Tamoxifen) after resistance-type exercise training&#xD;
&#xD;
      Methodology:&#xD;
&#xD;
      Study design Fifty-two postmenopausal women between 49 to 59 years will be divided into three&#xD;
      groups: participants without cancer (CLIMHEALTHY, n=13), participants survivors of breast&#xD;
      cancer without Hormone Therapy (CANCERWHT, n=13), participants survivors of breast cancer&#xD;
      with Aromatase Inhibitor Hormone Therapy (CANCERHT-A, n=13) and participants survivors of&#xD;
      breast cancer with Hormone Therapy with Tamoxifen (CANCERHT-T, n=13). All volunteers will be&#xD;
      subjected to 12 weeks of whole-body resistance-type exercise training (3x/wk). Before, and&#xD;
      after 12 weeks of training, whole-body dual energy x-ray absorptiometry (DEXA) scan will be&#xD;
      performed for measured skeletal muscle mass and fasting blood samples will be obtained.&#xD;
      Maximal strength will be determined by 1-repetition maximum (1RM), physical functioning by&#xD;
      the short physical performance battery (SPPB) and quality of life by QLQ-BR23 at the same&#xD;
      time points.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Study parameters/endpoints:&#xD;
&#xD;
      The main study endpoint is the increase in the skeletal muscle mass of whole-body assessed&#xD;
      vial dual energy x-ray absorptiometry (DEXA).&#xD;
&#xD;
      Secondary endpoints include: Maximal strength assessment (1RM); Hand grip strength; Short&#xD;
      physical performance battery (SPPB); quality of life (QLQ-BR23), Inflammatory and molecular&#xD;
      markers (blood samples analysis).&#xD;
&#xD;
      Other study parameters include: Age, body weight, body height, body mass index (BMI), lipid&#xD;
      profile, glucose, and insulin.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Expected results:&#xD;
&#xD;
      The impact of resistance-type exercise training to increase muscle mass in postmenopausal&#xD;
      women survivors of breast cancer with or without hormonal therapy remains unclear. With the&#xD;
      proposed project, the investigators expect that resistance-type exercise training will&#xD;
      increase skeletal muscle mass, although the impact will be relatively lower in the&#xD;
      participants survivors of breast cancer when compared with a group of healthy postmenopausal&#xD;
      woman. The potential findings will define the efficacy of resistance-type exercise training&#xD;
      to increase muscle mass in individuals with postmenopausal woman survivors of breast cancer.&#xD;
      Better maintenance, or even an increase in muscle mass and strength increases independence,&#xD;
      prolonging good health, recovery from disease and illness, and ultimately decreases burden on&#xD;
      healthcare systems. These results will allow the creation of local, regional, national and&#xD;
      international strategies to combat the adverse effects of breast cancer and its&#xD;
      antineoplastic treatment, especially in postmenopausal women.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">March 22, 2023</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">August 2024</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2023</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in kilograms of the skeletal muscle mass of whole-body measured via dual energy x-ray absorptiometry (DEXA)</measure>
    <time_frame>Before, and after 12 weeks of training</time_frame>
    <description>after prolonged resistance-type exercise training</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in kilograms of the arms strength measured via 1-Repetition Maximum (1RM) testing) after prolonged resistance-type exercise training</measure>
    <time_frame>Before, and after 12 weeks of training</time_frame>
    <description>Maximal strength assessment via 1RM testing of horizontal row, lat pull down and chest press exercises</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in kilograms of the legs strength measured via 1-Repetition Maximum (1RM) testing) after prolonged resistance-type exercise training</measure>
    <time_frame>Before, and after 12 weeks of training</time_frame>
    <description>Maximal strength assessment via 1RM testing of leg press, and leg extension exercises</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in kilograms of the hand grip strength measured via JAMAR handheld dynamometer after prolonged resistance-type exercise training</measure>
    <time_frame>Before, and after 12 weeks of training</time_frame>
    <description>Maximal strength assessment via 1RM testing of JAMAR handheld dynamometer</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in points of the physical performance measured via Short physical performance battery (SPPB) after prolonged resistance-type exercise training</measure>
    <time_frame>Before, and after 12 weeks of training</time_frame>
    <description>Measurement of physical performance via SPPB, the minimum value is 0 point and the maximum value is 12 points. Higher score in the Physical Performance mean a better outcome and lower score mean a worse outcome</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in points quality of life measured via questionnaire European Organisation for Research and Treatment of Cancer (EORTC QLQ-C30) after prolonged resistance-type exercise training</measure>
    <time_frame>Before, and after 12 weeks of training</time_frame>
    <description>Measurement of quality of life via EORTC QLQ-30, this questionnaire has 30 question covering functional state and cancer related symptoms. Besides, there are two specific question covering the &quot;overall health&quot; and &quot;overall quality of life&quot;. The scores obtained are standardized and a score between 0 and 100 is obtained. High values on the global health and functional status scales indicate a better quality of life. However, high values on the symptom scale indicate a lower quality of life</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in microgram per milliliter (µg/ml) of Human Insulin via ELISA after prolonged resistance-type exercise training</measure>
    <time_frame>Before, and after 12 weeks of training</time_frame>
    <description>Measurement in blood samples, the insulin will evaluate by ELISA using the Human Insulin ELISA Kit, following the manufacturer's recommendations</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in milligrams per deciliter (mg/dL) of glucose via methods enzymatic-colorimetric</measure>
    <time_frame>Before, and after 12 weeks of training</time_frame>
    <description>Measurement in blood samples, the glucose will determined by enzymatic-colorimetric methods using an automatic photometer.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in milligrams per deciliter (mg/dL) of lipid profile via methods enzymatic-colorimetric</measure>
    <time_frame>Before, and after 12 weeks of training</time_frame>
    <description>Measurement in blood samples, the lipid profile will determined by enzymatic-colorimetric methods using an automatic photometer</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>4</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">52</enrollment>
  <condition>Breast Cancer Survivors</condition>
  <condition>Postmenopause</condition>
  <condition>Resistance Training</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>CLIMHEALTHY</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>All postmenopausal women without breast cancer will be subjected to 12 weeks of full body resistance exercise training (3 times per week)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>CANCERWHT</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>All postmenopausal women survivors of breast cancer without Hormone Therapy will be subjected to 12 weeks of full body resistance exercise training (3 times per week)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>CANCERHT-T</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>All postmenopausal women survivors of breast cancer with Aromatase Inhibitor Hormone Therapy be subjected to 12 weeks of full body resistance exercise training (3 times per week)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>CANCERHT-A</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>All postmenopausal women survivors of breast cancer with Tamoxifen Hormone Therapy be subjected to 12 weeks of full body resistance exercise training (3 times per week)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Prolonged resistance-type exercise training</intervention_name>
    <description>All volunteers will be subjected to 12 weeks of whole-body resistance-type exercise training (3x/wk).</description>
    <arm_group_label>CANCERHT-A</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>CANCERHT-T</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>CANCERWHT</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>CLIMHEALTHY</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Healthy postmenopausal women and postmenopausal women survivors of breast cancer with&#xD;
             and without Hormonal Therapy (Aromatase Inhibitors and Tamoxifen) between 45 to 59&#xD;
             years.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Women survivors of breast cancer with active Hormone Therapy in the last 12 months.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Women breast cancer survivors with luminal molecular profile and positive estrogen&#xD;
             receptors.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Body mass index 18.5 &lt; BMI &lt; 30 kg/m2.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Volunteers without cognitive impairment (abbreviated Minimental &gt;13 points).&#xD;
&#xD;
        Exclusion Criteria:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Active antineoplastic treatment in the last 12 months.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  &gt;200 mL of volume difference between upper limbs and/or stage IV breast cancer.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Performing regular resistance training (2 or more times per week, carrying out&#xD;
             progressive training) in the previous 6 months.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Cardiovascular diseases that are contradictory for physical activity (not included&#xD;
             controlled Hypertension).&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  All co-morbidities interacting with mobility and muscle metabolism of the body and&#xD;
             that do not allow to (safely) perform the resistance-type exercise training (e.g.&#xD;
             debilitating arthritis, spasticity/rigidity, all neurological disorders and&#xD;
             paralysis).&#xD;
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <gender_based>Yes</gender_based>
    <minimum_age>45 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>49 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Gabriel N Marzuca-Nassr, PT, MSc, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>+56 45 2596713</phone>
    <email>gabriel.marzuca@ufrontera.cl</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Department of Rehabilitation Sciences, Faculty of Medicine, Universidad de La Frontera. Temuco, Chile</name>
      <address>
        <city>Temuco</city>
        <country>Chile</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Gabriel N Marzuca-Nassr, MSc, PhD</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Chile</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2023</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>December 22, 2022</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 9, 2023</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">January 19, 2023</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 10, 2023</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 10, 2023</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 12, 2023</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Universidad de La Frontera</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Gabriel Nasri Marzuca-Nassr</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>breast cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>hormone therapy</keyword>
  <keyword>exercise</keyword>
  <keyword>muscle mass</keyword>
  <keyword>strength</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Breast Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

