<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="9016">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 09, 2023</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT05707052</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>REC/RCR&amp;AHS/22/0230</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT05707052</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Neck-Trunk Stabilization Exercises and Bobath Therapy Spastic Diplegic Cerebral Palsy</brief_title>
  <official_title>Comparative Effects of Neck-Trunk Stabilization Exercises and Bobath Therapy on Trunk Control and Upper Limb Function in Children With Spastic Diplegic Cerebral Palsy: A Randomized Clinical Trial</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Riphah International University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Riphah International University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Physiotherapy is widely used in the treatment of children with cerebral palsy. This study is&#xD;
      conducted to identify the most appropriate physiotherapy approach. The purpose of the study&#xD;
      is to compare two physical rehabilitation strategies i.e., Neck-trunk stabilization exercises&#xD;
      and Bobath therapy, to investigate their effectiveness on trunk control and upper limb&#xD;
      function. The aims of treatment are to influence muscle tone and improve postural alignment&#xD;
      by specific handling technique.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The study will be a Randomized Clinical Trial conducted at the physiotherapy outpatient&#xD;
      clinic of the tertiary care hospital in Sialkot, Idrees Hospital. Following the approval of&#xD;
      the BASR, the study will be completed within six months. The sample will be taken using a&#xD;
      non-probability convenient sampling technique, and the sample will be randomly divided into&#xD;
      two groups. A sample size of 44 patients will be taken in this study. There will be two&#xD;
      groups. Both groups will receive conventional therapy consisting of stretching,&#xD;
      strengthening, range-of-motion exercises, positioning, and electrical stimulation. Group A:&#xD;
      This group will receive Neck-Trunk Stabilization exercises. Group B: This group will receive&#xD;
      Bobath therapy. The total intervention protocol will be given for six weeks' duration, with&#xD;
      three sessions per week of about 45 minutes each. Outcome measures tools will be Segmental&#xD;
      Assessment of Trunk Control (SATCo) and Manual Ability Classification System (MACS). Children&#xD;
      with spastic diplegic cerebral palsy will be measured at baseline and after 6 weeks.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">January 1, 2023</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">March 22, 2023</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">March 15, 2023</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Segmental Assessment of Trunk Control (SATCo)</measure>
    <time_frame>4th week</time_frame>
    <description>Changes from baseline SATCo provides a systematic method of assessing discrete levels of trunk control in children with motor disabilities. The SATCo determines the topmost (most cephalo) segment at which control of the upright posture is poor or not demonstrated i.e. is currently being learned for each of static, active and reactive control.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Manual Ability Classification System (MACS)</measure>
    <time_frame>4th week</time_frame>
    <description>Changes from baseline MACS as been used to classify how children with cerebral palsy use their hands when handling objects in daily activities.it is designed to reflect the typical manual performance of child. The ability of children from 4 - 18 years old with cerebral palsy to handle objects in everyday activities can be categorized into 5 levels.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">44</enrollment>
  <condition>Cerebral Palsy Spastic Diplegia</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Neck-Trunk Stabilization exercises</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>First neck and trunk exercise involved lifting the head in a modified bridge exercise position so that lower abdominal muscles contracted when the neck was bent, thereby activating the neck flexor muscle and the lower abdominal muscles simultaneously. Second exercise involved pushing the neck backward in supine position to activate the erector muscles of the neck and the upper thoracic vertebrae through the extension of the muscles of the back of the neck. Third exercise activated the deep abdominal muscles in bridge exercise positions so that the participants would experience the posterior inclined movement of the pelvis. Keep each posture for 10 seconds at a time and repeat 10 times with a rest interval of 3 seconds per each.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Bobath Therapy</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>trunk-pelvic-hip neutral alignment with anterior-posterior weight shifts on the ball,&#xD;
bilateral upper extremity abduction-traction for lateral weight shift,&#xD;
prone extension on the ball,&#xD;
forward weight shift for the trunk and hip extension and forward protective extension,&#xD;
diagonal weight shifts in flexion-rotation direction,&#xD;
lateral weight shift for simultaneous activation of flexors and extensors,&#xD;
bilateral shoulder flexion for latissimus dorsi elongation,&#xD;
pectoral elongation exercise for trunk extension,&#xD;
preparatory trunk activities (with continuous and/or intermittent compression and intermittent support),&#xD;
positioning and holding of the head-trunk Keep each posture for 10 seconds at a time with a rest interval of 3 seconds per each.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Neck-Trunk Stabilization Exercises and conventional physical therapy</intervention_name>
    <description>Neck-Trunk Stabilization Exercises along with conventional physical therapy in which stretching, strengthening, ROMs positioning and electrical stimulation are included.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Neck-Trunk Stabilization exercises</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Bobath Therapy and conventional physical therapy</intervention_name>
    <description>Bobath based exercises along with conventional physical therapy in which stretching, strengthening, ROMs positioning and electrical stimulation are included.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Bobath Therapy</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Children diagnosed with spastic diplegic cerebral palsy&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Children with score of GMFCS [2] [3] [4] levels(2, 16).&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Signed consent form from parents/guardians.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Exclusion Criteria:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Children with visual impairments&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Children with major auditory impairments&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Children with previous orthopedic surgery and Botulium toxin-A injection at least for&#xD;
             6 months&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Children having pharmacological intervention for the inhibition of spasticity&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Contractures&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Uncontrolled seizures&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Focal spasticity&#xD;
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>4 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>15 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Ali Raza, MS(OMPT)</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Riphah International University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Imran Amjad, Phd</last_name>
    <phone>03324390125</phone>
    <email>imran.amjad@riphah.edu.pk</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Idrees Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Sialkot</city>
        <state>Punjab</state>
        <zip>51300</zip>
        <country>Pakistan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Ali Raza, MsPT</last_name>
      <phone>03326099065</phone>
      <email>araza.frahs@riphah.edu.pk</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Ayesha Zulfiqar, MsPT(NMPT)</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Ali Raza, Ms(OMPT)</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Pakistan</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ejraei N, Ozer AY, Aydogdu O, Turkdogan D, Polat MG. The effect of neck-trunk stabilization exercises in cerebral palsy: randomized controlled trial. Minerva Pediatr (Torino). 2021 Sep 30. doi: 10.23736/S2724-5276.21.06206-6. Online ahead of print.</citation>
    <PMID>34590804</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Acar G, Ejraei N, Turkdogan D, Enver N, Ozturk G, Aktas G. The Effects of Neurodevelopmental Therapy on Feeding and Swallowing Activities in Children with Cerebral Palsy. Dysphagia. 2022 Aug;37(4):800-811. doi: 10.1007/s00455-021-10329-w. Epub 2021 Jun 25.</citation>
    <PMID>34173063</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Desouzart G. Physiotherapy intervention according to the Bobath concept in a clinical case of cerebral palsy. Ortho Res Online J. 2018;3(4).</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Shin JW, Song GB, Ko J. The effects of neck and trunk stabilization exercises on cerebral palsy children's static and dynamic trunk balance: case series. J Phys Ther Sci. 2017 Apr;29(4):771-774. doi: 10.1589/jpts.29.771. Epub 2017 Apr 20.</citation>
    <PMID>28533628</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Shin JW, Song GB. The effects of neck and trunk stabilization exercises on upper limb and visuoperceptual function in children with cerebral palsy. J Phys Ther Sci. 2016 Nov;28(11):3232-3235. doi: 10.1589/jpts.28.3232. Epub 2016 Nov 29.</citation>
    <PMID>27942155</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>January 2023</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>January 22, 2023</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 22, 2023</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">January 31, 2023</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 22, 2023</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 22, 2023</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">January 31, 2023</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Bobath; Cerebral palsy; Neck-Trunk Stabilization;</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Muscle Spasticity</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Paralysis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Cerebral Palsy</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

