<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="9211">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 09, 2023</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT05702905</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2022CR04</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT05702905</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Semaglutide Improves Metabolic Abnormalities and Fertility in Obese Infertile Women With Polycystic Ovary Syndrome</brief_title>
  <official_title>Semaglutide Improves Metabolic Abnormalities and Fertility in Obese Infertile Women With Polycystic Ovary Syndrome: a Prospective, Randomized, Open, Controlled Study</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Peking University First Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Peking University First Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>No</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      To investigate the efficacy of semaglutide in obese infertile women of childbearing age with&#xD;
      polycystic ovary syndrome (PCOS), we design this prospective, randomized, open and controlled&#xD;
      study. 75 obese infertile PCOS patients will be recruited and randomized into three groups:&#xD;
      metformin, semaglutide and metformin+semaglutide, on the basis of calorie-restricted diet and&#xD;
      physical exercise. All subjects will be treated for 12 weeks, and then stop taking the drug&#xD;
      for at least 8 weeks to initiate ovulation induction or ovulation induction combined with&#xD;
      artificial insemination. All subjects will be followed up for 24 weeks for pregnancy outcome.&#xD;
      The primary endpoint of the study is the percentage of weight loss at 12 weeks of treatment.&#xD;
      The secondary endpoints include HOMA-IR and androgen levels at 12 weeks of treatment,&#xD;
      ovulation rate at 24 weeks of follow-up, clinical pregnancy rate and cumulative pregnancy&#xD;
      rate, and depression, anxiety, diet and quality of life scores at 12 weeks of treatment.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      To investigate the efficacy of semaglutide in obese infertile women of childbearing age with&#xD;
      polycystic ovary syndrome (PCOS), we design this prospective, randomized, open and controlled&#xD;
      study. 75 obese infertile PCOS patients will be recruited and randomized into three groups:&#xD;
      metformin, semaglutide and metformin+semaglutide, on the basis of calorie-restricted diet and&#xD;
      physical exercise. Metformin and semaglutide will be administered in a dose increasing mode,&#xD;
      and then maintain until the end of 12 weeks, and metabolic related indexes will be evaluated.&#xD;
      After 12 weeks of treatment, all subjects will stop taking the drug for at least 8 weeks to&#xD;
      initiate ovulation induction or ovulation induction combined with artificial insemination.&#xD;
      All subjects will be followed up for 24 weeks to evaluate the fertility related indicators.&#xD;
      The primary endpoint of the study is the percentage of weight loss at 12 weeks of treatment.&#xD;
      The secondary endpoints include HOMA-IR and androgen levels at 12 weeks of treatment,&#xD;
      ovulation rate at 24 weeks of follow-up, clinical pregnancy rate and cumulative pregnancy&#xD;
      rate, and depression, anxiety, diet and quality of life scores at 12 weeks of treatment.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">April 2023</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 31, 2024</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 30, 2024</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 4</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>All subjects will be randomized into three groups: metformin single, semaglutide single, both metformin and semaglutide.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage change in bodyweight at 12 weeks for semaglutide versus metformin</measure>
    <time_frame>at the end of 12 weeks of treatment</time_frame>
    <description>Difference between body weight at 12 weeks and baseline divided by baseline body weight</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Achievement of weight reduction of at least 5% at 12 weeks for semaglutide versus metformin</measure>
    <time_frame>at the end of 12 weeks of treatment</time_frame>
    <description>Proportion of patients with weight loss at least 5% at 12 weeks of treatment</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>HOMA-IR at 12 weeks of treatment</measure>
    <time_frame>at the end of 12 weeks of treatment</time_frame>
    <description>compare HOMA-IR at 12 weeks of treatment among three groups</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>testosterone level at 12 weeks of treatment</measure>
    <time_frame>at the end of 12 weeks of treatment</time_frame>
    <description>compare testosterone level at 12 weeks of treatment among three groups</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>androstenedione level at 12 weeks of treatment</measure>
    <time_frame>at the end of 12 weeks of treatment</time_frame>
    <description>compare androstenedione level at 12 weeks of treatment among three groups</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>FAI (Free Androgen Index) at 12 weeks of treatment</measure>
    <time_frame>at the end of 12 weeks of treatment</time_frame>
    <description>compare FAI at 12 weeks of treatment among three groups</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Depression score by self-rating depression scale (SDS）at 12 weeks of treatment</measure>
    <time_frame>at the end of 12 weeks of treatment</time_frame>
    <description>Zung self-rating depression scale (SDS) contains 20 items. Each item is divided into four grades according to the frequency of symptoms, of which 10 are positive and 10 are negative. Positive scoring question rated as 1, 2, 3 and 4 in turn and reverse scoring questions rated as 4, 3, 2 and 1. Add all the scores to get the total rough score, and then multiply the rough score by 1.25 to get the integral part as the standard score. The lower the score, the better. According to the criteria of Chinese population, the cut-off value of SDS standard score is 53 points, of which 53-62 points is mild depression, 63-72 points is moderate depression, and more than 73 points is severe depression. SDS standard score ≥ 50 indicates depressive symptoms. Depression severity is evaluated by cumulative score of each item/80. Those below 0.5 are not depressed; 0.5-0.59 is mild depression; 0.6-0.69 is moderate to severe; more than 0.7 is severe depression.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Anxiety score by self-rating anxiety scale (SAS）at 12 weeks of treatment</measure>
    <time_frame>at the end of 12 weeks of treatment</time_frame>
    <description>Zung self-reating anxiety scale (SAS) adopts a four-grade score, which is mainly used to assess the frequency of symptoms. The standard is: &quot;1&quot; means no or little time; &quot;2&quot; means sometimes; &quot;3&quot; means most of the time; &quot;4&quot; means most or all of the time. Of the 20 items, 15 items are stated in negative words, and scored in the order of 1-4 above. The remaining five items are stated in positive words and scored in reverse order of 4 to 1. The main statistical indicator of SAS is the total score. Add the scores of 20 items to get a rough score. Multiply the rough score by 1.25 and take the integer part to get the standard score. According to the criteria of Chinese population, the cut-off value of SAS standard score is 50 points, of which 50-59 points is mild anxiety, 60-69 points is moderate anxiety, and more than 70 points is severe anxiety.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Diet score by TFEQ-18 (three factor eating questionaire) at 12 weeks of treatment</measure>
    <time_frame>at the end of 12 weeks of treatment</time_frame>
    <description>The Three-Factor Eating Questionnaire Revised 18-item includes three dimensions of questions: non-controlled eating (9 items), cognitive restricted eating (6 items), and emotional eating (3 items). Uncontrolled eating refers to a tendency to lose control of excessive eating when feeling hungry or stimulated by external factors. Cognitive restriction refers to consciously limiting food intake to control weight or promote weight loss. Emotional eating refers to the tendency to overeat under some negative emotional conditions. Questions 1 to 18 are scored with 1 to 4 points. The total score of the three dimensions is the total score of the scale. The higher the score of each dimension of the questionnaire, the higher the tendency of uncontrolled eating, cognitive restriction of eating and emotional eating.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Quality of life score at 12 weeks of treatment</measure>
    <time_frame>at the end of 12 weeks of treatment</time_frame>
    <description>The World Health Organization Quality of Life (WHOQOL) - BREF can generate scores in four fields. The scale contains two independent analysis items: Q1 asks the individual's total subjective feelings about their own quality of life, and Q2 asks the individual's total subjective feelings about their own health status. The domain score is positive (that is, the higher the score, the better the quality of life). The domain score is obtained by calculating the average score of the items to which it belongs and multiplying by 4.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Ovulation rate at 24 weeks of follow-up after the end of treatment</measure>
    <time_frame>at the end of 24 weeks of follow-up after the end of treatment</time_frame>
    <description>Number of patients with ovulation after natural and ovulation induction treatment/total number of patients</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Clinical pregnancy rate at 24 weeks of follow-up after the end of treatment</measure>
    <time_frame>at the end of 24 weeks of follow-up after the end of treatment</time_frame>
    <description>Clinical pregnancy rate=clinical pregnancy cycles/transplantation cycles</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Cumulative pregnancy rate at 24 weeks of follow-up after the end of treatment</measure>
    <time_frame>at the end of 24 weeks of follow-up after the end of treatment</time_frame>
    <description>Cumulative pregnancy rate=number of all pregnant patients/total number of patients</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">75</enrollment>
  <condition>PCOS (Polycystic Ovary Syndrome)</condition>
  <condition>Semaglutide</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>metformin</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>About 25 subjects will be allocated to this group to receive metformin only, as the active comparator of semaglutide groups. Metformin used in this trial is Glucophage ( 500mg per tablet）produced by Bristol-Myers Squibb.The initial dose of metformin will be 500mg twice daily, which will be increased to 1000mg twice daily after two weeks, and then maintained until the end of treatment in total 12 weeks.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>semaglutide</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>About 25 subjects will be allocated to this group to receive semaglutide only, as one of the experimental groups. Semaglutide used in this trial is WEGOVY (semaglutide) injection produced by Novo Nordisk. Administer WEGOVY once weekly, on the same day each week, at any time of day, with or without meals. Inject subcutaneously in the abdomen, thigh or upper arm. Initiate at 0.25 mg once weekly for 4 weeks. In 4 week intervals, increase the dose until a dose of 1.0 mg is reached, and then maintained 1.0 mg until the end of treatment in total 12 weeks..</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>semaglutide and metformin</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>About 25 subjects will be allocated to this group to receive both semaglutide and metformin, as another of the experimental groups. Metformin used in this trial is Glucophage ( 500mg per tablet）produced by Bristol-Myers Squibb.The initial dose of metformin will be 500mg twice daily, which will be increased to 1000mg twice daily after two weeks, and then maintained until the end of treatment in total 12 weeks. Semaglutide used in this trial is WEGOVY (semaglutide) injection produced by Novo Nordisk. Administer WEGOVY once weekly, on the same day each week, at any time of day, with or without meals. Inject subcutaneously in the abdomen, thigh or upper arm. Initiate at 0.25 mg once weekly for 4 weeks. In 4 week intervals, increase the dose until a dose of 1.0 mg is reached, and then maintained 1.0 mg until the end of treatment in total 12 weeks.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Metformin Hydrochloride 500 MG</intervention_name>
    <description>Metformin oral tablet (500mg per tablet) will be administered in a dose increasing mode: the initial dose will be 500mg twice daily, which will be increased to 1000mg twice daily after two weeks, and then maintained until the end of treatment in total 12 weeks.</description>
    <arm_group_label>metformin</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Glucophage</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Semaglutide, 1.34 mg/mL</intervention_name>
    <description>Inject semaglutide subcutaneously once weekly, on the same day each week, at any time of day, in a dose increasing mode: the initial dose of 0.25mg QW (once a week), increased to 0.5mg QW after 4 weeks, and increased to 1.0mg QW after another 4 weeks, and then maintained 1.0mg until the end of treatment in total 12 weeks.</description>
    <arm_group_label>semaglutide</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>WEGOVY</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Semaglutide, 1.34 mg/mL and Metformin Hydrochloride 500 MG</intervention_name>
    <description>Both Semaglutide injection and Metformin oral tablet will be administered as described above.</description>
    <arm_group_label>semaglutide and metformin</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>WEGOVY and Glucophage</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>calorie-restricted diet</intervention_name>
    <description>All subjects after randomization will be reviewed and evaluated by a nutritionist, and then will receive diet guidance. The clinical nutritionist will develop a written nutrition plan for each subject. The nutrition plan of this study adopted the method of calorie restriction diet (CRD) to develop a diet, which required 83.68 kJ/kg of energy per day, 1.2 g/kg of protein per day, 40%~55% of carbohydrate energy supply ratio, and 20%~30% of fat energy supply ratio, to ensure the intake of vegetables, fruits and other rich dietary fiber, and drinking more than 1.5 L per day. The nutritionist will explain the method of food exchange in detail to enrich the food types of patients. The diet diary will be distributed to each subject, and the subjects will be required to make a return visit once every four weeks, return the diet diary each time, and receive guidance according to their compliance.</description>
    <arm_group_label>metformin</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>semaglutide</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>semaglutide and metformin</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>physical exercise</intervention_name>
    <description>All subjects after randomization will be reviewed and evaluated by a trainer, and then will receive guidance of physical exercise.The trainer will formulate an exercise plan for each subject. The exercise plan consists of 30 minutes of moderate and low intensity continuous aerobic exercise every day, with a frequency of 5-7 days/week. The form of exercise can be determined according to personal hobbies, such as fast walking, jogging, climbing, swimming, etc. The exercise diary will be distributed to each subject, and the subjects are required to make a return visit once every four weeks, return the exercise diary each time, and the trainer will provide guidance to the subjects according to their compliance.</description>
    <arm_group_label>metformin</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>semaglutide</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>semaglutide and metformin</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:&#xD;
&#xD;
          1. Meet the PCOS diagnostic criteria (Rotterdam）&#xD;
&#xD;
          2. Age 22-40&#xD;
&#xD;
          3. BMI ≥ 28 kg/m2&#xD;
&#xD;
          4. Infertility: having normal sexual life and failing to conceive without contraception&#xD;
             for more than 1 year&#xD;
&#xD;
          5. Willing to be pregnant, and her husband has no serious infertility&#xD;
&#xD;
        Exclusion Criteria:&#xD;
&#xD;
          1. History of acute pancreatitis, individual or family history of medullary thyroid&#xD;
             cancer and multiple endocrine adenomas&#xD;
&#xD;
          2. Type 1 diabetes and special type diabetes&#xD;
&#xD;
          3. History of tumor&#xD;
&#xD;
          4. Serious cardiovascular and cerebrovascular disease, mental disease, liver or kidney&#xD;
             disease&#xD;
&#xD;
          5. Metformin, GLP-1 RA and other drugs affecting reproductive and metabolic functions&#xD;
             were used within 90 days before the study&#xD;
&#xD;
          6. Known allergy to metformin, GLP-1 RA and excipients&#xD;
&#xD;
          7. Severe endometriosis, low ovarian reserve, premature ovarian failure&#xD;
&#xD;
          8. Inability to tolerate pregnancy and ovulation induction therapy&#xD;
&#xD;
          9. Other conditions considered unsuitable for this study by researchers&#xD;
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <gender_based>Yes</gender_based>
    <minimum_age>22 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>40 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Tingting Zhang, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Peking University First Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Tingting Zhang, M.D.</last_name>
    <phone>86-10-83575103</phone>
    <email>cathine@sina.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>PekingUFH</name>
      <address>
        <city>Peking</city>
        <state>Beijing</state>
        <zip>100034</zip>
        <country>China</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>China</country>
  </location_countries>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Jensterle Sever M, Kocjan T, Pfeifer M, Kravos NA, Janez A. Short-term combined treatment with liraglutide and metformin leads to significant weight loss in obese women with polycystic ovary syndrome and previous poor response to metformin. Eur J Endocrinol. 2014 Feb 7;170(3):451-9. doi: 10.1530/EJE-13-0797. Print 2014 Mar.</citation>
    <PMID>24362411</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Jensterle M, Kravos NA, Pfeifer M, Kocjan T, Janez A. A 12-week treatment with the long-acting glucagon-like peptide 1 receptor agonist liraglutide leads to significant weight loss in a subset of obese women with newly diagnosed polycystic ovary syndrome. Hormones (Athens). 2015 Jan-Mar;14(1):81-90. doi: 10.1007/BF03401383.</citation>
    <PMID>25885106</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Salamun V, Jensterle M, Janez A, Vrtacnik Bokal E. Liraglutide increases IVF pregnancy rates in obese PCOS women with poor response to first-line reproductive treatments: a pilot randomized study. Eur J Endocrinol. 2018 Jul;179(1):1-11. doi: 10.1530/EJE-18-0175. Epub 2018 Apr 27.</citation>
    <PMID>29703793</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Han Y, Li Y, He B. GLP-1 receptor agonists versus metformin in PCOS: a systematic review and meta-analysis. Reprod Biomed Online. 2019 Aug;39(2):332-342. doi: 10.1016/j.rbmo.2019.04.017. Epub 2019 Apr 25.</citation>
    <PMID>31229399</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Cena H, Chiovato L, Nappi RE. Obesity, Polycystic Ovary Syndrome, and Infertility: A New Avenue for GLP-1 Receptor Agonists. J Clin Endocrinol Metab. 2020 Aug 1;105(8):e2695-709. doi: 10.1210/clinem/dgaa285.</citation>
    <PMID>32442310</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Xing C, Zhao H, Zhang J, He B. Effect of metformin versus metformin plus liraglutide on gonadal and metabolic profiles in overweight patients with polycystic ovary syndrome. Front Endocrinol (Lausanne). 2022 Aug 17;13:945609. doi: 10.3389/fendo.2022.945609. eCollection 2022.</citation>
    <PMID>36060969</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Papaetis GS, Kyriacou A. GLP-1 receptor agonists, polycystic ovary syndrome and reproductive dysfunction: Current research and future horizons. Adv Clin Exp Med. 2022 Nov;31(11):1265-1274. doi: 10.17219/acem/151695.</citation>
    <PMID>35951627</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Ge JJ, Wang DJ, Song W, Shen SM, Ge WH. The effectiveness and safety of liraglutide in treating overweight/obese patients with polycystic ovary syndrome: a meta-analysis. J Endocrinol Invest. 2022 Feb;45(2):261-273. doi: 10.1007/s40618-021-01666-6. Epub 2021 Aug 29.</citation>
    <PMID>34455568</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Liu X, Zhang Y, Zheng SY, Lin R, Xie YJ, Chen H, Zheng YX, Liu E, Chen L, Yan JH, Xu W, Mai TT, Gong Y. Efficacy of exenatide on weight loss, metabolic parameters and pregnancy in overweight/obese polycystic ovary syndrome. Clin Endocrinol (Oxf). 2017 Dec;87(6):767-774. doi: 10.1111/cen.13454. Epub 2017 Sep 13.</citation>
    <PMID>28834553</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Ma RL, Deng Y, Wang YF, Zhu SY, Ding XS, Sun AJ. Short-term combined treatment with exenatide and metformin for overweight/obese women with polycystic ovary syndrome. Chin Med J (Engl). 2021 Nov 3;134(23):2882-2889. doi: 10.1097/CM9.0000000000001712.</citation>
    <PMID>34732660</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Li R, Mai T, Zheng S, Zhang Y. Effect of metformin and exenatide on pregnancy rate and pregnancy outcomes in overweight or obese infertility PCOS women: long-term follow-up of an RCT. Arch Gynecol Obstet. 2022 Nov;306(5):1711-1721. doi: 10.1007/s00404-022-06700-3. Epub 2022 Jul 13.</citation>
    <PMID>35829765</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <verification_date>March 2023</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>December 23, 2022</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 18, 2023</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">January 27, 2023</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 28, 2023</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 28, 2023</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 29, 2023</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Peking University First Hospital</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Tingting ZHANG</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Associate Chief Physician , Associate Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>PCOS</keyword>
  <keyword>semaglutide</keyword>
  <keyword>obese</keyword>
  <keyword>metabolic abnormality</keyword>
  <keyword>fertility</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Polycystic Ovary Syndrome</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Congenital Abnormalities</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Syndrome</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Metformin</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <provided_document_section>
    <provided_document>
      <document_type>Study Protocol</document_type>
      <document_has_protocol>Yes</document_has_protocol>
      <document_has_icf>No</document_has_icf>
      <document_has_sap>No</document_has_sap>
      <document_date>January 17, 2023</document_date>
      <document_url>https://ClinicalTrials.gov/ProvidedDocs/05/NCT05702905/Prot_000.pdf</document_url>
    </provided_document>
    <provided_document>
      <document_type>Statistical Analysis Plan</document_type>
      <document_has_protocol>No</document_has_protocol>
      <document_has_icf>No</document_has_icf>
      <document_has_sap>Yes</document_has_sap>
      <document_date>January 17, 2023</document_date>
      <document_url>https://ClinicalTrials.gov/ProvidedDocs/05/NCT05702905/SAP_001.pdf</document_url>
    </provided_document>
  </provided_document_section>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

