<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="9432">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 09, 2023</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT05697965</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>Vancomycin in Arthroplasty</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT05697965</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>LocalVancomycinPowderToPreventPeriprostheticJointInfection.</brief_title>
  <official_title>TheUseofLocalVancomycinPowdertoPreventPeriprostheticJointInfectioninPrimaryTotalHipandKneeArthroplasty.ARandomizedControlledTrial.</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Assiut University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Assiut University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>No</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to evaluate the efficacy and complication profile of local&#xD;
      vancomycin application in primary arthroplasty. The investigators hypothesized that the use&#xD;
      of local antibiotics would decrease the rate of infection compared to controls and this will&#xD;
      be achieved by applying 1 gm of vancomycin powder intracapsularly.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Periprosthetic joint infection is a truly devastating complication of total joint&#xD;
      arthroplasty (TJA), causing most patients to undergo a revision surgery and to bear&#xD;
      significant psychological and financial burden. Surveys suggest patients of total joint&#xD;
      arthroplasty undergoing revision for infection have poorer functional outcomes and&#xD;
      satisfaction levels than patients undergoing revision for other reasons, with negative&#xD;
      consequences being more persistent .&#xD;
&#xD;
      Despite developments in infection prophylaxis and risk factor mitigation, patients with&#xD;
      periprosthetic joint infection represent a substantial societal and monetary cost to our&#xD;
      value-based health care system. Thus, there is significant interest in developing and&#xD;
      systematically evaluating new PJI prophylaxis measures to reduce this rate.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Historically, local wound vancomycin powder has been shown to safely reduce infection rates&#xD;
      in spine surgery. The earliest and strongest support for local vancomycin powder for primary&#xD;
      orthopedic surgery came from the spine literature, and it now has support in the shoulder and&#xD;
      elbow and foot and ankle literature. The use of topical vancomycin was first reported in 1989&#xD;
      when the application of topical vancomycin to the sternum in cardio thoracic patients reduced&#xD;
      rates of sternal infection from 3.6% to 0.45%). Similarly, multiple studies have shown that&#xD;
      vancomycin decreases the rate of postoperative infections in patients undergoing spinal&#xD;
      surgery.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Importantly, data on topical vancomycin powder used alone remain inconclusive for TJA, with&#xD;
      some stating that it may increase aseptic wound complications, and others stating that it&#xD;
      reduces PJI significantly .&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">March 1, 2023</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">August 2024</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">May 2024</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Factorial Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Participant)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Follow up for infected patients after 90 days with surgical site infection.</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months after operation</time_frame>
    <description>The purpose of this study is evaluation of the efficacy and complication profile of local vancomycin application in primary arthroplasty. The use of local antibiotics would decrease the rate of infection compared to controls and this will be achieved by applying 1 gm of vancomycin powder intracapsularly that will be evaluated by inflammatory markers CRP (if more than 1 gm/dl), ESR(more than 20) as laboratory investigations.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Aseptic wound complications such as skin erosion, wound dehiscence, and prolonged wound healing.</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months</time_frame>
    <description>The purpose of this study is evaluation of the efficacy and complication profile of local vancomycin application in primary arthroplasty. The investigators hypothesized that the use of local antibiotics would decrease the rate of infection compared to controls and this will be achieved by applying 1 gm of vancomycin powder intracapsularly by examination wound site if there's surgical site infection, dehescience, abscess, discharge.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">174</enrollment>
  <condition>Arthroplasty Complications</condition>
  <condition>Periprosthetic Fracture of Hip</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Vancomycin loaded group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>applying 1 gm of vancomycin powder intracapsularly during primary total knee and hip arthroplasty operations</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Non vancomycin loaded group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Total knee &amp; hip arthroplasty done without applying local vancomycin powder comparing the results with vancomycin loaded group</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Vancomycin</intervention_name>
    <description>applying 1 gm of vancomycin powder intracapsularly during primary total knee and hip arthroplasty to prevent periprosthetic joint infection</description>
    <arm_group_label>Vancomycin loaded group</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Vancomycin sulphate</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Total knee or total hip arthroplasty</intervention_name>
    <description>Primary total knee or total hip arthroplasty without using local vancomycin</description>
    <arm_group_label>Non vancomycin loaded group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Vancomycin loaded group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:&#xD;
&#xD;
        all patients population who will undergo primary total knee or total hip arthroplasty&#xD;
&#xD;
        Exclusion Criteria:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  patients with diabetes mellitus inflammatory arthritis diseases smokers BMI &gt; 40&#xD;
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Yossef Saleh</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Vice president</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Maro Boktor, Master</last_name>
    <phone>+01023454251</phone>
    <email>marombb54@gmail.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Mohammad AbdelNasser</last_name>
    <phone>01002438664</phone>
    <email>Abdelnasser.m.k@aun.edu.eg</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <reference>
    <citation>Wukich DK, Dikis JW, Monaco SJ, Strannigan K, Suder NC, Rosario BL. Topically Applied Vancomycin Powder Reduces the Rate of Surgical Site Infection in Diabetic Patients Undergoing Foot and Ankle Surgery. Foot Ankle Int. 2015 Sep;36(9):1017-24. doi: 10.1177/1071100715586567. Epub 2015 May 12.</citation>
    <PMID>25967254</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kurtz SM, Lau E, Watson H, Schmier JK, Parvizi J. Economic burden of periprosthetic joint infection in the United States. J Arthroplasty. 2012 Sep;27(8 Suppl):61-5.e1. doi: 10.1016/j.arth.2012.02.022. Epub 2012 May 2.</citation>
    <PMID>22554729</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sweet FA, Roh M, Sliva C. Intrawound application of vancomycin for prophylaxis in instrumented thoracolumbar fusions: efficacy, drug levels, and patient outcomes. Spine (Phila Pa 1976). 2011 Nov 15;36(24):2084-8. doi: 10.1097/BRS.0b013e3181ff2cb1.</citation>
    <PMID>21304438</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Yan H, He J, Chen S, Yu S, Fan C. Intrawound application of vancomycin reduces wound infection after open release of post-traumatic stiff elbows: a retrospective comparative study. J Shoulder Elbow Surg. 2014 May;23(5):686-92. doi: 10.1016/j.jse.2014.01.049.</citation>
    <PMID>24745317</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>February 2023</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>July 12, 2022</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 15, 2023</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">January 26, 2023</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 9, 2023</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 9, 2023</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">February 10, 2023</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Assiut University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Maro Maher Botros Boktor</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Resident physician at Orthopedic&amp; Trauma department,principal investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Periprosthetic Fractures</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hip Fractures</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Vancomycin</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

