<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="9674">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 09, 2023</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT05692960</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>UTK-IRB-22-07195</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT05692960</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Women's Interventions for Sexual Health: WISH</brief_title>
  <acronym>WISH</acronym>
  <official_title>Women's Interventions for Sexual Health: WISH, A Pilot Study</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>The University of Tennessee, Knoxville</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Breast Cancer Research Foundation</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>The University of Tennessee, Knoxville</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>Yes</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>Yes</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The overall objective of this program of research is to improve sexual health outcomes for&#xD;
      women diagnosed with breast cancer. Our team is developing a multi-component intervention for&#xD;
      the four key predictors of sexual health in female cancer survivors: self-image, vulvovaginal&#xD;
      tissue quality and symptoms, desire/energy, and relationship-partner concerns. This proposal&#xD;
      begins the proof-of-concept pilot study in women with a history of breast cancer to deliver a&#xD;
      multi-component intervention to improve vulvo-vaginal atrophy with a vaginal moisturizer, and&#xD;
      sexual energy and self-image with a mind-body intervention that involves relaxation and&#xD;
      subconscious suggestions with a hypnotic induction delivered via audio file. The primary&#xD;
      outcome will be to evaluate the feasibility and acceptability of a multi-component&#xD;
      intervention for sexual function. It is hypothesized that at least eighty percent of&#xD;
      randomized participants will complete the study without differential withdraws from the&#xD;
      control group.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Women's Interventions for Sexual Health (WISH), is a two-arm randomized clinical trial to&#xD;
      evaluate the feasibility and acceptability of a multi-component intervention addressing&#xD;
      changes in body image, sexual desire, and vaginal dryness in thirty adult post-treatment&#xD;
      breast cancer survivors. The study is eight weeks long and does not require any in-person&#xD;
      visits. If a breast cancer survivor is determined eligible, they will be educated on the&#xD;
      purpose, requirements, and procedures. If interested, they will be emailed the consent form&#xD;
      and will schedule a virtual consent/baseline visit. After consent is obtained, the&#xD;
      participant will be randomly assigned to a study arm, HRI (hypnotic relaxation intervention&#xD;
      plus vaginal moisturizer) or VVA (vulvovaginal atrophy moisturizer only), given a study&#xD;
      number, and educated on the use of Replens™ vaginal moisturizer. The participant will&#xD;
      complete online surveys at the virtual baseline visit. Replens™ vaginal moisturizer will be&#xD;
      sent to the participant's address and receipt of the moisturizer will be confirmed by study&#xD;
      staff before the agreed upon week one start date. The participant will use the moisturizer&#xD;
      every day during weeks one and two and every other day during weeks three through eight.&#xD;
      Participants randomized to the HRI group will also receive an MP3 player with three hypnotic&#xD;
      relaxation audio files and asked to complete a weekly practice log. Each hypnotic induction&#xD;
      audio file will be used for two weeks, three times per week, for a total of six weeks of&#xD;
      hypnosis. A second virtual visit will be held at two weeks to assess progress, adverse events&#xD;
      and provide education to the HRI group. Check in phone calls will be scheduled for weeks&#xD;
      four, six and eight. A link to online follow up surveys will be shared during weeks six and&#xD;
      eight.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">November 22, 2022</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2023</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2023</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>This is a two-arm, randomized clinical trial.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Supportive Care</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Screen failure rate (a measure of feasibility)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 30 days Recruitment to screening</time_frame>
    <description>The number of women screened ineligible</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Accrual rate (a measure of feasibility)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 30 days Screening to consent</time_frame>
    <description>The number of participants who consented divided by the number eligible</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Retention rate/Acceptability (a measure of feasibility)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline through study completion, 8 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>The number of participants who complete the 8 weeks of the study divided by the number who consented.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Female Sexual Function Index (FSFI)</measure>
    <time_frame>consent to week 8</time_frame>
    <description>Change in FSFI score</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Breast- Impact of Treatment Scale (BITS)</measure>
    <time_frame>consent to week 8</time_frame>
    <description>Change in ITS score</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Patient reported outcomes measurement information system (PROMIS) Sexual Function and Satisfaction</measure>
    <time_frame>consent to week 8</time_frame>
    <description>Change in PROMIS sexual function score</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">30</enrollment>
  <condition>Sexual Dysfunction, Physiological</condition>
  <condition>Body Image</condition>
  <condition>Libido; Loss, Aversion</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Hypnotic Relaxation Intervention (HRI)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>The hypnotic relaxation intervention consists of three different audio files, each about 20 minutes in length. These three hypnotic inductions build upon each other. The first hypnotic induction audio focuses on relaxation, feelings of wellness, wholeness, strength, and confidence. The second hypnotic induction audio focuses more specifically on body image related to sexuality and being a sexual being. The third hypnotic induction audio focuses on sexual desire, passion, and energy. Each hypnotic induction will be used for two weeks, three times per week for a total of six weeks of hypnosis.&#xD;
The vaginal moisturizer component of this arm is the same as that described for the VVA study arm.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Vulvovaginal Atrophy (VVA)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>This study arm might best be described as standard of care. Vulvovaginal dryness will be treated with a daily moisturizer for two weeks, then every other day for the remaining six weeks. Vaginal moisturizer will be applied at night, before sleep and after all sexual activity. Several moisturizers are available, including vaginal DHEA (IntraRosa®). Due to the need for reproducibility, we have decided to use one non-hormonal vaginal moisturizer, Replens™ moisture, which is a vaginal moisturizer consisting primarily of a purified water, glycerin, and mineral oil. Other ingredients included in the formulation are polycarbophyl, carbomer, homopolymer type B, hydrogenated palm oil glyceride, sorbic acid, sodium hydroxide. The moisturizing gel was determined to be a medical device for marketing by the FDA in 2010. It is non-hormonal (unlike vaginal DHEA) and therefore will be more likely to be acceptable by a broader range of oncology providers.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Hypnotic Relaxation Intervention (HRI)</intervention_name>
    <description>HRI is a combination intervention (Replens™ vaginal moisturizer device and hypnotic relaxation behavioral intervention)</description>
    <arm_group_label>Hypnotic Relaxation Intervention (HRI)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Vulvovaginal Atrophy (VVA)</intervention_name>
    <description>VVA is a standard of care intervention (Replens™ vaginal moisturizer device)</description>
    <arm_group_label>Vulvovaginal Atrophy (VVA)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  History of breast cancer, stages I, II or III&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Completed primary treatment (chemotherapy, radiation and/or surgery) ≥3 months and ≤ 5&#xD;
             years prior to registration&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  May use concurrent adjuvant endocrine therapy or HER2-targeted therapy while on study&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  May use topical products (e.g., lidocaine) vaginally prior to penetrative vaginal sex&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Ability to read and write English&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Able to engage in sexual activity&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Currently has a sexual partner Responds &quot;yes&quot; to &quot;Do you currently experience vaginal&#xD;
             or vulvar dryness and/or pain with sexual activity?&quot;&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Responds &quot;yes&quot; to at least one of the following questions:&#xD;
&#xD;
               1. &quot;Have you experienced negative changes in your body image since being diagnosed&#xD;
                  or treated for cancer?&quot; or&#xD;
&#xD;
               2. &quot;Have you experienced negative changes in your sexual desire since being&#xD;
                  diagnosed or treated for cancer?&quot;&#xD;
&#xD;
        Exclusion Criteria:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Antidepressants are allowed if a person has been on them for 30 days prior to&#xD;
             registration, and dose or treatment is not expected to change&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  History of sexual abuse&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Psychiatric disorder such as major depressive disorder, bipolar disorder, obsessive&#xD;
             compulsive disorder or schizophrenia. (Defined per medical history and/or patient&#xD;
             self-report)&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Currently enrolled in another study that addresses sexual health (enrollment in other&#xD;
             clinical trials will be allowed)&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Use of oral, transdermal or vaginal estrogen is not allowed while on study&#xD;
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>99 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Debra L Barton, PhD,RN,FAAN</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Tennessee Knoxville</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Carrie K Lafferty, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>865-974-9463</phone>
    <email>claffer2@utk.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Noel M Arring, DNP,PhD,RN</last_name>
    <phone>865-974-1988</phone>
    <email>narring@utk.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Tennessee Knoxville</name>
      <address>
        <city>Knoxville</city>
        <state>Tennessee</state>
        <zip>37996</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Carrie K Lafferty, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>865-974-9463</phone>
      <email>claffer2@utk.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Noel M Arring, DNP,PhD,RN</last_name>
      <phone>865-974-1988</phone>
      <email>narring@utk.edu</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Debra L Barton, PhD,RN,FAAN</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Noel M Arring, DNP,PhD,RN</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>January 2023</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>December 14, 2022</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 19, 2023</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">January 20, 2023</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 19, 2023</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 19, 2023</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">January 20, 2023</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>The University of Tennessee, Knoxville</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Debra Barton</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>McMahan-McKinley Endowed Professor of Gerontology</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>breast cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>vulvovaginal atrophy</keyword>
  <keyword>libido</keyword>
  <keyword>body image</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Sexual Dysfunction, Physiological</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Hypnotics and Sedatives</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>This is a small pilot study and as such, data will be thoroughly interrogated. However, if an investigator feels there are unanswered questions or wishes to add to a larger dataset, we would entertain all data sharing requests for deidentified data as appropriate.</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

