<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="9073">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 09, 2023</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT05705817</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>E-1201-22</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT05705817</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Assistive Soft Skills and Employment Training (ASSET) in TBI Injury</brief_title>
  <official_title>Assistive Soft Skills and Employment Training (ASSET) in Traumatic Brain Injury</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Kessler Foundation</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Kessler Foundation</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Pediatric traumatic brain injury (TBI) is often associated with difficulties in social&#xD;
      functioning. Loss of social contacts and difficulties maintaining social connections is&#xD;
      common after pediatric TBI, extending into adulthood. Social skills are a key aspect of&#xD;
      social functioning critical to forming and maintaining social relationships with others,&#xD;
      including family, friends, teachers and co-workers. Social skills deficits are thus critical&#xD;
      to social participation and overall quality of life. The identification of treatment&#xD;
      techniques to effectively address these issues are thus of paramount importance. The ability&#xD;
      to improve social skills in adolescents and young adults is critical as they transition from&#xD;
      school settings into the workforce. Impairments in social skills have been demonstrated to&#xD;
      underlie difficulties transitioning from school to work and independent living in students&#xD;
      with disabilities. Therefore, targeting social skills interventions as individuals enter&#xD;
      adulthood and enter the workforce is likely to improve overall functioning during this&#xD;
      transitional period in their lives.&#xD;
&#xD;
      The current study will examine preliminary efficacy of a manualized group intervention that&#xD;
      targets social skills, specifically work-related social skills known as soft skills.&#xD;
      Targeting not only general social skills, but soft skills in particular, is expected to be&#xD;
      particularly useful for teens and young adults as they transition from school into the&#xD;
      workforce.&#xD;
&#xD;
      The Assistive Soft Skills and Employment Training (ASSET) is a 15-session training program&#xD;
      that combines specific skill training, structured learning, social performance training and a&#xD;
      social hour to practice skills through a manualized group intervention. Specific skills&#xD;
      taught within the program include communication, attitude and enthusiasm, teamwork,&#xD;
      networking, problem-solving and critical thinking, professionalism, mental health and stress&#xD;
      management, awareness of self and others, workplace relationships and self-advocacy. ASSET&#xD;
      utilizes a manualized curriculum and provides additional support including handouts,&#xD;
      PowerPoint summaries, instructional procedures, video models, materials for caregivers, and&#xD;
      an online platform to support learning the program. ASSET has been utilized with young adults&#xD;
      with ASD with very positive results, improving performance on measures of social skills,&#xD;
      social communication, self-confidence/self-efficacy and psychological wellness. The current&#xD;
      proposal will test the efficacy of the ASSET program in youth and young adults with TBI&#xD;
      between the ages of 15 and 25, a critical time as individuals' transition from school&#xD;
      settings into the workforce. The proposal will evaluate the primary outcome of improvements&#xD;
      in social skills following completion of the ASSET program. Secondary outcomes of&#xD;
      self-efficacy, depression, anxiety and quality of life will also be evaluated following&#xD;
      completion of the program.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">May 1, 2023</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 1, 2024</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 1, 2024</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>N/A</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Social Skills Questionnaire for Traumatic Brain Injury</measure>
    <time_frame>Within 2 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>This is a 41-tem scale to assess social skills in TBI</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">20</enrollment>
  <condition>Traumatic Brain Injury</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Assistive Soft Skills and Employment Training (ASSET)</intervention_name>
    <description>The ASSET program is a 15-session training program that combines specific skill training, structured learning, social performance training and a social hour to practice skills through a manualized group intervention. Specific skills taught within the program include communication, enthusiasm and attitude, teamwork, networking, problem-solving and critical thinking, and professionalism.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Age 15-25&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  At least one year post injury.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Exclusion Criteria:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  any other significant neurological history other than their TBI.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  unstable or uncontrolled seizures (as defined by an increase in the rate of seizures&#xD;
             over the 3 months before study participation)&#xD;
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>15 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>25 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Jeannie Lengenfelder</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Kessler Foundation</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Jeannie Lengenfelder</last_name>
    <phone>19733248447</phone>
    <email>jlengenfelder@kesslerfoundation.org</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Nancy Moore</last_name>
    <phone>973.324.8450</phone>
    <email>nbmoore@kesslerfoundation.org</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <verification_date>May 2023</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>January 9, 2023</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 30, 2023</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">January 31, 2023</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 3, 2023</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 3, 2023</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 6, 2023</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Brain Injuries</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Brain Injuries, Traumatic</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Wounds and Injuries</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

