<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="9351">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 09, 2023</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT05699811</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>CHN-PLAGH-BT-078</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT05699811</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>IFNα Expressing Mesenchymal Stromal Cells for Locally Advanced/Metastatic Solid Tumors</brief_title>
  <official_title>Phase I/II Trial of Allograft Engineered MSC-IFNα Combined With or Without Immunochemotherapy for Locally Advanced/Metastatic Solid Tumors</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Chinese PLA General Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Wuxi Sinotide New Drug Discovery Institutes</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Chinese PLA General Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The goal of this first-in-human, single-center, prospective, open-label, phase 1/2 trial is&#xD;
      to evaluate the safety and efficacy of the interferon alpha expressing mesenchymal stromal&#xD;
      cells (MSC-IFNα) combined with or without immunochemotherapy in patients with locally&#xD;
      advanced/metastatic solid tumors. The main questions aimed to answer are 1) to evaluate the&#xD;
      safety and feasibility of MSC-IFNα in the treatment of locally advanced/metastatic solid&#xD;
      tumors;2) to evaluate the anti-tumor effects of the MSC-IFNα combined with or without&#xD;
      immunochemotherapy in the treatment of locally advanced/metastatic solid tumors; 3) to&#xD;
      evaluate the pharmacokinetics/pharmacodynamics of MSC-IFNα and related immune effector cells.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      [Introduction] Mesenchymal Stromal Cells (MSCs) have been shown to home to the sites of&#xD;
      injury or damage and secrete immunomodulatory factors. This feature makes MSCs an ideal&#xD;
      carrier to deliver drugs or cytokines to the tumor microenvironment (TME) and therefore have&#xD;
      a potential therapeutic role in cancer treatment.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Interferon(IFN) has been widely used for cancer treatment for its pleiotropic antitumor&#xD;
      effects. IFN receptor signals mediate intrinsic and extrinsic effects on tumor cells and the&#xD;
      TME, including tumor-infiltrating lymphocytes as well as tumor-associated stroma.&#xD;
      Additionally, IFNs also exert direct intrinsic antitumor effects including inhibition of cell&#xD;
      proliferation by inducing cell cycle arrest, cell death via apoptosis and ferroptosis, cell&#xD;
      differentiation, and senescence, thus acting as a tumor suppressor. Accumulating evidence&#xD;
      suggests that IFNs play critical roles in cancer immunotherapy, however, the variations in&#xD;
      responses and the adverse effects have reduced their popularity in clinical applications. New&#xD;
      IFN-based strategies should be considered as a high priority.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Our team has developed a protocol to genetically express IFNα in bone marrow-derived MSCs. In&#xD;
      vitro and in vivo experiments have shown that the MSC-IFNα cells possess a potent ability to&#xD;
      home to TME and to secret IFNα. By changing TME, MSC-IFNα induces strong anti-tumor effects&#xD;
      in several cancer types in animal models. In addition, preliminary data also indicated that&#xD;
      the combination of IFNα-MSCs with chemotherapy and/or programmed death-1(PD-1)/programmed&#xD;
      death-ligand 1(PD-L1)blockade may bring an even stronger anti-tumor immunity.&#xD;
&#xD;
      In this study, by producing MSC-IFNα cells with human umbilical-cord-derived mesenchymal&#xD;
      stromal cells (hUC-MSCs, passage 5 to passage 7), the investigators plan to conduct a&#xD;
      first-in-human, prospective, open-label, phase 1/2 trial to evaluate the safety and efficacy&#xD;
      of MSC-IFNα combined with or without immunochemotherapy in patients with locally&#xD;
      advanced/metastatic solid tumors.&#xD;
&#xD;
      [Study design] Phase 1 Arm 1. Safety evaluation of MSC-IFNα monotherapy A total of 3-9&#xD;
      subjects will be enrolled for the safety evaluation of MSC-IFNα monotherapy. All&#xD;
      treatment-related adverse events (TRAE) will be recorded for at least 28 days after cell&#xD;
      infusion. Subjects with any grade 3-4 TRAE that lasts for 7 days or more within the 28 days&#xD;
      after infusion will be determined as treatment intolerance (TI).&#xD;
&#xD;
      The first 3 subjects will receive MSC-IFNα infusion 1-4 times every 4-6 weeks at a dose of&#xD;
      2×10^6 cells/kg. If TI occurred in any of the 3 subjects, another 3 subjects will be enrolled&#xD;
      and received a 70% reduced MSC-IFNα dose (i.e. 6×10^5 cells/kg, 2x10^5/kg, and so on) until&#xD;
      tolerable dose (no TI in all 3 subjects) was reached.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Arm 2. Safety and efficacy evaluation of MSC-IFNα combined with immunochemotherapy.&#xD;
&#xD;
      A total of 3-9 subjects will be enrolled and receive MSC-IFNα infusion (tolerable dose&#xD;
      determined in Arm 1) every 4-6 weeks for 4 cycles. Immunochemotherapy, namely nab-paclitaxel&#xD;
      (125 mg/m2, 5 days before cell infusions), cyclophosphamide (200 mg/m2,4 days before cell&#xD;
      infusions) and anti-PD-1 antibody (200mg, 7 days after infusion) will be given. From the 5th&#xD;
      cycle, subjects will receive MSC-IFNα combined with anti-PD-1 antibody (200mg, 7 days after&#xD;
      infusion) every 4-6 weeks for another 4 cycles for efficacy consolation. From the 9th cycle,&#xD;
      subjects will receive anti-PD-1 antibody (200mg) alone every 3 weeks for another 4 cycles for&#xD;
      efficacy maintenance. The safety, efficacy, and other required data will be collected and the&#xD;
      optimized combined regimen (OCR) of MSC-IFNα and immunochemotherapy will be determined.&#xD;
      MSC-IFNα related AE will be continuously monitored in this arm, and reduced MSC-IFNα dose&#xD;
      will be considered if necessary.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Phase 2 A total of 10-30 subjects will be enrolled and received the OCR determined in the&#xD;
      phase 1 of the trial. The safety, efficacy, and other required data will be collected.&#xD;
&#xD;
      During the treatment, efficacy in all subjects will be assessed at baseline and every 8 weeks&#xD;
      thereafter until confirmed progressive disease, death, intolerable toxicity, withdrawal of&#xD;
      consent, or end of the study, whichever occurs first.&#xD;
&#xD;
      During post-treatment follow-up, efficacy and TRAEs in all subjects will be assessed every 12&#xD;
      weeks until death, withdrawal of consent, loss to follow-up, or end of the study, whichever&#xD;
      occurs first.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">February 23, 2023</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 31, 2026</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 31, 2025</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1/Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Sequential Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of treatment related adverse events(TRAE)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 12 months since the initiation of MSC-IFNα therapy</time_frame>
    <description>Treatment related adverse events (TRAE) are defined as any medical events since the initiation of MSC-IFNα therapy. All TRAEs will be recorded and graded according to the Common Terminology Criteria for Adverse Events (CTCAE V5.0)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Objective response rate (ORR) of MSC-IFNα combined with or without immunochemotherapy</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 12 months since the initiation of MSC-IFNα therapy</time_frame>
    <description>Objective response rate (ORR) is defined as the proportion of patients with a complete response or partial response to MSC-IFNα treatment according to Response Evaluation Criteria in Solid Tumors (RECIST 1.1) or immune RECIST (iRECIST)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Progression free survival (PFS) of MSC-IFNα combined with or without immunochemotherapy</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 12 months since the initiation of MSC-IFNα therapy</time_frame>
    <description>Progression free survival (PFS) is defined as the time from enrollment of the study to disease progression or death from any cause.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Duration of response(DOR) of MSC-IFNα combined with or without immunochemotherapy</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 12 months since the initiation of MSC-IFNα therapy</time_frame>
    <description>Duration of response(DOR) is defined as the length of time that a tumor continues to respond to treatment without the cancer growing or spreading</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall survival (OS) of MSC-IFNα combined with or without immunochemotherapy</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 12 months since the initiation of MSC-IFNα therapy</time_frame>
    <description>Overall survival (OS) is defined as the time from treatment to death, regardless of disease recurrence</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Allograft MSC-IFNa cells in peripheral blood and in tumor microenvironments.</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 12 months since the initiation of MSC-IFNα therapy</time_frame>
    <description>Engineered MSC-IFNa will be periodically monitored by quantitative polymerase chain reaction (qPCR)</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Serum interferon-α level after infusion of MSC-IFNα</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 12 months since the initiation of MSC-IFNα therapy</time_frame>
    <description>Serum interferon-α level will be dynamically monitored by enzyme-linked immunosorbent assay (ELISA)</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Serum interferon-β level after infusion of MSC-IFNα</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 12 months since the initiation of MSC-IFNα therapy</time_frame>
    <description>Serum interferon-β level will be dynamically monitored by enzyme-linked immunosorbent assay (ELISA)</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Serum interleukin-2 level after infusion of MSC-IFNα</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 12 months since the initiation of MSC-IFNα therapy</time_frame>
    <description>Serum interleukin-2 level will be dynamically monitored by enzyme-linked immunosorbent assay (ELISA)</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Serum interleukin-6 level after infusion of MSC-IFNα</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 12 months since the initiation of MSC-IFNα therapy</time_frame>
    <description>Serum interleukin-6 level will be dynamically monitored by enzyme-linked immunosorbent assay (ELISA)</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Serum tumor necrosis factor-α level after infusion of MSC-IFNα</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 12 months since the initiation of MSC-IFNα therapy</time_frame>
    <description>Serum tumor necrosis factor-α level will be dynamically monitored by enzyme-linked immunosorbent assay (ELISA)</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Dynamic changes of monocytes in peripheral blood after infusion of MSC-IFNα</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 12 months since the initiation of MSC-IFNα therapy</time_frame>
    <description>Dynamic changes of monocytes (CD14+/CD16+) cell number and proportion in peripheral blood will be monitored by flow cytometry</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Dynamic changes of CD4 T cells in peripheral blood after infusion of MSC-IFNα</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 12 months since the initiation of MSC-IFNα therapy</time_frame>
    <description>Dynamic changes of CD4 T cells (CD3+/CD4+) cell number and proportion in peripheral blood will be monitored by flow cytometry</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Dynamic changes of CD8 T cells in peripheral blood after infusion of MSC-IFNα</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 12 months since the initiation of MSC-IFNα therapy</time_frame>
    <description>Dynamic changes of CD8 T cells (CD3+/CD8+) cell number and proportion in peripheral blood will be monitored by flow cytometry</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Dynamic changes of nature killer (NK) cells in peripheral blood after infusion of MSC-IFNα</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 12 months since the initiation of MSC-IFNα therapy</time_frame>
    <description>Dynamic changes of nature killer (NK) cells (CD3-/CD16+/CD56+) cell number and proportion in peripheral blood will be monitored by flow cytometry</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">40</enrollment>
  <condition>Locally Advanced or Metastatic Solid Tumors</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>MSC-IFNα monotherapy</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Subjects will be enrolled for safety evaluation of MSC-IFNα monotherapy. Subjects will receive MSC-IFNα infusion from a dose of 2×10^6 cells/kg 1-4 times every 4-6 weeks. All treatment-related adverse events(TRAE) will be recorded for at least 28 days after the cell infusion.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>MSC-IFNα combined with immunochemotherapy</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Subjects will be enrolled and received MSC-IFNα combined with immunochemotherapy, namely nab-paclitaxel (125 mg/m2, 5 days before infusion), cyclophosphamide (200 mg/m2,4 days before infusion) and anti-PD-1 antibody (200mg, 7 days after infusion) for 4 cycles.&#xD;
From the 5th cycle, subjects will receive MSC-IFNα combined with anti-PD-1 antibody every 4-6 weeks for another 4 cycles for efficacy consolation. From the 9th cycle, subjects will receive anti-PD-1 antibody alone every 3 weeks for another 4 cycles for efficacy maintenance.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>MSC-IFNα</intervention_name>
    <description>MSC-IFNα form a dose of 2×10^6 cells/kg, intravenous infusion every 4-6 weeks</description>
    <arm_group_label>MSC-IFNα combined with immunochemotherapy</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>MSC-IFNα monotherapy</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Nab paclitaxel</intervention_name>
    <description>125mg/m2, intravenous infusion every 4-6 weeks</description>
    <arm_group_label>MSC-IFNα combined with immunochemotherapy</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Abraxane</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Cyclophosphamide</intervention_name>
    <description>200mg/m2, intravenous infusion every 4-6 weeks</description>
    <arm_group_label>MSC-IFNα combined with immunochemotherapy</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Anti-PD-1 monoclonal antibody</intervention_name>
    <description>200mg, intravenous infusion every 4-6 weeks</description>
    <arm_group_label>MSC-IFNα combined with immunochemotherapy</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Toripalimab Injection</other_name>
    <other_name>Sintilimab Injection</other_name>
    <other_name>Camrelizumab Injection</other_name>
    <other_name>Tislelizumab Injection</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:&#xD;
&#xD;
          1. Age from 18 to 75 years with estimated life expectancy &gt;3 months.&#xD;
&#xD;
          2. Histopathological confirmed locally advanced or metastatic solid tumors including, but&#xD;
             not limited to, lung cancer, breast cancer, colorectal cancer, hepatocellular&#xD;
             carcinoma, and sarcomas.&#xD;
&#xD;
          3. Failed to at least first-line and second-line treatments or initially diagnosed&#xD;
             locally advanced/metastatic solid tumors that have no National Comprehensive Cancer&#xD;
             Network(NCCN) guideline-recommended therapy.&#xD;
&#xD;
          4. Have at least one measurable target lesion.&#xD;
&#xD;
          5. Previous treatment must be completed for more than 4 weeks prior to the enrollment of&#xD;
             this study.&#xD;
&#xD;
          6. Have an Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group performance status (ECOG) of 0 to 2 at the&#xD;
             time of enrollment.&#xD;
&#xD;
          7. Have adequate organ function, which should be confirmed within 2 weeks prior to the&#xD;
             first dose of study drugs.&#xD;
&#xD;
          8. Previous treatment with anti-PD-1/PD-L1 antibodies is allowed.&#xD;
&#xD;
          9. Ability to understand and sign a written informed consent document.&#xD;
&#xD;
         10. Women of child-bearing potential must agree to use adequate contraception (hormonal or&#xD;
             barrier method of birth control; abstinence) prior to study entry and up to 90 days&#xD;
             after the last dose of the drug.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Exclusion Criteria:&#xD;
&#xD;
          1. Active, known, or suspected autoimmune diseases.&#xD;
&#xD;
          2. Known brain metastases or active central nervous system (CNS). Subjects with CNS&#xD;
             metastases who were treated with radiotherapy for at least 3 months prior to&#xD;
             enrollment, have no central nervous symptoms, and are off corticosteroids, are&#xD;
             eligible for enrollment, but require a brain MRI screening.&#xD;
&#xD;
          3. Subjects are being treated with either corticosteroid (&gt;10 mg daily prednisone&#xD;
             equivalent) or other immunosuppressive medications within 14 days of enrollment.&#xD;
&#xD;
          4. History of psychiatric disorders including depression, suicidality, and mania.&#xD;
&#xD;
          5. History of allergy or intolerance to study drug components.&#xD;
&#xD;
          6. Substance abuse, medical, psychological, or social conditions that may interfere with&#xD;
             the patient's participation in the study or evaluation of the study results.&#xD;
&#xD;
          7. Uncontrolled concurrent illness, including ongoing or active systemic infection,&#xD;
             symptomatic congestive heart failure, unstable angina pectoris, cardiac arrhythmia&#xD;
             (excluding insignificant sinus bradycardia and sinus tachycardia), or psychiatric&#xD;
             illness/social situations and any other illness that would limit compliance with study&#xD;
             requirements and jeopardize the safety of the patient.&#xD;
&#xD;
          8. History of human immunodeficiency virus (HIV) infection or acquired immunodeficiency&#xD;
             syndrome (AIDS).&#xD;
&#xD;
          9. Pregnant or breast-feeding. Women of childbearing potential must have a pregnancy test&#xD;
             performed within 7 days before enrollment, and a negative result must be documented.&#xD;
&#xD;
         10. Previous or concurrent cancer within 3 years prior to treatment start.&#xD;
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>75 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>WeiDong Han, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Chinsese PLA Gereral Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Yufang Shi, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>Wuxi Sinotide New Drug Discovery Institutes</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>WeiDong Han, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>010-66937231</phone>
    <email>hanwdrsw@sina.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Guanghua Rong, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>010-66947473</phone>
    <email>guanghua.rong@gmail.com</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Department of Biotherapeutic, Chinese PLA General Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Beijing</city>
        <country>China</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>WeiDong Han, Ph.D</last_name>
      <phone>+86-10-66937463</phone>
      <email>hanwdrsw@163.com</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>GuangHua Rong, Ph.D</last_name>
      <phone>+86-10-66947473</phone>
      <email>guanghua.rong@gmail.com</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>China</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>https://www.nature.com/articles/s41388-022-02201-4</url>
    <description>In vitro and in vivo studies of MSC-IFN-α</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>April 2023</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>January 7, 2023</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 23, 2023</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">January 26, 2023</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 27, 2023</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 27, 2023</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">April 28, 2023</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Chinese PLA General Hospital</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Han weidong</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Director of Biotherapeutic Department</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Paclitaxel</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Cyclophosphamide</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Tislelizumab</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Antibodies</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Antibodies, Monoclonal</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

