<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="9144">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 09, 2023</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT05704400</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>DUAL1</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT05704400</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Efficacy of Anti-CD20 Ab Associated With Anti-CD38 in the Childhood Multidrug Dependent and Resistant Nephrotic Syndrome</brief_title>
  <official_title>Efficacy of Chimeric Monoclonal Anti-CD20 Antibodies (Rituximab Biosimilar) Associated With Monoclonal Anti-CD38 (Daratumumab) in the Treatment of Childhood Multidrug Dependent and Resistant (MDNS, MRNS) Nephrotic Syndrome</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Istituto Giannina Gaslini</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Istituto Giannina Gaslini</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>No</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Nephrotic syndrome is considered a disease caused by an interplay of immunological stimuli&#xD;
      with adaptive immunity(CD80/CD40) as trigger and Treg in the mid between co-stimulatory&#xD;
      molecules and effectors. The positive effect of drugs blocking CD20 maturation in SDNS&#xD;
      suggests a main role of these cells in regulating the system. Multidrug dependent, multidrug&#xD;
      resistant nephrotic syndrome as well as post transplant FSGS recurrence patients can be&#xD;
      considered difficult to treat patients and the association of two drugs, one targeting CD20&#xD;
      and a targeting plasmacells can be use in order to block the stimulatory cascade at more&#xD;
      sites.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Nephrotic syndrome is considered a disease caused by an interplay of immunological stimuli&#xD;
      with adaptive immunity(CD80/CD40) as trigger and Treg in the mid between co-stimulatory&#xD;
      molecules and effectors. The positive effect of drugs blocking CD20 maturation in SDNS&#xD;
      suggests a main role of these cells in regulating the system. One possible explanation of&#xD;
      proteinuria resolution by anti-CD 20 in most but not all patients with SDNS/MDNS is that some&#xD;
      CD20 cells may escape the inhibition and mature in some cases to plasmacells. On this basis,&#xD;
      it seems reasonable to consider the association of two drugs, one targeting CD20 and one&#xD;
      targeting plasmacells in order to block the stimulatory cascade at more sites. There are&#xD;
      recent positive evidences from the association of 2 monoclonal antibodies that block&#xD;
      maturation of CD20 at different steps. One study utilized the humanized anti-CD20 antibody&#xD;
      obinutuzumab(single dose 1,000 mg 1.73m2) in combination with the anti-CD38 (plasmacells)&#xD;
      monoclonal antibody daratumumab (1,000 mg 1.73m2)18 in patients who relapsed after&#xD;
      conventional treatments with Prednisone, rituximab and CNI and developed dependence to the&#xD;
      combination of more than 2 drugs (MDNS). A cohort of 14 patients treated with the above&#xD;
      association were included in a retrospective analysis: all of them suspended oral drugs, 5&#xD;
      out of 14 presented recurrence of proteinuria after about 10 months, 9 out of 14 were in&#xD;
      stable remission after 20 months. Therefore, the use of 2 monoclonal antibodies in low doses&#xD;
      is potentially valuable considering the positive results and also taking in account the&#xD;
      safety of the treatment. While it is not possible to discern the separate effects of&#xD;
      obinutuzumab and daratumumab when given together, the preliminary positive results of their&#xD;
      combination may open new ways in the treatment of nephrotic syndrome and supports the&#xD;
      necessity of new studies in those patients who require more than one drug to maintain&#xD;
      remission. The investigators hypothesize that rituximab in place of obinutuzumab (not&#xD;
      available in Italy for the use in nephrotic syndrome) with daratumumab could produce the same&#xD;
      positive effects in MDNS and MRNS.&#xD;
&#xD;
      The Dual 1 is a before-after clinical trial testing the superiority of rituximab plus&#xD;
      daratumumab in maintaining drug free disease remission in patients with multi-drug dependent&#xD;
      nephrotic syndrome.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">March 1, 2023</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">March 1, 2025</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">March 1, 2024</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>N/A</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Phase II Proof of concept, the Dual 1 is a before-after clinical trial testing the superiority of rituximab plus daratumumab in maintaining drug free disease remission in patients with multi-drug dependent nephrotic syndrome</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Safety- number of treatment-related adverse events</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Primary: to test whether the combination of rituximab and daratumumab is safe and can achieve and maintain drug-free disease remission in patients with multi drug-dependent nephrotic syndrome within 12 months. The investigators will consider the number of participants with treatment-related adverse events as assessed by CTCAE v4.0 This outcome will not be compared but only studied following the intervention.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Efficacy- number of months in remission</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>To test whether the combination of rituximab and daratumumab can achieve and maintain drug-free disease remission in patients with multi drug-dependent nephrotic syndrome within 12 months The investigators will compare the outcome of log-albuminuria following the infusion of the two drugs to the log-albuminuria before the infusion, when patients were maintained by the association of MMF and CNI (i.e. the drug recommended by Clinical Practice Guidelines-KDIGO as benchmark of the treatment).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Prediction</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>To analyze B and T cell lymphocyte subsets pre and post-therapy with Rituximab/Daratumumab</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">20</enrollment>
  <condition>Nephrotic Syndrome</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>single arm</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Rituximab Biosimilar ABP 798</intervention_name>
    <description>Rituximab IV: the dose is standard for pediatric nephrotic syndrome; for dosage between 100 and 250 mg rituximab will be diluted in 100 ml of normal saline and administered at 2 ml/h for the first 30'; 3 ml/h for the second 30'; 6 ml/h for the third 30'; 15 ml/h until the end. For dosage between 260 and 500 mg rituximab will be diluted in 250 ml of normal saline and administered at 6 ml/h for the first 30'; 9 ml/h for the second 30'; 18 ml/h for the third 30'; 36 ml/h until the end. For dosage between 510 and 1000 mg rituximab will be diluted in 500 ml of normal saline and administered at 9 ml/h for the first 30'; thereafter, the infusion rate can be doubled every 30 minutes up to a maximum of 72 ml/h.</description>
    <arm_group_label>single arm</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Daratumumab</intervention_name>
    <description>Daratumumab vials 20 mg 1 ml will be collected to reach the desired dose of 16 mg /Kg, the dose is standard recommend to treat myeloma; diluted in 1000 ml of normal saline and infused at the constant speed of 50 ml/h. This will be reduced in case of cutaneous allergic reactions</description>
    <arm_group_label>single arm</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Age between 3 and 24 years&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Multidrug dependent or resistant nephrotic syndrome for at least six months before&#xD;
             enrolment. The need of at least 2 of the oral drugs listed below defines&#xD;
             multidrug-dependence: prednisone at any doses, MMF 1200 mg m2 and CNI 0.1 mg day given&#xD;
             in two doses. Dependence is defined by two consecutive relapses during double&#xD;
             therapies or within 14 days of ceasing one of the three components of the therapeutic&#xD;
             approach. Resistance is defined as lack of antiproteinuric effect of a double therapy&#xD;
             based on steroid plusCNI or mofetilmycophenolate (MMF).Steroid resistance is defined&#xD;
             by failure to achieve complete remission after 6 weeks with prednisone60 mg/m2.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Post transplant recurrence of FSGS.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Ability to provide consent and assent: parents'/guardian's written informed consent,&#xD;
             and child's assent given before any study-related procedure not part of the subject's&#xD;
             normal medical care, with the understanding that consent may be withdrawn by the&#xD;
             subject any time without prejudice to his or her future medical care.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Exclusion Criteria:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Positivity to autoimmunity tests (ANA, nDNA, ANCA)&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Reduction of C3 levels.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  eGFR&lt;60/ml/min/1,73 m2 valuated according to revised Bedside Schwartz Formula for&#xD;
             patients between 2 and 17 years and with CKD-EPI Creatinine 2009 Equation for 18 years&#xD;
             old patients.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Pregnancy&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Neoplasm&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Infections: previous or actual HBV (with HBeAb positivity) or HCV infection&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  CD20 B lymphocytes count &lt;2,5%&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Treatment with Rituximab or cyclophosphamide in the last 6 months&#xD;
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>3 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>24 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Gianmarco Ghiggeri, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>IRCCS G. Gaslini</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Gianmarco Ghiggeri, MD</last_name>
    <phone>+39010-56363523</phone>
    <email>gmarcoghiggeri@gaslini.org</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Andrea Angeletti, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>+39010-56363523</phone>
    <email>andreaangeletti@gaslini.org</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>IRCCS G. Gaslini</name>
      <address>
        <city>Genova</city>
        <zip>16148</zip>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Italy</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>January 2023</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>December 16, 2022</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 19, 2023</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">January 30, 2023</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 19, 2023</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 19, 2023</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">January 30, 2023</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Istituto Giannina Gaslini</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Gian Marco Ghiggeri MD, PhD</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Principal Investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Nephrotic Syndrome</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Nephrosis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Syndrome</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Rituximab</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Daratumumab</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Yes</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>The completed study will be summarized in a final report that accurately and completely presents the study objectives, methods, results, limitations of the study, and interpretation of findings.</ipd_description>
    <ipd_info_type>Study Protocol</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_info_type>Statistical Analysis Plan (SAP)</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_info_type>Clinical Study Report (CSR)</ipd_info_type>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

