<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="9421">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 09, 2023</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT05698186</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2022-009</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT05698186</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Thero2-01S22 in HER2-positive Breast Cancer</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Randomized, Double-blind, Placebo-controlled, Multicenter, Phase III Efficacy and Safety Study of Thero2-01S22 add-on Therapy on Top of First-line Anti-HER2 Targeted Treatment of Patients With Metastatic Breast Cancer</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Institut de cancérologie Strasbourg Europe</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Institut de cancérologie Strasbourg Europe</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>No</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Trastuzumab and pertuzumab based regimen are the standard of care for patients with human&#xD;
      epidermal growth factor receptor 2 (HER2) -positive metastatic breast cancer (MBC),&#xD;
      significantly improving survival outcomes. However, an unmet medical need remain for patients&#xD;
      with disease refractoriness and recurrence. Interestingly, HER2 over-expression is associated&#xD;
      with upregulation of vascular endothelial growth factor (VEGF) in cancer cells in vitro and&#xD;
      in vivo. Preclinical studies indicated that VEGF expression is positively regulated by HER2&#xD;
      signaling. In the clinical setting, HER2 over-expression correlated significantly with VEGF&#xD;
      over- expression in samples from patients with breast cancer. There is, therefore, a biologic&#xD;
      rationale for targeting both HER2 and VEGF pathways in patients with HER2-positive breast&#xD;
      cancer.&#xD;
&#xD;
      PURPOSE: The hypothesis that justifies this research is that the addition of Thero2-01S22 as&#xD;
      add-on therapy on top of first line anti-HER2 targeted treatment will improve the efficacy of&#xD;
      anti-HER2 targeted containing regimen at the metastatic setting for breast cancer.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This study is a two-part, multicenter, randomized, double-blind, placebo-controlled, Phase&#xD;
      III trial.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Part 1 will confirm the recommended Phase III dose of Thero2-01S22 when administered as&#xD;
      add-on therapy on top of first line anti-HER2 targeted treatment of patients with metastatic&#xD;
      breast, with the aim to obtain about 15 evaluable participants in Thero2-01S22 group and 15&#xD;
      in the placebo group.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Part 2 will assess the efficacy of Thero2-01S22 treatment at the recommended dose when&#xD;
      administered as add-on therapy on top of first line anti-HER2 targeted treatment of patients&#xD;
      with metastatic breast. Approximately 290 participants will be randomized to receive&#xD;
      Thero2-01S22 or Thero2-01S22 matching-placebo in combination with trastuzumab and pertuzumab.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Participants in both Part 1 and Part 2 will receive induction therapy according to local&#xD;
      practice with a taxane (docetaxel, paclitaxel, or nab-paclitaxel) or vinorelbine for 4 to 6&#xD;
      cycles in combination with pertuzumab and trastuzumab.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">May 15, 2023</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">May 15, 2027</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">May 15, 2027</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Quadruple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Part 1: confirm the recommended dose of Thero2-01S22 as add-on therapy on top of first line anti-HER2 targeted treatment of patients with metastatic breast for Part 2</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 6</time_frame>
    <description>Incidence of adverse events considered possibly related to Thero2-01S22 that occur any time from the first dose intake of IMP or placebo to week 6.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Part 2: compare the effects of anti-HER2 targeted containing regimen with and without Thero2-01S22 in terms of Objective response rate (ORR) at week 6</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 6</time_frame>
    <description>Objective response rate (ORR): Percentage of patients whose disease decreased (Partial Response, PR) and / or disappears (Complete Response, CR) after treatment, according to RECIST V1.1 criteria, Eisenhauer et al. 2009.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Part 1: determine the safety of the recommended dose of Thero2-01S22as add-on therapy on top of first line anti-HER2 targeted treatment of patients with metastatic breast cancer</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 6</time_frame>
    <description>Safety: Incidence of adverse events per Common Terminology Criteria for Adverse Events (graded according to CTCAE) version 5.0 criteria from randomization to week 6</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Part 1: determine the tolerability of the recommended dose of Thero2-01S22 as add-on therapy on top of first line anti-HER2 targeted treatment of patients with metastatic breast cancer in terms of dose interruption</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 6</time_frame>
    <description>Number of dose interruptions of Thero2-01S22 trastuzumab, pertuzumab, and induction chemotherapy. Assessment period: from randomization to week 6</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Part 1: determine the tolerability of the recommended dose of Thero2-01S22 as add-on therapy on top of first line anti-HER2 targeted treatment of patients with metastatic breast cancer in terms of palatability</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 6</time_frame>
    <description>Palatability of oral Thero2-01S22 measured with visual analog scale. Assessment period: from randomization to week 6</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Part 1: determine the tolerability of the recommended dose of Thero2-01S22 as add-on therapy on top of first line anti-HER2 targeted treatment of patients with metastatic breast cancer in terms of treatment duration</measure>
    <time_frame>From randomization to Week 6</time_frame>
    <description>Treatment duration (number of days) of therapy including Thero2-01S22 trastuzumab, pertuzumab, and induction chemotherapy. Assessment period: from randomization to week 6</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Part 1: characterize exposure of Thero2-01S22 when administered as add-on therapy on top of first line anti-HER2 targeted treatment of patients with metastatic breast</measure>
    <time_frame>PK samples at day 1 of cycle 1 and cycle 2(each cycle is 21 days): before IMP or placebo intake, and at 5, 10, 15, 60, 120, 160 minutes after the intake</time_frame>
    <description>Determination of Area Under Curve (AUC) after oral Thero2-01S22 administration. PK samples to be collected at day 1 of cycle 1 and cycle 2 (each cycle is 21 days): before IMP or placebo intake, and at 5, 10, 15, 60, 120, 160 minutes after the intake</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Part 1: characterize exposure of Thero2-01S22 when administered as add-on therapy on top of first line anti-HER2 targeted treatment of patients with metastatic breast</measure>
    <time_frame>PK samples at day 1 of cycle 1 and cycle 2(each cycle is 21 days): before IMP or placebo intake, and at 5, 10, 15, 60, 120, 160 minutes after the intake</time_frame>
    <description>Determination of Maximum Plasma Concentration (Cmax) after oral Thero2-01S22 administration. PK samples to be collected at day 1 of cycle 1 and cycle 2 (each cycle is 21 days): before IMP or placebo intake, and at 5, 10, 15, 60, 120, 160 minutes after the intake</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Part 1: evaluate preliminary efficacy of Thero2-01S22 when administered as add-on therapy on top of first line anti-HER2 targeted treatment of patients with metastatic breast cancer</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 6</time_frame>
    <description>Objective response rate (ORR): Percentage of patients whose disease decreased (Partial Response, PR) and / or disappears (Complete Response, CR) after treatment, according to RECIST V1.1 criteria, Eisenhauer et al. 2009.&#xD;
Calculated at week 6 after the last intake of IMP or placebo</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Part 2: compare the effects of anti-HER2 targeted containing regimen with and without Thero2-01S22 in terms of Progression-Free Survival (PFS)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 24 months</time_frame>
    <description>Progression-Free Survival (PFS): defined as the time interval from the date of randomization to the date of progression.&#xD;
Events considered as progression include local or distant progression, appearance of a second cancer or death (all causes) whichever occurs first</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Part 2: compare the effects of anti-HER2 targeted containing regimen with and without Thero2-01S22 in terms of Overall Survival (OS)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 24 months</time_frame>
    <description>Overall Survival (OS): defined as the time interval from the date of randomization to the date of death, regardless of disease progression</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Part 2: compare the effects of anti-HER2 targeted containing regimen with and without Thero2-01S22 in terms of safety</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 6 and up to the end of the study (24 months)</time_frame>
    <description>Compare the effects of anti-HER2 targeted containing regimen with and without Safety: Incidence of treatment-related adverse events (AEs) and serious adverse events (SAEs) classified according to the CTCAE v5.0 criteria</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Part 2: compare the effects of anti-HER2 targeted containing regimen with and without Thero2-01S22 in terms of cardiotoxicity in terms of decrease of Left Ventricular Ejection Fraction (LVEF)</measure>
    <time_frame>From week 6 up to 24 months</time_frame>
    <description>Decrease in Left Ventricular Ejection Fraction (LVEF) value compared to baseline according to the modality performed (ECG, MUGA, MRI)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Part 2: compare the effects of anti-HER2 targeted containing regimen with and without Thero2-01S22 in terms of cardiotoxicity in terms of cardiac toxicities revealed at physical examination</measure>
    <time_frame>From week 6 up to 24 months</time_frame>
    <description>Cardiac toxicities revealed at physical examination, graded according to CTCAE v5.0 criteria</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>4</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">320</enrollment>
  <condition>HER2-positive Breast Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Part 1: Anti-HER2 targeted therapy containing regimen + Thero2-01S22</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients will receive Thero2-01S22 at the recommended dose and induction therapy according to local practice with a taxane (docetaxel, paclitaxel, or nab-paclitaxel) or vinorelbine for 4 to 6 cycles in combination with pertuzumab and trastuzumab</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Part 1: Anti-HER2 targeted therapy containing regimen + Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients will receive placebo and induction therapy according to local practice with a taxane (docetaxel, paclitaxel, or nab-paclitaxel) or vinorelbine for 4 to 6 cycles in combination with pertuzumab and trastuzumab</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Part 2: Anti-HER2 targeted therapy containing regimen + Thero2-01S22</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients will receive Thero2-01S22 at the confirmed dose and induction therapy according to local practice with a taxane (docetaxel, paclitaxel, or nab-paclitaxel) or vinorelbine for 4 to 6 cycles in combination with pertuzumab and trastuzumab</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Part 2: Anti-HER2 targeted therapy containing regimen + Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients will receive placebo and induction therapy according to local practice with a taxane (docetaxel, paclitaxel, or nab-paclitaxel) or vinorelbine for 4 to 6 cycles in combination with pertuzumab and trastuzumab</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Thero2-01S22</intervention_name>
    <description>Blinded recommended dose BID for three (3) consecutive days starting the day before anti-HER2 targeted therapy containing regimen, at cycle 1 and cycle 2</description>
    <arm_group_label>Part 1: Anti-HER2 targeted therapy containing regimen + Thero2-01S22</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo</intervention_name>
    <description>Blinded placebo BID for three (3) consecutive days starting the day before anti-HER2 targeted therapy containing regimen, at cycle 1 and cycle 2</description>
    <arm_group_label>Part 1: Anti-HER2 targeted therapy containing regimen + Placebo</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Thero2-01S22</intervention_name>
    <description>Blinded confirmed dose BID for three (3) consecutive days starting the day before anti-HER2 targeted therapy containing regimen, at cycle 1 and cycle 2</description>
    <arm_group_label>Part 2: Anti-HER2 targeted therapy containing regimen + Thero2-01S22</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo</intervention_name>
    <description>Blinded placebo BID for three (3) consecutive days starting the day before anti-HER2 targeted therapy containing regimen, at cycle 1 and cycle 2</description>
    <arm_group_label>Part 2: Anti-HER2 targeted therapy containing regimen + Placebo</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:&#xD;
&#xD;
          1. Women aged &gt; 18&#xD;
&#xD;
          2. Metastatic setting of an histologically confirmed adenocarcinoma of the breast&#xD;
&#xD;
          3. Performance status = 0, 1 or 2&#xD;
&#xD;
          4. Metastatic disease requiring the initiation of an anti HER2 containing regimen&#xD;
&#xD;
          5. First line treatment for metastatic disease&#xD;
&#xD;
          6. Standard treatment including Trastuzumab and Pertuzumab in first line&#xD;
&#xD;
          7. Patients for whom a 3-month life expectancy is anticipated&#xD;
&#xD;
          8. Baseline LVEF value &gt; 50%, measured cardiac MRI or by echocardiography (Simpson's&#xD;
             method) or MUGA scan within 12 weeks before initiation of the treatment. According to&#xD;
             HERCEPTIN SPCs.&#xD;
&#xD;
          9. Overexpression of HER2 in the invasive component of the primary tumor (3+ by ICH or 2+&#xD;
             with confirmation of positivity by FISH or CISH)&#xD;
&#xD;
         10. Informed consent form signed&#xD;
&#xD;
        Exclusion Criteria:&#xD;
&#xD;
          1. Patients not eligible for anti-HER2 therapy&#xD;
&#xD;
          2. Patients previously treated at the metastatic setting by systemic treatment&#xD;
&#xD;
          3. Serious cardiac illness or medical conditions disallowing administration of anti-HER2&#xD;
             therapy. According to HERCEPTIN and PERJETA SPCs.&#xD;
&#xD;
          4. Known hypersensitivity to trastuzumab, pertuzumab, Thero2-01S22, murine proteins or to&#xD;
             any of the excipients.&#xD;
&#xD;
          5. Uncontrolled central nervous system metastatic lesion&#xD;
&#xD;
          6. Patients who, for social, geographic or psychological reasons, cannot be adequately&#xD;
             followed up and/or are incapable of undergoing regular controls&#xD;
&#xD;
          7. Pregnant or breastfeeding women&#xD;
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <gender_based>Yes</gender_based>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Xavier PIVOT, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>Institut de cancérologie Strasbourg Europe</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Valérie SARTORI</last_name>
    <phone>368767223</phone>
    <phone_ext>33</phone_ext>
    <email>v.sartori@icans.eu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Manon VOEGELIN</last_name>
    <phone>368767360</phone>
    <phone_ext>33</phone_ext>
    <email>promotion-rc@icans.eu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <verification_date>January 2023</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>November 30, 2022</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 13, 2023</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">January 26, 2023</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 13, 2023</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 13, 2023</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">January 26, 2023</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Breast Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

