<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="9661">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 09, 2023</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT05693272</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>COVAC-005</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT05693272</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Clinical Trial to Study the COVAC-1 Booster Dose in Generally Healthy Adults</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Randomized, Observer-Blind, Dose Escalation, Placebo-Controlled, Phase 1 Clinical Trial to Study the Safety and Immunogenicity of a COVAC-1 Booster Dose in Generally Healthy Adults</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Saskatchewan</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Government of Canada</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Government of Saskatchewan</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Saskatchewan</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      VIDO has developed a vaccine called COVAC-1.&#xD;
&#xD;
      The COVAC-1 study vaccine contains a portion of the SARS-CoV-2 spike protein, called S1. The&#xD;
      spike protein is the part of the virus that is responsible for attaching to the surface of&#xD;
      host cells. COVAC-1 contains a TriAdj adjuvant. An adjuvant is a compound that is added to a&#xD;
      vaccine to help the vaccine produce a better immune response. The vaccine is expected to&#xD;
      stimulate the body to make antibodies against the S1 protein. The antibodies will recognize&#xD;
      the viral spike protein if the body is exposed to the virus and prevent COVID-19 illness. In&#xD;
      animal studies, the immune response generated by the COVAC-1 vaccine was able to protect the&#xD;
      vaccinated animals against a severe SARS-CoV-2 infection.&#xD;
&#xD;
      The COVAC-005 Study is a Phase I, multi-centre trial of a SARS-CoV-2 vaccine booster. This is&#xD;
      a randomized, observer-blinded, and placebo-controlled study to assess the safety and&#xD;
      immunogenicity of COVAC-1 booster dose administered once in generally healthy adults 18-65&#xD;
      years of age who have received a minimum of 2 doses of an authorized COVID-19 vaccine at&#xD;
      least 4 months prior to Day 0.&#xD;
&#xD;
      The study will follow a dose-escalation design to test the safety and immunogenicity of three&#xD;
      dosage levels (10, 25 and 50 µg). In each dose escalation group participants will be&#xD;
      randomized in a 3:1 ratio, to receive either the investigational product or a placebo,&#xD;
      respectively. Stratification will be according to the Investigational product dose received.&#xD;
      Sub-analysis will be completed in two age groups, 18-54 and 55-65 years.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Study participants will be initially randomized to the lowest dose of 10 µg or placebo. After&#xD;
      approval by the Sponsor and based on the recommendations from the DSMB following the Day 7&#xD;
      safety analysis, new study participants will be allowed to be randomized in the higher dose&#xD;
      escalation group of 25 µg. Approval will also be sought from the Sponsor, based upon the DSMB&#xD;
      recommendation, to proceed with the higher dose of 50 µg. Within each dose escalation group&#xD;
      of 16 participants (12 active vaccine recipients, and 4 placebo recipients) it is proposed to&#xD;
      randomize a first cohort of 4 participants, including at least 3 active vaccine recipients,&#xD;
      and pending no holding rule is met after 48 hours, as determined by the post-injection phone&#xD;
      call, the remaining 12 participants within that dose escalation group will be randomized.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">January 31, 2023</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">May 30, 2024</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">May 30, 2024</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Sequential Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Quadruple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Assessment of the safety of COVAC-1 booster vaccine (10, 25 and 50 μg dosing of S1 antigen) in generally healthy volunteers</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 365 days</time_frame>
    <description>Incidence of solicited adverse events (AE) up to 7 days post-injection; unsolicited AEs up to 28 days post-injection; any clinically significant laboratory finding up to 28 days post-injection; and any serious AEs (SAEs), potential immune medicated disease (pIMDs), medically attended events or COVID-19 illness up to 365 days.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>To assess the antibody response induced by COVAC-1 booster pre-injection and post injection as measured by spike protein-specific Enzyme Linked Immunosorbent Assay (ELISA)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to Day 365.</time_frame>
    <description>Study samples will be tested to assess the level of anti-SARS-CoV-2 spike IgG binding antibodies present in the human serum samples by using a validated ELISA.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>To assess the immune response induced by COVAC-1 booster vaccine, as measured by cell immune response markers using flow cytometry.</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to Day 365.</time_frame>
    <description>Peripheral Blood Mononuclear Cells (PBMCs) samples collected pre- and post-injection will be assessed for spike protein-specific Helper T-lymphocytes (CD4+) and Cytotoxic T-lymphocytes (CD8+) population producing cytokine profile.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>To assess the immune response induced by COVAC-1 booster vaccine, as measured by cell immune response markers using an ELISpot assay.</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to Day 365.</time_frame>
    <description>Peripheral Blood Mononuclear Cells (PBMCs) samples collected pre- and post-injection will be assessed for spike peptide-specific T cell responses, IFN-gamma and IL-5, as a measurement of COVAC-1 immune response induction.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>To assess the antibody response induced by COVAC-1 booster pre-injection and post injection as measured by virus microneutralization assay.</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to Day 365.</time_frame>
    <description>Study samples will be tested to assess the level of SARS-CoV-2 Wuhan neutralizing antibodies present in the human serum samples by SARS-CoV-2 live virus microneutralization assay.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>To assess the antibody response induced by COVAC-1 booster pre-injection and post injection as measured by pseudovirus neutralization assay.</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to Day 365.</time_frame>
    <description>Study samples will be tested to assess the level of SARS-CoV-2 Wuhan pseudovirus neutralizing antibodies present in the human serum samples by SARS-CoV-2 pseudotyped virus neutralization assay.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>To assess the neutralizing antibody response induced by COVAC-1 against the Omicron and/or the most relevant currently circulating Variants of Concern.</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 365 days</time_frame>
    <description>Study samples will be tested to assess the level of neutralizing antibodies against the SARS-CoV-2 Omicron Variant of Concern and/or against other currently circulating Variants of Concern, present in the human serum samples by SARS-CoV-2 live virus microneutralization assay.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>4</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">47</enrollment>
  <condition>Severe Acute Respiratory Syndrome Coronavirus 2 Infection</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>COVAC-01 10µg group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>12 healthy adults ≥18 years of age receive the vaccine on Day 0.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>COVAC-01 25µg group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>12 healthy adults ≥18 years of age receive the vaccine on Day 0.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>COVAC-01 50µg group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>12 healthy adults ≥18 years of age receive the vaccine on Day 0.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo Control</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>12 healthy adults ≥18 years of age receive a dose of normal saline (placebo) on Day 0.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>COVAC-1</intervention_name>
    <description>Intramuscular vaccine against SARS-CoV-2</description>
    <arm_group_label>COVAC-01 10µg group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>COVAC-01 25µg group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>COVAC-01 50µg group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Saline Placebo</intervention_name>
    <description>Intramuscular injection of saline placebo</description>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo Control</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:&#xD;
&#xD;
          1. Male and female participants 18-65 years of age at the time of signing the informed&#xD;
             consent form for the study.&#xD;
&#xD;
          2. Good general health as confirmed by assessments completed no more than 30 days before&#xD;
             study D0. Participants with mild to moderate well controlled comorbidities or having a&#xD;
             medically stable condition, will be eligible. A stable medical condition is defined as&#xD;
             disease not requiring significant change in therapy or hospitalization due to&#xD;
             worsening during the 3 months prior to enrollment, and according to the judgment of&#xD;
             the Investigator, hospitalization during the entire study period is not anticipated.&#xD;
&#xD;
          3. Have received a minimum of 2 doses of an authorized COVID-19 vaccine at least 4 months&#xD;
             prior to the investigational booster dose injection. Proof of vaccination can be&#xD;
             provided as a digital copy of the vaccination receipt on the participant's device, a&#xD;
             screenshot of the receipt on the device, or a printed paper copy.&#xD;
&#xD;
          4. Male participants, and heterosexually active females of child-bearing potential, must&#xD;
             practice adequate contraception for 30 days prior to the injection and must agree to&#xD;
             continue adequate contraception until 180 days after the injection. Negative pregnancy&#xD;
             test will be obtained from female participants of child-bearing potential at screening&#xD;
             and at Day 0.&#xD;
&#xD;
          5. Provide a written informed consent for the study prior to performing any study-related&#xD;
             procedure. The Investigator or a qualified designee must ensure the appropriate&#xD;
             consent is in place.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Exclusion Criteria:&#xD;
&#xD;
          1. Presence of any febrile illness or any known or suspected acute illness on the day of&#xD;
             immunization.&#xD;
&#xD;
          2. Clinically significant bleeding disorder (e.g., clotting factor deficiency,&#xD;
             coagulopathy, or platelet disorder), or prior history of significant bleeding or&#xD;
             bruising following intramuscular injection or venipuncture.&#xD;
&#xD;
          3. Presence of an autoimmune disease.&#xD;
&#xD;
          4. Receiving systemic steroids in doses exceeding 20mg daily of prednisone or equivalent,&#xD;
             for ≥ 14 days within 1 month, or has recently received any other cytotoxic or&#xD;
             immunosuppressive drug within 6 months prior to the injection of the study vaccine.&#xD;
&#xD;
          5. Has a known malignancy diagnosed within the past 5 years. Participants with basal cell&#xD;
             carcinoma or squamous cell carcinoma of the skin are not excluded.&#xD;
&#xD;
          6. Currently receiving systemic immunomodulatory therapy or received chemotherapy within&#xD;
             the last 5 years excluding topical agents.&#xD;
&#xD;
          7. Has received blood products or immunoglobulins (IVIg or IMIg) within 3 months of study&#xD;
             entry/baseline serologic evaluation.&#xD;
&#xD;
          8. Currently on anti-tuberculosis therapy.&#xD;
&#xD;
          9. Had SARS-CoV-2 infection within 4 months prior to study Day 0. A potential participant&#xD;
             is considered to have COVID-19 infection base on one of the following:&#xD;
&#xD;
               -  Positive polymerase chain reaction (PCR) or rapid antigen test.&#xD;
&#xD;
               -  Documentation in a medical history report.&#xD;
&#xD;
               -  Reported by candidate.&#xD;
&#xD;
         10. Has received any non-COVID-19 authorized vaccines (e.g., influenza) within 2 weeks&#xD;
             prior to receiving study dose injection.&#xD;
&#xD;
         11. Has received any experimental SARS-CoV-2 / COVID-19 vaccines Receipt of&#xD;
             SARSCoV-2/COVID-19 vaccines that were experimental at the time of administration but&#xD;
             are currently authorized, more than 6 months prior to Day 0, will not lead to&#xD;
             exclusion.&#xD;
&#xD;
         12. Planning to receive booster doses of any authorized COVID-19 vaccine during the first&#xD;
             two months days from study vaccination.&#xD;
&#xD;
         13. Abnormal laboratory test results (hematology, biochemistry, and urinalysis) as&#xD;
             compared to the local normal lab ranges. To exclude transient abnormalities,&#xD;
             laboratory tests may be repeated once. Abnormal lab test results considered not&#xD;
             clinically significant by the Investigator will not be exclusionary.&#xD;
&#xD;
         14. Has a history of any reaction or known sensitivity likely to be exacerbated by any&#xD;
             component of the study vaccine.&#xD;
&#xD;
         15. Is currently participating in or has participated in a study of an investigational&#xD;
             agent within 6 months prior to the injection of the booster vaccine under study.&#xD;
&#xD;
         16. A female is not eligible to participate if she is pregnant or breast feeding&#xD;
&#xD;
         17. Being a member of the study team, or an immediate family member or household member of&#xD;
             a member on the study team.&#xD;
&#xD;
         18. Any condition, which in the opinion of the investigator may deem the participant&#xD;
             inappropriate for the study.&#xD;
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>65 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Diex Recherche Joliette Inc.</name>
      <address>
        <city>Joliette</city>
        <state>Quebec</state>
        <zip>J6E 2B4</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Diex Recherche Quebec Inc.</name>
      <address>
        <city>Québec City</city>
        <state>Quebec</state>
        <zip>G1V 4T3</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Diex Recherche Sherbrooke</name>
      <address>
        <city>Sherbrooke</city>
        <state>Quebec</state>
        <zip>J1L 0H8</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>DIEX Recherche Victoriaville</name>
      <address>
        <city>Victoriaville</city>
        <state>Quebec</state>
        <zip>G6P 6P6</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Canada</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>June 2023</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>December 22, 2022</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 12, 2023</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">January 20, 2023</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 1, 2023</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 1, 2023</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">June 2, 2023</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Saskatchewan</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Volker Gerdts</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Director &amp; CEO Vaccine and Infectious Disease Organization</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>COVID-19 Booster Vaccine</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Severe Acute Respiratory Syndrome</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>COVID-19</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

