<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="9238">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 09, 2023</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT05702255</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2022-9-55</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT05702255</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Self- Administered Acupressure for Diarrhea Predominant Irritable Bowel Syndrome</brief_title>
  <official_title>Effect of Self- Administered Acupressure on Diarrhea Predominant Irritable Bowel Syndrome Patients' Health Outcomes: a Double Blind- Sham Controlled Randomized Clinical Trial</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Alexandria University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Alexandria University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study aims to assess the effect of active self- administered acupressure compared to&#xD;
      sham self- administered acupressure on the health outcome for patient with diarrhea&#xD;
      predominant Irritable Bowel Syndrome&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Research suggests promising benefits of acupuncture in terms of symptom control and quality&#xD;
      of life improvements in patients with irritable bowel syndrome. but the cost of the needle&#xD;
      and the invasive nature of the procedure decreases patient compliance with acupuncture. in&#xD;
      this respect, acupressure can be taught to patients to allow them to perform it themselves,&#xD;
      instead of being administered by practitioners. Self-administered acupressure is less&#xD;
      time-intensive, low-cost, and flexible to perform. Nurses involved in irritable bowel&#xD;
      syndrome patient care play an active role in the practitioner-patient relationship By&#xD;
      assessing the specific symptoms that are present, determining the severity of symptoms and&#xD;
      the impact on the irritable bowel syndrome patient's life, and being knowledgeable of&#xD;
      available treatment options, the nurse involved in irritable bowel syndrome care becomes an&#xD;
      essential conduit of information and a valuable facilitator of a positive&#xD;
      practitioner-patient therapeutic relationship. In this way, nurses can help to limit the&#xD;
      negative consequences of this common disorder and improve overall treatment outcomes in this&#xD;
      population. . Thus this study will be conducted to assess the effectiveness of active&#xD;
      self-administered acupressure on diarrhea-predominant irritable bowel syndrome&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">February 5, 2023</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">May 2023</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">May 2023</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Supportive Care</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double (Participant, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
    <masking_description>a randomization sequence will be generated by an independent statistician. The randomization list will be recorded and enclosed in sequentially numbered, opaque envelopes. after finishing baseline assessment, the training researcher will open the envelopes to avoid selection bias. only the training researcher will know the group allocation. Participants and other relevant researchers (the outcome evaluator, data managers, and statisticians) will be blinded to the group allocation.</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Baseline mean of irritable Bowel Syndrome Symptom Severity Score</measure>
    <time_frame>Immediately before assigning the participants to the study groups</time_frame>
    <description>It is five item questionnaire measuring frequency and intensity of abdominal pain, the severity of abdominal distension, dissatisfaction with bowel habits, and the interference of IBS with daily life. Subjects respond to each question on a 100-point visual analogue scale. The total score ranges from 0 to 500. Subjects can be categorized as having mild (75-175), moderate (175-300), or severe (&gt;300) disease</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from the baseline irritable Bowel Syndrome Symptom Severity Score at 2 weeks</measure>
    <time_frame>after 2 weeks from the baseline</time_frame>
    <description>t is five item questionnaire measuring frequency and intensity of abdominal pain, the severity of abdominal distension, dissatisfaction with bowel habits, and the interference of IBS with daily life. Subjects respond to each question on a 100-point visual analogue scale. The total score ranges from 0 to 500. Subjects can be categorized as having mild (75-175), moderate (175-300), or severe (&gt;300) disease</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from the baseline irritable Bowel Syndrome Symptom Severity Score at 4 weeks</measure>
    <time_frame>after 4 weeks from the baseline</time_frame>
    <description>t is five item questionnaire measuring frequency and intensity of abdominal pain, the severity of abdominal distension, dissatisfaction with bowel habits, and the interference of IBS with daily life. Subjects respond to each question on a 100-point visual analogue scale. The total score ranges from 0 to 500. Subjects can be categorized as having mild (75-175), moderate (175-300), or severe (&gt;300) disease</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Irritable Bowel Syndrome Adequate Relief question</measure>
    <time_frame>At the baseline</time_frame>
    <description>It is a dichotomous single item that asks participants &quot;Over the past week have you had adequate relief of your irritable Bowel Syndrome symptoms?&quot; . A responder was defined as a patient who answered this question affirmatively.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Irritable Bowel Syndrome Adequate Relief question</measure>
    <time_frame>After 2 weeks from the baseline</time_frame>
    <description>It is a dichotomous single item that asks participants &quot;Over the past week have you had adequate relief of your irritable Bowel Syndrome symptoms?&quot; . A responder was defined as a patient who answered this question affirmatively.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Irritable Bowel Syndrome Adequate Relief question</measure>
    <time_frame>After 4 weeks from the baseline</time_frame>
    <description>It is a dichotomous single item that asks participants &quot;Over the past week have you had adequate relief of your irritable Bowel Syndrome symptoms?&quot; . A responder was defined as a patient who answered this question affirmatively.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Mean stool frequency after 2 weeks</measure>
    <time_frame>After 2 weeks from the patient endorsement</time_frame>
    <description>Defined by the bi-weekly change of frequency of defecation,patient will report the number of defecation per day to calculate it.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Mean change of stool frequency after 4 weeks</measure>
    <time_frame>After 4 weeks from the patient endorsement</time_frame>
    <description>Defined by the bi-weekly change of frequency of defecation,patient will report the number of defecation per day to calculate it.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Stool consistency</measure>
    <time_frame>at the baseline</time_frame>
    <description>Defined by the Bristol Stool Form Scale, It is an ordinal scale of stool types ranging from the hardest (Type 1) to the softest (Type 7). Types 1 and2 are considered to be abnormally hard stools while Types 6 and 7 are considered abnormally loose/liquid stools. Type 3, 4 and 5 are considered to be the most normal stool type</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in the frequency of stool consistency at 2 weeks from the baseline</measure>
    <time_frame>after 2 weeks from baseline</time_frame>
    <description>defined by the Bristol Stool Form Scale</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in the frequency of stool consistency at 4 weeks from the baseline</measure>
    <time_frame>after 4 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Defined by the Bristol Stool Form Scale, It is an ordinal scale of stool types ranging from the hardest (Type 1) to the softest (Type 7). Types 1 and2 are considered to be abnormally hard stools while Types 6 and 7 are considered abnormally loose/liquid stools. Type 3, 4 and 5 are considered to be the most normal stool type</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Demographic and clinical data</measure>
    <time_frame>before assignment of the participants to the study groups</time_frame>
    <description>A questionnaire will be developed to collect data about participants' age, gender, body mass index, physical activity status, diet, smoking status, medication used.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>the baseline mean of psychological distress measured by the Hospital Anxiety and Depression Scale</measure>
    <time_frame>at the baseline</time_frame>
    <description>the scale contains 14 items, seven statements on each sub-scale which assess symptoms experienced during the past week on four-point rating scale (0 to 3); a higher score depicts a worse condition. For each sub-scale the maximum score is 21. A score of ≥11 is considered a clinically significant disorder, whereas a score between 8 and 10 suggests a mild disorder</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from the baseline mean of the psychological distress measured by the Hospital Anxiety and Depression Scale at 4 weeks</measure>
    <time_frame>after 4 weeks from the baseline</time_frame>
    <description>the scale contains 14 items, seven statements on each sub-scale which assess symptoms experienced during the past week on four-point rating scale (0 to 3); a higher score depicts a worse condition. For each sub-scale the maximum score is 21. A score of ≥11 is considered a clinically significant disorder, whereas a score between 8 and 10 suggests a mild disorder</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Baseline mean of the quality of Life</measure>
    <time_frame>at the baseline</time_frame>
    <description>it will be measured by the irritable bowel syndrome quality of Life questionnaire. It consists of 34 items that assess the degree to which irritable bowel syndrome disturbed quality of life for a subject over the past 30 days through eight sub-scales. Each item is rated on a 5-point scale ranging from 1 to 5 with higher values indicating a lower quality of life.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from the baseline mean of the quality of life at 4 weeks</measure>
    <time_frame>Four weeks after the baseline assessment</time_frame>
    <description>it will be measured by the irritable bowel syndrome quality of Life questionnaire. It consists of 34 items that assess the degree to which irritable bowel syndrome disturbed quality of life for a subject over the past 30 days through eight sub-scales. Each item is rated on a 5-point scale ranging from 1 to 5 with higher values indicating a lower quality of life.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Related adverse Events</measure>
    <time_frame>from the patients endorsement till one week after study completion</time_frame>
    <description>An unfavorable change in the health of a participants that happens during a clinical study or within a week after the study has ended. This change may or may not be caused by the acupressure.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Adherence to the to active and sham self-administered acupressure of the study.</measure>
    <time_frame>throughout study completion, an average of 4 months</time_frame>
    <description>The adherence will be calculated as percentage of planned sessions of acupressure, and adherence rate above 80% was set as a minimum requirement to be regarded as acceptable</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>use of rescue medicine</measure>
    <time_frame>throughout study completion, an average of 4 months</time_frame>
    <description>participants will be asked to report the use of rescue medicine for diarrhea or gastrointestinal symptoms</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">150</enrollment>
  <condition>Irritable Bowel Syndrome With Diarrhea</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Active acupoints group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>All participants in the active group will be treated with basic acupoints Zhongwan (CV 12), Tianshu (ST25) in alternation with Sanyinjiao (SP 6), Zusanli (ST 36). Moreover according to traditional Chinese medicine diagnosis, additional acupoints will be added. The frequency of acupressure treatment will be twice a day for 4 weeks, in total 56 sets.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Sham acupoints group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Sham Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>All participants on the sham acupoints group will recieive sham Zhongwan (CV 12), sham Tianshu (ST25), sham Sanyinjiao (SP 6), and sham Zusanli (ST 36) acupressure. All the sham points are 2 cm outside and parallel to the actual points which do not match any recognized acupuncture points and are thought to have no therapeutic effect. The frequency of acupressure treatment will be twice a day for 4 weeks, in total 56 sets.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Active acupressure</intervention_name>
    <description>Participants will receive training (2 sessions, 2 days a part) by a training researcher. Patients will be taught on the acupoints location and the acupressure technique. Participants will be verified for the correct location of the acupoints, acupressure technique and strength. Participants will be instructed to use thumb or middle finger to self- press each acupoint using circular movements. The force of pressing must be sufficiently strong but still within a comfortable range. A lubricant will be uses to decrease friction between the acupoints and the finger. Follow up evaluation will be at the end of the week 2 and week 4 .The training researcher will make weekly calls to remind participants to perform acupressure and to answer questions</description>
    <arm_group_label>Active acupoints group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Sham acuptressure</intervention_name>
    <description>The same protocol as the active acupressure group.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Sham acupoints group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Diagnosed with diarrhea irritable bowel syndrome symptoms in accordance with Rome IV&#xD;
             diagnostic criteria&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Agreed to be on a fixed dose of the pharmacological therapy throughout the study&#xD;
&#xD;
        Exclusion Criteria:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Patients with severe lesions in major organs such as heart, liver and kidney,&#xD;
             hematopoietic diseases or tumors&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Eating disorders&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  History of major abdominal surgery&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  History of neurological and mental illness&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Usage of other treatment rather than the medical treatment on a regular basis 2 weeks&#xD;
             prior to randomization and throughout the study&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Previous history of drug or alcohol abuse 6 months prior to randomization&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Pregnant and lactating women.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Patient reporting of adequate relief of their irritable bowel syndrome symptoms the&#xD;
             week preceding the randomization&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Patient has too mild symptoms, i.e. not visual analogue scale &gt;40 on any of the five&#xD;
             GI questions of irritable bowel syndrome symptoms severity index&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Currently participating in other clinical trials&#xD;
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Maha G Asal, Phd</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Alexandria University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Zahraa H Ramzy, Phd</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Alexandria University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Rasha F Ahmed, Phd</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Alexandria University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Maha G Asal, Phd</last_name>
    <phone>+20101200413</phone>
    <email>maha-gamal@alexu.edu.eg</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Zahra H Ramzy, Phd</last_name>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>outpatient clinics of Main University Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Alexandria</city>
        <country>Egypt</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>maha asal, Pha</last_name>
      <phone>+20101200413</phone>
      <email>maha-gamal@alexu.edu.eg</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Egypt</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>February 2023</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>January 7, 2023</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 18, 2023</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">January 27, 2023</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 5, 2023</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 5, 2023</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">February 8, 2023</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Alexandria University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Maha Gamal Ramadan Asal</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Principle investgator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Irritable Bowel Syndrome</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Syndrome</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Diarrhea</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

