<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="9334">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 09, 2023</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT05700266</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>AA-ICAS</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT05700266</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Anticoagulation Using Rivaroxaban on Top of Aspirin in Intracranial Atherostenosis Stenosis</brief_title>
  <acronym>AA-ICAS</acronym>
  <official_title>Anticoagulation Using Rivaroxaban on Top of Aspirin in Recent Stroke/Transient Ischemic Attack Patients With Intracranial Atherostenosis Stenosis (AA-ICAS)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>The First Affiliated Hospital with Nanjing Medical University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Natural Science Foundation of China</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>The First Affiliated Hospital with Nanjing Medical University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The primary goal of the clinical trial is to test the effect of oral rivaroxaban plus aspirin&#xD;
      in patients with recent stroke/ transient ischemic attack (TIA) caused by intracranial artery&#xD;
      stenosis. Participants will be divided into 2 groups to receive either oral rivaroxaban plus&#xD;
      aspirin or oral clopidogrel plus aspirin. The main question it aims to answer is whether the&#xD;
      experimental group (oral rivaroxaban plus aspirin) is superior to the control group ( oral&#xD;
      clopidogrel plus aspirin) to lower recurrent stroke/TIA or death in these patients during 1&#xD;
      year of follow-up.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Intracranial atherosclerosis stenosis (ICAS) accounts for up to 30-50% of strokes amongst&#xD;
      Asian patient cohorts, in contrast to 5-10% of strokes amongst western patient cohorts. The&#xD;
      SAMMPRIS established aggressive medical management (dual antiplatelet therapy using asprin&#xD;
      and clopidogrel, intensive management of vascular risk factors, and lifestyle modification)&#xD;
      as a superior choice for symptomatic ICAS compared to the percutaneous transluminal&#xD;
      angioplasty and stenting. However, around 15% still had recurrent stroke or death during a&#xD;
      median follow-up of 32.4 months in SAMMPRIS study in the aggressive medical management group.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Rivaroxaban is a Non-vitamin K antagonist oral anticoagulant (NOAC) that Directly and&#xD;
      selectively inhibits factor Xa. 2019 European Society of Cardiology (ESC) recommended that&#xD;
      adding rivaroxaban (2.5mg twice a day) to aspirin for long-term secondary prevention in&#xD;
      patients with chronic coronary syndromes (post-myocardial infarction &gt;1 year) may be&#xD;
      considered (IIB). 2020 ESC also recommended the adding of rivaroxaban (2.5mg twice a day for&#xD;
      1 year) to aspirin plus clopidogrel in acute coronary syndrome (IIB).&#xD;
&#xD;
      The proposed study will directly compare rivaroxaban on top of aspirin with clopidogrel on&#xD;
      top of asprin for preventing recurrent stroke/TIA and death in recent stroke/TIA patients&#xD;
      with ICAS.&#xD;
&#xD;
      The investigators calculated that a sample of 1180 patients (590 in each arm) would provide&#xD;
      80% power to detect a relative risk reduction of 35% in the ravaxaban-aspirin group, with a&#xD;
      two-sided type I error of 0.05, assuming an event rate of 15% in the clopidogrel-aspirin&#xD;
      group and a 5% overall rate of withdrawal.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Baseline features of the two groups were compared with the use of an independent group t-test&#xD;
      (for means) or chi-square test (for percentages). Analysis of primary and secondary outcomes&#xD;
      was based on Kaplan-Meier estimates of cumulative incidence. All analyses were performed on&#xD;
      an intention-to-treat basis, unless specified otherwise. All tests were two-sided, and a P&#xD;
      value of 0.05 was considered to indicate statistical significance. All statistical analyses&#xD;
      were performed with the use of SPSS software.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">March 2023</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2024</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2024</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2/Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>This study is an investigator initiated, randomized, blinded endpoint assessment, clinical trial and conducted at 10 sites in the China. Patients meeting the enrollment criteria will be randomly assigned to one of the two treatment groups (1:1) and will be followed up for 1 year.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
    <masking_description>Endpoint assessments, including neurological function evaluation, primary and secondary ending points, will be performed blindly by an assessment group who are blind to this study.</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>any stroke (ischemic or hemorrhagic) or death during 1 year of follow-up</measure>
    <time_frame>the primary outcome will be assessed during 1 year of follow-up after recruitments.</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in the neurological function recovery</measure>
    <time_frame>Neurological function will be evaluated at 90 days, 6 months and 1 year after recruitments.</time_frame>
    <description>Neurological function will be evaluated using National Institute of Health stroke scale (NIHSS), modified Ranking Scale.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Major non-intracranial bleeding</measure>
    <time_frame>during 1 year of follow-up after recruitments.</time_frame>
    <description>Major non-intracranial bleeding is defined according to the International Society on Thrombosis and Haemostasis (ISTH) criteria:&#xD;
clinically overt bleeding with a fatal outcome, a reduction in haemoglobin level of ≥20 g/l within 7 days, transfusion of at least two units of blood, or symptomatic bleeding in a critical area or organ (intraspinal, intraocular, pericardial, intra-articular, intramuscular with compartment syndrome, retroperitoneal).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Clinically relevant non-major bleeding</measure>
    <time_frame>during 1 year of follow-up after recruitments.</time_frame>
    <description>Clinically relevant non-major bleeding is defined as bleeding not fulfilling the ISTH criteria, but that was clinically overt and led to hospitalization, change of antithrombotic therapy, or necessitated a medical or surgical intervention.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>acute myocardial infarction,acute limb ischemia</measure>
    <time_frame>during 1 year of follow-up after recruitments.</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">1180</enrollment>
  <condition>Ischemic Stroke</condition>
  <condition>Intracranial Atherosclerosis</condition>
  <condition>Stenosis</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Rivaroxaban and Aspirin</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Rivaroxaban (2.5mg orally twice a day for 90 days) and Aspirin (100mg once a day for 1 year)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Clopidogrel and Aspirin</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Clopidogrel (300mg loading dose, then 75mg once daily for 90 days) and Aspirin (100mg once a day for 1 year)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Rivaroxaban</intervention_name>
    <description>Rivaroxaban (2.5mg orally twice a day for 90 days)</description>
    <arm_group_label>Rivaroxaban and Aspirin</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Clopidogrel</intervention_name>
    <description>Clopidogrel (300mg loading dose, then 75mg once daily for 90 days)</description>
    <arm_group_label>Clopidogrel and Aspirin</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Aspirin</intervention_name>
    <description>Aspirin (100mg once a day for 1 year)</description>
    <arm_group_label>Clopidogrel and Aspirin</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Rivaroxaban and Aspirin</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Risk Factor Management in both arms</intervention_name>
    <description>Risk factors for stroke (LDL, blood pressure, non-HDL cholesterol, diabetes, smoking, weight, and physical activity) will be monitored and managed</description>
    <arm_group_label>Clopidogrel and Aspirin</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Rivaroxaban and Aspirin</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:&#xD;
&#xD;
          1. Age ≥ 30 years and ≤ 75 years&#xD;
&#xD;
          2. TIA or Acute ischemic stroke that occurred within 30 days prior to randomization.&#xD;
&#xD;
          3. Modified Rankin score of ≤ 3&#xD;
&#xD;
          4. TIA or Acute ischemic stroke attributed to a 50 to 99% stenosis of a major&#xD;
             intracranial artery (internal carotid artery [ICA], vertebral artery [VA], basilar&#xD;
             artery [BA] and the M1 segment of middle cerebral artery [MCA]). The diagnostic&#xD;
             evaluation for ICAS at each site is confirmed by the local investigator, using&#xD;
             magnetic resonance angiography (MRA), or computerized tomographic angiography (CTA),&#xD;
             high resolution MR, or digital substraction angiography (DSA).&#xD;
&#xD;
          5. To increase the likelihood that the symptomatic intracranial stenosis is&#xD;
             atherosclerotic, patients aged 30-49 years are required to meet at least one&#xD;
             additional criteria (i-vi) below:&#xD;
&#xD;
             i. insulin dependent diabetes for at least 15 years. ii. at least 2 of the following&#xD;
             atherosclerotic risk factors: hypertension (blood pressure ≥ 140/90 or on&#xD;
             antihypertensive therapy); dyslipidemia (low density lipoprotein [LDL] ≥ 130 mg /dl or&#xD;
             high density lipoprotein [HDL] &lt; 40 mg/dl or fasting triglycerides ≥150 mg/dl or on&#xD;
             lipid lowering therapy); smoking; non-insulin dependent diabetes or insulin dependent&#xD;
             diabetes of less than 15 years duration; family history of any of the following:&#xD;
             myocardial infarction, coronary artery bypass, coronary angioplasty or stenting,&#xD;
             stroke, carotid endarterectomy or stenting, peripheral vascular surgery in parent or&#xD;
             sibling who was &lt; 55 years of age for men or &lt; 65 for women at the time of the event.&#xD;
&#xD;
             iii. history of any of the following: myocardial infarction, coronary artery bypass,&#xD;
             coronary angioplasty or stenting, carotid endarterectomy or stenting, or peripheral&#xD;
             vascular surgery for atherosclerotic disease.&#xD;
&#xD;
             iv. any stenosis of an extracranial carotid or vertebral artery, another intracranial&#xD;
             artery, subclavian artery, coronary artery, iliac or femoral artery, other lower or&#xD;
             upper extremity artery, mesenteric artery, or renal artery that was documented by&#xD;
             non-invasive vascular imaging or catheter angiography and is considered&#xD;
             atherosclerotic. v. aortic arch atheroma documented by non-invasive vascular imaging&#xD;
             or catheter angiography.&#xD;
&#xD;
             vi. any aortic aneurysm documented by non-invasive vascular imaging or catheter&#xD;
             angiography that is considered atherosclerotic.&#xD;
&#xD;
          6. Patient agrees with follow-up visits and is available by phone.&#xD;
&#xD;
          7. Patient understands the purpose and requirements of the study, can make him/herself&#xD;
             understood, and has signed informed consent.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Exclusion Criteria:&#xD;
&#xD;
          1. Previous treatment of target intracranial lesion with a stent, angioplasty, or other&#xD;
             mechanical devices (e.g. mechanical thrombectomy, coil embolization)&#xD;
&#xD;
          2. Plan to perform angioplasty, stenting, coiling, thrombectomy, endarterectomy or&#xD;
             aneurysmal coil embolization for any other cerebral blood vessels (common carotid&#xD;
             artery [CCA], ICA, VA, MCA, anterior cerebral artery [ACA], posterior cerebral artery&#xD;
             [PCA] et al)&#xD;
&#xD;
          3. Intracranial tumor (except meningioma) or any intracranial vascular malformation&#xD;
&#xD;
          4. Thrombolytic therapy within 24 hours prior to randomization&#xD;
&#xD;
          5. Progressive neurological signs within 24 hours prior to enrollment&#xD;
&#xD;
          6. History of any intracranial hemorrhage (parenchymal, subarachnoid, subdural, epidural)&#xD;
&#xD;
          7. Intracranial arterial stenosis due to arterial dissection; MoyaMoya disease; any known&#xD;
             vasculitic disease; viral vasculopathy; neurosyphilis; any other intracranial&#xD;
             infection; any intracranial stenosis associated with cerebral spinal fluid&#xD;
             pleocytosis; radiation induced vasculopathy; fibromuscular dysplasia; sickle cell&#xD;
             disease; neurofibromatosis; benign angiopathy of central nervous system; postpartum&#xD;
             angiopathy; suspected vasospastic process; reversible cerebral vasoconstriction&#xD;
             syndrome (RCVS); suspected recanalized embolus&#xD;
&#xD;
          8. Presence of any of the following unequivocal cardiac sources of embolism: chronic or&#xD;
             paroxysmal atrial fibrillation, mitral stenosis, mechanical valve, endocarditis,&#xD;
             intracardiac clot or vegetation, myocardial infarction within three months, dilated&#xD;
             cardiomyopathy, left atrial spontaneous echo contrast, ejection fraction less than 30%&#xD;
&#xD;
          9. Known allergy or contraindication to aspirin, clopidogrel or rivaroxaban.&#xD;
&#xD;
         10. Active peptic ulcer disease, major systemic hemorrhage within 30 days, active bleeding&#xD;
             diathesis, platelets &lt; 100,000, hematocrit &lt; 30, international normalized ration [INR]&#xD;
             &gt; 1.5, clotting factor abnormality that increases the risk of bleeding, current&#xD;
             alcohol or substance abuse, uncontrolled severe hypertension (systolic pressure &gt; 180&#xD;
             mm Hg or diastolic pressure &gt; 115 mm Hg), severe liver impairment (aspartate&#xD;
             transaminase [AST] or alanine transaminase [ALT] &gt; 3 x normal, cirrhosis), creatinine&#xD;
             &gt; 3.0 (unless on dialysis)&#xD;
&#xD;
         11. Major surgery (including open femoral, aortic, cardiac or carotid surgery) within&#xD;
             previous 30 days or planned in the next 1 year after enrollment.&#xD;
&#xD;
         12. Any condition other than intracranial arterial stenosis that requires the subject to&#xD;
             take any antithrombotic medication other than aspirin (NOTE: exceptions allowed for&#xD;
             use of subcutaneous heparin for deep vein thrombosis (DVT) prophylaxis while&#xD;
             hospitalized)&#xD;
&#xD;
         13. Severe neurological deficit that renders the patient incapable of living independently&#xD;
&#xD;
         14. Dementia or psychiatric problem that prevents the patient from relevant evaluation or&#xD;
             follow-up reliably&#xD;
&#xD;
         15. Co-morbid conditions that may limit survival to less than 1 year&#xD;
&#xD;
         16. Currently breastfeeding, pregnancy or of childbearing potential and unwilling to use&#xD;
             contraception for the duration of this study&#xD;
&#xD;
         17. Enrollment in another study that would conflict with the current study.&#xD;
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>30 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>75 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Kezhong Zhang, Doctor</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>The First Affiliated Hospital with Nanjing Medical University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Zhaolu Wang, Doctor</last_name>
    <phone>+86-18100613663</phone>
    <email>wangzhaolu123@163.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Kezhong Zhang, Doctor</last_name>
    <phone>+86-13770840575</phone>
    <email>zhangkezhong8@126.com</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <verification_date>February 2023</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>December 26, 2022</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 17, 2023</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">January 26, 2023</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 20, 2023</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 20, 2023</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">February 22, 2023</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>The First Affiliated Hospital with Nanjing Medical University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Kezhong Zhang</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>rivaroxaban, stroke, intracranial atherosclerosis stenosis</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Stroke</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Ischemic Stroke</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Intracranial Arteriosclerosis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Atherosclerosis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Constriction, Pathologic</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Aspirin</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Rivaroxaban</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Clopidogrel</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>Individual participant data will be available to other researchers under reasonable request and approved by the ethics committee.</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

