<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="9808">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 09, 2023</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT05689723</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>Bergmann</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT05689723</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>The Effect of Spinal Manipulation on Hip Extension Strength and Jump Height</brief_title>
  <official_title>The Effect of Spinal Manipulation on Hip Extension Strength and Jump Height, A Double Blind Randomized Control Trial</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Messiah College</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Messiah College</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to study the effects of lumbar manipulation on hip extension&#xD;
      strength and jump height in healthy subjects.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Procedures to be followed: First, the subject will be asked to complete a medical history&#xD;
      form. Then they will be instructed on the procedure for strength and jump testing. Next,&#xD;
      range of motion of the low back will be measured. Then hip strength will be measured using a&#xD;
      digital handheld measurement tool. The subject will then be asked to jump as high as they can&#xD;
      on a floor mat. The subject will then receive a sealed envelope indicating the intervention&#xD;
      they will to receive, either the manipulation or a fake manipulation. Instructions will be&#xD;
      provided, and the subject will be positioned on a treatment table to receive the&#xD;
      intervention. At this point, they will either receive the manipulation or fake manipulation&#xD;
      on the right and left side. An immediate re-test of hip strength will be taken, and the&#xD;
      subject will again jump as high as they can on a floor mat. Follow-up measures of these tests&#xD;
      will be completed again 20 minutes after the intervention is given.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The participant will complete a medical history form and undergo a brief active range of&#xD;
      motion screen of the lumbar spine. The participant will complete a hip strength test&#xD;
      utilizing the microFET 2 Manual Muscle Tester Hand Held Dynamometer. The participant will&#xD;
      then jump as high as they can on the Just Jump System. A sealed envelope indicating the&#xD;
      intervention to be received will be given to the participant. An investigator blinded to the&#xD;
      pre and post-measures will open the envelope indicating the intervention to be performed. The&#xD;
      participant will be blinded to which intervention group they are categorized to. The&#xD;
      participant will be positioned on a high-low treatment table to receive the assigned&#xD;
      intervention, either intervention 1 (thrust mobilization) or 2 (sham mobilization). The&#xD;
      participant will either receive the thrust-mobilization or sham mobilization up to 2 times on&#xD;
      the left and right side. An immediate re-test of hip strength will be conducted followed by&#xD;
      performing the same three jumps. Follow-up measures at 20 minutes post-intervention will be&#xD;
      performed.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Intervention for the Thrust-mobilization Group The intervention group will receive passive&#xD;
      spinal rotational grade V mobilization, based on Maitland's approach. The intervention will&#xD;
      be performed with the subject in right sidelying and left sidelying. The operator's palpating&#xD;
      hand is placed over the L2-3 intervertebral space, and the other hand bends both legs of the&#xD;
      participant up to the range at which the L2-3 midposition is found. The participant is then&#xD;
      asked to straighten the lower leg and hook the upper leg over it with the upper leg's knee&#xD;
      positioned over the side of the plinth. While the lower component is kept still, the&#xD;
      participant's trunk is rotated until the hip starts to lift off from the plinth. The bottom&#xD;
      hand and uppermost hand rest under a pillow and the chest wall, respectively. With the&#xD;
      starting position settled, the operator stands behind the participant, takes up the slack&#xD;
      within the spine and then provides a grade V mobilization while stabilizing the uppermost&#xD;
      shoulder.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Intervention for the Sham Group Subjects are positioned in right sidelying. The experimenter&#xD;
      holds both knees with one arm while placing their opposite hand on the participant's lumbar&#xD;
      spine. The experimenter performs 1 min of ﬂexion and extension PROM without reaching&#xD;
      physiological end range in either direction of movement. This is repeated with the subject in&#xD;
      left sidelying.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Double Blind: The subjects will not know what intervention they are receiving - same generic&#xD;
      script is provided. One Investigator is performing all pre and post-tests without knowledge&#xD;
      of intervention, the other investigator is opening the envelope and providing the&#xD;
      intervention behind a screen without knowledge of test results. This investigator will record&#xD;
      the subjects assigned # and which intervention they received. Investigators will record data&#xD;
      on spreadsheet separately.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">January 2023</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">October 2023</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">October 2023</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Basic Science</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double (Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in hip extension strength</measure>
    <time_frame>immediately post instervention and 20 minutes post</time_frame>
    <description>microFET 2 Manual Muscle Tester Hand Held Dynamometer</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in jump height</measure>
    <time_frame>immediately post instervention and 20 minutes post</time_frame>
    <description>Just Jump System</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">44</enrollment>
  <condition>Weakness, Muscle</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Manipulation</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Left and right sidelyiing gaping high velocity low amplitude thrust mobilization</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Sham Manipulation</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Sham Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>The experimenter holds both knees with one arm while placing their opposite hand on the participant's lumbar spine. The experimenter performs 1 min of ﬂexion and extension PROM without reaching physiological end range in either direction of movement. This is repeated with the subject in left sidelying.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Lumbar manipulation</intervention_name>
    <description>Left and right sidelyiing gaping high velocity low amplitude thrust mobilization</description>
    <arm_group_label>Manipulation</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Sham Manipulation</intervention_name>
    <description>The experimenter holds both knees with one arm while placing their opposite hand on the participant's lumbar spine. The experimenter performs 1 min of ﬂexion and extension PROM without reaching physiological end range in either direction of movement. This is repeated with the subject in left sidelying.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Sham Manipulation</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Between the ages of 18 and 30&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  able to read and write in English and clearly understand the informed consent.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Exclusion Criteria:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  currently have low back pain&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  pregnant or may be pregnant&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  previously diagnosed with spondylolisthesis, a herniated disc, or have signs and&#xD;
             symptoms of nerve root compression&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  history of spine surgery&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  history of cancer, compression fracture, osteoporosis, osteopenia, or a history of&#xD;
             systemic, connective tissue, or neurological disease,&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  pain with the pre-manipulative hold&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  positive findings on medical history form, or physical exam,&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  presence of anxiety during the procedure&#xD;
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>30 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Karl Bergmann, ScD</last_name>
    <phone>717-796-1800</phone>
    <phone_ext>3339</phone_ext>
    <email>kbergmann@messiah.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Amy Humphrey, PhD(c)</last_name>
    <phone>717-796-1800</phone>
    <phone_ext>3035</phone_ext>
    <email>ahumphrey@messiah.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sueki DG, Cleland JA, Wainner RS. A regional interdependence model of musculoskeletal dysfunction: research, mechanisms, and clinical implications. J Man Manip Ther. 2013 May;21(2):90-102. doi: 10.1179/2042618612Y.0000000027.</citation>
    <PMID>24421619</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Wainner RS, Whitman JM, Cleland JA, Flynn TW. Regional interdependence: a musculoskeletal examination model whose time has come. J Orthop Sports Phys Ther. 2007 Nov;37(11):658-60. doi: 10.2519/jospt.2007.0110. No abstract available.</citation>
    <PMID>18057674</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Mintken PE, McDevitt AW, Cleland JA, Boyles RE, Beardslee AR, Burns SA, Haberl MD, Hinrichs LA, Michener LA. Cervicothoracic Manual Therapy Plus Exercise Therapy Versus Exercise Therapy Alone in the Management of Individuals With Shoulder Pain: A Multicenter Randomized Controlled Trial. J Orthop Sports Phys Ther. 2016 Aug;46(8):617-28. doi: 10.2519/jospt.2016.6319.</citation>
    <PMID>27477473</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>McDevitt A, Young J, Mintken P, Cleland J. Regional interdependence and manual therapy directed at the thoracic spine. J Man Manip Ther. 2015 Jul;23(3):139-46. doi: 10.1179/2042618615Y.0000000005.</citation>
    <PMID>26309384</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bergman GJ, Winter JC, van Tulder MW, Meyboom-de Jong B, Postema K, van der Heijden GJ. Manipulative therapy in addition to usual medical care accelerates recovery of shoulder complaints at higher costs: economic outcomes of a randomized trial. BMC Musculoskelet Disord. 2010 Sep 6;11:200. doi: 10.1186/1471-2474-11-200.</citation>
    <PMID>20819223</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Stupar M, Cote P, French MR, Hawker GA. The association between low back pain and osteoarthritis of the hip and knee: a population-based cohort study. J Manipulative Physiol Ther. 2010 Jun;33(5):349-54. doi: 10.1016/j.jmpt.2010.05.008.</citation>
    <PMID>20605553</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Pickar JG. Neurophysiological effects of spinal manipulation. Spine J. 2002 Sep-Oct;2(5):357-71. doi: 10.1016/s1529-9430(02)00400-x.</citation>
    <PMID>14589467</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Espi-Lopez GV, Arnal-Gomez A, Balasch-Bernat M, Ingles M. Effectiveness of Manual Therapy Combined With Physical Therapy in Treatment of Patellofemoral Pain Syndrome: Systematic Review. J Chiropr Med. 2017 Jun;16(2):139-146. doi: 10.1016/j.jcm.2016.10.003. Epub 2016 Nov 22.</citation>
    <PMID>28559754</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Grindstaff TL, Hertel J, Beazell JR, Magrum EM, Ingersoll CD. Effects of lumbopelvic joint manipulation on quadriceps activation and strength in healthy individuals. Man Ther. 2009 Aug;14(4):415-20. doi: 10.1016/j.math.2008.06.005. Epub 2008 Sep 20.</citation>
    <PMID>18805726</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Grindstaff TL, Hertel J, Beazell JR, Magrum EM, Kerrigan DC, Fan X, Ingersoll CD. Lumbopelvic joint manipulation and quadriceps activation of people with patellofemoral pain syndrome. J Athl Train. 2012 Jan-Feb;47(1):24-31. doi: 10.4085/1062-6050-47.1.24.</citation>
    <PMID>22488227</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sanders GD, Nitz AJ, Abel MG, Symons TB, Shapiro R, Black WS, Yates JW. Effects of Lumbosacral Manipulation on Isokinetic Strength of the Knee Extensors and Flexors in Healthy Subjects: A Randomized, Controlled, Single-Blind Crossover Trial. J Chiropr Med. 2015 Dec;14(4):240-8. doi: 10.1016/j.jcm.2015.08.002. Epub 2015 Nov 6.</citation>
    <PMID>26793035</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Yuen TS, Lam PY, Lau MY, Siu WL, Yu KM, Lo CN, Ng J. Changes in Lower Limb Strength and Function Following Lumbar Spinal Mobilization. J Manipulative Physiol Ther. 2017 Oct;40(8):587-596. doi: 10.1016/j.jmpt.2017.07.003. Erratum In: J Manipulative Physiol Ther. 2018 Jan 6;:</citation>
    <PMID>29187310</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Botelho MB, Alvarenga BAP, Molina N, Ribas M, Baptista AF. Spinal Manipulative Therapy and Sports Performance Enhancement: A Systematic Review. J Manipulative Physiol Ther. 2017 Sep;40(7):535-543. doi: 10.1016/j.jmpt.2017.03.014.</citation>
    <PMID>29191288</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sandell J, Palmgren PJ, Bjorndahl L. Effect of chiropractic treatment on hip extension ability and running velocity among young male running athletes. J Chiropr Med. 2008 Jun;7(2):39-47. doi: 10.1016/j.jcme.2008.02.003.</citation>
    <PMID>19674719</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>October 2022</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>October 3, 2022</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 10, 2023</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">January 19, 2023</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 10, 2023</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 10, 2023</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">January 19, 2023</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Muscle Weakness</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

