<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="9487">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 09, 2023</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT05696795</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2000033314</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT05696795</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Janus Kinase Inhibition in Sarcoidosis</brief_title>
  <official_title>JAK1 Inhibition in Sarcoidosis: an Opportunity for Pathogenesis Directed Therapy</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Yale University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Pfizer</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Yale University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>No</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to investigate the role of the oral JAK1 inhibitor, abrocitinib&#xD;
      200 mg once daily, for the treatment of patients with moderate to severe cutaneous&#xD;
      sarcoidosis.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      To determine if JAK1 specific inhibition is effective in treating sarcoidosis, an&#xD;
      inflammatory condition that can cause disfiguring skin lesions. The only FDA approved therapy&#xD;
      is prednisone, a nonspecific immunosuppressant. The primary outcome will be the percent&#xD;
      change in the Cutaneous Sarcoidosis Activity and Morphology Instrument (CSAMI) after 6 months&#xD;
      of abrocitinib 200 mg daily in 10 patients with moderate to severe cutaneous sarcoidosis.The&#xD;
      primary objective of this study is to determine whether oral abrocitinib reduces the CSAMI (a&#xD;
      cutaneous sarcoid clinical scoring tool) in patients with moderate to severe cutaneous&#xD;
      sarcoidosis. The CSAMI tool was selected over other scoring metrics given the highest&#xD;
      interrater reliability of this metric in cutaneous sarcoidosis and the ability to generate&#xD;
      subscores for active disease versus scarring. Secondary outcomes will include percent changes&#xD;
      in organ involvement on whole body PET-CT imaging, Patients reported outcomes 1) Sarcoidosis&#xD;
      related quality-of-life (QoL) metric (King's Sarcoidosis Questionnaire), 2) Skin related&#xD;
      quality of life (Skindex-16) metric, 3) sarcoidosis Fatigue Assessment Scale (FAS), and 4)&#xD;
      Rhinosinusitis Disability Index (RSDI). Secondary outcomes will also include evaluation of&#xD;
      molecular signatures before and during treatment. Soluble IL-2 receptor levels in plasma are&#xD;
      the most reliable known biomarker for sarcoidosis and will be assessed at 0 and 6 months.&#xD;
      Additional secondary outcomes will include correlative immunologic changes in skin tissue and&#xD;
      blood as a result of treatment. Documentation of any spontaneously reported adverse events&#xD;
      will be completed throughout the study.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">May 1, 2023</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">March 1, 2024</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">February 1, 2024</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>N/A</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Male and female subjects at least 18 years of age with moderate to severe cutaneous sarcoidosis.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in Cutaneous Sarcoidosis Activity and Morphology Instrument (CASMI) score</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 6 Months</time_frame>
    <description>Improvement in the Cutaneous Sarcoidosis Activity and Morphology Instrument (CSAMI) after 6 months of abrocitinib therapy. CSAMI is a validated clinical scoring tool for cutaneous sarcoidosis activity and severity. Scores range from 0 to 165. Higher score is worse.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percent Changes in Improvement in Internal Organ Involvement</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 6 Months</time_frame>
    <description>Internal organ involvement and activity will be determined using whole-body positron emission tomography - computed tomography (PET-CT) at baseline and after 6 months of treatment. Change in active inflammation in internal organs will be assessed by calculating total lesion glycolysis (TLG) in affected internal organs. Scores range from 0 to [no upper limit]. Higher score is worse.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in Patient Reported Outcomes Quality of Life (King's Sarcoidosis Questionnaire)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 6 Months</time_frame>
    <description>This tool assesses overall quality of life related to sarcoidosis through a questionnaire. Scores range from 1 to 100. Higher score is better.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in Skin related quality of life (Skindex-16)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 6 Months</time_frame>
    <description>Skindex-16 is a validated quality of life metric which assesses the effect of diseases involving the skin on individuals' quality of life. It is assessed using a questionnaire. Scores range from 0-96. Higher score is worse.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in Fatigue Assessment Scale (FAS)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 6 Months</time_frame>
    <description>FAS is a validated quality of life metric which assesses the effect of sarcoidosis on fatigue / energy level. It is assessed using a questionnaire. Scores range from 0 to 50. Higher score is worse.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in Rhinosinustitis Disability Index (RSDI)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 6 months</time_frame>
    <description>RSDI is a validated quality of life metric which assesses the effect sarcoidosis-related nasal sinus symptoms on quality of life. It is assessed using a questionnaire. Scores range from 0 to 120. Higher Score is worse.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">10</enrollment>
  <condition>Sarcoidosis</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Abrocitinib 200 mg daily</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>6 months of treatment with abrocitinib 200 mg daily</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Abrocitinib 200 mg</intervention_name>
    <description>Abrocitinib (Cibinqo) is FDA approved at 200 mg dose once daily for the treatment of atopic dermatitis. It is not currently FDA approved for the treatment of sarcoidosis.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Abrocitinib 200 mg daily</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:&#xD;
&#xD;
          1. Written informed consent.&#xD;
&#xD;
          2. Male and female patients age 18 years old or older.&#xD;
&#xD;
          3. Diagnosis of moderate to severe cutaneous sarcoidosis (CSAMI of 10 or greater) with&#xD;
             supportive skin biopsy in which other causes of granulomas (infectious, foreign body)&#xD;
             have been ruled out.&#xD;
&#xD;
          4. Patients with either:&#xD;
&#xD;
               1. Cutaneous Sarcoidosis Activity and Morphology (CSAMI) activity score greater than&#xD;
                  or equal to 10 (patients with a CSAMI greater than or equal to 10 have active&#xD;
                  cutaneous sarcoidosis involving several distinct cutaneous sites, have moderate&#xD;
                  to severe disease and would otherwise be considered candidates for systemic&#xD;
                  therapy), or&#xD;
&#xD;
               2. any CSAMI score and skin involvement causing functional impairment (i.e. nasal or&#xD;
                  visual field obstruction)&#xD;
&#xD;
          5. If patients are taking other systemic therapies for their sarcoidosis, they must be&#xD;
             taking a stable dose of the other medication(s) for at least 3 months with no plans to&#xD;
             change the regimen in the next 6 months. With the exception of methotrexate or low&#xD;
             dose prednisone (20 mg or less per day), use of concomitant immunosuppressants, e.g.&#xD;
             infliximab, azathioprine, etc., will not be permitted.&#xD;
&#xD;
               1. Washout of topical medications will be for 2 weeks.&#xD;
&#xD;
               2. Washout for oral medications will not be possible in most cases. Patients will be&#xD;
                  allowed to continue concomitant prednisone (up to 20 mg daily) or weekly&#xD;
                  methotrexate (up to 15 mg daily).&#xD;
&#xD;
          6. Females of childbearing potential must agree to use birth control during the study and&#xD;
             there must be a negative pregnancy test documented prior to starting the medication.&#xD;
&#xD;
          7. Patients must be willing to have skin biopsies, blood collection, and total body&#xD;
             photography and to comply with clinic visits.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Exclusion Criteria:&#xD;
&#xD;
          1. Age &lt;18 years old.&#xD;
&#xD;
          2. Patients with a history of malignancy (except history of successfully treated basal&#xD;
             cell or squamous cell carcinoma of the skin).&#xD;
&#xD;
             a) Cutaneous Sarcoidosis Activity and Morphology (CSAMI) activity score less than or&#xD;
             equal to 10 or&#xD;
&#xD;
          3. Patients known to be HIV or hepatitis B or C positive, or have an active, serious&#xD;
             infection herpes simplex, herpes zoster, and pneumonia. This would also include&#xD;
             localized infections as per what is reflected in their medical records.&#xD;
&#xD;
          4. Patients diagnosed with Rheumatoid Arthritis (RA).&#xD;
&#xD;
          5. Patients with positive tuberculin skin test or positive QuantiFERON TB test.&#xD;
&#xD;
          6. Patients with significant hepatic impairment (i.e., Child Pugh C).&#xD;
&#xD;
          7. Patients with moderate to severe renal impairment.&#xD;
&#xD;
          8. Patients with uncontrolled peptic ulcer disease.&#xD;
&#xD;
          9. Patients with advanced or untreated malignancy with the exception of treated&#xD;
             non-melanoma skin cancer.&#xD;
&#xD;
         10. Patients with a history of deep vein thrombosis and/or pulmonary embolism and/or&#xD;
             clotting disorder.&#xD;
&#xD;
         11. Patients taking immunosuppressive medications, with the exception of methotrexate (up&#xD;
             to 20 mg weekly allowed) and/or low-dose prednisone (up to 20 mg daily allowed),&#xD;
             including but not limited to mycophenolate mofetil, azathioprine, tacrolimus,&#xD;
             cyclosporine, or TNF-α inhibitors.&#xD;
&#xD;
         12. Women of childbearing potential who are unable or unwilling to use birth control while&#xD;
             taking the medication.&#xD;
&#xD;
         13. Women who are pregnant or nursing.&#xD;
&#xD;
         14. Current smoker or history of any tobacco use.&#xD;
&#xD;
         15. Screening labs outside the normal range for parameters associated with potential risk&#xD;
             for treatment under investigation. Including but not limited to:&#xD;
&#xD;
               1. Platelets &lt;150,000/mm3&#xD;
&#xD;
               2. Absolute neutrophil count &lt;1,000/mm3&#xD;
&#xD;
               3. Hemoglobin levels &lt;8 g/dL&#xD;
&#xD;
               4. Absolute Lymphocyte Count &lt;300/mm3&#xD;
&#xD;
         16. Patients with any medical, psychiatric or social condition that is likely to&#xD;
             unfavorably affect the risk-benefit of continued study participation, interfere with&#xD;
             study compliance or confound safety or efficacy assessments.&#xD;
&#xD;
         17. Patients who are taking moderate to strong inhibitors of both CYP2C19 and CYP2C9, or&#xD;
             strong CYP2C19 or CYP2C9 inducers, as well as P-gp substrate where small concentration&#xD;
             changes may lead to serious or life-threatening toxicities.&#xD;
&#xD;
         18. Patients who have recently received a live vaccine. Patients should wait a minimum of&#xD;
             2 weeks, if recently vaccinated, prior to initiating treatment and should not receive&#xD;
             a live vaccine during treatment or 2 weeks post-treatment.&#xD;
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>William Damsky, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Yale University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>William Damsky, M.D.</last_name>
    <phone>203-785-4092</phone>
    <email>william.damsky@yale.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Yvette Strong</last_name>
    <phone>203-737-2506</phone>
    <email>yvette.strong@yale.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Yale University</name>
      <address>
        <city>New Haven</city>
        <state>Connecticut</state>
        <zip>06510</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <contact>
      <last_name>William Damsky, M.D.</last_name>
      <phone>203-785-4092</phone>
      <email>william.damsky@yale.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Yvette Strong</last_name>
      <phone>2037372506</phone>
      <email>yvette.strong@yale.edu</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>William Damsky, M.D.</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>March 2023</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>January 13, 2023</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 13, 2023</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">January 25, 2023</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 15, 2023</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 15, 2023</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 16, 2023</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Yale University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>William Damsky</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Assistant Professor in Dermatology and Dermatopathology</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>abrocitinib</keyword>
  <keyword>JAK1 inhibitor</keyword>
  <keyword>sarcoidosis</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Sarcoidosis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Abrocitinib</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

