<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="9648">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 09, 2023</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT05693597</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>N.sativavsRID BreastCancerpt.</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT05693597</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Evaluation of the Effect of Nigella Sativa for the Prophylaxis to Radiation Induced Dermatitis in Breast Cancer Patients</brief_title>
  <official_title>Evaluation of the Effect of Nigella Sativa for the Prophylaxis to Radiation Induced Dermatitis in Breast Cancer Patients</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>German University in Cairo</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Ain Shams University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>German University in Cairo</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Radiation induced dermatitis (RID) is one of the leading adverse events of radiation therapy,&#xD;
      and if occurred could alter the course of therapy. The main pathways of RID is inflammation&#xD;
      and oxidative stress on local and systemic bases. Nigella sativa is an herbal medicine whose&#xD;
      anti-inflammatory and antioxidant activities have been proven in several clinical trials.&#xD;
      Thus, the aim of the present study is to evaluate the efficacy of Nigella sativa as a&#xD;
      prophylactic method against the development of RID.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Radiation induced dermatitis (RID) is one of the most commonly reported adverse events of&#xD;
      breast radiation therapy (RT).Radiation therapy toxicity is exhibited within hours to weeks&#xD;
      of exposure and persisting throughout the course of treatment. Radiation induced dermatitis&#xD;
      is a result of generation of reactive oxygen species (ROSs), which in return induces&#xD;
      epidermal and dermal inflammatory responses. Radiation causes structural tissue damage, which&#xD;
      trigger production of pro-inflammatory mediators; as NF-κB, iNOS, COX-2, EGFR, MCP-1, and&#xD;
      cytokines such as IL-1, IL-2, IL-6, TNF-a, and IFN- γ, and immune-stimulatory response;&#xD;
      involving an increased movement of leukocytes from the blood into the irradiated tissues.&#xD;
      Subsequently erythema, ulceration, and edema are developed. This is then followed by thinning&#xD;
      of the epidermis, accompanied with degeneration of glands, which manifests as dry&#xD;
      desquamation. If damage to the basal cells and glands is more severe, moist desquamation&#xD;
      occur. From previous, it can be deduced that inflammatory response plays a significant role&#xD;
      in the radiotherapy induced dermatitis.&#xD;
&#xD;
      There are many agents that are used in the management of RID in the clinical settings,&#xD;
      however, up till now there is none supported by the guidelines. Radiation induced dermatitis&#xD;
      occurrence, not only could it impair the patient's quality of life but it could also affect&#xD;
      the RT course of treatment, which could negatively influence the cancer treatment. Therefore&#xD;
      more effort is needed to find a method of prevention of RID, resulting from breast RT,&#xD;
      especially that there is no standard of care for prophylaxis to the radiation induced&#xD;
      dermatitis (RID).&#xD;
&#xD;
      Nigella sativa is herbal medicine that has been widely used in different parts of the world&#xD;
      by different cultures. It has been used traditionally as a remedy for several diseases&#xD;
      including fever, cough, chronic headache, dizziness, back pain, dysmenorrhea, obesity,&#xD;
      diabetes, infection and inflammation, hypertension, and gastrointestinal disorders such as&#xD;
      flatulence, and dysentery. Preclinical and clinical studies have demonstrated the&#xD;
      anti-inflammatory, immunomodulatory, antioxidant, analgesic, and antimicrobial properties of&#xD;
      N. sativa.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Thymoquinone (TQ) is the prominent constituent of Nigella sativa, to which the biological&#xD;
      properties have been attributed. Thymoquinone can act as a potent free radical and superoxide&#xD;
      radical scavenger at both nanomolar and micromolar range, respectively. As well as, its&#xD;
      beneficial effects on antioxidant enzymes, and its detrimental effects on pro-inflammatory&#xD;
      mediators/cytokines, and pro-inflammatory transcription factor; nuclear factor kappa B&#xD;
      (NF-κB).&#xD;
&#xD;
      Based on literature, Nigella sativa has been shown to have antioxidant and anti-inflammatory&#xD;
      effects. As, both the fixed oil of N. sativa, as well as thymoquinone (the main compound of&#xD;
      the essential oil), were proven to inhibit non-enzymatic lipid peroxidation and have an&#xD;
      appreciable free radical scavenging properties. Furthermore, orally administered Nigella&#xD;
      sativa oil showed a reduction of IL-4 and NO production in rats. Additionally, Thymoquinone&#xD;
      showed anti-inflammatory activity through inhibition of cyclooxygenase (COX) and&#xD;
      5-lipooxygenase (5-LPO), as well as through lowering TNF-α and IL-1β levels in arthritis in&#xD;
      rats. It is worth mentioning that thymoquinone was proven to significantly reduce pancreatic&#xD;
      ductal adenocarcinoma cell synthesis of MCP-1, TNF-a, IL-1β and Cox-2. It also inhibited the&#xD;
      constitutive and TNF-a-mediated activation of NF-kB.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Hence, many clinical trials have been using Nigella sativa, to see its anti-inflammatory and&#xD;
      antioxidant effects in different indications including its anti-inflammatory effect in&#xD;
      treatment of oral mucositis in head and neck cancers patients, and managing dermatitis in&#xD;
      breast cancer patients, and its antioxidant effect in patients with psoriasis, and acute&#xD;
      tonsillo-pharyngitis, and many more, where Nigella sativa showed to be not only safe but&#xD;
      effective as well. Nigella sativa oil, Baraka ® gelatin capsules, has been used in doses up&#xD;
      to 80 mg/kg/day in children with acute lymphoblastic leukemia, in the protection against&#xD;
      doxorubicin-induced cardiac toxicity and in the protection against Methotrexate induced&#xD;
      hepatotoxicity, where it was effective and safe.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">January 24, 2023</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">April 2024</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2023</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Group I (control): Patients will not receive any prophylactic intervention, as there is no standard of care for prophylaxis to the radiation induced dermatitis (RID).&#xD;
Group II (Topical intervention): Patients will receive Imtenan ® N. sativa oil apply 1.5 mls; twice daily; not sooner than 2 hours before and after radiation therapy; from day 1 of radiation therapy till the end.&#xD;
Group III (Oral intervention): Patients will receive Baraka ® N. sativa gelatin capsules; 40mg/Kg/day; from day 1 of radiation therapy till the end</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of development of radiation induced dermatitis</measure>
    <time_frame>6 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>If the patient developed Radiation induced dermatitis or not</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Evaluation of Severity of RID developed</measure>
    <time_frame>6 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>The severity of moist desquamation assessed by Common Terminology Criteria for Adverse Events (CTCAE, version6) criteria based on the clinical presentation.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Evaluation of Pain Intensity</measure>
    <time_frame>6 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Pain related assessment will be done through a Visual Analog Scale, with 0 being No pain and 10 being unbearable pain</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Evaluation of Incidence of Treatment-Emergent Adverse Events</measure>
    <time_frame>6 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Patients will be educated and instructed to report any adverse events</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Evaluation of Quality of life</measure>
    <time_frame>6 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Skin-related quality of life assessed through the Dermatology Life Quality Index (DLQI)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Evaluation of Time to develop grade 2 RID</measure>
    <time_frame>6 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Time to develop grade 2 RID incidence, will be assessed by Common Terminology Criteria for Adverse Events (CTCAE, version6) criteria based on the clinical presentation.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">132</enrollment>
  <condition>Radiation Dermatitis</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Group I (control)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients will not receive any prophylactic intervention, as there is no standard of care for prophylaxis to the radiation induced dermatitis (RID).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Group II (Topical intervention)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients will receive Imtenan ® N. sativa oil apply 1.5 mls; twice daily; not sooner than 2 hours before and after radiation therapy; from day 1 of radiation therapy till the end.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Group III (Oral intervention)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients will receive Baraka ® N. sativa gelatin capsules; 40-80 mg/Kg/day; from day 1 of radiation therapy till the end</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Imtenan Oil</intervention_name>
    <description>Cold Press Oil</description>
    <arm_group_label>Group II (Topical intervention)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Baraka Capsules</intervention_name>
    <description>Soft Gelatin Capsules</description>
    <arm_group_label>Group III (Oral intervention)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Histologically confirmed invasive, early stage breast carcinoma scheduled for adjuvant&#xD;
             radiotherapy.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Women aged ≥18 years.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Exclusion Criteria:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Prior exposure to radiotherapy&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Patients with generalized skin disorder&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Patients who failed to sign the written consent&#xD;
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>75 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Mayar Waleed Salaheldin Aly, M.Sc.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>German University in Cairo</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Mayar Waleed Salaheldin Aly, M.Sc.</last_name>
    <phone>00201097952433</phone>
    <email>mayar.waleed@guc.edu.eg</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Mohamed Hassan Solayman, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>00201005882550</phone>
    <email>mohamed.solayman@guc.edu.eg</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Ain Shams University Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Cairo</city>
        <country>Egypt</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Hagar Ibrahim Elghazawy, MD</last_name>
      <phone>00201006232406</phone>
      <email>dr.hagar.elghazawy@med.asu.edu.eg</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Egypt</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>https://www.mdpi.com/1718-7729/17/4/493</url>
    <description>Prophylaxis and management of acute radiation-induced skin reactions: A systematic review of the literature</description>
  </link>
  <link>
    <url>https://www.dovepress.com/radiation-induced-skin-reactions-mechanism-and-treatment-peer-reviewed-fulltext-article-CMAR</url>
    <description>Radiation-induced skin reactions: mechanism and treatment</description>
  </link>
  <link>
    <url>https://link.springer.com/article/10.1007/s00520-013-1896-2</url>
    <description>Clinical practice guidelines for the prevention and treatment of acute and late radiation reactions from the MASCC Skin Toxicity Study Group</description>
  </link>
  <link>
    <url>https://link.springer.com/article/10.1007/s00520-006-0063-4</url>
    <description>The prevention and management of acute skin reactions related to radiation therapy: a systematic review and practice guideline</description>
  </link>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.bccancer.bc.ca/nursing-site/Documents/Symptom%20Management%20Guidelines/14RadiationDermatitis.pdf</url>
    <description>Symptom Management Guidelines: RADIATION DERMATITIS</description>
  </link>
  <link>
    <url>https://academic.oup.com/ajhp/article-abstract/70/12/1025/5112266?redirectedFrom=fulltext</url>
    <description>Prevention and management of radiation-induced dermatitis, mucositis, and xerostomia</description>
  </link>
  <link>
    <url>https://scialert.net/abstract/?doi=pjbs.2004.441.451</url>
    <description>A Review of Medicinal Uses and Pharmacological Activities of Nigella sativa</description>
  </link>
  <link>
    <url>https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/10925395/</url>
    <description>Antioxidant activity of Nigella sativa essential oil</description>
  </link>
  <link>
    <url>https://pesquisa.bvsalud.org/portal/resource/pt/ibc-177883</url>
    <description>Ameliorating effects of Nigella sativa oil on aggravation of inflammation, oxidative stress and cytotoxicity induced by smokeless tobacco extract in an allergic asthma model in Wistar rats</description>
  </link>
  <link>
    <url>https://www.mdpi.com/2218-0532/87/1/3</url>
    <description>The Anti-Inflammatory Activity of Nigella sativa Balm Sticks</description>
  </link>
  <link>
    <url>https://innovareacademics.in/journals/index.php/ijcpr/article/view/35704</url>
    <description>Anti-Inflammatory Effect of Nigella Sativa Oil on Chemoradiation-Induced Oral Mucositis in Patients With Head and Neck Cancers</description>
  </link>
  <link>
    <url>https://www.jceionline.org/article/evaluation-of-efficacy-safety-and-antioxidant-effect-of-nigella-sativa-in-patients-with-psoriasis-a-3557</url>
    <description>Evaluation of efficacy, safety and antioxidant effect of Nigella sativa in patients with psoriasis: A randomized clinical trial</description>
  </link>
  <link>
    <url>https://www.dustri.com/article_response_page.html?artId=4697&amp;doi=10.5414/CPP46295&amp;L=0</url>
    <description>Symptomatic treatment of acute tonsillo-pharyngitis patients with a combination of Nigella sativa and Phyllanthus niruri extract</description>
  </link>
  <link>
    <url>https://europepmc.org/article/med/31964219</url>
    <description>Protective role of black seed oil in doxorubicin-induced cardiac toxicity in children with acute lymphoblastic leukemia</description>
  </link>
  <link>
    <url>https://www.longdom.org/open-access/protective-effect-of-nigella-sativa-oil-against-methotrexate-induced-hepatotoxicity-in-children-with-acute-lymphoblastic-leukemia-2329-6917.1000123.pdf</url>
    <description>Protective Effect of Nigella sativa Oil against Methotrexate Induced Hepatotoxicity in Children with Acute Lymphoblastic Leukemia</description>
  </link>
  <link>
    <url>https://tahomaclinic.com/Private/Articles3/RA/Gheita%202012%20-%20Effectiveness%20of%20Nigella%20sativa%20oil%20in%20rheumatoid%20arthritis.pdf</url>
    <description>Effectiveness of Nigella sativa Oil in the Management of Rheumatoid Arthritis Patients: A Placebo Controlled Study</description>
  </link>
  <link>
    <url>https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/14669258/</url>
    <description>Effect of Nigella sativa (black seed) on subjective feeling in patients with allergic diseases</description>
  </link>
  <link>
    <url>https://europepmc.org/article/med/8033378</url>
    <description>Dermatology Life Quality Index (DLQI)-a simple practical measure for routine clinical use</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>January 2023</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>January 4, 2023</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 11, 2023</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">January 23, 2023</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 30, 2023</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 30, 2023</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">January 31, 2023</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>German University in Cairo</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Mayar Waleed Salaheldin Aly</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Clinical Pharmacy Lecturer Assistant</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Nigella sativa</keyword>
  <keyword>Black seed</keyword>
  <keyword>Baraka</keyword>
  <keyword>Radiation induced dermatitis</keyword>
  <keyword>Breast cancer</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Dermatitis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Radiodermatitis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

