<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="9519">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 09, 2023</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT05696197</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>S64842</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT05696197</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Learning Potential of Patients With Parkinson's Disease After Two Weeks of Targeted Touchscreen Training</brief_title>
  <official_title>Predicting Motor Learning of an Upper Limb Task Based on Behavioral and Disease-specific Characteristics in Patients With Parkinson's Disease</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>KU Leuven</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>KU Leuven</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Parkinson's disease (PD) is characterized by severe motor and non-motor symptoms, including&#xD;
      upper limb dysfunction. Due to the degradation of dopaminergic neurons in the striatum, PD&#xD;
      patients experience difficulties with motor learning and more specifically with the&#xD;
      consolidation of motor memory. Recent work showed that intensive writing training improved&#xD;
      writing skills in PD. Although consolidation effects were present, difficulties with&#xD;
      retention were also still apparent. Besides impacting writing, manual dexterity deficits in&#xD;
      PD can also affect the use of touchscreens. Researchers from our lab demonstrated that&#xD;
      impairments were most pronounced in multi-direction sliding motions, indicating the need for&#xD;
      training of these motor skills. Our lab demonstrated the classic difficulties with retention&#xD;
      in PD after one session of training of a swipe and slide pattern on a tablet (SSP-task) as&#xD;
      single task (ST), although immediate gains were demonstrated. Therefore, in this study the&#xD;
      investigators will examine whether a two-week home-based training program of a tablet-based&#xD;
      SSP-training program will lead to immediate and consolidated improvements that are retained&#xD;
      in time. This program will combine ST and dual task (DT) training to provide variation during&#xD;
      the training period, but also to increase the cognitive challenge during learning, thereby&#xD;
      stimulation consolidation of learning. The primary aim of this study consists of&#xD;
      investigating the learning effects after two weeks of targeted touchscreen training.&#xD;
      Secondary, the investigators will examine whether these effects will also be retained after&#xD;
      four weeks without practice and whether targeted training results in consolidated&#xD;
      improvements, in terms of automaticity and transfer towards an untrained task. Given the&#xD;
      objective recording of compliance to the training protocol, the investigators will explore&#xD;
      the association between compliance rates and learning effects.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Given the impaired touchscreen skills and the espoused difficulties with retention in PD, th&#xD;
      e investigators will examine the training of touchscreen sliding motions delivered on a&#xD;
      tablet enabling practice in the home setting. Both ST and DT conditions will be offered in a&#xD;
      random order and feedback will be provided by means of knowledge of performance to enhance&#xD;
      motivation and retention, as proved successful in previous work. The objective of this study&#xD;
      is to examine the effects of this innovative training program immediately after two weeks of&#xD;
      targeted training as the primary outcome in a randomized controlled trial (RCT). To resemble&#xD;
      daily life as much as possible, all test and training sessions will be carried out in the&#xD;
      ON-phase of the medication-cycle, i.e., approximately 1 hour after last medication intake.&#xD;
      The effect of a 2-week home-based training program with a 4-week follow-up will be examined&#xD;
      by including 36 PD patients, who will be randomized (strata: age, H&amp;Y stage) in the&#xD;
      experimental or control group. Sample size was based on the pilot study using the SSP-task&#xD;
      showing an average movement time of 7.4s ± 3.43 in PD for sequence swiping at baseline in ST.&#xD;
      Based on literature, the researchers assumed an improvement of 20.2% following training at&#xD;
      retention. For the control group, the researchers expect a deterioration in performance of&#xD;
      5.6% after a period without training based on the changes observed in the control groups of&#xD;
      recent studies investigating manual dexterity parameters over time. Using an α = 0.05 and β =&#xD;
      0.20, a sample size was calculated for repeated measures ANOVA analysis with a within-between&#xD;
      factor interaction design (within: pre - post - retention; between: experimental group -&#xD;
      control group). Consequently, total sample size was estimated at 30 participants. Taking a&#xD;
      20% dropout rate into account, this resulted in a total of 18 participants in each group.&#xD;
&#xD;
      The experimental group will train the SSP task for a duration of two weeks, whereas the&#xD;
      control group will not receive any intervention. On day 1 (T0), all participants will undergo&#xD;
      an extensive screening session, including motor and non-motor screening. Testing can be&#xD;
      performed at the subject's home or in our laboratory according to patients' preference.&#xD;
&#xD;
      The average slide duration (in ms) and the accuracy (as the number of correctly formed&#xD;
      patterns in %) on the SSP-task will be recorded as the main digitised outcomes, objectively&#xD;
      recorded via the tablet. In addition to evaluating the immediate effects of touchscreen&#xD;
      training, the investigators will also test retention effects after four weeks without&#xD;
      training as a secondary outcome. Further, consolidation of learning will be assessed using&#xD;
      secondary outcomes such as the SSP-test in ST and DT conditions to assess automaticity of&#xD;
      learning, the mobile phone task to test transfer of learning (MPT, typing a predefined&#xD;
      telephone number on a smartphone). As tertiary outcomes, specific questionnaires to capture&#xD;
      motor and cognitive performance will be administered. Following the baseline session, the&#xD;
      experimental group will receive 10 training sessions of the SSP-training (5 days/week, 10&#xD;
      min/session) over a period of two weeks. The training is home-based and unsupervised but is&#xD;
      extensively explained by an expert trainer. The control group does not receive training. Both&#xD;
      immediately after training (T1) and after a four-week retention period (T2), touchscreen&#xD;
      motor skills will be re-assessed at home. The most appropriate linear mixed models will be&#xD;
      used to analyse SSP performance, with group (intervention - control) as between-subject&#xD;
      factor and time (baseline - post - retention) as within-subject factor. LEDD and other&#xD;
      confounders will be included as covariates.&#xD;
&#xD;
      PD is a highly heterogeneous disorders, not only affecting motor but also cognitive&#xD;
      functions. In fact, up to 80% of patients develops dementia over the disease course. Previous&#xD;
      studies have identified global cognitive function as important determinants of training&#xD;
      success. Therefore, cognitive function will be assessed extensively during the baseline&#xD;
      session to investigate the association with training responsiveness. A global cognitive&#xD;
      screen will consist of the Montreal Cognitive Assessment. Moreover, 2 specific tests will be&#xD;
      used to assess each cognitive subdomain. Attention and working memory will be assessed using&#xD;
      a digit and visual span forward and backward. The trail making test and alternating names&#xD;
      test will be used for executive function. Visuospatial function will be examined using the&#xD;
      short form of the Benton's judgement of line orientation and the Rey Osterrieth Complex&#xD;
      figure. The 30-min recall of the latter test will also be used to assess memory, together&#xD;
      with the Rey Auditory Verbal Learning test. The Boston naming test and the Animal fluency&#xD;
      test of the Controlled Oral Word Association test will be used to assess language. Other&#xD;
      non-motor features, such as anxiety, depression, and sleep quality, will be tested using&#xD;
      validated questionnaires for PD.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Another important determinant of rehabilitation success is training compliance. However,&#xD;
      previous studies have used self-reported logbooks of home-based exercise, which show high&#xD;
      inter-participant variability. As such, our training program overcomes this limitation as&#xD;
      training compliance is automatically recorded via the digitized training tablet. The&#xD;
      investigators will explore whether compliance to training has an impact on learning effects&#xD;
      within the training group by using a correlation analysis between compliance rates and&#xD;
      training-related changes in performance.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">January 10, 2022</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2023</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2023</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Parallel, randomization in two groups (intervention/control)</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Average slide duration (in ms) after two weeks of training</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and post-training (2 weeks)</time_frame>
    <description>The automatically recorded slide duration will be averaged and compared between the experimental group and the control group.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Performance accuracy (in %)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, post (2 weeks) and retention (4 weeks)</time_frame>
    <description>The performance accuracy will be calculated as the number of correctly performed patterns and will be compared between the experimental group and the control group.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Retention effects on average slide duration (in ms) after four weeks follow-up</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, post (2 weeks) and retention (4 weeks)</time_frame>
    <description>The automatically recorded slide duration will be averaged and compared between the experimental group and the control group.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Consolidation effects of two weeks of training</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, post-training (2 weeks)</time_frame>
    <description>Using the behavioral data gathered at the different time points described in Time frame, dual task interference will be calculated and compared between groups (experimental vs control), moreover the transfer towards an untrained task will be examined and compared between groups. The untrained task contains the mobile phone task, in which the time necessary to type in a predefined telephone number is recorded (in s).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">36</enrollment>
  <condition>Parkinson Disease</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Experimental group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Practicing the Swipe Slide Pattern task in ST and DT conditions, offered in a random order over a period of 2 weeks, 5 days a week, approximately 10 minutes per training session. Training will be performed independently at home.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants in the control group will receive no intervention during the study period. They are given the opportunity to perform the SSP-training after the study period to ensure motivation in this group.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Targeted touchscreen training</intervention_name>
    <description>Participants will practice the Swipe Slide Pattern (SSP) task independently at home in both ST and DT condition, offered in a random order. During this task, participants form different pre-defined patterns by moving their finger over a touchscreen, resembling a touchscreen unlock trace. The DT condition includes the SSP-task while counting either red or green lights illuminated on the screen. They will receive 10 training sessions of the SSP-task over a period of two weeks. Each week will consist of 5 consecutive days of training for approximately 10 minutes per session. Participants will perform 9 trials of 12 patterns each, alternated with rest periods of 14 seconds. Instruction and answers are also included. Feedback will be provided by means of knowledge of performance. On each training day, participants will receive a reminder on the training tablet.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Experimental group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Diagnosis of Parkinson's disease based on the 'UK Brain Bank' criteria&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Hoehn and Yahr (H&amp;Y) stage I-III, participants in H&amp;Y stage I should have the right&#xD;
             side as the most affected side&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Right handed, or right-handed use of touchscreen devices.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Exclusion Criteria:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Cognitive decline (Mini Mental State Examination &lt; 24)&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Comorbidities of the upper limb that could interfere with the study and are not caused&#xD;
             by Parkinson's disease&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Other neurological disorders besides Parkinson's disease&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Color blindness as determined by the Ishihara test for color deficiency&#xD;
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Alice Nieuwboer, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>KU Leuven</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Joni De Vleeschhauwer, MSc</last_name>
    <phone>+32 16 32 43 34</phone>
    <email>joni.devleeschhauwer@kuleuven.be</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Department of Rehabilitation Sciences KU Leuven</name>
      <address>
        <city>Leuven</city>
        <zip>3000</zip>
        <country>Belgium</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Joni De Vleeschhauwer, MSc</last_name>
      <phone>+32 16 32 43 34</phone>
      <email>joni.devleeschhauwer@kuleuven.be</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Alice Nieuwboer, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Belgium</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Nackaerts E, Heremans E, Vervoort G, Smits-Engelsman BC, Swinnen SP, Vandenberghe W, Bergmans B, Nieuwboer A. Relearning of Writing Skills in Parkinson's Disease After Intensive Amplitude Training. Mov Disord. 2016 Aug;31(8):1209-16. doi: 10.1002/mds.26565. Epub 2016 Mar 17.</citation>
    <PMID>26990651</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Nieuwboer A, Rochester L, Muncks L, Swinnen SP. Motor learning in Parkinson's disease: limitations and potential for rehabilitation. Parkinsonism Relat Disord. 2009 Dec;15 Suppl 3:S53-8. doi: 10.1016/S1353-8020(09)70781-3.</citation>
    <PMID>20083008</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Nackaerts E, Ginis P, Heremans E, Swinnen SP, Vandenberghe W, Nieuwboer A. Retention of touchscreen skills is compromised in Parkinson's disease. Behav Brain Res. 2020 Jan 27;378:112265. doi: 10.1016/j.bbr.2019.112265. Epub 2019 Sep 27.</citation>
    <PMID>31568836</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sidaway B, Ala B, Baughman K, Glidden J, Cowie S, Peabody A, Roundy D, Spaulding J, Stephens R, Wright DL. Contextual Interference Can Facilitate Motor Learning in Older Adults and in Individuals With Parkinson's Disease. J Mot Behav. 2016 Nov-Dec;48(6):509-518. doi: 10.1080/00222895.2016.1152221. Epub 2016 Jun 24.</citation>
    <PMID>27340809</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Taghizadeh G, Azad A, Kashefi S, Fallah S, Daneshjoo F. The effect of sensory-motor training on hand and upper extremity sensory and motor function in patients with idiopathic Parkinson disease. J Hand Ther. 2018 Oct-Dec;31(4):486-493. doi: 10.1016/j.jht.2017.08.001. Epub 2017 Nov 14.</citation>
    <PMID>29150384</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Correa TV, da Silva Rocha Paz T, Allodi S, de Britto VLS, Correa CL. Progressive muscle-strength protocol for the functionality of upper limbs and quality of life in individuals with Parkinson's disease: Pilot study. Complement Ther Med. 2020 Aug;52:102432. doi: 10.1016/j.ctim.2020.102432. Epub 2020 May 23.</citation>
    <PMID>32951706</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Aarsland D, Andersen K, Larsen JP, Lolk A, Kragh-Sorensen P. Prevalence and characteristics of dementia in Parkinson disease: an 8-year prospective study. Arch Neurol. 2003 Mar;60(3):387-92. doi: 10.1001/archneur.60.3.387.</citation>
    <PMID>12633150</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lofgren N, Conradsson D, Joseph C, Leavy B, Hagstromer M, Franzen E. Factors Associated With Responsiveness to Gait and Balance Training in People With Parkinson Disease. J Neurol Phys Ther. 2019 Jan;43(1):42-49. doi: 10.1097/NPT.0000000000000246.</citation>
    <PMID>30531385</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Strouwen C, Molenaar EALM, Munks L, Broeder S, Ginis P, Bloem BR, Nieuwboer A, Heremans E. Determinants of Dual-Task Training Effect Size in Parkinson Disease: Who Will Benefit Most? J Neurol Phys Ther. 2019 Jan;43(1):3-11. doi: 10.1097/NPT.0000000000000247.</citation>
    <PMID>30531381</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Nasreddine ZS, Phillips NA, Bedirian V, Charbonneau S, Whitehead V, Collin I, Cummings JL, Chertkow H. The Montreal Cognitive Assessment, MoCA: a brief screening tool for mild cognitive impairment. J Am Geriatr Soc. 2005 Apr;53(4):695-9. doi: 10.1111/j.1532-5415.2005.53221.x. Erratum In: J Am Geriatr Soc. 2019 Sep;67(9):1991.</citation>
    <PMID>15817019</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>BLACKBURN HL, BENTON AL. Revised administration and scoring of the digit span test. J Consult Psychol. 1957 Apr;21(2):139-43. doi: 10.1037/h0047235. No abstract available.</citation>
    <PMID>13416432</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Llinas-Regla J, Vilalta-Franch J, Lopez-Pousa S, Calvo-Perxas L, Torrents Rodas D, Garre-Olmo J. The Trail Making Test. Assessment. 2017 Mar;24(2):183-196. doi: 10.1177/1073191115602552. Epub 2016 Jul 28.</citation>
    <PMID>26318386</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hyde T, Fritsch T. Assessing executive function in Parkinson disease: the alternating names test. Part I. Reliability, validity, and normative data. Parkinsonism Relat Disord. 2011 Feb;17(2):100-5. doi: 10.1016/j.parkreldis.2010.08.023. Epub 2010 Nov 30.</citation>
    <PMID>21123105</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Winegarden BJ, Yates BL, Moses JA, Benton AL, Faustman WO. Development of an optimally reliable short form for Judgment of Line Orientation. Clin Neuropsychol. 1998;12(3):311-314. doi:10.1076/clin.12.3.311.1992</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gullett JM, Price CC, Nguyen P, Okun MS, Bauer RM, Bowers D. Reliability of three Benton Judgment of Line Orientation short forms in idiopathic Parkinson's disease. Clin Neuropsychol. 2013;27(7):1167-78. doi: 10.1080/13854046.2013.827744. Epub 2013 Aug 19.</citation>
    <PMID>23957375</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Poreh A, Shye S. Examination of the Global and Local Features of the Rey Osterrieth Complex Figure Using Faceted Smallest Space Analysis Examination of the Global and Local Features of the Rey Osterrieth Complex Figure Using Faceted Smallest Space Analysis *. Clin Neuropsychol. 1998;12(4):453-467. doi:10.1076/clin.12.4.453.7240</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Schmidt M. Rey Auditory Verbal Learning Test: RAVLT : A Handbook. Western Psychological Services; 1996. https://books.google.be/books?id=UOcPRAAACAAJ</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kaplan E, Goodglass H, Weintraub S. The Boston Naming Test. Lea &amp; Fibiger; 1983.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Tombaugh TN, Kozak J, Rees L. Normative data stratified by age and education for two measures of verbal fluency: FAS and animal naming. Arch Clin Neuropsychol. 1999 Feb;14(2):167-77.</citation>
    <PMID>14590600</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Leentjens AF, Dujardin K, Pontone GM, Starkstein SE, Weintraub D, Martinez-Martin P. The Parkinson Anxiety Scale (PAS): development and validation of a new anxiety scale. Mov Disord. 2014 Jul;29(8):1035-43. doi: 10.1002/mds.25919. Epub 2014 May 23.</citation>
    <PMID>24862344</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Almeida OP, Almeida SA. Short versions of the geriatric depression scale: a study of their validity for the diagnosis of a major depressive episode according to ICD-10 and DSM-IV. Int J Geriatr Psychiatry. 1999 Oct;14(10):858-65. doi: 10.1002/(sici)1099-1166(199910)14:103.0.co;2-8.</citation>
    <PMID>10521885</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Buysse DJ, Reynolds CF 3rd, Monk TH, Berman SR, Kupfer DJ. The Pittsburgh Sleep Quality Index: a new instrument for psychiatric practice and research. Psychiatry Res. 1989 May;28(2):193-213. doi: 10.1016/0165-1781(89)90047-4.</citation>
    <PMID>2748771</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Schootemeijer S, van der Kolk NM, Ellis T, Mirelman A, Nieuwboer A, Nieuwhof F, Schwarzschild MA, de Vries NM, Bloem BR. Barriers and Motivators to Engage in Exercise for Persons with Parkinson's Disease. J Parkinsons Dis. 2020;10(4):1293-1299. doi: 10.3233/JPD-202247.</citation>
    <PMID>32925106</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Schmidt M, Paul SS, Canning CG, Song J, Smith S, Love R, Allen NE. The accuracy of self-report logbooks of adherence to prescribed home-based exercise in Parkinson's disease. Disabil Rehabil. 2022 Apr;44(8):1260-1267. doi: 10.1080/09638288.2020.1800106. Epub 2020 Aug 7.</citation>
    <PMID>32762573</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>January 2023</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>January 13, 2023</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 23, 2023</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">January 25, 2023</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 23, 2023</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 23, 2023</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">January 25, 2023</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>KU Leuven</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Alice Nieuwboer</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Full Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Neurological rehabilitation</keyword>
  <keyword>Motor learning</keyword>
  <keyword>Touchscreen skills</keyword>
  <keyword>Home-based training</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Parkinson Disease</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

