<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="9855">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 09, 2023</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT05688800</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>p.t.REC/012/004127</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT05688800</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Pressure Release Versus Thoracic Manipulation in Rhomboids MPS</brief_title>
  <official_title>Pressure Release Versus Thoracic Spine Manipulation in Rhomboids Myofascial Pain Syndrome</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Cairo University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Cairo University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of the stud will be to compare the effect of pressure release with thoracic spine&#xD;
      manipulation on pain intensity level and pain pressure threshold, thoracic spine ROM and&#xD;
      physical function onactive rhomboids muscle trigger point in myofascial pain syndrome.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Myofascial pain syndrome (MPS) is one of the most common chronic disorders causing persistent&#xD;
      musculoskeletal pain which is characterized by myofascial trigger points (MTrPs) in palpable&#xD;
      taut bands of skeletal muscle. In recent years, due to our modern lifestyle people is exposed&#xD;
      to postural stresses, inefficient biomechanics, repetitive postural dysfunction, which are&#xD;
      some of the causes of myofascial pain syndrome .Active Rhomboid muscle trigger point are one&#xD;
      of the main causes of inter- scapular pain, as the referral pattern of this muscle is on the&#xD;
      medial border of the scapula. The aim of the study is to find if there any significant&#xD;
      difference between the effect of pressure release and thoracic spine manipulation on pain&#xD;
      intensity level, pain pressure threshold ,thoracic spine ROM and physical function and&#xD;
      symptoms in people with musculoskeletal disorders of the upper limb on active rhomboids&#xD;
      muscle trigger point in myofascial pain syndrome. 66 participants will be allocated randomly&#xD;
      to three groups ; The Participants will be assigned randomly into three groups by simple&#xD;
      methods of randomization. Control group: will receive conventional physical therapy&#xD;
      treatment, Experimental group 1: will receive conventional physical therapy treatment in&#xD;
      addition to pressure release Experimental group 2: will receive conventional physical therapy&#xD;
      treatment in addition to thoracic spine manipulation.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">March 2023</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2023</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2023</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Control group: will receive conventional physical therapy treatment Experimental group 1: will receive conventional physical therapy treatment in addition to pressure release Experimental group 2: will receive conventional physical therapy treatment in addition to thoracic spine manipulation</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double (Participant, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Pain Intensity level</measure>
    <time_frame>up to three weeks</time_frame>
    <description>pain intensity level will be measured by visual analogue scale (VAS)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Pressure Pain threshold level (PPT)</measure>
    <time_frame>up to three weeks</time_frame>
    <description>pressure pain threshold level (PPT) will be measured by digital algometer</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Rom of Motion</measure>
    <time_frame>up to three weeks</time_frame>
    <description>rom will be measured by digital inclinometer</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Physical function</measure>
    <time_frame>up to three weeks</time_frame>
    <description>physical function will be measured by Disability of Arm, Shoulder, and Hand questionnaire (DASH)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">66</enrollment>
  <condition>Myofascial Pain Syndrome</condition>
  <condition>Trigger Point Pain, Myofascial</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Each participant include 22 participants will receive conventional physical therapy treatment including TENS, continuous ultrasound ,infra-red radiation and combined stretching and strengthening exercise</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Experimental group 1 :pressure release technique</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Each participant include 22 participants will receive the conventional physical therapy treatment in addition to pressure release technique</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Experimental group 2: thoracic spine manipulation</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Each participant include 22 participants will receive the conventional physical therapy treatment in addition to thoracic spine manipulation</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>conventional therapy</intervention_name>
    <description>Participants in control group will receive conventional physical therapy treatment including Conventional TENS high frequency (90-130hz) low intensity according to the patient sensation for 30-45 min(Gozani, 2019) , continuous ultrasound with frequency 1 MHz and intensity 0.8 W/cm 2 will be applied by slow circular perpendicular movements with slightly deep pressure. Application time was 5 minutes at each side of the level of C7_T4 along the medial borders of the scapulae width, infra-red radiation will be four 15 minutes and directed perpendicular to the inter-scapular area, centered at the level of C7_T4 long and between the 2 medial borders of the scapulae width . Also combined stretching and strengthening exercise will be added due to its greater pain-relieving effect</description>
    <arm_group_label>Control group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Experimental group 1 : pressure release technique</intervention_name>
    <description>Participants who are assigned to this group will receive conventionalphysical therapy treatment in addition to pressure release technique. the participant will be positioned either sitting or prone position according to his preferred position, the researcher will apply the pressure release procedure by a pressure below the PPT dependent onsoft tissue release. When the researcher detected a reduction in soft tissue resistance, the amount of compression will be increased. The pressure should -33- be nonpainful, applied at slow rate, and will maintained until release of tissue barrier. Further pressure was increased to reach a new barrier. The pressure will last 60 seconds. With the thumb or the second and third fingers, the non-painful manual therapy approach was applied to the active MTrPs of therhomboid muscle</description>
    <arm_group_label>Experimental group 1 :pressure release technique</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Experimental group 2: thoracic spine manipulation</intervention_name>
    <description>Thoracic spine manipulation will be performed as screw thrust manipulation technique; the vertebral transverse processes will beforced from posterior to anterior direction. The direction of the manipulation should be identified by applying springing test to the adjacent spinous process to determine the painful and stiff segment. Patient will be prone and researcher hand placement will be positioned as the following one pisiform on the right facet of the above, and the other pisiform on the left facet of the below vertebrae.A slack will be taken up. The thrust applied directly toward the patient once</description>
    <arm_group_label>Experimental group 2: thoracic spine manipulation</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:&#xD;
&#xD;
        Participants ages will be from 18 to 30 years Participants will be from both genders.&#xD;
        Participants that have Myofascial pain syndrome due to at least one active trigger points&#xD;
        in rhomboid muscle (Haleema and Riaz, 2021). Participants have myofascial pain syndrome&#xD;
        since more than three months. Presence of a palpable taut band in a skeletal muscle&#xD;
&#xD;
        Exclusion Criteria:&#xD;
&#xD;
        Malignancy. Fractures of the Thoracic spine. Cervical radiculopathy or myelopathy. Vascular&#xD;
        syndromes such as vertebrobasilar insufficiency. Rheumatoid arthritis. Neck or upper back&#xD;
        surgery. Taking anticoagulants. Local infection. Whiplash injury. Open wounds. Pregnancy.&#xD;
        Receiving radiation or chemotherapy. Scapular pain due to any degeneration disease.&#xD;
        Osteoporosis. Cardiac pacemaker. Any contraindication for thoracic manipulation&#xD;
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>30 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>marwa medhat fawzy, bachelor</last_name>
    <phone>01111666514</phone>
    <email>dr.marwa24red@gmail.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <verification_date>January 2023</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>January 9, 2023</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 9, 2023</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">January 18, 2023</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 9, 2023</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 9, 2023</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">January 18, 2023</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Cairo University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Marwa Medhat Fawzy Mohamed</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>principle investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Myofascial pain syndrome</keyword>
  <keyword>pressure release</keyword>
  <keyword>Thoracic manipulation</keyword>
  <keyword>Active trigger point</keyword>
  <keyword>Rhomboids trigger point</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Myofascial Pain Syndromes</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Fibromyalgia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Syndrome</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

