<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="9494">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 09, 2023</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT05696678</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2023-3020</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT05696678</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Improving ObsQoR-11 With Continuous Wound Infusion Versus Intrathecal Morphine After Elective Cesarean Delivery</brief_title>
  <acronym>CIVIMEC</acronym>
  <official_title>Improving ObsQoR-11 With Continuous Wound Infusion Versus Intrathecal Morphine After Elective Cesarean Delivery: A Randomized Double-Blinded Controlled Trial Targeting Patients' Recovery and Satisfaction</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Ciusss de L'Est de l'Île de Montréal</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Ciusss de L'Est de l'Île de Montréal</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this prospective randomized double-blinded and controlled study is to evaluate&#xD;
      the quality of recovery after elective cesarean delivery using the Obstetric&#xD;
      Quality-of-Recovery-11 (ObsQoR-11) score at 24 hours between patients receiving intrathecal&#xD;
      morphine (ITM group) compared to patients receiving a ropivacaine continuous wound infusion&#xD;
      (CWI group).&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Background:&#xD;
&#xD;
      Cesarean delivery (CD) is one of the most frequently practiced surgeries in the world. Most&#xD;
      anesthetic techniques include the use of intrathecal morphine for post-operative analgesia.&#xD;
      While it is the gold standard, it still carries significant side effects. Recently, other&#xD;
      analgesic options have been evaluated. Continuous anesthetic wound infusion can provide&#xD;
      satisfactory analgesia without intrathecal morphine administration. Quality of recovery and&#xD;
      patients' satisfaction are patients'-oriented outcomes which are now recommended as primary&#xD;
      aim in clinical research. However, most of previous studies evaluating different&#xD;
      post-operative analgesia management in cesarean delivery have focused primarily only on pain&#xD;
      scores or opioid consumption, which were not always clinically relevant even if some&#xD;
      statistical difference was reported between groups. A new scoring tool, ObsQoR-11, have&#xD;
      recently been validated for evaluating recovery after cesarean delivery. The goal of the&#xD;
      present study is to demonstrate an improvement in the quality of recovery after cesarean&#xD;
      delivery as well as in patients' satisfaction when ropivacaine continuous wound infusion is&#xD;
      used compared to the standard management with intrathecal morphine.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Hypothesis:&#xD;
&#xD;
      The investigators hypothesized that the use of ropivacaine continuous wound infusion instead&#xD;
      of intrathecal morphine for postoperative pain management will improve the ObsQoR-11 recovery&#xD;
      score as well as patients' satisfaction after elective cesarean delivery.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Primary objective:&#xD;
&#xD;
      To evaluate the ObsQoR-11 score at 24 hours between patients receiving intrathecal morphine&#xD;
      (ITM group) compared to patients receiving a ropivacaine continuous wound infusion (CWI&#xD;
      group).&#xD;
&#xD;
      Secondary objectives:&#xD;
&#xD;
        1. To evaluate the global health score of the patient (subpart of the ObsQoR-11) between&#xD;
           ITM and CWI patients.&#xD;
&#xD;
        2. To evaluate the quality of recovery after elective cesarean delivery using the ObsQoR-11&#xD;
           score at 48 and 72 hours between ITM and CWI patients.&#xD;
&#xD;
        3. To evaluate the impact of the perioperative pain management on each item of ObsQoR-11&#xD;
           questionnaire including the quality of care the mother can provide to her child between&#xD;
           ITM and CWI patients.&#xD;
&#xD;
        4. To evaluate pain scores at rest, at mobilization and the worst pain score as well as the&#xD;
           opioid consumption (morphine equivalent) in the postanesthesia care unit (PACU), at 2,&#xD;
           4, 6, 12, 24, 48, 72 hours and 5 and 7 days after elective cesarean delivery between ITM&#xD;
           and CWI patients.&#xD;
&#xD;
        5. To evaluate the nausea and vomiting incidence and severity during the first 24 hours&#xD;
           after elective cesarean delivery (2, 4, 6, 12 and 24 hours) between ITM and CWI&#xD;
           patients.&#xD;
&#xD;
        6. To evaluate the severity of the pruritus during the first 24 hours after elective&#xD;
           cesarean delivery (2, 4, 6, 12 and 24 hours) between ITM and CWI patients.&#xD;
&#xD;
        7. To evaluate the time to first mobilization with ambulation after elective cesarean&#xD;
           delivery between ITM and CWI patients.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Methods:&#xD;
&#xD;
      Patients scheduled for an elective cesarean delivery performed under spinal anesthesia and&#xD;
      meeting our inclusion criteria will be fully informed about the study protocol. Interested&#xD;
      patients will be invited to sign the informed consent form (ICF). Included patients will be&#xD;
      invited to answer questionnaires to collect socio-demographic and medical history data (e.g.&#xD;
      comorbidities, pregnancy details, etc…). Patients will be randomized in one of two groups by&#xD;
      a random computer-generated number using a 1:1 randomization ratio and variable random blocks&#xD;
      of 4 and 6.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Each patient will receive a prophylactic antacid medication consisting of 30 mL of sodium&#xD;
      citrate 30 minutes before the surgery.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Standard monitors will be placed on the patient including a continuous pulse oximeter,&#xD;
      continuous electrocardiography (ECG) and noninvasive blood pressure device taking blood&#xD;
      pressure every 2.5 minutes (Dräger Perseus® A500, Drägerwerk AG &amp; Co. KGaA, Lübeck, Germany).&#xD;
&#xD;
      Induction and anesthesia maintenance:&#xD;
&#xD;
      The anesthesia technique will be standardized. Upon arrival in the OR, spinal anesthesia will&#xD;
      be performed in the sitting position at the lumbar level (L2-L5) with a Whitacre needle 25&#xD;
      Gauge (G) (BD, Mississauga ON, Canada).&#xD;
&#xD;
      The control group (ITM) will receive a dose of 10.5 mg of bupivacaine 0.75% (1.4 ml),10 mcg&#xD;
      of fentanyl (0.2 ml) and 100 mcg of morphine (0.2 ml). The patient will then be immediately&#xD;
      placed in the supine position (plus tilt to the left) with a phenylephrine infusion running&#xD;
      at 0.5 mcg/kg/min (lean body weight).&#xD;
&#xD;
      The intervention group (CWI) will receive a dose of 10.5 mg of bupivacaine 0.75% (1.4 ml), 10&#xD;
      mcg of fentanyl (0.2 ml). The patient will then be immediately placed in the supine position&#xD;
      (plus tilt to the left) with a phenylephrine infusion running at 0.5 mcg/kg/min (lean body&#xD;
      weight).&#xD;
&#xD;
      Ten minutes after the spinal injection, the sensory block will be evaluated to make sure it&#xD;
      reaches a T4 level with the ice-test. If the sensory blockade is unsatisfactory, which means&#xD;
      the spinal anesthesia will need to be complemented with intravenous analgesics or hypnotics,&#xD;
      then the patient will be withdrawn from the study.&#xD;
&#xD;
      A 1.5 mcg.kg-1 phenylephrine bolus (lean body weight) will be administered if the patient&#xD;
      presents a hypotension or nausea/vomiting episode.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Hypotension will be defined as a decrease of the mean arterial blood pressure (BP) below 80%&#xD;
      of normal baseline (pre- spinal anesthesia injection) values (as measured before intrathecal&#xD;
      injection) for 2 consecutive BP values.&#xD;
&#xD;
      If the hypotension persists, a phenylephrine infusion will be titrated until BP reaches an&#xD;
      adequate value. If the mean arterial blood pressure increases above 120% of normal baseline&#xD;
      values (for 2 consecutive BP values), the phenylephrine infusion will be diminished by steps&#xD;
      of 0.2 mcg/kg/min.&#xD;
&#xD;
      If the heart rate decreases under 50 beats/minute while the arterial pressure remains normal,&#xD;
      a 0.2 mg IV glycopyrrolate bolus will be administered. If the heart rate decreases under 50&#xD;
      beats/minute while the mean arterial pressure decreases under 80% of normal values, a 5 mg IV&#xD;
      ephedrine bolus will also be administered. At any time during the surgery, the&#xD;
      anesthesiologist can derogate from this protocol if he deems that the security of the patient&#xD;
      is at risk.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Prophylactic antibiotics will be administered to each patient before the incision.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Nausea and vomiting prophylaxis will consist of metoclopramide 10 mg IV after spinal&#xD;
      anesthesia. A rescue therapy of ondansetron 4 mg IV will be administered if the patient&#xD;
      develops nausea or vomiting despite the prophylaxis.&#xD;
&#xD;
      After umbilical cord clamping, carbetocin 100 mcg IV will be administered.&#xD;
&#xD;
      At the end of the surgery:&#xD;
&#xD;
      In the control group (ITM), at wound closure, a 19 Gauge 150 mm catheter (InfiltraLong,&#xD;
      PAJUNK® Medical System L.P., Norcross GA, USA) will be placed under the fascia and will be&#xD;
      linked to an elastometric pump (Baxter International Inc., Deerfield IL, USA) filled with&#xD;
      sterile saline (600 ml). A bolus of 20 ml will be administered, and an 8 ml/h infusion (based&#xD;
      on previous published studies) will be started. Patients will also receive 100 mg of&#xD;
      indomethacin and 1950 mg of acetaminophen per rectum (PR) at the end of the surgery, before&#xD;
      the transfer to PACU.&#xD;
&#xD;
      In the intervention group (CWI), at wound closure, a 19 Gauge 150 mm catheter (InfiltraLong,&#xD;
      PAJUNK® Medical System L.P., Norcross GA, USA) will be placed under the fascia and will be&#xD;
      linked to an elastometric pump (Baxter International Inc., Deerfield IL, USA) filled with&#xD;
      0.2% ropivacaine (600 ml). A bolus of 20 ml will be administered, and an 8 ml/h infusion will&#xD;
      be started. Patients will also receive 100 mg of indomethacin and 1950 mg of acetaminophen PR&#xD;
      at the end of the surgery.&#xD;
&#xD;
      The placement of the catheter in the fascial plane between the fascia of the transversalis&#xD;
      muscle and the parietal peritoneum has been validated in previous studies.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Management in postanesthesia care unit:&#xD;
&#xD;
      After cesarean delivery, the patient will be transported to the postanesthesia care unit&#xD;
      (PACU). The patient will be discharged from PACU to the ward when specific criteria are&#xD;
      achieved (Bromage and Aldrete scores). The arriving time at PACU will be T0. From T0, all&#xD;
      criteria of the study will be evaluated as defined.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Management in ward:&#xD;
&#xD;
      For the management of post-operative pain, all patients will benefit from the same protocol&#xD;
      for the following 24 hours and after:&#xD;
&#xD;
      They will receive acetaminophen 975 mg Per Oral (PO) every 6 hours (regular) and naproxen 500&#xD;
      mg PO Bis In Die (BID) (regular) for 72 hours.&#xD;
&#xD;
      If the pain level is deemed at more than 3/10 on a Numeric Pain Rating (NRS) scale, patients&#xD;
      will be educated to request oxycodone 5 to 7.5 mg PO every 4 hours as needed. If oxycodone is&#xD;
      not enough or if the patient cannot tolerate medications by mouth, morphine 5 to 7.5 mg&#xD;
      subcutaneous (SC) every 4 hours will be administered as needed. The doses of opioids needed&#xD;
      as rescue therapy will be noted in the patients' CRF. All opioids consumed will be converted&#xD;
      into equi-analgesic doses of PO morphine for analysis (morphine 10 mg IV or SC =&#xD;
      hydromorphone 1.5 mg IV or SC = oxycodone 20 mg PO).&#xD;
&#xD;
      During the hospital stay, if the patient feels nauseous enough to require medical treatment&#xD;
      ondansetron 4 mg IV every 8 hours will be administered as needed. If the nausea is&#xD;
      persistent, metoclopramide 10 mg IV every 4 hours will be given. The dose may be repeated&#xD;
      after 1 hour if the patient is still symptomatic. (For a maximum dosage of metoclopramide 20&#xD;
      mg every 4 hours). In the event both medications fail to decrease the nausea, dimenhydrinate&#xD;
      50 mg every 6 hours will be available as needed.&#xD;
&#xD;
      If the patient experiences pruritus that is deemed severe enough to treat, nalbuphine 2.5 mg&#xD;
      SC every 4 hours will be administered. If the patient is not relieved after an hour, the&#xD;
      medication will be repeated once for a maximum dosage of 5 mg SC every 4 hours. If this&#xD;
      medication is not enough, after being reevaluated by the nursing team an hour later, the&#xD;
      patient will receive diphenhydramine 25 mg IV, repeatable once, for a maximum dosage of 50 mg&#xD;
      IV every 4 hours.&#xD;
&#xD;
      The patient will receive a visit from the research team or from the nursing staff at hours 2,&#xD;
      4, 6, 12 and 24 after the cesarean delivery. Every time, the following elements will be noted&#xD;
      in the patients' case report form (CRF):&#xD;
&#xD;
        -  Pain scores at rest, cough, mobilization (walking) on a numerical rating scale (0 to 10)&#xD;
&#xD;
        -  Pruritus level and incidence graded on a scale of 0 to 3 (0 indicating no pruritus, 1&#xD;
           indicating mild pruritus requiring no treatment, 2 indicating moderate pruritus&#xD;
           responsive to treatment, and 3 indicating severe pruritus unresponsive to treatment)&#xD;
&#xD;
        -  Nausea and vomiting level and incidence graded on a scale of 0 to 3 (0 indicating no&#xD;
           nausea or vomiting, 1 indicating mild nausea requiring no treatment, 2 indicating&#xD;
           moderate nausea responsive to treatment, and 3 indicating severe nausea unresponsive to&#xD;
           treatment and/or vomiting) After 24 hours, the following elements will also be assessed:&#xD;
           ObsQoR-11 questionnaire and score, total PO morphine equivalent consumed, number of&#xD;
           medication administration required for pruritus, number of medication administration&#xD;
           required for nausea and time of the first mobilization.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Same evaluations will be done at 48 and 72 hours. The catheter will be removed under aseptic&#xD;
      conditions at home at 72 hours by the patient after instructions given by the nursing staff.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">February 2023</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">November 2023</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">August 2023</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Randomized double-blinded and controlled study</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Triple (Participant, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
    <masking_description>Only the anesthesiologist in charge in the operating room will be aware of treatment group.</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>ObsQoR-11 at 24 hours</measure>
    <time_frame>24 hours after end of surgery</time_frame>
    <description>Quality of recovery after cesarean delivery using ObsQoR-11 score at 24 hours between patients receiving intrathecal morphine (ITM) compared to patients receiving a ropivacaine continuous wound infusion CWI)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Global health score</measure>
    <time_frame>24, 48 and 72 hours after end of surgery</time_frame>
    <description>Global health score of the patient (subpart of the ObsQoR-11) between ITM and CWI patients</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>ObsQoR-11 at 48 and 72 hours</measure>
    <time_frame>48 and 72 hours after end of surgery</time_frame>
    <description>Quality of recovery after elective cesarean delivery using the ObsQoR-11 score at 48 and 72 hours between ITM and CWI patients</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>ObsQoR-11 items</measure>
    <time_frame>24, 48 and 72 hours after end of surgery</time_frame>
    <description>Evaluate the impact of the perioperative pain management on each item of ObsQoR-11 questionnaire including the quality of care the mother can provide to her child between ITM and CWI patients</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pain scores</measure>
    <time_frame>In postanesthesia care unit (PACU), at 2, 4, 6, 12, 24, 48, 72 hours and 5 and 7 days after the end of surgery</time_frame>
    <description>Pain scores at rest, at coughing and at mobilization after elective cesarean delivery between ITM and CWI patients</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Opioid consumption</measure>
    <time_frame>In postanesthesia care unit (PACU), at 2, 4, 6, 12, 24, 48, 72 hours and 5 and 7 days after the end of surgery</time_frame>
    <description>Opioid consumption (morphine equivalent) after elective cesarean delivery between ITM and CWI patients</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Nausea and vomiting score</measure>
    <time_frame>At 2, 4, 6, 12, 24 hours after the end of surgery</time_frame>
    <description>Nausea and vomiting incidence and severity during the first 24 hours after elective cesarean delivery between ITM and CWI patients</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pruritus score</measure>
    <time_frame>At 2, 4, 6, 12, 24 hours after the end of surgery</time_frame>
    <description>Pruritus incidence and severity during the first 24 hours after elective cesarean delivery between ITM and CWI patients</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Time to first mobilization with ambulation</measure>
    <time_frame>During the first 24 hours after the end of surgery</time_frame>
    <description>Time to first mobilization with ambulation after elective cesarean delivery between ITM and CWI patients</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">96</enrollment>
  <condition>Quality of Recovery</condition>
  <condition>Anesthesia</condition>
  <condition>Postoperative Pain</condition>
  <condition>Cesarean Section</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Intrathecal Morphine (Control Group)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Spinal anesthesia with intrathecal morphine and postoperative continuous wound infusion with sterile saline.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Continuous Wound Infusion (Intervention Group)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Spinal anesthesia without intrathecal morphine and postoperative continuous wound infusion with ropivacaine.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Intrathecal Morphine</intervention_name>
    <description>Patient will receive a spinal anesthesia with a dose of 10.5 mg of bupivacaine 0.75% (1.4 ml),10 mcg of fentanyl (0.2 ml) and 100 mcg of morphine (0.2 ml) for cesarean delivery. At the end of surgery, at wound closure, a 19 Gauge 150 mm catheter will be placed under the fascia and will be linked to an elastometric pump filled with sterile saline (600 ml). A bolus of 20 ml will be administered, and an 8 ml/h infusion will be started. The catheter will be removed at 72 hours.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Intrathecal Morphine (Control Group)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Ropivacaine 0.2%</intervention_name>
    <description>Patient will receive a spinal anesthesia with a dose of 10.5 mg of bupivacaine 0.75% (1.4 ml),10 mcg of fentanyl (0.2 ml) and 100 mcg of morphine (0.2 ml) for cesarean delivery. At the end of surgery, at wound closure, a 19 Gauge 150 mm catheter will be placed under the fascia and will be linked to an elastometric pump filled with sterile saline (600 ml). A bolus of 20 ml will be administered, and an 8 ml/h infusion will be started. The catheter will be removed at 72 hours.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Continuous Wound Infusion (Intervention Group)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  American Society of Anesthesiologists status I and II&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Maternal age above 18 years' old&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Elective cesarean delivery&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Spinal anesthesia&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  At least 37 weeks of gestational age&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  French-speaking patients (able to read and sign the consent form)&#xD;
&#xD;
        Exclusion Criteria:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Chronic pain&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Chronic usage of any opioids&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Cardiopathy&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Unexpected difficult spinal anesthesia requiring general anesthesia or unsatisfactory&#xD;
             sensory blockade&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Unexpected complications requiring strong hemodynamic support (transfusions, volume&#xD;
             challenges, multiple vasopressors, inotropic drugs…) or requiring anti-hypertensive&#xD;
             medication (including magnesium)&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Any contraindication (e.g. coagulopathy) or patient's refusal for spinal anesthesia&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Morbid obesity (BMI &gt; 40 at the time of delivery)&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Active labour&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Emergency CD&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Fetal abnormality or prematurity (&lt; 37 weeks of gestational age)&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Multiple gestation&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Inability to cooperate due to language or physical/mental incapacity&#xD;
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Philippe PR Richebé, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>(514) 252-3400</phone>
    <phone_ext>4620</phone_ext>
    <email>philipperichebe@live.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Nadia NG Godin</last_name>
    <phone>(514) 252-3400</phone>
    <phone_ext>3193</phone_ext>
    <email>ngodin.hmr@ssss.gouv.qc.ca</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>CIUSSS de l'Est de l'Ile de Montreal</name>
      <address>
        <city>Montréal</city>
        <state>Quebec</state>
        <zip>H1T2M4</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Philippe PR Richebé, MD,PhD</last_name>
      <phone>5147436558</phone>
      <email>philippe.richebe@umontreal.ca</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Nadia NG Godin</last_name>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Canada</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>January 2023</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>August 23, 2022</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 13, 2023</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">January 25, 2023</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 25, 2023</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 25, 2023</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">January 26, 2023</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Ciusss de L'Est de l'Île de Montréal</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Philippe Richebe</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Director of Research, Principal Investigator, Anesthesiologist, Associate Professor, MD, PhD</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>ObsQoR-11</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Pain, Postoperative</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Morphine</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Ropivacaine</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

