<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="9388">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 09, 2023</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT05698862</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>GBGABAWP2</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT05698862</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Mapping the Impact of Gut Microbiota on Brain and Behavior Through the Lens of GABA</brief_title>
  <acronym>GutBrainGABA</acronym>
  <official_title>Mapping the Impact of Gut Bacteria on Brain and Behaviour Through the Lens of GABA (GutBrainGABA)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Reading</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>European Research Council</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Reading</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Gut microbiota produce different metabolites within the human body, which include&#xD;
      neurotransmitters. Animal studies have demonstrated a critical role for the gut microbiota in&#xD;
      various aspects of brain and behavioural function, and a smaller number of studies in humans&#xD;
      have shown differences of gut microbiota composition in psychiatric conditions. However,&#xD;
      almost nothing is known about the impact of neurotransmitters produced by the gut microbiota&#xD;
      on human brain and behaviour.&#xD;
&#xD;
      The way in which differences in brain, behaviour and personality traits are associated with&#xD;
      the gut microbiota, and how they are influenced by a probiotic will be explored, with a&#xD;
      special focus on GABA (Gamma Amino Butyric Acid).&#xD;
&#xD;
      Abnormalities of microbiota composition have been identified in metabolic disorders, such as&#xD;
      inflammatory bowel disease and obesity, and psychiatric conditions, such as depression and&#xD;
      anxiety.&#xD;
&#xD;
      The aim of this intervention trial will be to answer the following fundamental questions:&#xD;
&#xD;
        1. Does the population of gut bacteria capable of producing GABA modulate brain-based&#xD;
           measures of GABA?&#xD;
&#xD;
        2. Does the population of gut bacteria capable of producing GABA influence performance in&#xD;
           behavioural tasks known to depend on GABA-ergic function?&#xD;
&#xD;
      The impact of a GABA producing probiotic on the measures of GABA in the brain and serum,&#xD;
      relevant metabolites in blood, faecal and urine samples and performance in GABA dependent&#xD;
      behavioural tasks will be investigated in this trial.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This interventional trial will involve a double-blind placebo-controlled crossover trial&#xD;
      structured in 4 appointments: week 0 (W0), week 4 (W4), week 8 (W8) and week 12 (W12). The&#xD;
      study will therefore last 12 weeks, and will include a screening visit and 4 study visits.&#xD;
&#xD;
      The interventional study has a cross-over design, and participants will therefore be invited&#xD;
      to consume both the active probiotic supplement and the placebo at different times. The&#xD;
      probiotic supplement (Lactobacillus brevis) was chosen based on the ability to produce GABA&#xD;
      in vitro (Monteagudo et al., 2022). The placebo will be maltodextrin The products will be&#xD;
      provided as capsules and are identical in texture and appearance.&#xD;
&#xD;
      For participants to be considered compliant and therefore included in the study they will be&#xD;
      require:&#xD;
&#xD;
        1. to take the probiotic supplement or placebo at least 6 out of every 7 days of the trial&#xD;
           for the week period;&#xD;
&#xD;
        2. to provide faecal, blood and urine samples and to be tested with a battery involving&#xD;
           behaviour and brain measures relating to GABA levels/activity and&#xD;
&#xD;
        3. to complete a food diary using an online app once every 4 weeks.&#xD;
&#xD;
      As age and BMI are factors associated with significant variation in gut microbiota&#xD;
      composition/brain and behaviour functioning, both study arms will be matched on these&#xD;
      criteria.&#xD;
&#xD;
      All interested Individuals will be invited to complete an initial screening questionnaire,&#xD;
      which includes questions related to a) the study inclusion criteria. Individuals who meet the&#xD;
      study inclusion criteria will then be asked to complete b) an MRI contraindications&#xD;
      questionnaire and, in absence of any MRI-related contraindications, they will be asked to c)&#xD;
      complete a medical/lifestyle questionnaire to confirm the absence of any exclusion criteria.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Individuals who meet the inclusion criteria will be invited to attend a screening visit at&#xD;
      the University of Reading for familiarisation with the procedures and for any clarification&#xD;
      they might need. Participants will be provided with a sample collection kit (for faecal and&#xD;
      urine sample collection), will be instructed on how to use it, and will be asked to track&#xD;
      their diet using an online app (eNutri).&#xD;
&#xD;
      All study appointments will take place at the University of Reading. On the day of the study&#xD;
      appointment, participants will be asked to provide a fresh faecal sample and spot urine&#xD;
      sample (first morning urine), collected using the sample kit they were provided with at the&#xD;
      screening visit. A venous blood sample (equal to 10ml/ 2tsp) will be collected by experienced&#xD;
      and trained phlebotomists at the University of Reading. Participants will then undergo a&#xD;
      neuroimaging battery, which will include structural magnetic resonance images, magnetic&#xD;
      resonance spectroscopy (MRS) to quantify concentrations of GABA in determined regions of the&#xD;
      brain, and functional magnetic resonance imaging to evaluate functional connectivity between&#xD;
      brain areas. Participants will then complete a battery of GABA-dependent behavioural assays&#xD;
      including a facial emotion recognition task, a motor learning task, and a tactile frequency&#xD;
      discrimination task. Participants will then complete the Autism Spectrum Quotient (AQ), the&#xD;
      State and Trait Anxiety Inventory (STAI), and the Centre for Epidemiological Studies&#xD;
      Depression Scale (CES-D). Participants will complete this battery of tasks at each of the&#xD;
      four study visits at W0, W4, W8 and W12.&#xD;
&#xD;
      At the end of visit 1 (W0), participants will be provided with either the probiotic OR&#xD;
      placebo supplement to consume daily for the next 4 weeks, i.e. between study visits 1 and 2.&#xD;
      At the end of visit 2 (W4), participants will not be provided with any supplements as they&#xD;
      will enter their 4-week period of washout. At the end of visit 3 (W8), participants will be&#xD;
      provided with either the probiotic OR placebo supplement to consume daily for the next 4&#xD;
      weeks. If the participant received the probiotic following visit 1, they will receive the&#xD;
      placebo at this point, and vice versa. Participants will be asked to take this daily until&#xD;
      their fourth and final study visit (W12). Study visit 4 finalises the study.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">May 21, 2022</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 31, 2026</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 31, 2026</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Crossover Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Basic Science</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double (Participant, Investigator)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in GABA concentrations in the brain assessed using Magnetic Resonance Spectroscopy (MRS)</measure>
    <time_frame>1. Baseline (Week 0), 2. Following intervention (Week 4 or Week 12, depending on intervention arm assignment), 3. Following washout (Week 8), 4. Following placebo (Week 4 or Week 12, depending on intervention arm assignment)</time_frame>
    <description>Concentrations of GABA will be quantified using MRS. MRS data will be analysed separately in the time domain using an open-source magnetic resonance spectroscopy analysis tool, such as Osprey.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in GABA-ergic activity in the sensorimotor component of the resting state network assessed using resting state functional Magnetic Resonance Imagine (rs-fMRI)</measure>
    <time_frame>1. Baseline (Week 0), 2. Following intervention (Week 4 or Week 12, depending on intervention arm assignment), 3. Following washout (Week 8), 4. Following placebo (Week 4 or Week 12, depending on intervention arm assignment)</time_frame>
    <description>GABA-ergic activity will be measured using rs-fMRI. MRI data will be analysed..</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in GABA concentrations in urine assessed by Liquid chromatography-mass spectrometry (LC-MS).</measure>
    <time_frame>1. Baseline (Week 0), 2. Following intervention (Week 4 or Week 12, depending on intervention arm assignment), 3. Following washout (Week 8), 4. Following placebo (Week 4 or Week 12, depending on intervention arm assignment)</time_frame>
    <description>Concentrations of GABA will be measured in urine samples by LC-MS.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in GABA concentrations in serum assessed by Liquid chromatography-mass spectrometry (LC-MS).</measure>
    <time_frame>1. Baseline (Week 0), 2. Following intervention (Week 4 or Week 12, depending on intervention arm assignment), 3. Following washout (Week 8), 4. Following placebo (Week 4 or Week 12, depending on intervention arm assignment)</time_frame>
    <description>Concentrations of GABA will be measured in serum samples by LC-MS.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in faecal bacteria quantity assessed by Fluorescent In Situ Hybridisation Followed by Flow Cytometry (FISH-FCM)</measure>
    <time_frame>1. Baseline (Week 0), 2. Following intervention (Week 4 or Week 12, depending on intervention arm assignment), 3. Following washout (Week 8), 4. Following placebo (Week 4 or Week 12, depending on intervention arm assignment)</time_frame>
    <description>Quantity of faecal bacteria will be assessed by FISH-FCM</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in compositional diversity of faecal microbiota attributable to intervention assessed by 16S ribosomal RNA (16S rRNA) gene amplicon sequencing</measure>
    <time_frame>1. Baseline (Week 0), 2. Following intervention (Week 4 or Week 12, depending on intervention arm assignment)</time_frame>
    <description>Compositional diversity of faecal microbiota attributable to intervention will measured by 16S rRNA sequencing methods</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in metabolic profile in faecal samples assessed by Nuclear Magnetic Resonance spectroscopy (NMR)</measure>
    <time_frame>1. Baseline (Week 0), 2. Following intervention (Week 4 or Week 12, depending on intervention arm assignment), 3. Following washout (Week 8), 4. Following placebo (Week 4 or Week 12, depending on intervention arm assignment)</time_frame>
    <description>The metabolic profile will be measured in faecal samples using NMR</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in metabolic profile in urine samples assessed by Nuclear Magnetic Resonance spectroscopy (NMR)</measure>
    <time_frame>1. Baseline (Week 0), 2. Following intervention (Week 4 or Week 12, depending on intervention arm assignment), 3. Following washout (Week 8), 4. Following placebo (Week 4 or Week 12, depending on intervention arm assignment)</time_frame>
    <description>The metabolic profile will be measured in urine samples using NMR</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in metabolic profile in serum samples assessed by Nuclear Magnetic Resonance spectroscopy (NMR)</measure>
    <time_frame>1. Baseline (Week 0), 2. Following intervention (Week 4 or Week 12, depending on intervention arm assignment), 3. Following washout (Week 8), 4. Following placebo (Week 4 or Week 12, depending on intervention arm assignment)</time_frame>
    <description>The metabolic profile will be measured in serum samples using NMR</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in blood pressure assessed by measures of systolic and diastolic blood pressure</measure>
    <time_frame>1. Baseline (Week 0), 2. Following intervention (Week 4 or Week 12, depending on intervention arm assignment), 3. Following washout (Week 8), 4. Following placebo (Week 4 or Week 12, depending on intervention arm assignment)</time_frame>
    <description>Blood pressure will be recorded during the intervention using an upper arm blood pressure monitor</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in motor function performance assessed by reaction time</measure>
    <time_frame>1. Baseline (Week 0), 2. Following intervention (Week 4 or Week 12, depending on intervention arm assignment), 3. Following washout (Week 8), 4. Following placebo (Week 4 or Week 12, depending on intervention arm assignment)</time_frame>
    <description>Motor performance data will be calculated by averaging the reaction time from correct trials (i.e., where participants pressed the button corresponding to the visual sequence presented).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in emotion recognition performance assessed by reaction time and accuracy</measure>
    <time_frame>1. Baseline (Week 0), 2. Following intervention (Week 4 or Week 12, depending on intervention arm assignment), 3. Following washout (Week 8), 4. Following placebo (Week 4 or Week 12, depending on intervention arm assignment)</time_frame>
    <description>Emotion recognition task accuracy and reaction time will be calculated in response to six emotions and a neutral facial expression.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in tactile discrimination performance assessed by reaction time, static threshold and dynamic threshold</measure>
    <time_frame>1. Baseline (Week 0), 2. Following intervention (Week 4 or Week 12, depending on intervention arm assignment), 3. Following washout (Week 8), 4. Following placebo (Week 4 or Week 12, depending on intervention arm assignment)</time_frame>
    <description>Tactile discrimination reaction time and thresholds will be obtained from each participant using established 'staircase' threshold estimation procedures.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in levels of trait and state anxiety assessed by the State-Trait Anxiety Inventory (STAI)</measure>
    <time_frame>1. Baseline (Week 0), 2. Following intervention (Week 4 or Week 12, depending on intervention arm assignment), 3. Following washout (Week 8), 4. Following placebo (Week 4 or Week 12, depending on intervention arm assignment)</time_frame>
    <description>Trait and state levels of anxiety will be assessed by the STAI questionnaire</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in levels of depression assessed by the Centre for Epidemiological Studies Depression questionnaire (CES-D)</measure>
    <time_frame>1. Baseline (Week 0), 2. Following intervention (Week 4 or Week 12, depending on intervention arm assignment), 3. Following washout (Week 8), 4. Following placebo (Week 4 or Week 12, depending on intervention arm assignment)</time_frame>
    <description>Levels of depression will be assessed by the CES-D questionnaire</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">60</enrollment>
  <condition>Healthy</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Probiotic</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Probiotic supplement (Lactobacillus brevis)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Placebo (maltodextrin)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Dietary Supplement</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Probiotic</intervention_name>
    <description>Participants will be required to take a probiotic supplement of Lactobacillus brevis daily (1 capsule 5B CFU/day)</description>
    <arm_group_label>Probiotic</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Dietary Supplement</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo</intervention_name>
    <description>Participants will be required to take the placebo maltodextrin daily (1 capsule/day)</description>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Male&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Right-handed&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Caucasian/White&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Between 18 and 50 years of age&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Grew up in the UK or other European country&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Body Mass Index 18.5 to 30.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Exclusion Criteria:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Use of antibiotics within the last 3 months&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Use of protonic pump inhibitors (PPIs) within the last 3 months&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Current or history of regular smoking within the last 6 months&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Regular consumption of &gt;14 units of alcohol per week&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Current use of psychotropic drugs for medicinal or recreational purposes&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Current use of probiotic/prebiotic supplements&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Current diagnosis of neurological, developmental or psychiatric condition&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Current diagnosis of gut microbiota related conditions such as inflammatory bowel&#xD;
             disease or irritable bowel syndrome&#xD;
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Male</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>50 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Bhismadev Chakrabarti, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Reading</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Bhismadev chakrabarti, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>+44 118 378 5551</phone>
    <email>b.chakrabarti@reading.ac.uk</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Glenn Gibson</last_name>
    <phone>+44 118 378 8715</phone>
    <email>g.r.gibson@reading.ac.uk</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Reading</name>
      <address>
        <city>Reading</city>
        <zip>RG6 6AH</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United Kingdom</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>January 2023</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>January 3, 2023</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 16, 2023</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">January 26, 2023</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 16, 2023</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 16, 2023</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">January 26, 2023</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Reading</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Bhismadev Chakrabarti</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Professor of Neuroscience and Mental Health</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Gamma Amino Butyric Acid (GABA)</keyword>
  <keyword>Brain function</keyword>
  <keyword>Gut microbiota</keyword>
  <keyword>Behaviour</keyword>
  <keyword>Probiotics</keyword>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

