<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="9446">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 09, 2023</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT05697562</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>HEMbol</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT05697562</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Evaluation of Superior Rectal Arterial Embolization in Hemorrhoidal Disease</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Randomized Comparative Evaluation of Superior Rectal Arterial Embolization in Hemorrhoidal Disease</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Universitair Ziekenhuis Brussel</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Universitair Ziekenhuis Brussel</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      SRAE is a promising treatment of bleeding HD as a minimally invasive approach without&#xD;
      sphincter damage nor direct mucosal anorectal trauma. Feasibility, efficacy and safety were&#xD;
      studied in several trials. A randomized controlled study should confirm the benefits of this&#xD;
      technique and will define its therapeutic role in HD.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Embolization and DG-HAL are based on the same concept of vascular occlusion of hemorrhoidal&#xD;
      branches of the rectal artery. Furthermore, DG-HAL and RBL are equally effective procedures.&#xD;
      The assumption is that treatment with SRAE is not inferior in comparison to RBL or DG HAL in&#xD;
      respectively patients without or with antiplatelet/anticoagulation therapy in terms of&#xD;
      symptom control and bleeding (non-inferiority study).&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Hemorrhoidal disease (HD) is the most common anorectal pathology. Therapeutic management of&#xD;
      HD ranges from conservative treatment and instrumental treatment to surgical approach. Beside&#xD;
      these, certain minimally invasive techniques such as radiofrequency ablation, laser&#xD;
      coagulation and Superior Rectal Artery Embolization (SRAE) are gaining interest. SRAE is a&#xD;
      promising treatment of bleeding HD as a minimally invasive approach without sphincter damage&#xD;
      nor direct mucosal anorectal trauma. Feasibility, efficacy and safety were studied in several&#xD;
      trials. A randomized controlled study should confirm the benefits of this technique and will&#xD;
      define its therapeutic role in HD. Embolization and DG-HAL are based on the same concept of&#xD;
      vascular occlusion of hemorrhoidal branches of the rectal artery. Furthermore, DG-HAL and RBL&#xD;
      are equally effective procedures. The assumption is that treatment with SRAE is not inferior&#xD;
      in comparison to RBL or DG HAL in respectively patients without or with&#xD;
      antiplatelet/anticoagulation therapy in terms of symptom control and bleeding&#xD;
      (non-inferiority study).&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">February 1, 2023</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 15, 2026</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 15, 2025</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Patients will be divided in 2 groups: Anticoagulation group (A) and No Anticoagulation group (NA), based on their regular medication. In both groups, A and NA, are 2 study arms, resp. DG HAL as standard clinical practice versus SRAE (group A) and RBL as standard clinical practice versus SRAE (arm NA). See figure below.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>symptom control</measure>
    <time_frame>from baseline to 3 months</time_frame>
    <description>the main objective is to control the symptoms, for this the Hemorrhoidal Bleeding Score is to be used</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Symptom control</measure>
    <time_frame>from baseline to 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>a secondary objective is to control the symptoms, for this the Hemorrhoidal Bleeding Score is to be used</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Patient reported effectiveness</measure>
    <time_frame>from baseline till 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>a secondary objective is to report patient effectiveness, this will be measured using Patient-Reported Outcome Measure-Haemorrhoidal Impact and Satisfaction score (PROM-HISS)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Patient reported effectiveness</measure>
    <time_frame>from baseline till 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>a secondary objective is to report patient effectiveness, this will be measured using the 5-level EQ-5D-5L score</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>clinical effectiveness</measure>
    <time_frame>from baseline till 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>a secondary objective is to report clinical effectiveness, this will be measured using the Goligher score</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>prevalence of complications</measure>
    <time_frame>from baseline till 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>a secondary objective is to report the prevalence of complications, this will be measured using among others the pain score reported by Visual Analogue Scale (VAS)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>prevalence of re-interventions</measure>
    <time_frame>from baseline till 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>a secondary objective is to report the prevalence of re-interventions, this will be measured among others with the pain score reported by Visual Analogue Scale (VAS)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>prevalence of fecal incontinence</measure>
    <time_frame>from baseline till 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>a secondary objective is to report the prevalence of fecal incontinence, this will be measured using the Jorge-wexner score</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>4</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">80</enrollment>
  <condition>Hemorrhoids</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>anticoagulation group with DG HAL</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>anticoagulation group with SRAE</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>no anticoagulation group with RBL</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>no anticoagulation group with SRAE</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Rubber band ligatures (RBL)</intervention_name>
    <description>This instrumental technique is realized during consultation. A rubber band is applied on top of each hemorrhoidal complex via a proctoscope. This banding causes an ulceration which heals with resulting fibrosis. The patient can receive a maximum of 3 RBL during each session, which can be repeated up to 3 times at a 6 weeks interval.</description>
    <arm_group_label>no anticoagulation group with RBL</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Superior Rectal Artery Embolization (SRAE)</intervention_name>
    <description>This technique is realized under local anesthesia during a one-day hospitalization. The interventional radiologist will perform the procedure in the angiography room. After local anesthesia right femoral artery puncture is performed and a 4 F or 5 F introducer sheath is placed using the Seldinger technique. With an appropriate 4 or 5 F catheter the superior rectal artery is catheterized. With a microcatheter the different branches are selectively occluded with microcoils. The endpoint of embolization is reached when all SRA branches above the pubic ramus are embolized, with cessation of flow distally or a static column of contrast.&#xD;
The procedure can be repeated with addition of the embolization of the middle rectal wall artery (MRA) in case of failure after 12 weeks.</description>
    <arm_group_label>anticoagulation group with SRAE</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>no anticoagulation group with SRAE</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Doppler-Guided Hemorrhoidal Artery Ligation (DG-HAL)</intervention_name>
    <description>The procedure is performed in lithotomy position with a modified proctoscope including a Doppler transducer (THD device) under anesthesia during a one-day hospitalization. This transanal Doppler guidance enables accurate detection and targeted suture ligation of the SRAs Following gel lubrication, the proctoscope is inserted through the anal canal reaching the low rectum, about 6-7 cm from the anal verge. After identification of the best place for artery ligation, the Doppler system is turned off. The artery will be directly ligated with a Z-stitch at the site of the best Doppler signal.</description>
    <arm_group_label>anticoagulation group with DG HAL</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  All patients referred for Hemorrhoidal disease with bleeding are eligible. Significant&#xD;
             bleeding is defined as a HBS of ≥ 5.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Age &gt; 18 years old;&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Sexes eligible for study: all&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Hemorrhoidal disease grade I-III according the Goligher classification with rectal&#xD;
             bleeding as predominant symptom&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  History of prior instrumental treatment of HD does not prohibit inclusion&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Able to understand and read Dutch, French or English&#xD;
&#xD;
        Exclusion Criteria:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Permanent hemorrhoidal prolapse/grade IV hemorrhoidal disease&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Rectal prolapse&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  History of proctological surgery for HD&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Acute complicated course of HD i.e. acute thrombosis (fluxio hemorrhoidalis or&#xD;
             perianal hematoma)&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Anal stenosis, congenital of acquired&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Chronic anal fissure&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Active rectal inflammation, including peri-anal abscess (e.g. Inflammatory Bowel&#xD;
             Disease, infectious,…)&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  History of colorectal or anal cancer&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  History of rectal or sigmoidal resection&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Portal hypertension and liver cirrhosis Child Pugh C&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Radiation rectitis&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Neurological disease involving anal sphincter musculature&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Severe psychiatric disorder&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Pregnancy&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Allergy to iodinated contrast agents&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Colorectal neoplasia as the cause of bleeding (excluded with a (virtual) colonoscopy&#xD;
             in the last year)&#xD;
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Magali Surmont</last_name>
    <phone>+32 2 477</phone>
    <phone_ext>60 01</phone_ext>
    <email>magali.surmont@uzbrussel.be</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Virgini Van Buggenhout</last_name>
    <phone>+32 2 477</phone>
    <phone_ext>50 14</phone_ext>
    <email>virgini.vanbuggenhout@uzbrussel.be</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <verification_date>November 2022</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>December 21, 2022</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 24, 2023</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">January 26, 2023</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 24, 2023</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 24, 2023</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">January 26, 2023</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Hemorrhoids</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

