<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="9375">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 09, 2023</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT05699187</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2021P002531</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT05699187</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Face Transplantation</brief_title>
  <official_title>Face Transplantation</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Massachusetts General Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Massachusetts General Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Face allotransplantation will be performed in facial trauma patients. Immune suppression will&#xD;
      primarily be provided according to standard three-drug regimen. The primary outcome to be&#xD;
      evaluated in the proposed trial is face allograft acceptance.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Patients with severe facial disfigurement referred or self-identified to the MGH Face&#xD;
      Transplantation Program will undergo a consultation with the PI (Dr. Cetrulo) who will&#xD;
      perform a thorough clinical assessment and explain in detail the treatment protocol, risks&#xD;
      and benefits of the face allotransplantation procedure and alternative options. At the time&#xD;
      of appointment, candidates will be first requested to sign a face transplant Research&#xD;
      Informed Consent form . Following the signing of these documents, the candidate will meet&#xD;
      with the MGH Transplant Center team (see below for description of entire team), a clinical&#xD;
      pharmacist, dietician, and a transplant social worker.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Appropriate subjects will then undergo further evaluation/medical screening procedures to&#xD;
      determine their candidacy for face transplantation. Prospective recipients who are selected&#xD;
      based on results of screening procedures will be invited to review and sign the full informed&#xD;
      consent form prior to being wait-listed for the procedure.&#xD;
&#xD;
      There is a significant evaluation using tests, procedures, consults, and evaluations that&#xD;
      will be performed as part of the standard of care for those clinically-approved for organ&#xD;
      transplantation.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">March 2023</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2030</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2027</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>N/A</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of motor function of face</measure>
    <time_frame>1 Year</time_frame>
    <description>Function of face as assessed by ability to move face, smile, frown, etc.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of intact sensation of face</measure>
    <time_frame>1 Year</time_frame>
    <description>Sensation of face intact using standard methods (sharp vs dull, presence of numbness)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of an ascetically satisfactory appearing face</measure>
    <time_frame>1 Year</time_frame>
    <description>Evaluated by overall appearance, symmetry</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of a cost benefit to facial transplant</measure>
    <time_frame>1 Year</time_frame>
    <description>This will be assessed by standard treatment of facial disfigured patients vs face transplant</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of rejection episodes on triple therapy immunosuppression</measure>
    <time_frame>1 Year</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">4</enrollment>
  <condition>Facial Trauma</condition>
  <condition>Facial Deformity</condition>
  <condition>Facial Injuries</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Face Transplant Recipient</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>The procedure will be carried out simultaneously by two teams of transplant surgeons for each face transplanted in the operation. The teams will be divided between the functions of tissue recovery (donor operation) and transplant surgery (recipient operation). In most cases the facial graft will include the entire nose; the soft tissues of the mid-face, including all its blood vessels, muscles, and nerves; and a significant portion of the mid-facial skeleton.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Face allotransplantation</intervention_name>
    <description>Facial allotransplantation</description>
    <arm_group_label>Face Transplant Recipient</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Recent (≥6 months) or remote (i.e., several decades) severe facial disfigurement&#xD;
             and/or facial functional impairment covering at least 25% of face and/or a major part&#xD;
             e.g. nose, lips and desiring face transplantation.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Aged 18-65 years. Noted should be that the maximal age difference between donor and&#xD;
             recipient will be 10 years.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Completion of the protocol informed consent form.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  No co-existing medical condition which, in the opinion of the study team, could affect&#xD;
             the immunomodulatory protocol, surgical procedure, or functional results (see Donor&#xD;
             and Recipient Exclusion Criteria below. If the condition is amenable to treatment, the&#xD;
             study team must agree that said condition should not significantly enhance the&#xD;
             surgical risks of facial transplantation.)&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  No co-existing psycho-social problems (i.e., alcoholism, drug abuse).&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Negative for malignancy for past 5 years.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Negative for HIV at transplant.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Negative crossmatch with donor.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  If female of child-bearing potential, negative serum pregnancy test. If female of&#xD;
             child-bearing potential, consent to use reliable contraception for at least one year&#xD;
             following transplantation.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Patient agrees to comply with the protocol and states a dedication to the&#xD;
             immunomodulatory treatment regimen.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  No smoking for 6 months prior to transplant, as confirmed by blood testing.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Exclusion Criteria:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Positive for any of the following conditions: Untreated sepsis, HIV (active or&#xD;
             seropositive), active tuberculosis, hepatitis B or C (HCV Ab+ and HCV RNA+ (HCV Ab+&#xD;
             but RNA negative is acceptable), HBVcAb+, HBVsAg+ or viral DNA+), viral encephalitis,&#xD;
             toxoplasmosis, malignancy (within past 5 years), current/recent (within months of&#xD;
             donation/consent) IV drug abuse, paralysis of ischemic or traumatic origin, inherited&#xD;
             peripheral neuropathy, infectious, post infectious, or inflammatory (axonal or&#xD;
             demyelinating) neuropathy, toxic neuropathy (i.e. heavy metal poisoning, drug&#xD;
             toxicity, industrial agent exposure), mixed connective tissue disease, severe&#xD;
             deforming rheumatoid or osteoarthritis in the limb.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Conditions that, in the opinion of the study team, may impact the immunomodulatory&#xD;
             protocol potentially exposing the recipient to an unacceptable risk under&#xD;
             immunosuppressive treatment, including all liver and renal disease.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Sensitized recipients with high levels (&gt;=50%) of panel-reactive HLA antibodies.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Conditions that may impact the success of the surgical procedure or increase the risk&#xD;
             of postoperative complications including inherited coagulopathies like Hemophilia,&#xD;
             Von-Willebrand's disease, Protein C and S deficiency, Thrombocythemias, Thalassemias,&#xD;
             Sickle Cell disease, etc.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Mixed connective tissue diseases and collagen diseases can result in poor wound&#xD;
             healing after surgery.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Conditions that may impact functional outcomes including lipopolysaccharidosis and&#xD;
             amyloidosis (may impact nerve regeneration) or rare disorders of bone healing like&#xD;
             osteopetrosis.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Pregnant, breastfeeding or planning to become pregnant within the next 2 years.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Unable or unwilling to use an acceptable birth control method for 2 years following&#xD;
             transplant. The patient cannot have given birth in the past 2 years. We acknowledge&#xD;
             that a female recipient of childbearing age must carefully consider the associated&#xD;
             risks of the transplant and immunosuppression and personally prioritize these issues&#xD;
             and the lead face transplant surgeon (Dr. Cetrulo) will implement this subject in the&#xD;
             preoperative education of the patient during consultation.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Patients will be required to stop smoking for 6 months prior to listing and abstain&#xD;
             from postoperative smoking&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  If a subject does not receive a transplant after one year of enrollment, clinical&#xD;
             consent will be re-obtained from that subject and clinical consent will be re-obtained&#xD;
             yearly while the subject is enrolled and waiting for a donor.&#xD;
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>65 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Curt Cetrulo, MD, FACS, FAAP</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Massachusetts General Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Curt Cetrulo, MD, FACS, FAAP</last_name>
    <phone>877-424-5678</phone>
    <email>CCETRULO@mgh.harvard.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Curt Cetrulo, MD, FACS, FAAP</last_name>
    <email>CCETRULO@mgh.harvard.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <verification_date>January 2023</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>January 12, 2023</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 24, 2023</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">January 26, 2023</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 24, 2023</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 24, 2023</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">January 26, 2023</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Massachusetts General Hospital</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Curtis L. Cetrulo, MD</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Curtis L. Cetrulo, Jr., M.D., FACS, FAAP</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Transplant</keyword>
  <keyword>Face Transplant</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Facial Injuries</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Facies</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

