<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="9584">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 09, 2023</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT05694988</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>efferon-ct-2022-03</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT05694988</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Combination of Cytokine Hemosorption and High-volume Hemofiltration in Acute Pancreatitis</brief_title>
  <official_title>An Open Controlled Randomized Study of the Efficacy and Safety of the Method of Combined Use of Non-selective Hemosorption (Efferon CT) and High Volume Hemofiltration (HVHF) in Patients With Acute Pancreatitis.</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Efferon JSC</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Efferon JSC</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Mortality from severe acute pancreatitis reaches 42%. The prognosis of acute pancreatitis is&#xD;
      associated with the development of acute inflammatory response syndrome (SIRS) and multiple&#xD;
      organ failure (MOF). Due to the lack of etiological therapy, the treatment of acute&#xD;
      pancreatitis is predominantly symptomatic.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Severity and mortality are associated with early systemic inflammatory response syndrome&#xD;
      (SIRS) and septic complications in the later stages of the disease.&#xD;
&#xD;
      In connection with a pronounced inflammatory reaction (&quot;cytokine storm&quot;) in the early phase&#xD;
      of endogenous intoxication of acute pancreatitis, a promising therapeutic approach is the&#xD;
      extracorporeal removal of cytokines.&#xD;
&#xD;
      This prospective study intends to study the effect of hemoperfusion (Efferon CT) in&#xD;
      combination with high-volume hemofiltration (HVHF) on the severity of symptoms of endogenous&#xD;
      intoxication and indicators of organ dysfunction in acute pancreatitis.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Acute pancreatitis in emergency surgery ranks third in frequency of its manifestation, second&#xD;
      only to acute appendicitis and cholecystitis. The incidence of acute pancreatitis is growing&#xD;
      from year to year and is more than 38 patients per 10,000 population per year. In 25% of&#xD;
      patients, the development of pancreatitis is destructive.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Mortality in this pathology is mainly associated with the development of severe necrotic&#xD;
      forms that cause a systemic inflammatory response of the body. The formation of pancreatic&#xD;
      necrosis occurs within 1-2 days of illness, and it is at this time that the therapeutic&#xD;
      effect is most effective.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Mortality in patients with acute pancreatitis reaches 20-60% depending on the nature of the&#xD;
      disease, the phase of the pathological process, the severity of concomitant diseases, the&#xD;
      severity of multiple organ failure syndrome (MODS), purulent-septic complications, and the&#xD;
      development of septic shock. The main factors determining an unfavorable prognosis are the&#xD;
      frequency of multiple organ failure and the development of sepsis, their intensity, as well&#xD;
      as the developed septic shock. In the case of the onset and progression of multiple organ&#xD;
      failure in the first 48 hours, they speak of early severe pancreatitis, which is&#xD;
      characterized by a more unfavorable prognosis.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Acute pancreatitis is a systemic rather than a local critical condition. Associated&#xD;
      complications include sepsis, multiple organ failure, ARDS, acute renal failure, disseminated&#xD;
      intravascular coagulation syndrome, acute liver failure, etc. According to some reports, at&#xD;
      least 50% of deaths in the early stage of acute pancreatitis are associated with multiple&#xD;
      organ failure, and failure of three or more organs, mortality rises to 95%.&#xD;
&#xD;
      The moment when timely treatment can affect the outcome of the disease is often missed.&#xD;
      Against the background of a picture of developed pancreatic necrosis, complications arise at&#xD;
      lightning speed, despite the measures taken to prevent them.&#xD;
&#xD;
      The earliest possible detection of patients with an aggressive, destructive nature of the&#xD;
      disease is very important for the entire complex of intensive care. The severity of the&#xD;
      patient's condition with acute pancreatitis is largely determined by the severity of&#xD;
      endotoxemia. The latter, in turn, depends on the cytokine response of the body.&#xD;
&#xD;
      To date, the early pathogenetic mechanisms of acute pancreatitis and its complications have&#xD;
      not been sufficiently studied. The question of what happens at the subcellular level, what&#xD;
      processes are responsible for the development of severe forms of the disease, extraorganic&#xD;
      complications, remains insufficiently studied.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Treatment of acute pancreatitis is traditionally divided into conservative and surgical. The&#xD;
      start time of conservative measures, their components, an adequate assessment of&#xD;
      effectiveness affect the timing and extent of surgical intervention.&#xD;
&#xD;
      At the moment, there is no specific surgical approach for sterile and infected pancreatic&#xD;
      necrosis. It is known that mortality from infected pancreatic necrosis is 2-3 times higher&#xD;
      than from a sterile process.&#xD;
&#xD;
      &quot;Cytokine storm&quot;, which occurs in the acute phase of pancreatitis, leads to aggravation of&#xD;
      intoxication, inadequate and untimely correction of which underlies the development of&#xD;
      pancreatogenic shock, multiple organ failure and septic complications.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Organ hypoperfusion, tissue hypoxia, endotoxicosis, systemic inflammatory and&#xD;
      anti-inflammatory reactions induced by &quot;mediator aggression&quot; and electrolyte disturbances are&#xD;
      the most important links in the etiopathogenesis of acute pancreatitis and multiple organ&#xD;
      failure. Therefore, the use of detoxification methods aimed at removing toxic substances,&#xD;
      normalizing organ perfusion, reducing systemic inflammation in the treatment of patients with&#xD;
      acute pancreatitis is pathogenetically justified in order to prevent multiple organ failure,&#xD;
      pancreatic shock and sepsis.&#xD;
&#xD;
      In the last 10 years, various methods of extracorporeal detoxification have become widespread&#xD;
      in the practice of intensive care for severe forms of acute pancreatitis.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Nevertheless, there is no consensus among specialists regarding the timing of the application&#xD;
      of certain methods, taking into account the phase course of acute pancreatitis, the required&#xD;
      frequency of procedures and their effectiveness.&#xD;
&#xD;
      In acute pancreatitis, severe endotoxemia occurs early, leading to multiple organ failure.&#xD;
      Allocate biochemical, immunological and microbial components of endogenous intoxication,&#xD;
      which include intermediate and final metabolites of the processes of autolysis and secondary&#xD;
      infection.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Detoxification underlies the prevention and pathogenetic treatment of complications of acute&#xD;
      pancreatitis. Numerous studies have shown that the use of extracorporeal sorption methods&#xD;
      that eliminate pro-inflammatory cytokines improves the results of treatment of patients with&#xD;
      manifestations of endogenous intoxication.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Accumulated evidence in recent years suggests that continuous veno-venous hemofiltration is&#xD;
      beneficial in acute pancreatitis by removing inflammatory molecules and medium and low&#xD;
      molecular weight toxic substances by convection. Particular attention is paid to high-volume&#xD;
      hemofiltration, which can give a better effect in the treatment of acute pancreatitis.&#xD;
&#xD;
      The 2012 study by La-Ping Chu (China) &quot;Clinical effects of pulsed high-volume hemofiltration&#xD;
      in severe acute pancreatitis complicated by multiple organ dysfunction syndrome&quot; also&#xD;
      confirmed that high-volume hemofiltration has a pronounced beneficial effect on clinical&#xD;
      symptoms and laboratory parameters in acute pancreatitis with multiple organ failure .&#xD;
&#xD;
      In acute pancreatitis, a large number of soluble inflammatory mediators circulate in the&#xD;
      patient's blood. Thus, the elimination of cytotoxins with standard continuous hemofiltration&#xD;
      with a water exchange rate of 35 ml/kg/h may not be adequate for the severity of symptoms of&#xD;
      the disease. The advantage of &quot;high volume&quot; is the removal of substances with a higher&#xD;
      molecular weight, which include many inflammatory mediators. Numerous animal studies have&#xD;
      shown a positive effect of high volume hemofiltration (HVHF) on survival in endotoxic models.&#xD;
      Human studies have shown that HVHF improves hemodynamics in septic shock. But the great&#xD;
      concern of researchers has always been the difficulty of performing high-volume&#xD;
      hemofiltration as a continuous method. That is why it is of interest to study the&#xD;
      effectiveness of short-pulse hemofiltration techniques in acute pancreatitis.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Recently, a search is underway for new approaches to the treatment of patients in the early&#xD;
      stages of acute pancreatitis, even before the development of severe complications that&#xD;
      significantly worsen the prognosis of the disease. One of them may be the extracorporeal&#xD;
      removal of excessively produced inflammatory mediators (cytotoxins) from the systemic&#xD;
      circulation by sorption. Nevertheless, very few studies have been devoted to the use of the&#xD;
      hemosorption method in the early stage of acute pancreatitis, before the appearance of&#xD;
      purulent-septic complications.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Hemosorption is a modern method of removing from the patient's blood substances that are&#xD;
      toxic to body cells. Currently, there are no multicenter randomized studies confirming the&#xD;
      need to use extracorporeal therapy methods as one of the main areas of pathogenetic therapy&#xD;
      for acute pancreatitis. At the same time, there is more and more evidence of a significant&#xD;
      effect of an increase in the level of cytokines on the pathogenesis of the disease and its&#xD;
      progressive deterioration, which suggests a possible positive role of the cytokine&#xD;
      hemosorption method performed in the early phase of acute pancreatitis.&#xD;
&#xD;
      In connection with the above data, it seems interesting to determine the degree of influence&#xD;
      of the combined method of cytokine hemosorption (Efferon CT) and high-volume hemofiltration&#xD;
      on the clinical manifestations of endogenous intoxication and organ dysfunction in acute&#xD;
      pancreatitis. proceeding without septic complications.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">November 1, 2022</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">April 30, 2024</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">January 30, 2024</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>The study will be randomized stratified 1:1. The stratification criterion is the patient's SOFA index score.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Effect of the combined use of the Efferon CT device and HVHF on indicators of organ dysfunction</measure>
    <time_frame>1-72 hours</time_frame>
    <description>The value of indicators on the SOFA scale every 24 hours ± 1 hour from the start of hemoperfusion (0 hour) to 72 hours.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Effect of using the combined use of the Efferon CT device and HVHF on systemic hemodynamic parameters</measure>
    <time_frame>1-72 hours</time_frame>
    <description>Time (number of hours) from randomization to end of vasopressor support.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Effect of the combined use of the Efferon CT device and HVHF on pulmonary oxygen metabolism function</measure>
    <time_frame>1-72 hours</time_frame>
    <description>Value of oxygenation index (Pa02 / Fi02 (Pa) every 24 hours ± 1 hour from the start of hemoperfusion (hour 0) to 72 hours.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Effect of the combined use of the Efferon CT device and HVHF on the indicators of the cardiac index</measure>
    <time_frame>1-72 hours</time_frame>
    <description>Ultrasound assessment of LVOT VTI or RVOT VTI gain</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">60</enrollment>
  <condition>Acute Pancreatitis Without Necrosis or Infection</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Baseline therapy</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>Basic therapy - the routine practice of an institution for the treatment of patients with uninfected acute pancreatitis</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Basic therapy + Efferon CT + HVHF</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Basic therapy, which is the routine practice of an institution for the treatment of patients with acute nonseptic pancreatitis in combination with extracorporeal hemoperfusion therapy (Efferon CT) and high-volume hemofiltration (HVHF).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Efferon CT</intervention_name>
    <description>Efferon CT (JSC Efferon, Moscow, RF) is a device for extracorporeal blood purification by direct hemoperfusion. Detoxification is carried out by sorption of cytokines and other products of endogenous intoxication with a molecular size of up to 55 kDa.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Basic therapy + Efferon CT + HVHF</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Age from 18 to 75 years old,&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Acute pancreatitis according to the Atlanta classification of OP (2012), without signs&#xD;
             of infection,&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Acute pancreatitis confirmed by tomography. Score according to the Modified CTSI&#xD;
             Pancreatitis Severity Index: from 4 points and above,&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  No more than 3 days from the onset of an attack of acute pancreatitis,&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  APACHE II score - at least 10,&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  The patient must receive adequate fluid therapy (at least 30 ml/kg) from the time of&#xD;
             randomization until the first therapy,&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  The patient's condition allows therapy for at least 4 hours.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Exclusion Criteria:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Age over 75,&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  More than 3 days from the onset of an attack of acute pancreatitis,&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  An attack of acute pancreatitis, as an exacerbation of chronic pancreatitis.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Acute pancreatitis as a complication of a surgical operation,&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  DS - Septic shock (Sepsis-3, 2016)&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  The presence of a focus of non-sanitized surgical infection,&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Charlson comorbidity index&gt; 5 points,&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Critical hypoxemia (PaO2/FiO2 &lt; 150 mm Hg),&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  GCS level of consciousness &lt; 12 points,&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Obesity 3 degrees and above (weight over 150 kg),&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Blood triglyceride level &gt;1000 mg/dl, (11.2 mmol/l),&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Dementia,&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Inability to achieve or maintain min SBP ≥ 65 mm Hg. Art., despite vasopressor therapy&#xD;
             and infusion therapy in tech. 24 hours&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Presence of end-stage renal disease requiring RRT,&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  The presence of cirrhosis of the liver (&gt; 5 points according to the Child-Pugh&#xD;
             classification),&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Unresolved biliary hypertension syndrome,&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Acute thromboembolism of the pulmonary artery, confirmed by tomography,&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Acute myocardial infarction within the last 4 weeks,&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Acute cerebrovascular accident,&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Transfusion reaction,&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Severe congestive heart failure,&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Uncontrolled bleeding (acute blood loss in the last 24 hours).&#xD;
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>75 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Makariy Mendibaev, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Demikhov City Clinical Hospital of the Moscow Health Department</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Alexandr Shelehov-Kravchenko, PhD, MD</last_name>
    <phone>+79636564765</phone>
    <email>alexandr.shelehov@gmail.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>V.P. Demikhov City Clinical Hospital No. 68</name>
      <address>
        <city>Moscow</city>
        <zip>109263</zip>
        <country>Russian Federation</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Makariy Mendibaev, MD</last_name>
      <phone>+79153225032</phone>
      <email>makariy.mendibaev@yandex.ru</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Nikolay Chaus, MD, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Makariy Mendibaev, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Russian Federation</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>January 2023</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>January 13, 2023</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 13, 2023</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">January 23, 2023</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 25, 2023</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 25, 2023</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">January 26, 2023</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>acute pancreatitis</keyword>
  <keyword>sepsis</keyword>
  <keyword>cytokines apsorbtion</keyword>
  <keyword>hemoperfusion</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Pancreatitis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Necrosis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

