<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="9666">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 09, 2023</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT05693181</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>007-2022</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT05693181</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Cord Blood Cells in Patients With Acute SCI</brief_title>
  <acronym>SUBSCI II</acronym>
  <official_title>Systemic Administration of Allogenic Mononuclear Cord Blood Cells in Patients With Acute Severe Contusion Spinal Cord Injury: Safety and Efficiency Evaluation, Stages I/II</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Sklifosovsky Institute of Emergency Care</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>State-Financed Health Facility &quot;Samara Regional Medical Center Dinasty&quot;</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>K.L. Hetagurov North-Osetian State University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Sklifosovsky Institute of Emergency Care</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is a prospective, single-blinded, single-center, randomized, comparative, interventional&#xD;
      clinical study of systemic mononuclear multiple allogenic cord blood cells administration&#xD;
      safety and efficiency in patients having acute severe contusion spinal cord injury (ASIA&#xD;
      A/B), phase I/II&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Phase I/II of the SUBSCI II (Systemic Umbilical Cord Blood Administration in Patients with&#xD;
      Acute Severe Contusion Spinal Cord Injury II) study is focused on safety and primary efficacy&#xD;
      of multiple systemic infusions of allogeneic unrelated human umbilical cord blood mononuclear&#xD;
      cells in patients with severe acute spinal cord contusion having severe neurologic deficit&#xD;
      (ASIA A/B).&#xD;
&#xD;
      In a previous clinical study (SUBSCI I/IIa) complete safety and significant efficiency of&#xD;
      systemic administration of human umbilical cord blood cells (HUCBCs) was demonstrated.&#xD;
      Current study is established to confirm and verify the obtained results in a larger group of&#xD;
      patients.&#xD;
&#xD;
      SUBSCI II study includes 80 patients with acute severe contusion spinal cord injury (SCI) and&#xD;
      American Spinal Injury Association (ASIA) level A/B deficit divided into 2 groups&#xD;
      (experimental and control groups, 40 patients in each). Patients will be treated with 4&#xD;
      infusions of group-matched and rhesus-matched cord blood samples following primary&#xD;
      decompressive and stabilizing surgery within 7 days after SCI. All patients will be followed&#xD;
      up for 12 months after SCI.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">December 5, 2022</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">August 30, 2025</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 31, 2024</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1/Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Participant)</masking>
    <masking_description>Participants in the experimental group will obtain 4 systemic (i.v.) infusions of allogenic group- and rhesus-compatible non-related mononuclear cord blood cell samples (500 +/- 50 x 10'6 cells each).&#xD;
Participants in the control group will obtain the similar volume of vehicle (sterile saline).&#xD;
Participant's devision will be performed in a randomized manner. Randomization will be performed using standard randomization computer table.&#xD;
All participants will be blinded concerning the therapy mode.</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Adverse events</measure>
    <time_frame>Continuously for 12 months post-SCI</time_frame>
    <description>All adverse events (AEs) are registered within follow-up period. All registered AEs are classified using CTCAE classification and relation to the performed therapy.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Motor function</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from Baseline 12 months post-SCI</time_frame>
    <description>Evaluation of motor function dynamics in upper (UEMS), lower (LEMS) and all (GEMS) limbs</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Neurological deficit</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from Baseline 12 months post-SCI</time_frame>
    <description>Evaluation of general neurological deficit dynamics using ASIA scale</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Sensory function</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from Baseline 12 months post-SCI</time_frame>
    <description>Evaluation of pain, tactile, temperature and proprioceptive sensory function dynamics below SCI level and comparison between two groups</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Neuropathic pain syndrome</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months post-SCI</time_frame>
    <description>Evaluation of neuropathic pain syndrome dynamics and comparison between two groups</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Independent verticalization and motion ability</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from Baseline 12 months post-SCI</time_frame>
    <description>Evaluation of Independent verticalization and motion ability dynamics and comparison between two groups</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Limb muscle spasticity</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from Baseline 12 months post-SCI</time_frame>
    <description>Evaluation of limb muscle spasticity level dynamics using modified Ashworth or Tardieu scales and comparison between two groups</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Psychological status</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from Baseline 12 months post-SCI</time_frame>
    <description>Evaluation of psychological status dynamics using Beck depression and anxiety scales and comparison between two groups</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pelvic functions</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from Baseline 12 months post-SCI</time_frame>
    <description>Evaluation of pelvic functions dynamics (bladder fulfillment feeling, independent urination ability, urodynamic examination)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Life quality</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from Baseline 12 months post-SCI</time_frame>
    <description>Evaluation of life quality level in two groups using FIM (Functional Independence Measurement) scale and SF36 questionnaire</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Electrophysiology parameters</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months post-SCI</time_frame>
    <description>Assessment of electrophysiology objective parameters (electroneuromyography parameters with transcranial magnetic stimulation - full block, partial block or no block; somatosensory evoked potentials, motor evoked potentials)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Cell immunization</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months post-SCI</time_frame>
    <description>Assessment of patient's immunization to infused cell samples</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">80</enrollment>
  <condition>Spinal Cord Injury, Acute</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Cell Therapy</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients having acute severe contusion spinal cord injury (cervical, thoracic or upper-lumbar) and ASIA A/B neurological deficit, within 7 days post-SCI, after primary decompressive and stabilizing surgery. All participants meet inclusion and exclusion criteria. All participants obtain 4 infusions of allogenic non-related group- and rhesus-compatible mononuclear cord blood cells samples (500 +/- 50 x 10*6 cells each) with a 1-week interval. All participants are followed up for 12 months post-SCI.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Vehicle</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients having acute severe contusion spinal cord injury (cervical, thoracic or upper-lumbar) and ASIA A/B neurological deficit, within 7 days post-SCI, after primary decompressive and stabilizing surgery. All participants meet inclusion and exclusion criteria. All participants obtain 4 infusions of vehicle (sterile saline) with a 1-week interval. All participants are followed up for 12 months post-SCI.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Multiple systemic (i.v.) administration of allogenic non-related group- and rhesus-compatible mononuclear cord blood cells</intervention_name>
    <description>Each HUCBCs sample contain 500 +/- 50 x 10*6 allogenic non-related group- and rhesus-compatible mononuclear cord blood cells</description>
    <arm_group_label>Cell Therapy</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Control vehicle (sterile saline)</intervention_name>
    <description>Sterile saline infusion in control patients</description>
    <arm_group_label>Vehicle</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Both males and females, 18 to 75 years old&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Contusion spinal cord injury (SCI) at cervical, thoracic or upper lumbar (cone level)&#xD;
             levels&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  admission by 7 days post-SCI&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  spinal cord contusion confirmed using MRI (T1- and T2-weighted images, STIR)&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  ASIA A/B neurological deficit&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  identical level of neurological deficit at admission and at the moment of patient&#xD;
             inclusion&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  primary decompressive and stabilizing surgery performed within 5 days post-SCI and&#xD;
             prior to the first cell sample infused&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  patient is ready to participate and fulfill the requirements of the study protocol&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  informed consent signed by the patient or his legal representative&#xD;
&#xD;
        Exclusion Criteria:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  motor function preserved in lower limbs at admission (LEMS &gt; 0 points) corresponding&#xD;
             to ASIA C, D or E deficit level&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  any spinal cord injury different from contusion (tear, defibering, concussion,&#xD;
             SCIWORA, SCIWONA) confirmed using MRI&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  severe combined trauma (ISS &gt; 35 points)&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  inability to perform primary decompressive and stabilizing surgery within 5 days&#xD;
             post-SCI and prior to the first cell sample infused&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  persistent systolic arterial pressure (AP) &gt; 185 mmHg or diastolic AP &gt; 105 mmHg or&#xD;
             need of aggressive AP lowering using systemic antihypertensive medication at the&#xD;
             moment of patient inclusion&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  acute myocardial infarction&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  blood glucose level &lt; 3.5 Mmol/L or &gt;21 Mmol/L or ineffective antidiabetic therapy for&#xD;
             24 hours&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  acute or deterioration of chronic diseases of central nervous system (CNS) (e.g.&#xD;
             stroke, non-traumatic subarachnoid hemorrhages and others at the discretion of&#xD;
             investigator)&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  hypotension or cardiovascular shock AND systolic AP &lt; 90 mmHg OR need for intensive&#xD;
             systemic inotropic therapy at the moment of patient inclusion&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  objective need for artificial ling ventilation (ALV) at admission or prior to the&#xD;
             stage I surgery&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  acute kidney failure or deterioration of chronic kidney failure (creatinin level &gt; 250&#xD;
             mumol/L or carbamide level &gt; 25 Mmol/L)&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  liver failure (general bilirubin level &gt; 25 mumol/L, alanine aminotransferase (ALT)&#xD;
             and aspartate aminotransferase (AST) levels &gt; 4 times exceeding upper reference limit)&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  other significant disorders of vital functions&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  acute of deterioration of chronic diseases of internal organs preventing from cell&#xD;
             samples infusion&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  autoimmune diseases (active or anamnestic) preventing from cell samples infusion&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  allergic reactions of any type for any component of HUCBC samples&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  pregnancy or lactation&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  significant surgeries or severe traumas within 3 months prior to patient inclusion&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  acute or chronic infection diseases (tuberculosis, lues, HIV, hepatitis B, hepatitis C&#xD;
             etc.)&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  moderate or severe hematological and/or oncohematological diseases preventing from the&#xD;
             cell samples infusion&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  any malignant tumors (both operated and not operated) or benign tumors (not operated&#xD;
             or not totally removed) at the moment of patient inclusion&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  neurological and/or psychiatric diseases preventing patient from complete&#xD;
             understanding of study protocol or fulfillment of the study protocol requirements&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  other reasons preventing patient from complete understanding of study protocol or&#xD;
             fulfillment of the study protocol requirements&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  patient's participation in any other clinical trials or studies within 6 months prior&#xD;
             to inclusion&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  immunosuppressive therapy obtained by the patient for any reason at admission&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  allergic reaction for full blood or blood component transfusion in the past&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  need for extracorporal detoxication methods application (hemodialysis, plasmapheresis,&#xD;
             sorption etc.)&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  bone marrow or internal organs (both donor and relative) transplantation in the past&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  patient's participation in any studies applying regenerative technologies (grow&#xD;
             factors, cytokines, cell therapy, gene therapy etc.) within 1 year prior to inclusion&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  patient's rejection to sign the informed consent&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  any other reasons preventing patient's inclusion according to the investigator's&#xD;
             opinion&#xD;
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>75 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>N.V. Sklifosovsky Emergency Care Institute</name>
      <address>
        <city>Moscow</city>
        <zip>129090</zip>
        <country>Russian Federation</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Vladimir A. Smirnov, M.D., Ph.D.</last_name>
      <phone>+7-925-750-39-22</phone>
      <email>vla_smirnov@mail.ru</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Sergey E. Zuev, M.D.</last_name>
      <phone>+7-915-377-00-80</phone>
      <email>zu85@bk.ru</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Andrew A. Grin', Prof., M.D., Ph.D.</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Vladimir A. Smirnov, M.D., Ph.D.</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Sergey E. Zuev, M.D.</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Alexander E. Talypov, M.D., Ph.D.</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Anton Yu. Kordonsky, M.D., Ph.D.</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Ivan S. Lvov, M.D., Ph.D.</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Yana V. Morozova, M.D., Ph.D.</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Sergey M. Radaev, M.D., Ph.D.</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Russian Federation</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>January 2023</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>November 21, 2022</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 12, 2023</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">January 20, 2023</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 12, 2023</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 12, 2023</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">January 20, 2023</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Sklifosovsky Institute of Emergency Care</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Vladimir A. Smirnov</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Senior researcher, M.D., Ph.D.</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>spinal cord injury</keyword>
  <keyword>SCI</keyword>
  <keyword>neurological deficit</keyword>
  <keyword>stem cells</keyword>
  <keyword>cell therapy</keyword>
  <keyword>regenerative</keyword>
  <keyword>paraplegia</keyword>
  <keyword>tetraplegia</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Spinal Cord Injuries</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>Personal contacts via E-mail or phone after the completion of the study</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

