<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="9007">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 09, 2023</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT05707221</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>cleaning of ROA</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT05707221</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Effect of Different Cleaning Regimes on Biofilm Formation of Acrylic Based Removable Orthodontic Appliance</brief_title>
  <official_title>Effect of Different Cleaning Regimes on Biofilm Formation of Acrylic Based Removable Orthodontic Appliance</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Baghdad</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Baghdad</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study is to evaluate the effects of different cleaning regimes i.e. chemical and&#xD;
      mechanical on biofilm formation of an acrylic based removable orthodontic appliance and to&#xD;
      find out if surface modification i.e. polished acrylic fitting surface, have an impact on&#xD;
      cleaning the biofilm formation.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      It is double-blind, parallel, randomized clinical trial conducted in the orthodontic clinic&#xD;
      after obtaining the ethical approval from the ethics committee of the department. Thirty nine&#xD;
      orthodontic patients who meet the eligibility criteria will be included in the study and will&#xD;
      be provided by the patient information sheet and consent form that will explain the nature of&#xD;
      the study. After initial approval from the patient an alginate impression of the maxillary&#xD;
      arch will be taken and a negative replica will be made by type IV stone. The wire framework&#xD;
      of the removable appliance will be fabricated according to the design for the case. After&#xD;
      applying a separating medium, an acrylic base will be fabricated using the orthodontic&#xD;
      acrylic powder and liquid (Orthocryle, Dentaurum, Ispringen, German) with a ratio of (2.5&#xD;
      parts powder to 1 part liquid) according to the manufacturer's instruction with four wells on&#xD;
      each side of the fitting surface of the appliance. Acrylic samples i.e. tiles of different&#xD;
      surface texture will be made. An acrylic sheet of 1 mm thickness will be made using a mold&#xD;
      material. One sheet will be polished using a conventional polishing technique until a glossy&#xD;
      surface appears, whereas, the other sheet will be kept without modification. Tiles of 5mm in&#xD;
      diameter will be bored using a trephine bur on both sides of the acrylic sheets and each set&#xD;
      of tiles i.e. the polished and unpolished samples will be color coated from its seated&#xD;
      surface. The acrylic tiles (5mm in diameter and 1mm thickness) will be placed and fixed into&#xD;
      the holes created using sticky wax. The acrylic samples will be randomly seated, The&#xD;
      appliance will be sterilized using proper sterilization protocol. The removable appliance&#xD;
      will be assigned randomly and blindly and fitted into the oral cavity of the patient for one&#xD;
      week. Each individual will be given by an independent person a pack containing the cleansing&#xD;
      pack and an instruction sheet describing the cleaning regimen for his/ her appliance. The&#xD;
      packs are similar in shape and color and will be prepared by a third person who does not know&#xD;
      the purpose of the study. The participant will be grouped into three groups:&#xD;
&#xD;
        1. Brushing with denture brush and chlorhexidine (CHX) toothpaste (lacalut Active, Germany)&#xD;
           for one minute.&#xD;
&#xD;
        2. Chemical cleaning i.e. Lacalut cleaning tablet (lacalut DENT cleaning tab, Germany),&#xD;
           fill the cup to the marked line (150 mL) with tap water, dissolve one cleansing tablet&#xD;
           and wait for 20 minutes then wash it with tap water.&#xD;
&#xD;
        3. Combination of brushing with CHX toothpaste and cleaning tablet. At the end of the study&#xD;
           period, the acrylic samples will be removed carefully and applied into a petri dish&#xD;
           containing PBS via a sterile tweezer. The samples will be then immersed twice in a 25ml&#xD;
           sterile tubes containing PBS to remove the planktonic bacteria and inserted into 5ml&#xD;
           bijou tube containing 1mm PBS. The sample will be vortex mixed for 1 minute to&#xD;
           disseminate the biofilm and create a homogenous solution. Ten-fold serial dilutions will&#xD;
           be carried out in PBS before the samples are plated onto blood agar (BA), to give the&#xD;
           total anaerobic count, mitis salivarius agar (MS), a selective agar for streptococci&#xD;
           spp. and Mannitol salt agar (MA) for Staphylococci spp. BA and MS plates will be&#xD;
           incubated anaerobically for 2-4 days at 37ºC using anaerobic cabinet whereas the MA will&#xD;
           be incubated for 2 days in aerobic condition. All organisms from both selective and&#xD;
           nonselective agars will be distinguished by colony morphology and will be characterized&#xD;
           by Gram reaction and other confirmatory tests: 1. Catalase testing 2. Coagulase testing&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">April 17, 2022</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">April 30, 2023</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">February 25, 2023</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>The removable appliance will be assigned randomly and blindly and fitted into the oral cavity of the patient for one week. Each individual will be given a pack containing the cleansing pack and an instruction sheet describing the cleaning regimen for his/ her appliance. The packs are similar in shape and color and will be prepared by a third person who does not know the purpose of the study. The volunteer will be grouped into three groups:&#xD;
Group 1: patients will be instructed to brush both sides of the removable appliance once a day for 1 minute before bedtime using the denture brush and the CHX toothpaste (lacalut active, Germany) provided and water. Group 2: patients will be instructed to immerse the appliance in 150 ml cup with tap water and dissolve one cleansing (lacalut DENT cleaning tablet, Germany) tablet for 20 minutes according to the manufacture instructions. Group 3: Combination of brushing with CHX and cleaning tablets.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Other</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double (Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
    <masking_description>Sequence Generation: A computer random generator will be used to develop a simple randomization Allocation Concealment: This will be achieved using sequentially numbered, opaque and sealed envelopes which will be numbered according to the study numbers. Each envelope includes the treatment allocation card (group 1, 2 or 3) and the related cleaning method with instruction card.&#xD;
Blinding: An independent person will be responsible for giving the patient the envelope, all data collection and counting will be completed by a microbiologist who would not know about the study.</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>microbial evaluation between the three cleaning methods</measure>
    <time_frame>7 days</time_frame>
    <description>numbers of streptococcus species, staphylococcus species and total anaerobic bacteria will be evaluated after isolation from acrylic discs and culture.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>microbial evaluation between the polished and unpolished acrylic discs</measure>
    <time_frame>7 days</time_frame>
    <description>numbers of streptococcus species, staphylococcus species and total anaerobic bacteria will be evaluated after isolation from acrylic discs and culture.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">39</enrollment>
  <condition>Oral Disease</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>mechanical cleaning method by denture brush and Chlorhexidine toothpaste</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>patients will be instructed to brush both sides of the removable appliance once a day for 1 minute before bedtime using the toothbrush and the CHX toothpaste provided and water</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>chemical cleaning method with cleaning tablet</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>patients will be instructed to immerse the appliance in 150 ml cup with tap water and dissolve one cleansing tablet for 20 minutes according to the manufacture instructions.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>combination of mechanical and chemical cleaning</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>first submitted to the mechanical method, followed by the chemical method.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>cleaning removable acrylic appliance with denture brush and chlorhexidine toothpaste</intervention_name>
    <description>mechanical cleaning of removable appliance by the patient for 7 days before bedtime for one minute</description>
    <arm_group_label>mechanical cleaning method by denture brush and Chlorhexidine toothpaste</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Denture brush (Foramen denture brush, Spain), CHX toothpaste(Lacalute Active, Germany)</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>cleaning removable acrylic appliance with cleansing tablet</intervention_name>
    <description>chemical cleaning by patient for 7 days with cleansing tablet</description>
    <arm_group_label>chemical cleaning method with cleaning tablet</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>cleansing tablet (Lacalute cleansing tablet, Germany)</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>combination of mechanical and chemical cleaning</intervention_name>
    <description>cleaning the appliance with denture brush and CHX toothpaste followed by the cleansing tablet</description>
    <arm_group_label>combination of mechanical and chemical cleaning</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>cleaning with brushing then with the cleaning tablet</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Presence of full upper permanent dentition&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Well-aligned teeth or mild crowding (less than 3mm)&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  No history of sensitivity to any ingredient contained in the cleaning materials&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Nonsmoker&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Caries free&#xD;
&#xD;
        Exclusion Criteria:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Participant taking steroid-based or antibacterial mouthwash or broad-spectrum&#xD;
             antibiotics&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Mouth breather&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Participant taking medication that reduces salivary flow&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Pregnant lactating female&#xD;
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>7 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>45 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Dheaa Al-Groosh, Ph.D</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>University of Baghdad</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>safa khawwam, B.D.S</last_name>
    <phone>+9647704221054</phone>
    <phone_ext>+964</phone_ext>
    <email>safa.emad1203a@codental.uobaghdad.edu.iq</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Dheaa Al-Groosh, Ph.D</last_name>
    <phone>+9647737776503</phone>
    <phone_ext>+964</phone_ext>
    <email>d.al-groosh@codental.uobaghdad.edu.iq</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Baghdad college of dentistry</name>
      <address>
        <city>Baghdad</city>
        <state>Bab-Almuadham</state>
        <zip>10047</zip>
        <country>Iraq</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Iraq</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Albanna RH, Farawanah HM, Aldrees AM. Microbial evaluation of the effectiveness of different methods for cleansing clear orthodontic retainers: A randomized clinical trial. Angle Orthod. 2017 May;87(3):460-465. doi: 10.2319/072916-585.1. Epub 2016 Nov 15.</citation>
    <PMID>27845562</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Eichenauer J, Serbesis C, Ruf S. Cleaning removable orthodontic appliances: a survey. J Orofac Orthop. 2011 Oct;72(5):389-95. doi: 10.1007/s00056-011-0043-2. English, German.</citation>
    <PMID>21990062</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Leao RS, Maior JRS, Lemos CAA, Vasconcelos BCDE, Montes MAJR, Pellizzer EP, Moraes SLD. Complications with PMMA compared with other materials used in cranioplasty: a systematic review and meta-analysis. Braz Oral Res. 2018 Jun 7;32:e31. doi: 10.1590/1807-3107bor-2018.vol32.0031.</citation>
    <PMID>29898018</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lima EM, Moura JS, Del Bel Cury AA, Garcia RC, Cury JA. Effect of enzymatic and NaOCl treatments on acrylic roughness and on biofilm accumulation. J Oral Rehabil. 2006 May;33(5):356-62. doi: 10.1111/j.1365-2842.2005.01564.x.</citation>
    <PMID>16629894</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Pathak AK, Sharma DS. Biofilm associated microorganisms on removable oral orthodontic appliances in children in the mixed dentition. J Clin Pediatr Dent. 2013 Spring;37(3):335-9. doi: 10.17796/jcpd.37.3.92230h6256v8697t.</citation>
    <PMID>23855182</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Puri G, Berzins DW, Dhuru VB, Raj PA, Rambhia SK, Dhir G, Dentino AR. Effect of phosphate group addition on the properties of denture base resins. J Prosthet Dent. 2008 Oct;100(4):302-8. doi: 10.1016/S0022-3913(08)60210-3.</citation>
    <PMID>18922259</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Rodriguez-Renteria M, Marquez-Preciado R, Ortiz-Magdaleno M, Bermeo-Escalona J, Sanchez-Vargas LO. Frequency of Pathogenic Microorganisms in Removable Orthodontic Appliances and Oral Mucosa in Children. J Clin Pediatr Dent. 2021 Apr 1;45(2):135-139. doi: 10.17796/1053-4625-45.2.11.</citation>
    <PMID>33951170</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Schwindling FS, Rammelsberg P, Stober T. Effect of chemical disinfection on the surface roughness of hard denture base materials: a systematic literature review. Int J Prosthodont. 2014 May-Jun;27(3):215-25. doi: 10.11607/ijp.3759.</citation>
    <PMID>24905261</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Xiao J, Moon Y, Li L, Rustchenko E, Wakabayashi H, Zhao X, Feng C, Gill SR, McLaren S, Malmstrom H, Ren Y, Quivey R, Koo H, Kopycka-Kedzierawski DT. Candida albicans Carriage in Children with Severe Early Childhood Caries (S-ECC) and Maternal Relatedness. PLoS One. 2016 Oct 14;11(10):e0164242. doi: 10.1371/journal.pone.0164242. eCollection 2016.</citation>
    <PMID>27741258</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>January 2023</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>December 25, 2022</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 27, 2023</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">January 31, 2023</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 27, 2023</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 27, 2023</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">January 31, 2023</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Baghdad</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Dheaa Hussein Al-Groosh</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Prof.Dr Dheaa Hussein Al-Groosh</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Oral biofilm</keyword>
  <keyword>Removable Orthodontic appliance</keyword>
  <keyword>Cleaning Removable appliances</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Mouth Diseases</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Chlorhexidine</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <provided_document_section>
    <provided_document>
      <document_type>Study Protocol, Statistical Analysis Plan, and Informed Consent Form</document_type>
      <document_has_protocol>Yes</document_has_protocol>
      <document_has_icf>Yes</document_has_icf>
      <document_has_sap>Yes</document_has_sap>
      <document_date>December 29, 2021</document_date>
      <document_url>https://ClinicalTrials.gov/ProvidedDocs/21/NCT05707221/Prot_SAP_ICF_000.pdf</document_url>
    </provided_document>
  </provided_document_section>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

