<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="9484">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 09, 2023</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT05696860</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>BUU2019/8-18</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT05696860</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Microstream® Capnography in Endobronchial Ultrasonography Applications Under Sedation</brief_title>
  <official_title>The Effect of Microstream® Capnography on Patient Safety in Endobronchial Ultrasonography Applications Under Sedation</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Bursa Uludag Universitesi</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Bursa Uludag Universitesi</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Purpose: Researchers wanted to investigate the effect of capnography monitoring in addition&#xD;
      to routine monitoring on the development of desaturation and other vital parameters in&#xD;
      endobronchial ultrasonography (EBUS) cases.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Method: 100 patients who underwent EBUS under sedation will be included in this prospective&#xD;
      and randomized controlled study. The cases will be divided into two groups of 50 people each.&#xD;
      In the first group, standard monitoring will be performed, and in the second group, in&#xD;
      addition to standard monitoring, capnography monitoring will be used. Heart rate, blood&#xD;
      pressure, peripheral oxygen saturation (SpO2) values in both groups, end-tidal carbon dioxide&#xD;
      (EtCO2), respiratory rate and integrated pulmonary index (IPI) values in the second group&#xD;
      will be recorded in all cases. Disturbances in vital parameters and airway interventions,&#xD;
      which were common in both groups, will ve compared. The frequency of problems detected by&#xD;
      capnography monitoring in the second group will be examined.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Endobronchial ultrasonography (EBUS) is an examination method that has been increasingly used&#xD;
      in diagnosing and staging lung cancer, mediastinal lymphadenopathy and masses in recent&#xD;
      years. This procedure is performed under anesthesia. General anesthesia or sedation is&#xD;
      generally preferred as an anesthesia option. Desaturation may frequently develop during this&#xD;
      procedure. Follow-up with standard perioperative monitoring methods (heart rate - HR,&#xD;
      respiratory rate - SS, peripheral oxygen saturation - SpO2) is not a proper approach to&#xD;
      detecting respiratory depression before desaturation develops.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Capnography is a monitoring method that detects respiratory depression before desaturation&#xD;
      develops by making instant end-tidal carbon dioxide (EtCO2) measurements. It has been stated&#xD;
      that it significantly reduces the risk of desaturation in many surgical and interventional&#xD;
      procedures performed under sedation and general anesthesia. In addition, respiratory&#xD;
      disorders such as bronchospasm, apnea or hypopnea can be detected by capnography. However,&#xD;
      there is no information about capnography's effect on desaturation development or its&#xD;
      contribution to standard monitoring in EBUS cases.&#xD;
&#xD;
      The purpose of this study was to investigate the effects of capnography monitoring in&#xD;
      addition to routine monitoring on the development of desaturation and other vital parameters&#xD;
      in EBUS cases under moderate sedation according to the Ramsay Sedation Scale (RSS). The&#xD;
      primary aim was to compare the groups in terms of the development of desaturation, and the&#xD;
      secondary aim was in terms of duration of hypoxemia, development of severe hypoxemia, lowest&#xD;
      SpO2 value, development of hypotension, and bradycardia.&#xD;
&#xD;
      150 patients who will undergo elective EBUS procedure, have scores between 1-3 according to&#xD;
      the American Society of Anesthesiologists (ASA) classification, are pregnant or not suspected&#xD;
      of pregnancy, approve the informed consent form, and are not allergic to the sedation agents&#xD;
      to be used, will be included in the study. Patients with an ASA score of 4 and above,&#xD;
      pregnant or suspected pregnancy, patients with difficult airway features, and emergency cases&#xD;
      will be excluded from the study.&#xD;
&#xD;
      The cases will be divided into two groups of 75 people using the closed envelope method.&#xD;
      There will be cases in which capnography monitorization was performed in group 1&#xD;
      (experimental group), and cases in which capnography monitoring was not performed in group 2&#xD;
      (control group). In all cases, age, gender, weight, height, ASA class, doses of applied&#xD;
      anesthesia drugs, and smoking history will be recorded. After obtaining informed consent in&#xD;
      all cases Standard monitoring and BIS monitoring will be performed before sedation, including&#xD;
      HR, SS, SpO2, BP, and 3-lead electrocardiographic analysis. In addition to standard&#xD;
      monitoring in patients in Group 1, ETCO2, integrated pulmonary index (IPI) will be measured&#xD;
      non-invasively prior to sedation through a nasal cannula (FilterLine®) connected to the&#xD;
      capnography device (Capnostream® 20p). Sedation and analgesia will be performed in accordance&#xD;
      with the routine sedation-analgesia protocol used by our department in EBUS cases. There will&#xD;
      be no changes to the routine protocol. In accordance with this protocol, after the patient is&#xD;
      taken to the operating room, 5 ml of 2% lidocaine will be applied with a reservoir mask for&#xD;
      topical anesthesia. As a sedative agent, 1-2 mg of midazolam will be administered&#xD;
      intravenously. A nasopharyngeal airway will be placed and 5 lt/min oxygen will be given to&#xD;
      all patients throughout the operation. In induction, remifentanil will be administered at a&#xD;
      level of 0.04 µg/kg/min and Propofol at a level of 0.5-1 mg/kg/hour. The target sedation&#xD;
      level will be determined as 60-80 BIS score and will be level 3 (moderate sedation, sleepy&#xD;
      but responsive to verbal stimuli) according to the Ramsey Sedation Scale. All parameters&#xD;
      measured before sedation in both groups; It will be recorded at 3 minutes, 6 minutes, 9&#xD;
      minutes after sedation, and at 3-minute intervals until the end of the operation.&#xD;
&#xD;
      During the operation, in the cases in Group 1, apnea (the ETCO2 waveform is not seen for 10&#xD;
      seconds), hypopnea (at least 50% decrease in the peak ETCO2 level in 2 consecutive waveforms&#xD;
      compared to the initial value and the peak ETCO2 level in the second wave is lower than the&#xD;
      first) and the number of bronchospasm, The number of episodes of cough, tachycardia,&#xD;
      bradycardia, hypoxemia (SpO2&lt;90%) in both groups, duration of anesthesia, duration of the&#xD;
      procedure (time between insertion and removal of the bronchoscope) and recovery time&#xD;
      (spontaneous opening of the eyes of the patients with the removal of the bronchoscope,&#xD;
      performing the finger-nose test) and the time elapsed between the time he was able to tell&#xD;
      his birth dates) will be recorded. If bronchospasm, upper airway obstruction, apnea,&#xD;
      bradypnea develop during the procedure, jaw-thrust maneuvers, head-tilt maneuvers, verbal and&#xD;
      tactile warnings will be recorded.&#xD;
&#xD;
      After the operation, the cases will be taken to the recovery unit. From the moment of entry&#xD;
      in the recovery unit; BP, EtCO2, SpO2 and IPI values will be recorded every 5 minutes until&#xD;
      the exit time. In accordance with the routine sobering protocol; Patients with a Modified&#xD;
      Aldrete Score of 9 or higher will be sent to the clinic.&#xD;
&#xD;
      The frequency and interrelationship of the parameters evaluated in both groups will be&#xD;
      examined. Between the group that underwent capnography and the group that did not; It will be&#xD;
      investigated whether there is a significant difference in terms of apnea, desaturation&#xD;
      episodes and interventions.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">May 8, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">February 28, 2023</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">February 1, 2023</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Supportive Care</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Quadruple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Desaturation Development - Peripheric oxygen saturation decrease less than 90% on Pulse Oximetry</measure>
    <time_frame>During Sedation, an average of 1 hour</time_frame>
    <description>Compare Experimental and Control Groups in Terms of Desaturation Development</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">100</enrollment>
  <condition>Capnography</condition>
  <condition>Endobronchial Ultrasound</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Monitorization with Capnography</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients followed with capnography and standard monitorization</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Monitorization Without Capnography</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients followed with standard monitorization</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Capnography Monitoring</intervention_name>
    <description>Capnography monitoring</description>
    <arm_group_label>Monitorization with Capnography</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  American Society of Anesthesiologists (ASA) score of 1-3,&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  No pregnancy or suspected pregnancy&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  No allergy history&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Signed informed consent&#xD;
&#xD;
        Exclusion Criteria:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Emergency EBUS cases&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  ASA score of 4&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Allergy or pregnancy history&#xD;
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <gender_based>Yes</gender_based>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Fatma Nur Kaya</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Supervisor</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Bursa Uludag University Department of Anesthesiology and Reanimation</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bursa</city>
        <country>Turkey</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Turkey</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>January 2023</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>December 26, 2022</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 23, 2023</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">January 25, 2023</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 23, 2023</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 23, 2023</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">January 25, 2023</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Bursa Uludag Universitesi</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Sinem Cetinkaya Ozpar</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Doctor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

