<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="9495">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 09, 2023</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT05696665</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>F.2-81/2022-GENL/104/JPMC</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>9447</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>Dr Saara Ahmad Muddasir Khan</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>Dr Mahboob Alam</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT05696665</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Role of Saffron and Chamomile in the Management of Parkinson's Disease</brief_title>
  <acronym>SAFCHEMRxPar</acronym>
  <official_title>Role of Saffron and Chamomile and Their Active Compounds in the Management of Parkinson Disease in the Context of Psychometric and Biochemical Measures</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Jinnah Postgraduate Medical Centre</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Aga Khan University Hospital, Pakistan</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Liaquat National Hospital &amp; Medical College</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Jinnah Postgraduate Medical Centre</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      In multitudinous preclinical studies, Saffron and Chamomile are found effective in treating&#xD;
      PD. They can mitigate the neurodegenerative progression of the disease by curtailing&#xD;
      dopaminergic and neuronal loss and by inhibiting alpha-synuclein aggregation. They also&#xD;
      possess antioxidant and anti-inflammatory activities. The synergism of both drugs can manage&#xD;
      Parkinson's disease and related neurological disorders although, clinical trials are needed&#xD;
      for further elaboration. Therefore, the purpose of the study is to evaluate the effects of&#xD;
      Saffron and Chamomile and their active compounds in treating Parkinson's disease. This&#xD;
      combination may change psychometric measures (MDS-Unified Parkinson's Disease Rating Scale),&#xD;
      biomarkers (including Alpha-synuclein), and oxidative stress-related to Parkinson's disease.&#xD;
      This combination along with conventional therapy might be beneficial in managing patients&#xD;
      with Parkinson's disease&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Parkinson's disease(PD) is a distinctive clinical disorder with a multifactorial range of&#xD;
      etiology and symptoms. This neurodegenerative disease is spreading at exponent rates. It can&#xD;
      impact individuals enormously. As a degenerative disease, its progression can span decades.&#xD;
      The disease has profound repercussions for caregivers and is also a socio-economic burden for&#xD;
      society SAFFRON Saffron is a spice obtained from the stigmas of the Crocus sativus L flower,&#xD;
      grown extensively in Iran and other parts of the world, including Greece and India. According&#xD;
      to current data, saffron cultivation and usage date back approximately 3000 years, although&#xD;
      the oldest records of this plant date back to the Assyrian era.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Saffron is a perennial plant that grows to a height of 10 to 30 cm. Numerous leaves branch&#xD;
      out from the bulb's center, culminating in two to three blooms. The color is determined by&#xD;
      the amount of lycopene and carotenoid contained inside a three-branched stigma stigma.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Saffron contains 5% fat, 5% minerals, 10% moisture , 12% protein, 63% sugars and 5% crude&#xD;
      fiber. Stigmas contain around 150 volatile chemicals, including terpenes, and alcohol, along&#xD;
      with their esters. Three important bioactive components in Saffron are crocin, safranal, and&#xD;
      picrocrocin, which are responsible for Saffron's taste, unique color r. Saffron's bitter&#xD;
      flavor is created by picrocrocin, which eventually transforms into safranal. Additionally,&#xD;
      lycopene, zeaxanthin, carotene, vitamins including thiamine and riboflavin are active&#xD;
      components Saffron contains about 150 compounds, however the most physiologically active are&#xD;
      two carotenoids called crocin and crocetin .Both of these compounds have been evaluated&#xD;
      pharmacokinetically in animal and human research. According to pharmacokinetic studies Crocin&#xD;
      is not accessible in the bloodstream as it is after oral intake but converted to crocetin in&#xD;
      the colon. Additionally, it may cross the blood-brain barrier and enter the central nervous&#xD;
      system through passive transcellular diffusion, making it beneficial in neurodegenerative&#xD;
      illnesses.&#xD;
&#xD;
      CHAMOMILE Matricaria recutita chamomilla is an annual plant native to Europe and Asia with&#xD;
      branching, tall, and smooth stems. Apigenin, apigenin-7-O-glucoside, luteolin, and&#xD;
      luteolin-7-O-glucoside, terpene bisabolol ,caffeic acid, farnesene, chamazulene, chlorogenic&#xD;
      acid flavonoids (apigenin, quercetin, , patuletin and luteolin), and coumarin are the&#xD;
      chemical components found in this plant.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Pharmacological activities German chamomile is beneficial for treating stomachaches, IBS, and&#xD;
      sleeplessness. It has anti-inflammatory, antibacterial, and relaxing properties.&#xD;
      Additionally, it has acaricidal effects. Several animal studies have revealed that this herb&#xD;
      has neuroprotective,anxiolytic, antimutagenic, cholesterol-lowering, wound healing, and&#xD;
      antidiabetic effects. Chamomile was shown to have weak antibacterial and antioxidant&#xD;
      capabilities, but substantial antiplatelet and anticarcinoma activities in in vitro&#xD;
      experiments.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Rationale of the study :&#xD;
&#xD;
      In various preclinical studies role of saffron and chamomile is found effective in treating&#xD;
      Parkinson disease. Their neuroprotective and antioxidant effects are also widely known.&#xD;
      Although, efficacy of this combination in treating Parkinson disease as a clinical trial is&#xD;
      yet to be analyzed .Therefore, this clinical trial is designed to determine the effects of&#xD;
      saffron and chamomile as combination in compared to approved pharmacotherapy&#xD;
&#xD;
      Aim :&#xD;
&#xD;
      To study the effects of Saffron and Chamomile in the treatment of with reference to&#xD;
      psychometric biochemical , and Insilco measures.&#xD;
&#xD;
      HYPOTHESIS Null Hypothesis There is no beneficial effects of Saffron and chamomile in the&#xD;
      treatment of Parkinson disease Alternative Hypothesis Saffron and chamomile have efficacy in&#xD;
      the treatment of Parkinson disease&#xD;
&#xD;
      AIM &amp; OBJECTIVES&#xD;
&#xD;
      1. To evaluate and compare :&#xD;
&#xD;
        -  clinical efficacy of saffron and chamomile in the management of Parkinson disease.&#xD;
&#xD;
        -  the effects of saffron and chamomile on plasma biomarkers in the management of Parkinson&#xD;
           disease.&#xD;
&#xD;
        -  the antioxidant effects of saffron and chamomile in the management of Parkinson disease.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">July 5, 2022</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2023</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2023</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>GROUP A Conventional drugs only 40 GROUP B:Conventional drugs +1000 mg chamomile 30 mg saffron in a capsule form GROUP C:GROUP C Conventional drugs +500mgApigenin +30mg Crocin 40</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Movement Disorder Society-Sponsored Revision of the Unified Parkinson's Disease Rating Scale</measure>
    <time_frame>4months</time_frame>
    <description>The MDS-UPDRS can be used to evaluate various aspects of Parkinson's disease, including non-motor and motor experiences of daily living and motor complications. It includes a motor evaluation and characterizes the extent and burden of disease across various populations. All items have five response options with uniform anchors of 0 = normal, 1 = slight, 2 = mild, 3 = moderate, and 4 = severe.Each parkinsonian sign or symptom is rated on a 5-point Likert-type scale (ranging from 0 to 4), with higher scores indicating more severe impairment. The maximum total UPDRS score is 199, indicating the worst possible disability from PD</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Levels of Alpha-synuclein and Human Neurofilament Light</measure>
    <time_frame>4 months</time_frame>
    <description>levels of Alpha-synuclein and Human Neurofilament Light will be measured on day 0 and last day of trial using Elisa</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Level of antioxidant:Superoxide Dismutase (SOD)</measure>
    <time_frame>4 months</time_frame>
    <description>levels of Superoxide Dismutase (SOD) will be measured on day 0 and last day of trial</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of treatment -Emergent Adverse Events(Safety and Evaluation)</measure>
    <time_frame>4 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">120</enrollment>
  <condition>Parkinson Disease</condition>
  <condition>Neurodegenerative Diseases</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Group A</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>conventional therapy only</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Group B</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>conventional therapy +500 mg chamomile 15 mg saffron twice daily</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Group C</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>conventional therapy +500mgApigenin +30mg Crocin once daily</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>conventional therapy</intervention_name>
    <description>Patients will be kept on conventional therapy and no added drugs will be given</description>
    <arm_group_label>Group A</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Saffron and Chamomile</intervention_name>
    <description>Patients will be given saffron and chamomile in capsule formulation twice daily</description>
    <arm_group_label>Group B</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Crocin and Apigenin</intervention_name>
    <description>Active ingredients of saffron(Crocin) and Chamomile(Apigenin) will be given in capsule formultaion once daily</description>
    <arm_group_label>Group C</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  • All diagnosed patients aged 40-years and above of either sex will be included&#xD;
&#xD;
               -  Diagnosis will be based on the UK Parkinson Disease Society Brain Bank Clinical&#xD;
                  Diagnostic Criteria reported by neurophysicians.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Exclusion Criteria:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  • Patients with atypical Parkinsonism will be excluded.&#xD;
&#xD;
               -  Patients with uncontrolled comorbidities will also be excluded.&#xD;
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>40 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>85 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Fizzah Ali, MBBS,MPhil</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Liaquat National hospital and Medical college</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Fizzah Ali, MBBS, MPhil</last_name>
    <phone>+923333235882</phone>
    <email>fizzah.saqib@gmail.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Fizzah Mudassir, MBBS, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>+923343448258</phone>
    <email>saara.mudassir@aku.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Jinnah Postgraduate Medical Centre (JPMC),</name>
      <address>
        <city>Karachi</city>
        <state>Sindh</state>
        <zip>00000</zip>
        <country>Pakistan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Fizzah Ali, MPhill</last_name>
      <phone>03333235882</phone>
      <email>fizzah.saqib@gmail.com</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Saara Mudassir, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>0333 3448258</phone>
      <email>saara.muddasir@aku.edu</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Fizzah Ali</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Saara /mudassir, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Mehboob Alam, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Junaid Ahmed, FCPS</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Pakistan</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/35274200/</url>
    <description>efficacy of parkinson disease</description>
  </link>
  <link>
    <url>https://link.springer.com/article/10.1007/s12035-020-01941-2</url>
    <description>Crocin Reverses Depression-Like Behavior in Parkinson</description>
  </link>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Rajaei Z, Hosseini M, Alaei H. Effects of crocin on brain oxidative damage and aversive memory in a 6-OHDA model of Parkinson's disease. Arq Neuropsiquiatr. 2016 Sep;74(9):723-729. doi: 10.1590/0004-282X20160131.</citation>
    <PMID>27706421</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Haeri P, Mohammadipour A, Heidari Z, Ebrahimzadeh-Bideskan A. Neuroprotective effect of crocin on substantia nigra in MPTP-induced Parkinson's disease model of mice. Anat Sci Int. 2019 Jan;94(1):119-127. doi: 10.1007/s12565-018-0457-7. Epub 2018 Aug 29.</citation>
    <PMID>30159851</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Inoue E, Shimizu Y, Masui R, Hayakawa T, Tsubonoya T, Hori S, Sudoh K. Effects of saffron and its constituents, crocin-1, crocin-2, and crocetin on alpha-synuclein fibrils. J Nat Med. 2018 Jan;72(1):274-279. doi: 10.1007/s11418-017-1150-1. Epub 2017 Nov 17.</citation>
    <PMID>29147836</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Inoue E, Suzuki T, Shimizu Y, Sudo K, Kawasaki H, Ishida N. Saffron ameliorated motor symptoms, short life span and retinal degeneration in Parkinson's disease fly models. Gene. 2021 Oct 5;799:145811. doi: 10.1016/j.gene.2021.145811. Epub 2021 Jul 2.</citation>
    <PMID>34224829</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>De Monte C, Carradori S, Chimenti P, Secci D, Mannina L, Alcaro F, Petzer A, N'Da CI, Gidaro MC, Costa G, Alcaro S, Petzer JP. New insights into the biological properties of Crocus sativus L.: chemical modifications, human monoamine oxidases inhibition and molecular modeling studies. Eur J Med Chem. 2014 Jul 23;82:164-71. doi: 10.1016/j.ejmech.2014.05.048. Epub 2014 May 22.</citation>
    <PMID>24904963</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Ghasemi Tigan M, Ghahghaei A, Lagzian M. In-vitro and in-silico investigation of protective mechanisms of crocin against E46K alpha-synuclein amyloid formation. Mol Biol Rep. 2019 Aug;46(4):4279-4292. doi: 10.1007/s11033-019-04882-9. Epub 2019 May 20.</citation>
    <PMID>31111370</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Anusha C, Sumathi T, Joseph LD. Protective role of apigenin on rotenone induced rat model of Parkinson's disease: Suppression of neuroinflammation and oxidative stress mediated apoptosis. Chem Biol Interact. 2017 May 1;269:67-79. doi: 10.1016/j.cbi.2017.03.016. Epub 2017 Apr 4.</citation>
    <PMID>28389404</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Siddique YH, Jyoti S. Alteration in biochemical parameters in the brain of transgenic Drosophila melanogaster model of Parkinson's disease exposed to apigenin. Integr Med Res. 2017 Sep;6(3):245-253. doi: 10.1016/j.imr.2017.04.003. Epub 2017 Apr 29.</citation>
    <PMID>28951838</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Mohammadzadeh L, Ghasemzadeh Rahbardar M, Razavi BM, Hosseinzadeh H. Crocin Protects Malathion-Induced Striatal Biochemical Deficits by Inhibiting Apoptosis and Increasing alpha-Synuclein in Rats' Striatum. J Mol Neurosci. 2022 May;72(5):983-993. doi: 10.1007/s12031-022-01990-3. Epub 2022 Mar 10.</citation>
    <PMID>35274200</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <verification_date>January 2023</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>December 20, 2022</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 23, 2023</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">January 25, 2023</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 23, 2023</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 23, 2023</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">January 25, 2023</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Jinnah Postgraduate Medical Centre</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Fizzah Ali</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Assistant Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>saffron</keyword>
  <keyword>Chamomile</keyword>
  <keyword>Parkinson</keyword>
  <keyword>Apigenin</keyword>
  <keyword>Crocin</keyword>
  <keyword>Neurodegenerative disorder</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Parkinson Disease</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Neurodegenerative Diseases</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Yes</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>All IPD and results along with publications will be shared</ipd_description>
    <ipd_info_type>Study Protocol</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_info_type>Statistical Analysis Plan (SAP)</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_info_type>Informed Consent Form (ICF)</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_info_type>Clinical Study Report (CSR)</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_time_frame>6 months after publication of the primary outcomes</ipd_time_frame>
    <ipd_access_criteria>Data and study material will be shared6months after the completion of study and after publicationsof primary outcomes</ipd_access_criteria>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

