<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="9202">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 09, 2023</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT05703061</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>Pro2018000606</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT05703061</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Sleep in Adolescents - Pilot Study</brief_title>
  <official_title>Sleep in Adolescents - Pilot Study</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Rutgers, The State University of New Jersey</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Rutgers, The State University of New Jersey</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The goal of this pilot clinical trial is to determine the feasibility and acceptability of&#xD;
      increasing time in bed to 10 hours per night in children aged 14-17 years. The main question&#xD;
      it aims to answer are:&#xD;
&#xD;
        -  How much additional sleep short-sleeping-adolescents (~7h TIB/night) will obtain when&#xD;
           asked to increase time-in-bed to 10h/night for seven consecutive nights compared to&#xD;
           those who are not asked to increase time-in-bed?&#xD;
&#xD;
        -  Are adolescents able to comply with study demands: wearing two devices (one on wrist and&#xD;
           one on hip) and completing daily sleep diaries and call-ins for seven days?&#xD;
&#xD;
        -  By acquiring participant feedback, how feasible and acceptable is it to increase time in&#xD;
           bed for sleep to 10h/night using a questionnaire and semi-structured interview?&#xD;
&#xD;
        -  Complete a phone screen&#xD;
&#xD;
        -  Come to Rutgers Sleep Lab for an orientation to obtain equipment, answer questionnaires&#xD;
           and study staff will obtain consent&#xD;
&#xD;
        -  Wear a wrist device and a hip device for one week to observe sleep and physical activity&#xD;
&#xD;
        -  If assigned to the 10 hour time-in-bed group, they will follow specific procedures to&#xD;
           ensure protocol adherence&#xD;
&#xD;
        -  Come to the Rutgers Sleep Lab for a follow up to give back equipment and answer&#xD;
           questionnaires&#xD;
&#xD;
      Researchers will compare the control group to the 10 hour time in bed group to see if it is&#xD;
      feasible for 14-17 year olds to be in bed for that long and wear two devices.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      We are conducting this research study to determine if it is feasible to have teenagers devote&#xD;
      more time to being in bed for sleep. Specifically, we will try to determine how much more&#xD;
      teens sleep when spending 10 hours in bed for a week. If after it is determined from a phone&#xD;
      screen that the child is eligible, they will be asked to come into our Center for an&#xD;
      Orientation.&#xD;
&#xD;
      During this visit, we will explain the research study to participants and families in more&#xD;
      detail. Families that enroll will visit the Center one more time at the end of the study.&#xD;
      During the orientation visit, we will determine the child's final eligibility based on how&#xD;
      much he/she sleeps and a measurement of the child's height and weight. If eligible and&#xD;
      interested in participating, the child would wear two devices -one that measures sleep and&#xD;
      one that measures activity - and keep a sleep diary for a week. During this week, the child&#xD;
      would also call/text our Center twice each day to report on his/her bedtime and wake time.&#xD;
      The second visit to the center occurs at the end of that week.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">January 2023</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2023</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">May 2023</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Participants will be assigned to either a control group or an increased time in bed (10 hours/night) group.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Other</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Feasibility and Acceptability of Increasing Time in Bed to 10 hours per Night in Adolescents</measure>
    <time_frame>The questionnaire will take approximately 5-10 minutes.</time_frame>
    <description>An acceptability and feasibility questionnaire will be administered to participants at a follow up visit to measure the difficulty of increasing time in bed to 10 hours per night and wearing the two devices given. This questionnaire serves as feedback for the principal investigator to measure the feasibility of adolescents increasing time in bed to 10 hours per night and wearing two devices. Roughly half the questions are open ended and gauge the participants' physical experience during the study. The other half are scored 0-4 and ask about the participants' increase or decrease in school performance, overall mental health status, and physical health status during the day. For the questions that rank 0-4, a 0 indicates that specific aspect became a lot worse since the study, and a 4 indicates it became a lot better, or it increased over the course of the study.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">30</enrollment>
  <condition>Sleep</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Normal Sleep Condition Group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>This group will not partake in the intervention, they will sleep the normal amount that they do on a regular basis. Participants will wear a hip physical activity monitor and a wrist actigraph to measure sleep.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>10-hour Time in Bed Group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>This group will partake in the intervention of increasing time in bed to 10 hours per night. Participants will wear a hip physical activity monitor and a wrist actigraph to measure sleep.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>10-hour Time in Bed</intervention_name>
    <description>Participants will be asked to increase their time in bed to 10-hours per night for 7 consecutive days.</description>
    <arm_group_label>10-hour Time in Bed Group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Parent-reported child age of 14-17 years&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Typical sleep duration of approximately 7hr/night on school nights&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  BMI for age and gender in the &gt;5th percentile but not greater than 100% overweight.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Parent must be the primary caretaker and at home during bed/wake times&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Reported willingness and ability to complete all study-related tasks, including&#xD;
             wearing the wrist actigraph and hip accelerometer daily.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Exclusion Criteria:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Diagnosable sleep disorder (including Sleep Disordered Breathing) based on parent&#xD;
             report and participant's score on Sleep Disorders Inventory for Students-Adolescents&#xD;
             (SDIS-A).&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Medication use or parent-reported diagnosis of a serious medical condition (including&#xD;
             psychiatric conditions) that may impact sleep.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Excessive intake of caffeine (&gt;300mg/day), drug (including nicotine) or alcohol use,&#xD;
             or a history of substance abuse.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Actively trying to lose weight.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Trans-meridian (east-west/west-east) travel during past month or planned travel during&#xD;
             study time frame.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Inability to understand or complete protocol to ensure that consent/assent and&#xD;
             reliable and valid measures are obtained.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Sibling of enrolled subjects, to minimize risk of bias in study findings.&#xD;
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>14 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>17 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Andrea Spaeth, Ph.D</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Associate Professor, Lab Director</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Taylor McCoy, B.S.</last_name>
    <phone>732-554-1532</phone>
    <email>tm953@kines.rutgers.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Rutgers Sleep Lab</name>
      <address>
        <city>New Brunswick</city>
        <state>New Jersey</state>
        <zip>08901</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Taylor McCoy, B.S.</last_name>
      <phone>732-554-1532</phone>
      <email>tm953@kines.rutgers.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Andrea Spaeth, Ph.D</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>https://www.sleepinventory.com/</url>
    <description>Sleep Disorders Inventory for Students</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Luginbuehl M B-KK, Ferron J, Anderson WM, Benbadis SR. Pediatric sleep disorders: Validation of the SleepDisorders Inventory for Students. . School Psychol Rev. 2008; 37(3):409-31.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Actigraph Data Collection, Proofing, and Scoring Procedures AW2 2018</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Santos-Lozano A, Santin-Medeiros F, Cardon G, Torres-Luque G, Bailon R, Bergmeir C, Ruiz JR, Lucia A, Garatachea N. Actigraph GT3X: validation and determination of physical activity intensity cut points. Int J Sports Med. 2013 Nov;34(11):975-82. doi: 10.1055/s-0033-1337945. Epub 2013 May 22.</citation>
    <PMID>23700330</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>January 2023</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>January 5, 2023</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 18, 2023</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">January 27, 2023</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 18, 2023</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 18, 2023</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">January 27, 2023</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Rutgers, The State University of New Jersey</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Andrea M. Spaeth, PhD</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Assistant Professor, Undergraduate Academic Director</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Yes</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>All individual participant data that will be collected will be shared with other researchers, after deidentification.</ipd_description>
    <ipd_info_type>Study Protocol</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_info_type>Informed Consent Form (ICF)</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_time_frame>Immediately following publication.</ipd_time_frame>
    <ipd_access_criteria>Anyone who wishes to access the data can do so.</ipd_access_criteria>
  </patient_data>
  <provided_document_section>
    <provided_document>
      <document_type>Study Protocol</document_type>
      <document_has_protocol>Yes</document_has_protocol>
      <document_has_icf>No</document_has_icf>
      <document_has_sap>No</document_has_sap>
      <document_date>November 4, 2022</document_date>
      <document_url>https://ClinicalTrials.gov/ProvidedDocs/61/NCT05703061/Prot_000.pdf</document_url>
    </provided_document>
  </provided_document_section>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

