<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="9595">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 09, 2023</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT05694767</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>IIT2022039-EC-2</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT05694767</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Prospective, One-arm and Open Clinical Study of CM313 in the Treatment of Immune Thrombocytopenia</brief_title>
  <acronym>2022-CM313-ITP</acronym>
  <official_title>A Prospective, One-arm and Open Clinical Study to Assess Safety and Efficacy of Anti-Human CD38 Monoclonal Antibody CM313 in the Treatment of Primary Immune Thrombocytopenia</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Institute of Hematology &amp; Blood Diseases Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Institute of Hematology &amp; Blood Diseases Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      To evaluate the safety and efficacy of CM313 in the treatment of immune thrombocytopenia in&#xD;
      patients who have not responded adequately or relapsed after first-line treatment and at&#xD;
      least one second-line therapy including rituximab and/or TPO-RA.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Immune thrombocytopenia (ITP) is an organ-specific autoimmune disease, which is characterized&#xD;
      by decreased platelet count and skin and mucosal bleeding. ITP is a kind of disease with&#xD;
      increased platelet destruction and impaired platelet production caused by autoimmunity.&#xD;
      Conventional treatment of adult ITP includes first-line glucocorticoid and immunoglobulin&#xD;
      therapy, second line TPO and TPO receptor agonist, splenectomy and other immunosuppressive&#xD;
      treatments (such as rituximab, vincristine, azathioprine, etc.). ITP is one of the most&#xD;
      common hemorrhagic diseases. At present, the treatment response of ITP is not good, and a&#xD;
      considerable number of patients need drug maintenance treatment, which seriously affects the&#xD;
      quality of life of patients and increases the economic burden of patients. Therefore, there&#xD;
      is still a lack of effective treatment for adult ITP, especially for recurrent and refractory&#xD;
      ITP patients, which is one of the problems that have attracted more attention and need to be&#xD;
      solved urgently.&#xD;
&#xD;
      The main pathogenesis of ITP is the loss of platelet autoantigen immune tolerance, which&#xD;
      leads to abnormal activation of humoral and cellular immunity. It is characterized by&#xD;
      antibody mediated platelet destruction and insufficient platelet production by&#xD;
      megakaryocytes. The residual long-term autoreactive plasma cells may be a source of&#xD;
      therapeutic resistance to autoimmune cytopenia. Antiplatelet specific plasma cells have been&#xD;
      detected in the spleen of patients with rituximab refractory ITP. Therefore, the strategy of&#xD;
      simply eliminating B cells may not work, because LLPC will continue to produce pathogenic&#xD;
      antibodies. However, targeting LLPC becomes a new strategy to treat autoimmune diseases.&#xD;
&#xD;
      CM313, a kind of anti-CD38 antibody, is a new type of monoclonal antibody targeting CD38. It&#xD;
      targets plasma cells and has carried out some clinical studies in multiple myeloma, with good&#xD;
      therapeutic effects. In addition, the clinical trials of similar CD38 monoclonal antibody&#xD;
      drugs, such as daratumumab, in the treatment of autoimmune diseases, including membranous&#xD;
      nephropathy, systemic lupus erythematosus (SLE) and ITP, are also being carried out&#xD;
      simultaneously. We assume that autologous reaction LLPC may be the cause of treatment failure&#xD;
      in some ITP patients. Therefore, the use of CD38 monoclonal antibody to clear long-term&#xD;
      surviving plasma cells in ITP patients may be a new strategy for treating ITP patients.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Therefore, the investigators designed this clinical trial to evaluate the safety and efficacy&#xD;
      of CM313 in the treatment of immune thrombocytopenia in patients who are steroid-refractory&#xD;
      or steroid-dependent, and fail to respond to at least one previous second-line therapy,&#xD;
      including rituximab and/ or TPO agonist.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">January 22, 2023</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 30, 2024</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 30, 2024</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>N/A</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>To evaluate of response after CM313 treatment at week 8</measure>
    <time_frame>8 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Proportion of subjects with a platelet count ≥ 50 × 10^9/L at week 8 in absence of rescue therapy, and without having had dose increment of TPO-RA or corticosteroids during the study period</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Safety of CM 313</measure>
    <time_frame>24 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Incidence, severity, and relationship of treatment emergent adverse events after CM 313 treatment</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Response rate of treatment</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Response rate including: 1. Proportion of subjects with a platelet count ≥ 50 × 10^9/L at week 2, week 4, week 6 and week 10 in absence of rescue therapy, and without having had dose increment of TPO-RA or corticosteroids during the study period; 2. Proportion of subjects achieving platelet counts ≥ 50×10^9/L at least once in absence of rescue therapy, and without having had dose increment of TPO-RA or corticosteroids during the first 12 weeks; 3. Proportion of subjects whose platelet counts ≥ 30×10^9/L and at least two times of baseline platelet count at least once in absence of rescue therapy, and without having had dose increment of TPO-RA or corticosteroids during the first 12 weeks.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Duration from treatment initiation to platelet count ≥50×10^9/L</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Duration from treatment initiation to platelet count ≥50×10^9/L without having received any platelet elevating therapy or having had dose increment of TPO-RA and/or corticosteroids</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Cumulative weeks of platelet ≥50×109/L and platelet ≥50×109/L</measure>
    <time_frame>24 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Cumulative weeks of platelet ≥50×109/L and platelet ≥50×109/L without having received any platelet elevating therapy or having had dose increment of TPO-RA and/or corticosteroids</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of subjects with clinically significant bleeding as assessed using the world health organization (WHO) bleeding scale</measure>
    <time_frame>24 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Changes of the subjects' numbers in WHO bleeding score after CM313 treatment according to the reported World Health Organization's Bleeding Scale. The WHO Bleeding Scale is a measure of bleeding severity with the following grades: grade 0 = no bleeding, grade 1= petechiae, grade 2= mild blood loss, grade 3 = gross blood loss, and grade 4 = debilitating blood loss.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Measurements of platelet glycoprotein (GP) autoantibodies</measure>
    <time_frame>24 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>level of anti-GPIIb/IIIa and Ib/IX antibodies before and after CM313 therapy</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Measurements of immunoglobulin quantification</measure>
    <time_frame>24 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>The level of IgG, IgA, IgM and IgE quantification before and after CM313 therapy</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Measurements of various subsets of immunocompetent cells</measure>
    <time_frame>24 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>To assess the changes of the percentage of B cell subsets，regulatory B cells（Breg），regulatory T cells (Treg)，supressor T cells（Ts），monocyte subcets, helper T cells（Th）subsets and the functionally-polarized CD4+ T cell subsets, etc. in peripheral blood mononuclear cells（PBMCs）before and after CM313 therapy, and to compare with the healthy controls.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">20</enrollment>
  <condition>Immune Thrombocytopenia</condition>
  <condition>Treatment</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Intervention (CM313)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>20 enrolled subjects: once a week x 8 doses</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>CM313 Injection</intervention_name>
    <description>intravenous CM313 administration&#xD;
This study adopts a prospective, single arm, open design method. Twenty subjects were enrolled in the study and were treated with CD38 monoclonal antibody (CM 313: 16mg/kg/w) for 8 weeks.&#xD;
The first stage is the main research stage (d1-w8), which is the core treatment period. The subjects will receive intravenous infusion of 16mg/kg CM313 once a week for 8 weeks to observe the safety and efficacy during treatment.&#xD;
The second stage (w9-w24) is the stage of withdrawal from the visit, mainly to observe the safety and continuous efficacy of CM313 after treatment.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Intervention (CM313)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Age 18 and above, male or female&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Conform to the diagnostic criteria of immune Thrombocytopenia (ITP)&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Diagnosis of ITP ≥3 months, and with a platelet count of &lt;30 X 109/L measured within 2&#xD;
             days prior to inclusion&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Failure to achieve response or relapse after corticosteroid therapy, and at least one&#xD;
             second-line therapy including rituximab or TPORAs.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  The previous emergency treatment of ITP (e.g. methylprednisolone, platelet&#xD;
             transfusion, IVIG transfusion) must be completed at least 2 weeks before the first&#xD;
             administration&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Signed and dated written informed consent&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  With normal hepatic and renal functions&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  ECOG physical state score ≤ 2 points&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Cardiac function of the New York Society of Cardiac Function ≤ 2&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Patients receiving maintenance treatment (including corticosteroids (less than or&#xD;
             equal to 0.5mg/kg prednisone), TPO receptor agonists, etc.) must have a stable dose at&#xD;
             least 4 weeks before the first administration, and azathioprine, danazol, cyclosporin&#xD;
             A, tacrolimus, sirolimus, etc. must be stopped at least 4 weeks before the first&#xD;
             administration; The end of rituximab treatment was&gt;3 months.&#xD;
&#xD;
        April 10, 2023 After approval by the Ethics Committee on , subjects no longer require&#xD;
        platelet glycoprotein autoantibodies positivity upon enrollment.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Exclusion Criteria:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Received any treatment of anti-CD38 antibody drug&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Uncontrollable primary diseases of important organs, such as malignant tumors, liver&#xD;
             failure, heart failure, renal failure and other diseases;&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  HIV positive;&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Accompanied by uncontrollable active infection, including hepatitis B, hepatitis C,&#xD;
             cytomegalovirus, EB virus and syphilis positive;&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Accompanied by extensive and severe bleeding, such as hemoptysis, upper&#xD;
             gastrointestinal hemorrhage, intracranial hemorrhage, etc.;&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  At present, there are heart diseases, arrhythmias that need treatment or hypertension&#xD;
             that researchers judge is poorly controlled;&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Patients with thrombotic diseases such as pulmonary embolism, thrombosis and&#xD;
             atherosclerosis;&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Those who have received allogeneic stem cell transplantation or organ transplantation&#xD;
             in the past;&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Patients with mental disorders who cannot normally obtain informed consent and conduct&#xD;
             trials and follow-up;&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Patients whose toxic symptoms caused by pre-trial treatment have not disappeared;&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Other serious diseases that may limit the subject's participation in this test (such&#xD;
             as diabetes; Severe cardiac insufficiency; Myocardial obstruction or unstable&#xD;
             arrhythmia or unstable angina pectoris in recent 6 months; Gastric ulcer, etc.);&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Patients with septicemia or other irregular severe bleeding;&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Patients taking antiplatelet drugs at the same time;&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Pregnant women, suspected pregnancies (positive pregnancy test for human chorionic&#xD;
             gonadotropin in urine at screening) and lactating patients.&#xD;
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Lei Zhang, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Chinese Academy of Medical Science and Blood Disease Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Yunfei Chen, MD</last_name>
    <phone>+8618502220788</phone>
    <email>chenyunfei@ihcams.ac.cn</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Chinese Academy of Medical Science and Blood Disease Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Tianjin</city>
        <state>Tianjin</state>
        <zip>300020</zip>
        <country>China</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Yunfei Chen, MD</last_name>
      <phone>+86-22-23909009</phone>
      <email>chenyunfei@ihcams.ac.cn</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>China</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>April 2023</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>December 15, 2022</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 12, 2023</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">January 23, 2023</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 12, 2023</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 12, 2023</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">April 13, 2023</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Institute of Hematology &amp; Blood Diseases Hospital</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Zhang Lei, MD</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>vice Director of Thrombosis and Hemostasis Center</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Thrombocytopenia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Purpura, Thrombocytopenic, Idiopathic</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Yes</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>Researchers qualified can request the dataset, including de-identified individual subject data. Data may be requested from PI from 12 months 36 months after study completion.</ipd_description>
    <ipd_info_type>Study Protocol</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_info_type>Statistical Analysis Plan (SAP)</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_info_type>Informed Consent Form (ICF)</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_time_frame>12 months to 36 months after study completion</ipd_time_frame>
    <ipd_access_criteria>Upon request to PI</ipd_access_criteria>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

