<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="9463">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 09, 2023</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT05697250</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>550740</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT05697250</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>High Versus Low Power Settings During Ureteroscopic Laser Lithotripsy</brief_title>
  <official_title>High Versus Low Power Settings During Ureteroscopic Laser Lithotripsy - a Prospective, Randomised Clinical Trial</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Haukeland University Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Haukeland University Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The primary aim of the study is to compare the operative times following ureteroscopic&#xD;
      lithotripsy for renal stones with Thulium Fiber Laser using low and high power settings.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Secondary aims are to compare the results of low and high power settings in terms of stone&#xD;
      free rates, laser time, laser activation patterns, intraoperative and postoperative&#xD;
      complications.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Patients ≥ 18 years with renal stones (8-25 mm) scheduled for ureteroscopic lithotripsy at&#xD;
      the Day Surgery Clinic at Haukeland University Hospital in Bergen, Norway, are eligible for&#xD;
      inclusion in the study. After written consent and inclusion, patients are randomised to laser&#xD;
      lithotripsy using either low power settings (Group 1: 4-6 Watt, short pulse mode) or high&#xD;
      power settings (Group 2: 16-18 Watt, short pulse mode). The ureteroscopic procedures are&#xD;
      performed in general anaesthesia using a standardised technique. All patients are followed up&#xD;
      with a low dose CT scan 3 months post endoscopically to assess stone free status as well as a&#xD;
      consultation at the outpatient clinic.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Results and data for the two randomisation groups are compared according to the aims of the&#xD;
      study.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      BACKGROUND: The Holmium:Yttrium-Aluminium-Garnet (Ho:YAG) has been considered the&#xD;
      gold-standard laser for ureteroscopy (URS) because of its versatility, with the ability to&#xD;
      break all kinds of stones in the urinary tract as well as tumor- and soft tissue ablation.&#xD;
      Recently, a new Thulium fiber laser (TFL) has been introduced, with more favourable basic&#xD;
      physical characteristics. Previous pre-clinical studies have predicted TFL lithotripsy to be&#xD;
      up to four times faster than Ho:YAG lithotripsy using the same power settings. Earlier this&#xD;
      year the present investigators published the first clinical randomised trial comparing the&#xD;
      outcomes after ureteroscopic lithotripsy using TFL and Ho:YAG. The study demonstrated that&#xD;
      the TFL gained superior stone free rate (SFR) compared to Ho:YAG, in addition to lower&#xD;
      complication rate and shorter operative times. Due to the study, the investigators believe&#xD;
      the TFL is emerging as the laser of choice. In the study very low laser settings were shown&#xD;
      to be highly efficient using TFL during URS lithotripsy. However, no consensus exists on the&#xD;
      preferred laser settings for the TFL during this procedure, and a variety of different&#xD;
      settings have been suggested included high power settings as high as 45 Watts (W).&#xD;
&#xD;
      To date, there are no clinical randomised trials comparing different laser settings for TFL&#xD;
      to determine what is optimal regarding the clinical outcomes.&#xD;
&#xD;
      AIMS OF THE STUDY: The primary aim of the study is to compare the operative times following&#xD;
      URS lithotripsy for renal stones with TFL using low and high power settings. Secondary aims&#xD;
      are to compare the results of low and high power settings in terms of SFR, laser time, laser&#xD;
      activation patterns, intraoperative and postoperative complications.&#xD;
&#xD;
      STUDY DESIGN: The study is planned as a prospective randomized trial. All patients ≥ 18 years&#xD;
      scheduled to URS lithotripsy for renal stones, 8-25 mm, at the day surgery unit at Haukeland&#xD;
      University Hospital (HUH) are invited to be enrolled in the study. After written informed&#xD;
      consent, patients are randomized to URS TFL lithotripsy with either low or high power laser&#xD;
      settings.&#xD;
&#xD;
      LASER SETTINGS: The laser settings in the two study groups are standardized and need to be&#xD;
      maintained throughout the procedure.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Group 1 - low power (4-6W), short pulse: 0.4 - 0.6 Joules (J) at 10 Herz (Hz) Group 2 - high&#xD;
      power (16-18W), short pulse: 0.4 J / 40 Hz 0.6 J / 30 Hz 0.8 J / 20 Hz&#xD;
&#xD;
      Standard start-up settings in Group 1 (low power) is 0.4J / 10Hz (4W) and in Group 2 (high&#xD;
      power) 0.4J / 40Hz (16W).&#xD;
&#xD;
      THE URS PROCEDURE: The URS procedure is performed in general anaesthesia and prophylactic&#xD;
      antibiotics prior to surgery start will be administered according to the department's&#xD;
      guidelines, either according to urine culture or current local regime.&#xD;
&#xD;
      The procedure starts with a cystoscopy followed by semirigid URS when considered appropriate.&#xD;
      A safety guide wire and an access sheath can be used at the surgeon's discretion but is&#xD;
      routinely omitted during URS at HUH. Balloon dilatation is performed on demand. Both&#xD;
      semirigid and flexible ureteroscopes can be used for the endoscopy. Room-tempered,&#xD;
      gravitational irrigation fluid at 60 cm height is used throughout the procedure. When&#xD;
      reaching the stone, the envelope revealing the result of randomization for either high or low&#xD;
      laser settings is opened. A 150μm laser fiber can be used for stone disintegration. The stone&#xD;
      is disintegrated using TFL with predefined settings as described below and according to the&#xD;
      randomization group. To make the procedures as similar as possible, the stone should be&#xD;
      dusted/disintegrated to as small particles as possible rather than fragmented and retrieved.&#xD;
      Only residual particles not suitable for further disintegration can be retrieved at the end&#xD;
      of the procedure to render the patient stone free.&#xD;
&#xD;
      A double J-stent can be placed after the procedure if deemed necessary, and if so, this is&#xD;
      removed according to standard routine after 1-2 weeks in the outpatient clinic.&#xD;
&#xD;
      FOLLOW-UP: Follow-up with computed tomography (CT) is performed at 3 months post&#xD;
      endoscopically for all patients to assess stone free status and exclude a ureteral stricture&#xD;
      in addition to a clinical consultation.&#xD;
&#xD;
      ETHICAL CONSIDERATIONS AND APPROVALS: All patients eligible for inclusion in the study will&#xD;
      receive oral and written information. Participation in the study is voluntarily, and the&#xD;
      patient can choose to withdraw at any point during the study process. Inclusion in the study&#xD;
      will only be done after the consent form is signed.&#xD;
&#xD;
      The study is approved by The National Committees for Research Ethics in Norway (REK: 550740).&#xD;
      In addition, application for approval by The Data Protection Authorities at Haukeland&#xD;
      University Hospital has been sent.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">January 23, 2023</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 31, 2024</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 30, 2024</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>The patients are randomised to ureteroscopic stone treatment with Thulium Fiber Laser with either low or high laser settings. The ureteroscopic procedures are performed in a standardised manner irrespective of the laser settings, and follow-up is similar in both groups.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
    <masking_description>Stone free status is assessed on low dose CT 3 months post endoscopically by an outcome assessor blinded to the randomisation.</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Operative time</measure>
    <time_frame>During surgery (approximately 1 hour), registered immediately after surgery</time_frame>
    <description>Surgical time in minutes, counted from start of the procedure with insertion of the cystoscope until emptying the bladder in the end.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Stone free rate</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months post endoscopically</time_frame>
    <description>Assessment of stone free status (or the presence of residual fragments) on low dose CT 3 months post endoscopically.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Laser activation patterns - duration</measure>
    <time_frame>During surgery (approximately 1 hour), registered immediately after surgery</time_frame>
    <description>Duration of laser activation periods during laser lithotripsy in seconds</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Laser activation patterns - number</measure>
    <time_frame>During surgery (approximately 1 hour), registered immediately after surgery</time_frame>
    <description>Number of laser activation periods during laser lithotripsy</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Intraoperative complications</measure>
    <time_frame>During surgery (approximately 1 hour), registered immediately after surgery</time_frame>
    <description>Complications occurred during the endoscopic procedure (bleeding, perforation, avulsion, mucosal abrasion, blurred vision)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Post operative complications</measure>
    <time_frame>After surgery until 3 months post endoscopically.</time_frame>
    <description>Complications occurred after the endoscopic procedure (up to 3 months post endoscopically).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">150</enrollment>
  <condition>Renal Stone</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Group 1 - low power laser settings</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>4-6 Watts, short pulse mode. 0.4 - 0.6 J at 10 Hz.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Group 2 - high power laser settings</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>16-18 Watts, short pulse mode. 0.4 J / 40 Hz, 0.6 J / 30 Hz or 0.8 J / 20 Hz.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Laser power settings (Thulium Fiber Laser)</intervention_name>
    <description>Ureteroscopic lithotripsy using low power laser settings (0.4 - 0.6 J at 10 Hz corresponding to 2.4 - 6.0 Watts) or high power laser settings (0.4 J at 40 Hz, 0.6 J at 30 Hz or 0.8 J at 20 Hz corresponding to 16 - 18 Watts).</description>
    <arm_group_label>Group 1 - low power laser settings</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Group 2 - high power laser settings</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Patients ≥ 18 years scheduled for URS lithotripsy for renal stones, 8-25 mm, at the&#xD;
             day surgery unit at Haukeland University Hospital&#xD;
&#xD;
        Exclusion Criteria:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Concomitant ureteral stone&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Urinary diversion&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Active infection&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Untreated cancer in the upper urinary tract&#xD;
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Øyvind Ulvik, Assoc Prof</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Haukeland University Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Øyvind Ulvik, Assoc Prof</last_name>
    <phone>+47 90918595</phone>
    <email>doc.ulvik@online.no</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Mathias S Æsøy, MD</last_name>
    <email>mathias.asoy@gmail.com</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Haukeland University Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bergen</city>
        <state>Vestland</state>
        <zip>5021</zip>
        <country>Norway</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Øyvind Ulvik, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>90918595</phone>
      <phone_ext>+47</phone_ext>
      <email>doc.ulvik@online.no</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Norway</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>January 2023</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>December 29, 2022</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 16, 2023</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">January 25, 2023</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 20, 2023</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 20, 2023</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">February 21, 2023</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Kidney Calculi</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Nephrolithiasis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

