<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="9834">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 09, 2023</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT05689242</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>sedation in Colonoscopy</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT05689242</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Intravenous Nalbuphine Versus Intravenous Dexmedetomidine for Conscious Sedation in Patients Undergoing Colonoscopy</brief_title>
  <official_title>Comparative Study Between Intravenous Nalbuphine Versus Intravenous Dexmedetomidine for Conscious Sedation in Patients Undergoing Colonoscopy</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Assiut University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Assiut University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The aim of this study is to compare the sedative, analgesic effect and hemodynamic changes&#xD;
      due to dexmedetomidine and nalbuphine during elective colonoscopy.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Colonoscopy can be performed for the screening of cancer, adenomas, and polyps, for the&#xD;
      assessment of known or possible bleeding, and for the evaluation of possible causes of&#xD;
      abdominal pain, gastrointestinal symptoms, and/or changes in bowel habits. colonoscopy is&#xD;
      associated with discomfort and sometimes pain. At present, the commonly used methods are the&#xD;
      intravenous injection of propofol, etomidate, ketamine, and other drugs to make the patient's&#xD;
      unconscious. The disadvantage is that the patient cannot cooperate during the examination&#xD;
      (e.g., for changing position), and medical staff is needed to assist in turning over the&#xD;
      patient, if necessary. This may compress the patient's stomach and abdomen, which may cause&#xD;
      gastric reflux and aspiration, which may cause pneumonia, with morbidity and even mortality.&#xD;
      Nalbuphine hydrochloride is a mixed agonist-antagonist opioid with a duration of action of&#xD;
      approximately 3-6 hours. It is chemically related to both the agonist analgesic oxymorphone&#xD;
      and the antagonist naloxone, and acts as an antagonist at the μ receptor and as an agonist at&#xD;
      the κ receptor, resulting in analgesia and sedation with minimal effects in the&#xD;
      cardiovascular system. Any slight RD that occurs would be restricted by a ceiling effect.&#xD;
      Dexmedetomidine, a new drug, is highly selective α2-adrenergic receptor agonist. It possesses&#xD;
      hypnotic, sedative, anxiolytic, sympatholytic, and analgesic properties without producing&#xD;
      significant respiratory depression. It also reduces both anesthetic and opioid analgesic&#xD;
      requirements during the perioperative period. It has an impressive safety margin,and it may&#xD;
      be suitable for conscious sedation during painful procedures.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">March 2023</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2024</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2024</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 4</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Factorial Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Other</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Triple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>variable is to compare the sedation effect between Nalbuphine and Dexmedetomidine.</measure>
    <time_frame>before the study drug administration (baseline), after the study drug administration ,Then every 5min till the examination ends,at PACU admission, and 30 min after procedure.</time_frame>
    <description>3- Sedation score: sedation will be monitored immediately after examination, at PACU admission, and 30 min after procedure by Ramsay Sedation Scale (RSS; 1974) The RSS scores sedation at six different levels, according to how rousable the patient is.&#xD;
Patient is anxious and agitated or restless, or both.&#xD;
Patient is cooperative, oriented and tranquil.&#xD;
Patient responds to commands only.&#xD;
Patient exhibits brisk response to light glabellar tap or loud auditory stimulus.&#xD;
Patient exhibits a sluggish response to light glabellar tap or loud auditory stimulus.&#xD;
Patient exhibits no response</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>variables are the hemodynamic comparison, pain score assessment and adverse event among two groups.</measure>
    <time_frame>before the study drug administration (baseline), after the study drug administration ,Then every 5min till the examination ends,at PACU admission, and 30 min after procedure.</time_frame>
    <description>4- Pain score: Intensity of pain will be monitored immediately after examination, at PACU admission, and 30 min after procedure by visual analogue score (VAS),The (VAS) consist of 10cm line, with to end points representing 0 (no pain) and 10 (pain as bad as it possibly be), ask the patient to rete their current level of pain by placing a mark on the line, by using a ruler to measure the distance from 0 (no pain point) to the current pain mark</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">66</enrollment>
  <condition>Colonoscopy</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Group I</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Receive initial loading dose of (Dexmedetomidine 1 μg/kg I.V) diluted up to 10 ml with normal saline infused over 10 min, followed by a continuous infusion of 0.2-0.8 μg/kg/h through a 50 ml syringe and an electronic infusion pump</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Group II</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Receive (Nalbuphine 0.1 to 0.2 mg/kg I.V) diluted up to 10 ml with normal saline infused slowly over 10 min.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Dexmedetomidine Injection [Precedex]</intervention_name>
    <description>intravenous dexmedetomidine for group I and nalubphine for group II in colposcopy</description>
    <arm_group_label>Group I</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Group II</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>nalbuphine</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:&#xD;
&#xD;
          1. The subject is scheduled for elective colonoscopy.&#xD;
&#xD;
          2. The subject is ≥ 18 years and ≤ 80 years.&#xD;
&#xD;
          3. Both sexes.&#xD;
&#xD;
          4. No obvious abnormalities in preoperative ECG, blood routine ,electrolytes, and other&#xD;
             tests .&#xD;
&#xD;
          5. ASA class 1-3.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Exclusion Criteria:&#xD;
&#xD;
          1. Subject is known or believed to be pregnant or lactating women.&#xD;
&#xD;
          2. Patients allergic to α2-adrenergic agonist or sulfa drugs&#xD;
&#xD;
          3. Chronic Opioid Use (daily or almost daily use of opioids for &gt; 3 months).&#xD;
&#xD;
          4. Patients that are immunologically compromised, or receiving chronic steroids (&gt;30&#xD;
             days), excluding inhalers.&#xD;
&#xD;
          5. Sleep apnea syndrome or difficult airway.&#xD;
&#xD;
          6. Patient known to be asthmatic or recent chest infection.&#xD;
&#xD;
          7. Patients that are prisoners.&#xD;
&#xD;
          8. Patient refusal.&#xD;
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>80 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>omar AB abulfadl, bachelor's</last_name>
    <phone>0021069909234</phone>
    <email>omarabulfadl1@gmail.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>hamdy youssef, prof</last_name>
    <phone>0021090008490</phone>
    <email>hamdyayoussef@yahoo.com</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ulmer BJ, Hansen JJ, Overley CA, Symms MR, Chadalawada V, Liangpunsakul S, Strahl E, Mendel AM, Rex DK. Propofol versus midazolam/fentanyl for outpatient colonoscopy: administration by nurses supervised by endoscopists. Clin Gastroenterol Hepatol. 2003 Nov;1(6):425-32. doi: 10.1016/s1542-3565(03)00226-x.</citation>
    <PMID>15017641</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Muller S, Borowics SM, Fortis EA, Stefani LC, Soares G, Maguilnik I, Breyer HP, Hidalgo MP, Caumo W. Clinical efficacy of dexmedetomidine alone is less than propofol for conscious sedation during ERCP. Gastrointest Endosc. 2008 Apr;67(4):651-9. doi: 10.1016/j.gie.2007.09.041. Epub 2008 Mar 4.</citation>
    <PMID>18291396</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kaygusuz K, Gokce G, Gursoy S, Ayan S, Mimaroglu C, Gultekin Y. A comparison of sedation with dexmedetomidine or propofol during shockwave lithotripsy: a randomized controlled trial. Anesth Analg. 2008 Jan;106(1):114-9, table of contents. doi: 10.1213/01.ane.0000296453.75494.64.</citation>
    <PMID>18165564</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Karanth H, Murali S, Koteshwar R, Shetty V, Adappa K. Comparative Study between Propofol and Dexmedetomidine for Conscious Sedation in Patients Undergoing Outpatient Colonoscopy. Anesth Essays Res. 2018 Jan-Mar;12(1):98-102. doi: 10.4103/aer.AER_206_17.</citation>
    <PMID>29628562</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Candiotti KA, Bergese SD, Bokesch PM, Feldman MA, Wisemandle W, Bekker AY; MAC Study Group. Monitored anesthesia care with dexmedetomidine: a prospective, randomized, double-blind, multicenter trial. Anesth Analg. 2010 Jan 1;110(1):47-56. doi: 10.1213/ane.0b013e3181ae0856. Epub 2009 Aug 27.</citation>
    <PMID>19713256</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Scott J, Huskisson EC. Graphic representation of pain. Pain. 1976 Jun;2(2):175-84. No abstract available.</citation>
    <PMID>1026900</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>January 2023</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>January 8, 2023</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 17, 2023</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">January 19, 2023</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 17, 2023</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 17, 2023</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">January 19, 2023</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Assiut University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>OMAR ABDELAZIZ ABOELFADL</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>omar abdelaziz abulfadl abdelaziz</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Dexmedetomidine</keyword>
  <keyword>nalbuphine</keyword>
  <keyword>colonoscopy</keyword>
  <keyword>Conscious Sedation</keyword>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Dexmedetomidine</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Nalbuphine</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

