<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="9218">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 09, 2023</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT05702762</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>22-010</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT05702762</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Single Dose Aminoglycosides for Acute Uncomplicated Cystitis in the Emergency Department Setting</brief_title>
  <official_title>Single Dose Aminoglycosides for Acute Uncomplicated Cystitis in the Emergency Department Setting</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Mercy Health Ohio</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Northeast Ohio Medical University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Mercy Health Ohio</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this research study is to determine if gentamicin is as effective treatment of&#xD;
      acute uncomplicated cystitis (urinary tract infection) using aminoglycosides versus the&#xD;
      current standards of care. The current standards of care in our region are often to prescribe&#xD;
      a multi-day antibiotic prescription that is taken multiple times per day whereas gentamicin&#xD;
      will be a one-time dose in the emergency department. Gentamicin is the medicine being&#xD;
      studied.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Urinary tract infections (UTIs) account for more than 8 million office visits and 1 million&#xD;
      emergency department visits each year in the United States, making them one of the most often&#xD;
      encountered indications for antibiotic use in ambulatory care. Escherichia Coli has been&#xD;
      shown to be the main cause of uncomplicated cystitis, occurring in 75-95% of cases, with&#xD;
      other Enterobacteriaceae like Proteus mirabilis, Klebsiella pneumoniae and Staphylococcus&#xD;
      saprophyticus comprising the majority of the other potential causes of cystitis. E. coli is&#xD;
      also the most frequently encountered nitrite positive Enterobacteriaceae locally as well,&#xD;
      representing nearly 3 out of every 4 culture specimens in the Boardman-specific gram-negative&#xD;
      urine antibiogram (74%), 209 out of 284 to be exact. Some of the typical antibiotics used to&#xD;
      treat these organisms had seen rising resistance rates from 2003-2012, with substantial&#xD;
      increases in the resistance to both ciprofloxacin (3.6% to 11.8%) and&#xD;
      trimethoprim-sulfamethoxazole (17.2% to 22.2%) in the United States. Gentamicin offers 93%&#xD;
      sensitivity towards E. coli in the local antibiogram, whereas sulfamethoxazole-trimethoprim&#xD;
      and fluoroquinolones offer 75% and 69%, respectively. More importantly, the current standard&#xD;
      of care, cefdinir, only offers around 80% sensitivities locally. While nitrofurantoin has&#xD;
      retained high levels of antibiotic activity against E. coli, it is contraindicated in the&#xD;
      elderly and patients with poor renal function. This growing rate of resistance has placed a&#xD;
      larger emphasis on finding alternative treatment options.&#xD;
&#xD;
      As stated above, Goodlet et al. reviewed 13 studies totaling 13,804 patients, and data from&#xD;
      11 out of the 13 revealed a microbiological cure rate of 94.5% +/- 4.3% using single dose&#xD;
      aminoglycosides to treat urinary tract infections. Seven of these studies had comparator&#xD;
      groups that included medications such as oral cephalosporins, Fosfomycin,&#xD;
      trimethoprim-sulfamethoxazole and amoxicillin. No difference in initial or sustained&#xD;
      microbiological cure rate in those that received aminoglycosides versus other medications was&#xD;
      demonstrated. Only two of the thirteen studies evaluated clinical cure rates which were shown&#xD;
      to be 82.8% and 94.7%, respectively. In the studies with 30 day follow up, an overall&#xD;
      recurrence rate at 30 days was found to be 19% (84/443 patients). The recurrence rate seen&#xD;
      using aminoglycosides is improved when compared to the general population, as 27% of women&#xD;
      have been found to experience recurrence of their symptoms within 6 months of having urinary&#xD;
      tract infections. Aminoglycosides were at one time a standard first-line therapeutic option&#xD;
      to treat UTIs but fell out of favor due to their side effect profile.&#xD;
&#xD;
      The most concerning adverse effects of aminoglycosides were mainly seen in association with&#xD;
      multi-day regimens of the drugs. Their nephrotoxic and ototoxic effect are seen in less than&#xD;
      1% of patients evaluated, but saw their use decrease roughly 41% between 2002-2009. In the&#xD;
      Goodlet et al. study only 63 of the 13,804 patients (0.5%) reported adverse effects&#xD;
      associated with the single dose aminoglycoside treatment. Only 7 total cases (0.05%) reported&#xD;
      nephrotoxicity and 53 total cases (0.38%) reported signs of vestibular toxicity such as&#xD;
      tinnitus and equilibrium disorders. Additionally, in a study of over 10,000 patients&#xD;
      receiving single dose amikacin for UTI, nephrotoxicity was only reported in 0.04% of cases.&#xD;
      Another review looking at 24,107 patients that had received a single dose of gentamicin&#xD;
      reported no cases of ototoxicity as well. Comparably, sulfamethoxazole-trimethoprim carries&#xD;
      common and rare risks of hyperkalemia, blood dyscrasias, hypersensitivity reactions, and&#xD;
      other adverse events affecting nearly every organ system of the body. Fluoroquinolones carry&#xD;
      common and rare risks of QT segment prolongation, peripheral neuropathy, dysglycemia, adverse&#xD;
      events affecting the whole body and even a long-term syndrome effecting tens of thousands of&#xD;
      people called fluoroquinolone-associated disability (FQAD). Beta-lactams such as cefdinir&#xD;
      commonly cause gastrointestinal symptoms but more rarely effect other organ systems such as&#xD;
      the skin, metabolic and hematologic abnormalities, and other adverse events as well. While&#xD;
      adverse effects may occur with aminoglycosides, the studied risk of single dose use is not&#xD;
      extreme and comparable with adverse effects seen with current standards of care.&#xD;
&#xD;
      While there is a proven cure rate utilizing single dose aminoglycosides to treat acute&#xD;
      uncomplicated cystitis, they will also provide several other benefits when used in the&#xD;
      emergency department setting. The single dosing of antibiotic in the emergency department&#xD;
      removes the need for patient adherence to outpatient antibiotic therapy, thus reducing&#xD;
      possible bounce back visits. Gentamicin can also be administered intramuscularly, as it was&#xD;
      in all the above studies, both removing the need for IV access and expediting possible&#xD;
      disposition in the emergency department. Lastly, greater than 75% of outpatient UTI&#xD;
      prescriptions are written for durations that are not recommended, which is an issue that can&#xD;
      be removed from the equation entirely utilizing single dose treatment. Treating patients with&#xD;
      single dose aminoglycosides for acute uncomplicated cystitis in the emergency department may&#xD;
      provide better compliance with the same efficacy, resulting in a new standard of care for&#xD;
      treatment in the emergency department.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">October 1, 2022</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 30, 2024</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 30, 2023</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Multicenter prospective open label randomized controlled study</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Clinical Resolution</measure>
    <time_frame>7 days from presentation</time_frame>
    <description>If patient is or is not still having any pain with urination, urinary frequency or urinary urgency</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Clinical Resolution</measure>
    <time_frame>30 days from presentation</time_frame>
    <description>If patient is or is not still having any pain with urination, urinary frequency or urinary urgency</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">160</enrollment>
  <condition>Urinary Tract Infections</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Gentamicin</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Subjects will be given one (1) injection intramuscular gentamicin 5 mg/kg (actual body weight unless patient is &gt;120% ideal body weight in which case adjusted body weight will be utilized).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Standard of Care</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Oral antibiotic prescription</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Gentamicin</intervention_name>
    <description>5 mg/kg intramuscular injection</description>
    <arm_group_label>Gentamicin</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Standard of Care</intervention_name>
    <description>Usual oral antibiotic multi-day dosing based on local antibiogram</description>
    <arm_group_label>Standard of Care</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Oral dose regimen for simple urinary tract infection: Including cephalexin, cefdinir, sulfamethoxazole/trimethoprim, and nitrofurantoin at appropriate dose, frequency, and duration</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  At least 18 years of age, woman, pre-menopausal, non-pregnant with clinical signs of&#xD;
             urinary tract infection and nitrite positive urine.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Exclusion Criteria:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Contraindications include hypersensitivity to gentamicin or other aminoglycosides.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Patients younger than 18 years of age.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Pregnant or post-menopausal patients.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Patients without symptoms of UTI, nitrite negative urine, or any patient with working&#xD;
             diagnosis of complicated UTI such as pyelonephritis or any patient catheterized.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  ANY history of pre-existing renal impairment.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Patient that has any listed or reports taking ANY nephrotoxic or wit drug-drug&#xD;
             interaction medication in the past 7 days (see Appendix 5).&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  ANY history of hearing loss, tinnitus, or vertigo.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  ANY patient that has received general anesthesia or neuromuscular blockade in past 7&#xD;
             days.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Patients with ANY history of neuromuscular disorders including: myasthenia gravis,&#xD;
             amyotrophic lateral sclerosis, muscular dystrophy, botulism, congenital myasthenic&#xD;
             syndromes, congenital myopathies, myositis, Lambert-Eaton syndrome, mitochondrial&#xD;
             myopathy, myotonic dystrophy, neuromyotonia, or peripheral neuropathy.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Patients with ANY history of thrombocytopenia.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Patient that has any listed or reports taking ANY anticoagulants in the past 7 days.&#xD;
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Jacob Sieger, DO</last_name>
    <phone>6104571345</phone>
    <email>jsieger@mercy.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Vincent Peyko, PharmD</last_name>
    <phone>3307185919</phone>
    <email>vjpeyko@mercy.com</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>St. Elizabeth Youngstown Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Youngstown</city>
        <state>Ohio</state>
        <zip>44501</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Joseph Dombroski, DO</last_name>
      <phone>330-272-4938</phone>
      <email>joedombroski@gmail.com</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>https://academic.oup.com/cid/article/52/5/e103/388285</url>
    <description>. International clinical practice guidelines for the treatment of acute uncomplicated cystitis and pyelonephritis in women</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Goodlet KJ, Benhalima FZ, Nailor MD. A Systematic Review of Single-Dose Aminoglycoside Therapy for Urinary Tract Infection: Is It Time To Resurrect an Old Strategy? Antimicrob Agents Chemother. 2018 Dec 21;63(1):e02165-18. doi: 10.1128/AAC.02165-18. Print 2019 Jan.</citation>
    <PMID>30397061</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Durkin MJ, Keller M, Butler AM, Kwon JH, Dubberke ER, Miller AC, Polgreen PM, Olsen MA. An Assessment of Inappropriate Antibiotic Use and Guideline Adherence for Uncomplicated Urinary Tract Infections. Open Forum Infect Dis. 2018 Aug 10;5(9):ofy198. doi: 10.1093/ofid/ofy198. eCollection 2018 Sep.</citation>
    <PMID>30191156</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ababneh M, Harpe S, Oinonen M, Polk RE. Trends in aminoglycoside use and gentamicin-resistant gram-negative clinical isolates in US academic medical centers: implications for antimicrobial stewardship. Infect Control Hosp Epidemiol. 2012 Jun;33(6):594-601. doi: 10.1086/665724. Epub 2012 Apr 19.</citation>
    <PMID>22561715</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Foxman B. The epidemiology of urinary tract infection. Nat Rev Urol. 2010 Dec;7(12):653-60. doi: 10.1038/nrurol.2010.190.</citation>
    <PMID>21139641</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kang CI, Kim J, Park DW, Kim BN, Ha US, Lee SJ, Yeo JK, Min SK, Lee H, Wie SH. Clinical Practice Guidelines for the Antibiotic Treatment of Community-Acquired Urinary Tract Infections. Infect Chemother. 2018 Mar;50(1):67-100. doi: 10.3947/ic.2018.50.1.67.</citation>
    <PMID>29637759</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sanchez GV, Babiker A, Master RN, Luu T, Mathur A, Bordon J. Antibiotic Resistance among Urinary Isolates from Female Outpatients in the United States in 2003 and 2012. Antimicrob Agents Chemother. 2016 Apr 22;60(5):2680-3. doi: 10.1128/AAC.02897-15. Print 2016 May.</citation>
    <PMID>26883714</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>January 2023</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>September 22, 2022</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 18, 2023</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">January 27, 2023</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 18, 2023</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 18, 2023</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">January 27, 2023</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>gentamicin</keyword>
  <keyword>single dose antibiotic treatment</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Urinary Tract Infections</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Cystitis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Emergencies</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Gentamicins</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Cephalexin</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Nitrofurantoin</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Cefdinir</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Trimethoprim, Sulfamethoxazole Drug Combination</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Trimethoprim</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Sulfamethoxazole</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

