<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="9239">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 09, 2023</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT05702242</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>22-2177</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT05702242</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Randomized Controlled Trial of No Strings Intrauterine Device (IUD) Removal Techniques</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Randomized Controlled Trial of No Strings Intrauterine Device (IUD) Removal Techniques: Alligator Forceps Versus Manual Vacuum Aspiration (MVA)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Colorado, Denver</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Colorado, Denver</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The goal of this clinical trial is to compare success rates of two removal techniques for&#xD;
      intrauterine devices (IUDs) that have missing or non-visible strings. The investigators will&#xD;
      also collect preliminary data to better understand patient and provider satisfaction, maximum&#xD;
      pain score, procedure time, and complications with the two techniques. Participants will be&#xD;
      randomized to IUD removal with either an alligator forceps or manual vacuum aspiration (MVA)&#xD;
      technique. This study will provide important data on these removal techniques, which could&#xD;
      possibly expand options for and access to no strings IUD removals.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Intrauterine devices (IUDs) are a commonly used, highly effective form of long-acting&#xD;
      reversible contraception in the United States. Approximately 4-18% of people with an IUD in&#xD;
      place with have missing or non-visible IUD strings, mostly commonly due to IUD string&#xD;
      retraction into the cervix. Currently, expert opinion suggests to remove IUDs with no visible&#xD;
      strings using by using an alligator forceps that is placed into the uterine cavity with or&#xD;
      without ultrasound guidance. Removal of no strings IUDs with manual vacuum aspiration (MVA)&#xD;
      has been suggested as a possible alternative to alligator forceps. MVA is a commonly used&#xD;
      technique for the management of miscarriage, abortion, and endometrial sampling and has&#xD;
      potential benefits as a low cost, portable device that is readily available in family&#xD;
      planning clinic and many office-based obstetrics and gynecology practices.&#xD;
&#xD;
      The study will compare MVA to alligator forceps for IUD removal with no visible strings. The&#xD;
      investigators will enroll females presenting for no strings IUD removals. Potential&#xD;
      participants will be screened for eligibility and will be excluded if they have visible IUD&#xD;
      strings, have a positive pregnancy test, have a partially retained IUD (e.g., IUD arm only),&#xD;
      or are unwilling to be randomized to either arm. The investigators will perform a screening&#xD;
      pelvic exam and transvaginal ultrasound (if not already completed prior to the visit).&#xD;
      Participants will then be randomized to one of the two removal techniques: MVA or alligator&#xD;
      forceps. The investigators will document successful removal with the first pass of the&#xD;
      instrument as well as successful removal with multiple attempts of the same technique. A&#xD;
      maximum of 3 MVA removal attempts will be performed after which time, the provider will&#xD;
      switch to using an alligator forceps as the current standard of care. Preliminary data will&#xD;
      also be collected on patient and provider satisfaction, patient pain scores, procedure time,&#xD;
      and complications.&#xD;
&#xD;
      This study will provide important data on MVA as a technique for IUD removals with no visible&#xD;
      strings. No studies have compared IUD removal techniques and expanding options for removal&#xD;
      techniques has the potential to increase access to care.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">January 2023</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2024</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2024</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>First-pass IUD removal rates</measure>
    <time_frame>12-18 months</time_frame>
    <description>To compare the first-pass intrauterine device (IUD) removal rates of using manual vacuum aspiration versus alligator forceps for IUD removal with no visible strings.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall IUD removal success rates</measure>
    <time_frame>12-18 months</time_frame>
    <description>To describe the overall success rates of IUD removal with no visible strings using alligator forceps versus manual vacuum aspiration.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Preliminary data on satisfaction</measure>
    <time_frame>12-18 months</time_frame>
    <description>To gather preliminary data on patient and provider satisfaction.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Preliminary data on pain scores</measure>
    <time_frame>12-18 months</time_frame>
    <description>To gather preliminary data on maximum procedural pain scores measured by visual analog scale (VAS).</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Preliminary data on procedure time</measure>
    <time_frame>12-18 months</time_frame>
    <description>To gather preliminary data on total procedure time.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Preliminary data on complications</measure>
    <time_frame>12-18 months</time_frame>
    <description>To gather preliminary data on complications of no strings IUD removals.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">75</enrollment>
  <condition>IUD Threads Not Visible</condition>
  <condition>IUD Removal Complication</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Removal with alligator forceps</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Standard of care removal with passage of an intrauterine alligator forceps under ultrasound guidance to grasp and remove the IUD. If required, multiple attempts will be performed using this technique.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Removal with manual vacuum aspiration</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Intrauterine placement of an MVA under ultrasound guidance adjacent to the IUD to remove the IUD. Multiple attempts will be performed up to a maximum of 3 unsuccessful MVA attempts, after which time, the provider will switch to the alligator forceps technique, given that this is the current standard of care.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>IUD removal with no visible strings</intervention_name>
    <description>Removal with either alligator forceps or MVA</description>
    <arm_group_label>Removal with alligator forceps</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Removal with manual vacuum aspiration</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Alligator forceps</intervention_name>
    <description>IUD removal with alligator forceps</description>
    <arm_group_label>Removal with alligator forceps</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Manual Vacuum Aspirator</intervention_name>
    <description>IUD removal with MVA</description>
    <arm_group_label>Removal with manual vacuum aspiration</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Ipas 60-mL double valve aspirator</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Female&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Ages 18 - 45 years old&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Confirmed intrauterine IUD by pelvic ultrasound&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Desires IUD removal&#xD;
&#xD;
        Exclusion Criteria:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Currently pregnant&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  IUD strings are visible&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Partial retained IUD (e.g. IUD arm only)&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Unwilling to be randomized to either arm&#xD;
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>45 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Cara Clure, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Colorado, Denver</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Cara Clure, MD</last_name>
    <phone>303-724-8482</phone>
    <email>cara.clure@cuanschutz.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Eva Dindinger, MPH</last_name>
    <phone>303-724-8482</phone>
    <email>eva.dindinger@cuanschutz.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Comprehensive Women's Health Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Denver</city>
        <state>Colorado</state>
        <zip>80230</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Cara Clure, MD</last_name>
      <phone>303-724-8576</phone>
      <email>cara.clure@cuanschutz.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Eva Dindinger, MPH</last_name>
      <phone>303-724-8482</phone>
      <email>eva.dindinger@cuanschutz.edu</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Prabhakaran S, Chuang A. In-office retrieval of intrauterine contraceptive devices with missing strings. Contraception. 2011 Feb;83(2):102-6. doi: 10.1016/j.contraception.2010.07.004. Epub 2010 Aug 23. No abstract available.</citation>
    <PMID>21237334</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Marchi NM, Castro S, Hidalgo MM, Hidalgo C, Monteiro-Dantas C, Villarroeal M, Bahamondes L. Management of missing strings in users of intrauterine contraceptives. Contraception. 2012 Oct;86(4):354-8. doi: 10.1016/j.contraception.2012.01.018. Epub 2012 Mar 27.</citation>
    <PMID>22459233</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Verma U, Astudillo-Davalos FE, Gerkowicz SA. Safe and cost-effective ultrasound guided removal of retained intrauterine device: our experience. Contraception. 2015 Jul;92(1):77-80. doi: 10.1016/j.contraception.2015.02.008. Epub 2015 Feb 21.</citation>
    <PMID>25708503</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Swenson C, Royer PA, Turok DK, Jacobson JC, Amaral G, Sanders JN. Removal of the LNG IUD when strings are not visible: a case series. Contraception. 2014 Sep;90(3):288-90. doi: 10.1016/j.contraception.2014.04.007. Epub 2014 Apr 21.</citation>
    <PMID>24835830</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Mizia K, Ramsay P. The effectiveness and safety of ultrasound-guided removal of a Mirena((R)) intrauterine system when the strings are not visible and conventional office procedures have failed. Aust N Z J Obstet Gynaecol. 2013 Aug;53(4):386-8. doi: 10.1111/ajo.12103. Epub 2013 Jun 26.</citation>
    <PMID>23802598</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>da Silva Nobrega AB, Pitangui ACR, Vieira CS. Factors associated with missing strings and expulsion after postplacental insertion of copper T380A intrauterine devices. Int J Gynaecol Obstet. 2022 Apr;157(1):67-75. doi: 10.1002/ijgo.13806. Epub 2021 Jul 27.</citation>
    <PMID>34197636</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Wu JP, Porch E, Womack JP. Successful retrieval of an intrauterine device with &quot;missing strings&quot; using a manual vacuum aspirator in a desired early pregnancy: case report. J Minim Invasive Gynecol. 2011 Mar-Apr;18(2):254-6. doi: 10.1016/j.jmig.2010.11.008.</citation>
    <PMID>21354074</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Jain A, Singh S, Elliyas S. Effectiveness of Manual Vacuum Aspiration (MVA) Device in the Management of Intrauterine Copper Devices (IUCD) with Missing Strings: A Prospective Interventional Study. J Obstet Gynaecol India. 2021 Aug;71(4):424-429. doi: 10.1007/s13224-021-01440-x. Epub 2021 Mar 15.</citation>
    <PMID>34566303</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Guillebaud J, Kasonde JM. A simple scheme for managing the problem of 'lost threads' with intrauterine devices. Fertil Contracept. 1979 Apr;3(2):24-32.</citation>
    <PMID>12309485</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>January 2023</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>January 5, 2023</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 17, 2023</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">January 27, 2023</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 17, 2023</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 17, 2023</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">January 27, 2023</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

