<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="9488">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 09, 2023</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT05696782</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>IRB00092850</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>WFBCCC 62422</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT05696782</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Quick Start Durvalumab Following Chemoradiation for Stage III Nonsmall Cell Lung Cancer</brief_title>
  <official_title>Phase II Pilot Study of Quick Start Durvalumab Following Chemoradiation for Stage III Nonsmall Cell Lung Cancer</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Wake Forest University Health Sciences</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Wake Forest University Health Sciences</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This research study aims to determine what effects (good and bad) Durvalumab has on&#xD;
      participants and their cancer with a &quot;quick start&quot; of Durvalumab within 14 days of finishing&#xD;
      chemotherapy and radiation. The study will also determine the logistic barriers to the quick&#xD;
      start of Durvalumab.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Primary Objective: Assess the treatment fidelity for early Durvalumab initiation (i.e.,&#xD;
      within 14 days after the last day of radiation therapy) following chemoradiation for Stage&#xD;
      III, unresectable nonsmall cell lung cancer.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Secondary Objectives:&#xD;
&#xD;
        -  Assess the treatment fidelity for very early Durvalumab initiation (i.e., within seven&#xD;
           days after the last day of radiation therapy) following chemoradiation for Stage III,&#xD;
           unresectable nonsmall cell lung cancer.&#xD;
&#xD;
        -  Assess barriers to earlier Durvalumab initiation following chemoradiation for Stage III&#xD;
           nonsmall cell lung cancer.&#xD;
&#xD;
        -  Describe the toxicity of Durvalumab when initiated quickly after chemoradiation for&#xD;
           Stage III nonsmall cell lung cancer as compared to historical controls.&#xD;
&#xD;
        -  Describe the efficacy of Durvalumab when initiated quickly after chemoradiation for&#xD;
           Stage III nonsmall cell lung cancer as compared to historical controls.&#xD;
&#xD;
        -  Describe the patient-reported outcomes of Durvalumab when initiated quickly after&#xD;
           chemoradiation for Stage III nonsmall cell lung cancer as compared to historical&#xD;
           controls.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">July 2023</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2026</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">May 2025</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>N/A</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of Participants to Achieve Fidelity to Early Treatment with Durvalumab - Early Initiation (1-14 days)</measure>
    <time_frame>48 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Fidelity is defined as a dichotomous composite indicator (yes/no) that describes whether the patient received very early (1-7 days) initiation of Durvalumab as per protocol with all four of the following criteria having been met: (i) CT chest obtained after the last day of radiation therapy and before the first infusion of Durvalumab, (ii) first infusion within 14 days of completing radiation therapy, (iii) second and third doses received within 63 days of the first dose, and (iv) all infusions at least 28 days apart.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of Participants to Achieve Fidelity to Early Treatment with Durvalumab - Very Early (1-7 days)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 13 months</time_frame>
    <description>Fidelity is defined as a dichotomous composite indicator (yes/no) that describes whether the patient received very early (1-7 days) initiation of Durvalumab as per protocol with all four of the following criteria having been met: (i) CT chest obtained after the last day of radiation therapy and before the first infusion of Durvalumab, (ii) first infusion within 7 days of completing radiation therapy, (iii) second and third doses received within 63 days of the first dose, and (iv) all infusions at least 28 days apart.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of Barriers to Initiation of Durvalumab - Very Early (Days 1-7)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 13 months</time_frame>
    <description>Descriptive frequencies of participant survey answers will be examined to conduct qualitative analyses and determine appropriate categories of answers on the free text responses. We will examine barriers/obstacles for everyone in the sample, even those who achieve fidelity; such patients could have experienced delays even if they were still able to achieve fidelity. We will stratify answers/responses by fidelity status.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of Barriers to Initiation of Durvalumab - Early (Days 8-14)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 13 months</time_frame>
    <description>Descriptive frequencies of participant survey answers will be examined to conduct qualitative analyses and determine appropriate categories of answers on the free text responses. We will examine barriers/obstacles for everyone in the sample, even those who achieve fidelity; such patients could have experienced delays even if they were still able to achieve fidelity. We will stratify answers/responses by fidelity status.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidences of All Adverse Events</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 13 months after intervention</time_frame>
    <description>Adverse events, serious adverse events and immune-related adverse events will be tabulated by fidelity status (1-7 days vs. 8-14 days vs. neither) using National Cancer Institute Common Terminology Criteria, version 5.0.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of Participants Who Have Immune-Mediated Pneumonitis - Early Fidelity (1-14 days)</measure>
    <time_frame>Within 85 days of intervention (Cycles 1-3)</time_frame>
    <description>Participants with early (1-14 days) fidelity who have immune-mediated early-onset pneumonitis will be estimated and statistically compared in a one-sample test of proportions.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of Participants Who Have All-Cause Pneumonitis - Early Fidelity (1-14 days)</measure>
    <time_frame>Within 85 days of intervention (Cycles 1-3)</time_frame>
    <description>Participants with all-cause early-onset pneumonitis among those with early (1-14 days) fidelity and statistically compare it, using a one-sample test of proportions.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of Participants to Discontinue Durvalumab Due to Adverse Events</measure>
    <time_frame>One year</time_frame>
    <description>Participants with early fidelity who discontinue Durvalumab at any point due to an adverse event of any cause and compare it using a one-sample test of proportions.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall Survival</measure>
    <time_frame>One year</time_frame>
    <description>Using Kaplan-Meier life table methods, overall survival is defined as the number of participants alive at 12 months after the first dose of Durvalumab.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Progression-Free Survival</measure>
    <time_frame>One year</time_frame>
    <description>Using Kaplan-Meier methods, progression-free survival is defined as the number of participants alive and without disease progression as documented by the treating provider at 12 months after the first dose of Durvalumab.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Response Rate</measure>
    <time_frame>One year</time_frame>
    <description>Best objective response rate (ORR) to Durvalumab is defined by either a complete response (CR) or partial response (PR) as per RECIST 1.1 criteria by investigator assessment and confirmed on at least two sequential imaging studies that are at least four weeks apart</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Patient-Reported Outcomes Scores (PROs) - European Organization for Research and Treatment of Cancer (EORTC) Quality of Life Questionnaire-Core 30 (QLQ-C30) Version 3</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline to 12 weeks after start of intervention</time_frame>
    <description>The change in PROs scores from baseline to week 12 using paired t-tests and compare mean difference scores to the null hypothesis value of zero change to compare between fidelity status (1-7 days vs. 8-14 days vs. neither). Scale scores range from 0 to 100. A high score for a functional scale represents a high level of functioning, whereas a high score for a symptom scale/single item represents a high level of symptomatology.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Patient-Reported Outcomes Scores (PROs) - Quality of Life Questionnaire-Lung Cancer 13 (QLQ-LC13) Questionnaire</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline to 12 weeks after start of intervention</time_frame>
    <description>The QLQ-LC13 includes questions assessing lung cancer-associated symptoms (cough, hemoptysis, dyspnea and site specific pain), treatment-related side effects (sore mouth, dysphagia, peripheral neuropathy and alopecia) and pain medication. The change in PROs scores from baseline to week 12 using paired t-tests and compare mean difference scores to the null hypothesis value of zero change to compare between fidelity status (1-7 days vs. 8-14 days vs. neither). Scale scores range from 0 to 100. A high score for a functional scale represents a high level of functioning, whereas a high score for a symptom scale/single item represents a high level of symptomatology.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Respiratory Patient Reported Outcomes (PROs) - COPD Assessment Test (CAT)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline to 12 weeks after start of intervention</time_frame>
    <description>The COPD Assessment Test (CAT) is a questionnaire for people with Chronic Obstructive Pulmonary Disease (COPD). It is designed to measure the impact of COPD on a person's life and how this changes over time. Range of CAT scores from 0-40. Higher scores denote a more severe impact of COPD. The change in PROs scores using paired t-tests and compare mean difference scores to the null hypothesis value of zero change to compare between fidelity status (1-7 days vs. 8-14 days vs. neither).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Respiratory Patient Reported Outcomes (PROs) - Modified Medical Research Council (mMRC) Dyspnea Scale</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline to 12 weeks after start of intervention</time_frame>
    <description>The mMRC (Modified Medical Research Council) Dyspnea Scale is used to assess the degree of baseline functional disability due to dyspnea.The mMRC breathlessness scale ranges from grade 0 to 4 with grade 4 indicating a higher level of respiratory disease severity.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">28</enrollment>
  <condition>Nonsmall Cell Lung Cancer Stage III</condition>
  <condition>Unresectable Non-Small Cell Lung Carcinoma</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Quick Start Durvalumab</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Standard of care test and procedures for cancer treatments along with Durvalumab treatment at physician's discretion</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Durvalumab</intervention_name>
    <description>Participants will receive Durvalumab 1500 mg intravenously every two weeks for 60 minutes. Each treatment is called a cycle and lasts for four weeks (or 28 days).</description>
    <arm_group_label>Quick Start Durvalumab</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>the EORTC Core Quality of Life Questionnaire (EORTC QLQ-C30)</intervention_name>
    <description>Participants will be asked to answer all 30 items on the EORTC Core Quality of Life questionnaire (EORTC QLQ-C30). This patient-reported outcome measure is designed to measure cancer patients' physical, psychological and social functions. The measure can be completed using a paper form, by verbally providing answers to the study team, or by entering the answers online into REDCap using a computer or mobile device. The total time to complete the questionnaire is approximately 11 minutes (</description>
    <arm_group_label>Quick Start Durvalumab</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Diagnostic Test</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>COPD Assessment Test (CAT)</intervention_name>
    <description>Participants will be asked to answer all items on the COPD assessment test (8 items) and the patient-reported outcome measures designed to measure respiratory function. The measures can be completed using a paper form, by verbally providing answers to the study team, or by entering the answers online into REDCap using a computer or mobile device. The total time to complete the questionnaire is less than 5 minutes.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Quick Start Durvalumab</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Diagnostic Test</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Modified Medical Research Council (mMRC) dyspnea scale</intervention_name>
    <description>Participants will be asked to answer the modified medical research council dyspnea scale (1 item), and the patient-reported outcome measures designed to measure respiratory function. The measures can be completed using a paper form, by verbally providing answers to the study team, or by entering the answers online into REDCap using a computer or mobile device. The total time to complete the questionnaire is less than 5 minutes.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Quick Start Durvalumab</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Histological or cytological documentation of nonsmall cell lung cancer that is Stage&#xD;
             III according to the American Joint Committee on Cancer Staging Manual, 8th Edition&#xD;
             (2017).&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Unresectable or medically inoperable as determined by the investigator.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  The participant has definitive radiation therapy (e.g., 54 Gy to 66 Gy in 30 to 35&#xD;
             fractions) for lung cancer that is either (a) planned to start within the next 28&#xD;
             days, or (b) currently being administered, or (c) has been completed within the last&#xD;
             14 days.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Platinum-based chemotherapy for lung cancer that is either (a) planned to start within&#xD;
             the next 28 days, (b) currently being administered, or (c) has been completed within&#xD;
             the last 14 days. Chemotherapy must be for at least two cycles and be administered&#xD;
             either before radiation therapy (&quot;induction&quot; or &quot;sequential&quot;) or during radiation&#xD;
             therapy (&quot;concurrent&quot;).&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Consolidation Durvalumab is planned for nonsmall cell lung cancer after radiation and&#xD;
             chemotherapy.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Eighteen years old or greater.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  ECOG performance status of 0-2.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Life expectancy of greater than three months.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Patients with sexual relationships in which either they or their partner may become&#xD;
             pregnant must use contraception during the study treatment period.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Ability to understand and be willing to sign an IRB-approved informed consent document&#xD;
             directly or via a legally authorized representative.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Exclusion Criteria:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Uncontrolled respiratory symptoms (i.e., cough, dyspnea, fevers, chest pain, or an&#xD;
             increase from baseline oxygen requirements) that are interfering with activities of&#xD;
             daily living.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Nonsmall cell lung cancer is known to have progressed during radiation therapy.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Nonsmall cell lung cancer is known to have a tumor with a mutation in EGFR associated&#xD;
             with sensitivity to first-line therapy with a tyrosine kinase inhibitor (i.e.,&#xD;
             Ex19del, L858R, EGFR S768I, L861Q, or G719X). If not already known, testing for EGFR&#xD;
             mutations is not required for study enrollment.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Prior exposure to an immune checkpoint inhibitor targeting CTLA-4, PD-1, or PD-L1.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Active autoimmune disease requiring systemic immunosuppression at the time of&#xD;
             enrollment.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  History of autoimmune pneumonitis requiring high-dose systemic steroids (equivalent&#xD;
             prednisone &gt;20 mg/day for more than one week).&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Uncontrolled intercurrent illness includes ongoing or active infection, symptomatic&#xD;
             congestive heart failure, unstable angina pectoris, cardiac arrhythmia, or psychiatric&#xD;
             illness/social situations that would limit compliance with study requirements.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Patients who are pregnant or breastfeeding.&#xD;
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Thomas Lycan, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Wake Forest Baptist Comprehensive Cancer Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Study Nurse</last_name>
    <phone>3367137748</phone>
    <email>saverill@wakehealth.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Wake Forest Baptist Comprehensive Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Winston-Salem</city>
        <state>North Carolina</state>
        <zip>27157</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Study Nurse</last_name>
      <phone>336-713-7748</phone>
      <email>saverill@wakehealth.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Thomas Lycan, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>April 2023</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>January 12, 2023</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 12, 2023</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">January 25, 2023</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 1, 2023</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 1, 2023</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">June 5, 2023</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Lung Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Carcinoma, Non-Small-Cell Lung</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Durvalumab</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

