<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="9046">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 09, 2023</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT05706389</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>NUS-IRB-2021-946</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT05706389</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Does Alpha-ketoglutarate Supplementation Lower BiologicaL agE in Middle- Aged Adults?</brief_title>
  <acronym>ABLE</acronym>
  <official_title>Does Alpha-ketoglutarate Supplementation Lower BiologicaL agE in Middle- Aged Adults?</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National University of Singapore</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Agency for Science, Technology and Research</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>AMILI Pte. Ltd.</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National University of Singapore</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Geroscience is an emerging interdisciplinary field of study in gerontological sciences. With&#xD;
      emphasis on understanding the mechanistic drivers of aging, it seeks translational approaches&#xD;
      that could eventually be applied to improve human healthspan and delay age-associated chronic&#xD;
      diseases. Contrary to popular opinion that aging is irreversible, advances in geroscience&#xD;
      research have demonstrated that aging is modifiable and inhibiting or activating specific&#xD;
      molecular pathways can improve healthspan and extend lifespan in model organisms. Advocates&#xD;
      of geroscience take the view that age-related chronic diseases are best treated by slowing&#xD;
      the aging process, rather than using the prevailing disease-centric approach of addressing&#xD;
      each disease alone. Thus, the concept is that biological aging, rather than chronological&#xD;
      aging, is amenable to intervention.&#xD;
&#xD;
      In this regard, geroscientists are at the forefront of longevity medicine in rigorously&#xD;
      testing novel supplements, drugs and other prophylactics that can enhance healthspan. Some of&#xD;
      these interventions involve repurposing existing drugs such as rapamycin, a well-known&#xD;
      immunosuppressant, at different dosing regimens to specifically target biological hallmarks&#xD;
      of aging.&#xD;
&#xD;
      This study will investigate the effects of alpha-ketoglutarate (AKG), an endogenous&#xD;
      metabolite, on biomarkers of aging in middle-aged residents of Singapore.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Recent growing understanding on mechanisms of aging as gradual changes in body systems&#xD;
      through several cellular and molecular levels has raised research interests in the biology of&#xD;
      aging. There are seven established overlapping processes of aging: oxidative stress,&#xD;
      macromolecular damage, epigenetic changes, abnormal metabolism, impaired proteostasis,&#xD;
      decline in stem cell functions and inflammation. These overlapping changes over the lifetime&#xD;
      affect the onset of age-related diseases and possibly the aging process itself. However,&#xD;
      lifestyle and pharmacologic interventions can modify the deterioration of aging pathways. AKG&#xD;
      is a generally regarded as safe (GRAS) micronutrient and has shown great potential in&#xD;
      extending healthspan. Here, we aim to study the role of AKG in the modulation of aging.&#xD;
&#xD;
      The aim is to evaluate the anti-aging function of AKG and determine whether AKG can modulate&#xD;
      biological pathways of aging in middle-aged adults in Singapore. Our hypothesis is that AKG&#xD;
      will affect DNA methylation which will be associated with the change in blood biomarkers of&#xD;
      aging and change in physiological function. It allows us to study the longitudinal effects of&#xD;
      AKG on clinical and biological outcomes.&#xD;
&#xD;
      This is a 6-month double-blinded, placebo-controlled longitudinal interventional study on&#xD;
      middle-aged participants to study the effect of AKG on biomarkers of aging, with another 3&#xD;
      months of post-intervention follow-up. The total duration of participation in this study is 9&#xD;
      months.&#xD;
&#xD;
      The rationale for this study design is to study the long-term effect of 1 g AKG in&#xD;
      middle-aged adults. Our study design of 6 months of intervention (1 g AKG vs placebo) will&#xD;
      allow us to understand the effect of AKG treatment on DNA methylation, and another 3 months&#xD;
      of post-intervention follow-up will help us understand if there is any long-term effect of&#xD;
      AKG. In order to minimize recruitment bias, our study design is double-blinded.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">February 24, 2023</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">January 15, 2025</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">January 15, 2024</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Double-blinded, placebo-controlled longitudinal interventional study on middle-aged participants</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Quadruple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in blood DNA methylation status, years</measure>
    <time_frame>from baseline to end of intervention (6 months)</time_frame>
    <description>DNA methylation aging clock</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Complete blood count</measure>
    <time_frame>from baseline to end of intervention (6 months)</time_frame>
    <description>comparison of blood count at baseline and 6 months</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Carotid-femoral Pulse Wave Velocity change</measure>
    <time_frame>from baseline to end of intervention (6 months)</time_frame>
    <description>comparison of PWV at baseline and 6 months</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Central Blood pressure change</measure>
    <time_frame>from baseline to end of intervention (6 months)</time_frame>
    <description>comparison of Central Blood pressure at baseline and 6 months</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Body Mass Index (BMI) change</measure>
    <time_frame>from baseline to end of intervention (6 months)</time_frame>
    <description>comparison of BMI at baseline and 6 months</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Brachial Blood pressure change</measure>
    <time_frame>from baseline to end of intervention (6 months)</time_frame>
    <description>comparison of Brachial Blood pressure at baseline and 6 months</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Waist/hip ratio change</measure>
    <time_frame>from baseline to end of intervention (6 months)</time_frame>
    <description>comparison of Waist/hip ratio at baseline and 6 months</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Bone Mineral Density, g/cm2 change</measure>
    <time_frame>from baseline to end of intervention (6 months)</time_frame>
    <description>comparison of Bone Mineral Density at baseline and 6 months</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Fat-free mass, change (kg)</measure>
    <time_frame>from baseline to end of intervention (6 months)</time_frame>
    <description>comparison of fat-free mass at baseline and 6 months</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Fat mass, change (kg)</measure>
    <time_frame>from baseline to end of intervention (6 months)</time_frame>
    <description>comparison of fat mass at baseline and 6 months</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Handgrip strength change (kg)</measure>
    <time_frame>from baseline to end of intervention (6 months)</time_frame>
    <description>comparison of handgrip strength at baseline and 6 months</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>8-RM leg extension change (kg)</measure>
    <time_frame>from baseline to end of intervention (6 months)</time_frame>
    <description>comparison of 8RM leg extension at baseline and 6 months</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Cardiopulmonary exercise test (CPET): Change in Volume of Oxygen consumption (V̇O2), L/min</measure>
    <time_frame>from baseline to end of intervention (6 months)</time_frame>
    <description>comparison of VO2 during CPET at baseline and 6 months</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Cardiopulmonary exercise test (CPET): Change in Volume of Oxygen consumption per kg body weight (V̇O2/kg), L/min/kg</measure>
    <time_frame>from baseline to end of intervention (6 months)</time_frame>
    <description>comparison of VO2/kg during CPET at baseline and 6 months</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Cardiopulmonary exercise test (CPET): change in lactate</measure>
    <time_frame>from baseline to end of intervention (6 months)</time_frame>
    <description>comparison of lactate levels during CPET at baseline and 6 months</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Cardiopulmonary exercise test (CPET): change in heart rate</measure>
    <time_frame>from baseline to end of intervention (6 months)</time_frame>
    <description>comparison of heart rate levels during CPET at baseline and 6 months</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Cardiopulmonary exercise test (CPET): aerobic and anaerobic threshold change</measure>
    <time_frame>from baseline to end of intervention (6 months)</time_frame>
    <description>comparison of aerobic and anaerobic threshold levels during CPET at baseline and 6 months</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Cardiopulmonary exercise test (CPET): excess post-exercise oxygen consumption change</measure>
    <time_frame>from baseline to end of intervention (6 months)</time_frame>
    <description>comparison of excess post-exercise oxygen consumption levels during CPET at baseline and 6 months</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Skin autofluorescence, au</measure>
    <time_frame>from baseline to end of intervention (6 months)</time_frame>
    <description>comparison of skin autofluorescence levels at baseline and 6 months</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Quality-of-Life questionnaires (SF-36 questionnaires)</measure>
    <time_frame>from baseline to end of intervention (6 months)</time_frame>
    <description>comparison of Quality-of-life at baseline and 6 months</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Quality-of-Life questionnaires (EuroQoL-5D-5L)</measure>
    <time_frame>from baseline to end of intervention (6 months)</time_frame>
    <description>comparison of Quality-of-life at baseline and 6 months</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Sleep (modified Pittsburgh sleep quality Questionnaire )</measure>
    <time_frame>from baseline to end of intervention (6 months)</time_frame>
    <description>comparison of sleep at baseline and 6 months</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Sleep (Satisfaction, Alertness, Timing, Efficiency and Duration (SATED) Questionnaire )</measure>
    <time_frame>from baseline to end of intervention (6 months)</time_frame>
    <description>comparison of sleep at baseline and 6 months</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Global preferences survey (GPS)</measure>
    <time_frame>from baseline to end of intervention (6 months)</time_frame>
    <description>comparison of global preferences (GPS) at baseline and 6 months</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>AKG, glutamate, glutamine concentrations in serum</measure>
    <time_frame>from baseline to end of intervention (6 months)</time_frame>
    <description>Metabolites in serum change</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Immune parameters (Complete Blood Count)</measure>
    <time_frame>from baseline to end of intervention (6 months)</time_frame>
    <description>Immune parameters change</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Immune parameters (inflammatory parameters in serum, mg/dL)</measure>
    <time_frame>from baseline to end of intervention (6 months)</time_frame>
    <description>Immune parameters change</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Clinical Blood parameters: Renal function, mg/dL</measure>
    <time_frame>from baseline to end of intervention (6 months)</time_frame>
    <description>Clinical Blood parameters change</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Clinical Blood parameters: Lipid profile test, mmol/L</measure>
    <time_frame>from baseline to end of intervention (6 months)</time_frame>
    <description>Clinical Blood parameters change</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Clinical Blood parameters: Glucose, mg/dL</measure>
    <time_frame>from baseline to end of intervention (6 months)</time_frame>
    <description>Clinical Blood parameters change</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Clinical Blood parameters: insulin, mg/dL</measure>
    <time_frame>from baseline to end of intervention (6 months)</time_frame>
    <description>Clinical Blood parameters change</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Clinical Blood parameters: HbA1C, mmol/mol</measure>
    <time_frame>from baseline to end of intervention (6 months)</time_frame>
    <description>Clinical Blood parameters change</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Clinical Blood parameters: Metabolites, mmol/l</measure>
    <time_frame>from baseline to end of intervention (6 months)</time_frame>
    <description>Clinical Blood parameters change</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Cognitive function test by Montreal Cognitive Assessment (MoCA)</measure>
    <time_frame>from baseline to end of intervention (6 months)</time_frame>
    <description>Cognitive function change</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in saliva DNA methylation status, years</measure>
    <time_frame>from baseline to end of intervention (6 months)</time_frame>
    <description>DNA methylation aging clock</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">120</enrollment>
  <condition>Aging</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Ca-AKG</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Pill format, 500mg/pill, half of daily dose</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Pill format, indistinguishable from active pill</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Dietary Supplement</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Ca-AKG</intervention_name>
    <description>Eligible participants will be randomised to receive Ca-AKG or Placebo for 6 months.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Ca-AKG</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  participants whose biological age (as measured by blood DNA methylation) is greater&#xD;
             than their chronological age&#xD;
&#xD;
        Exclusion Criteria:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  pregnant women&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  more than ONE of the following chronic medical conditions (based on the medical&#xD;
             history and during screening), they are NOT eligible to participate in the study:&#xD;
&#xD;
               1. Waist circumference more than or equal to 90 cm for males or more than or equal&#xD;
                  to 80 cm for females&#xD;
&#xD;
               2. Fasting triglycerides more than or equal to 1.7 mmol/l&#xD;
&#xD;
               3. High-density lipoprotein less than 1.0 mmol/l in men or less than 1.3 mmol/l in&#xD;
                  women&#xD;
&#xD;
               4. Blood pressure more than or equal to 130/85 mmHg or use of antihypertensive&#xD;
                  medication&#xD;
&#xD;
               5. Fasting glucose more than or equal to 6.0 mmol/l&#xD;
&#xD;
               6. Osteopenia&#xD;
&#xD;
               7. Mild Osteoarthritis not interfering in daily activities&#xD;
&#xD;
               8. Fatty liver&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Participants will NOT be recruited if they fall in the following categories:&#xD;
&#xD;
               1. Pre-existing, or history of major CVD (coronary artery disease, heart failure,&#xD;
                  stroke, peripheral vascular disease, pulmonary hypertension), severe/uncontrolled&#xD;
                  hypertension (under 3 or more than 3 prescribed medications), rheumatic heart&#xD;
                  disease, congenital heart disease, deep vein thrombosis, pulmonary embolism&#xD;
&#xD;
               2. Type 1 diabetes and Type 2 diabetes under oral metformin or insulin therapy and&#xD;
                  with diabetic complications such as diabetic retinopathy, diabetic nephropathy&#xD;
&#xD;
               3. Active cancer or treatment of cancer in the last 3 years&#xD;
&#xD;
               4. Chronic obstructive pulmonary disease (COPD), severe asthma (taking daily&#xD;
                  medications)&#xD;
&#xD;
               5. Pregnant women will not be recruited into this study because of the safety issues&#xD;
                  associated with X-ray irradiation during DXA scan&#xD;
&#xD;
               6. Potential female participants who plan on pregnancy within the next 9 months of&#xD;
                  study period&#xD;
&#xD;
               7. Multiple sclerosis and autoimmune/immune deficiency diseases such as Rheumatic&#xD;
                  arthritis, HIV, Crohn's disease&#xD;
&#xD;
               8. Recent history of sepsis or infection (within 3 months of in-patient&#xD;
                  hospitalization)&#xD;
&#xD;
               9. Any psychiatric disease or neurodegenerative diseases such as Alzheimer's&#xD;
                  Disease, Parkinson's Disease, Lewy body dementia, and any eating disorders&#xD;
&#xD;
              10. Any metal implants in the body&#xD;
&#xD;
              11. Hepatitis and Liver cirrhosis (independent of severity)&#xD;
&#xD;
              12. Severe kidney disease (GFR less than 30 ml/min/1.73 m2)&#xD;
&#xD;
              13. Skin disease (on oral or systemic medication for immune system)&#xD;
&#xD;
              14. Subjects receiving any other similar investigational product within 60 days or 5&#xD;
                  halflives before the screening, whichever that is longer&#xD;
&#xD;
              15. Any serious medical illness which in the PI's judgment may jeopardize the subject&#xD;
                  by his or her participation in this study or may hamper his or her ability to&#xD;
                  perform and complete procedures required in the study&#xD;
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>40 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>60 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Elena Sandalova, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>+6596646302</phone>
    <email>sanelena@nus.edu.sg</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Sangeetha Adiyapatham</last_name>
    <phone>+6592391978</phone>
    <email>sangeetha_adi@visitor.nus.edu.sg</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Centre for Healthy Longevity, Alexandra Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Singapore</city>
        <zip>159964</zip>
        <country>Singapore</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Sangetha Adiyapatham</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Singapore</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>April 2023</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>December 25, 2022</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 20, 2023</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">January 31, 2023</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 23, 2023</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 23, 2023</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">April 25, 2023</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>National University of Singapore</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Andrea Maier</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Oon Chiew Seng Professor in Medicine, Healthy Ageing and Dementia Research</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Aging</keyword>
  <keyword>Geroscience</keyword>
  <keyword>Alpha-Ketoglutarate</keyword>
  <keyword>DNA methylation</keyword>
  <keyword>Healthspan</keyword>
  <keyword>epigenetic aging clock</keyword>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

