<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="9946">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 09, 2023</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT05686954</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>PROJECT00006633</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT05686954</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Cottonseed Oil Dose Response</brief_title>
  <official_title>Nutritional Effects of Different Doses of Cottonseed Oil in Humans</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Georgia</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Cotton Incorporated</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Georgia</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Adding cottonseed oil to the diet has been shown to improve cholesterol profiles and other&#xD;
      markers of chronic disease risk in both healthy and at-risk adults. However, CSO has only&#xD;
      been tested in the context of high-fat diets. The goal of this clinical trial is to learn&#xD;
      about the health effects of lower amounts of cottonseed oil (CSO) added to the diet in adults&#xD;
      at increased risk for cardiovascular disease.&#xD;
&#xD;
      The main questions it aims to answer are:&#xD;
&#xD;
        -  How do different amounts of CSO in the diet affect fasting cholesterol profiles and&#xD;
           markers of liver function?&#xD;
&#xD;
        -  How do different amounts of CSO in the diet affect fasting and post-meal markers of&#xD;
           lipid metabolism (i.e. triglycerides) and glycemic control (i.e. blood sugar and&#xD;
           insulin)?&#xD;
&#xD;
        -  How do different amounts of CSO in the diet affect fasting and post-meal markers of&#xD;
           chronic disease risk factors such as oxidative stress, inflammation, coagulation&#xD;
           potential, and appetite control?&#xD;
&#xD;
      Participants will be asked to:&#xD;
&#xD;
        -  Consume provided breakfast shakes and snacks daily for 28-days.&#xD;
&#xD;
        -  Attend three weekly short visits for fasting blood draws, body measurements, and collect&#xD;
           the next week of study materials.&#xD;
&#xD;
        -  Attend two longer (5.5 h) testing visits which include eating a standardized breakfast&#xD;
           meal and having blood drawn periodically before and after breakfast.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Researchers will compare CSO LOW, CSO MID, CSO HIGH, and Control groups (receiving a mixture&#xD;
      of oils) to see if lower doses of CSO in the diet impart the same health benefits as&#xD;
      previously shown with high doses of CSO.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Cardiovascular disease risk factors, including higher BMIs and poor cholesterol profiles, are&#xD;
      on the rise and contribute to the United States' growing disease burden. Cottonseed oil (CSO)&#xD;
      is found readily in our food supply. Our previous studies have demonstrated that&#xD;
      incorporating CSO into the diet is sufficient to reduce fasting total cholesterol (TC) and&#xD;
      low-density lipoprotein cholesterol (LDL-c), increase high-density lipoprotein cholesterol&#xD;
      (HDL-c), and improve postprandial lipid and/or glycemic responses in both healthy and at-risk&#xD;
      populations. However, in these human studies, diets provided 30-44% of total energy from CSO,&#xD;
      which corresponded to high-fat (HF) diet intake (40-50% of energy). The impact of lower doses&#xD;
      of CSO on human health has yet to be tested. Therefore, this study aims to investigate&#xD;
      whether lower doses of CSO are equally effective as previously proven high doses for&#xD;
      improving fasting and postprandial lipid metabolism and markers of chronic disease risk. If&#xD;
      lower doses of CSO in the diet are found to improve these markers, these study findings could&#xD;
      lead to improvements in health.&#xD;
&#xD;
      This prospective clinical study is a single-blinded, randomized control trial in adults at&#xD;
      increased risk for cardiovascular disease (poor cholesterol profiles or overweight/obesity).&#xD;
      There are four diet interventions: CSO LOW (10% energy from CSO), CSO MID (20% energy from&#xD;
      CSO), CSO HIGH (30% energy from CSO), and CON (10% energy from control oil mix). The study&#xD;
      protocol consists of a 28-day intervention where participants are provided breakfast shakes&#xD;
      and snacks that contain different amounts of cooking oil depending on their random group&#xD;
      assignment.&#xD;
&#xD;
      There are a total of 6 testing visits: screening (v0), pre-intervention (v1), 3 weekly short&#xD;
      visits (v2, v3, v4), and post-intervention (v5).&#xD;
&#xD;
      At screening (v0), qualification is confirmed based on anthropometrics and fasting blood&#xD;
      draw, which is analyzed for a cholesterol panel and blood glucose. Additionally, energy&#xD;
      requirements are estimated at this visit for use in the diet intervention.&#xD;
&#xD;
      At v1, participants will have anthropometrics measured, including body composition, by&#xD;
      BodPod. Next, a certified phlebotomist places an IV catheter and takes the fasting blood&#xD;
      sample. Then the participant consumes a high-saturated-fat meal challenge which delivers 35%&#xD;
      of their estimated energy needs (from v0). Then the participant has blood drawn 8 times using&#xD;
      the IV catheter over the next 5 hours.&#xD;
&#xD;
      28-day dietary intervention: Before leaving v1, participants are sent home with their first&#xD;
      week's supply of daily shakes and snacks corresponding to their randomly assigned group. The&#xD;
      ingredients for the breakfast shakes and snacks are identical between groups, the only&#xD;
      difference being the amount of the assigned oil incorporated into the foods. All foods are&#xD;
      portioned based on individual energy needs as estimated at v0.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Participants return weekly (v2, v3, v4) to return study materials and collect food for the&#xD;
      next week. At these weekly visits, participants also have a fasting blood draw, body measures&#xD;
      and consume their first breakfast shake of the week in the lab.&#xD;
&#xD;
      At the end of the 28-day dietary intervention, participants return for v5, where all&#xD;
      procedures from v1 are repeated.&#xD;
&#xD;
      The investigators hypothesize that CSO LOW, CSO MID, and CSO HIGH will improve the proposed&#xD;
      overall health outcomes and markers of chronic disease risk without changing inflammatory&#xD;
      markers compared to the control group.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">March 1, 2023</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">May 2027</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">May 2026</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Four groups of 28-day parallel feeding trials with three groups receiving different amounts of cottonseed oil (low, mid, high) and one group serving as control receiving a mixture of oils that match the fatty acid profile of the average American diet.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Participant)</masking>
    <masking_description>Participants are blinded to which group they are in and what oil they are receiving.</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in fasting serum lipoprotein and cholesterol concentrations</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, 4 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>The concentration of fasting serum total cholesterol, high-density lipoprotein cholesterol, low-density lipoprotein cholesterol, apolipoprotein B (mg/dl)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in fasting serum lipoprotein particle numbers</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, 4 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Number of particles of low density lipoproteins (LDL), LDL small, HDL large, LDL medium, lipoprotein (a) (nmol/L)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in fasting and postprandial plasma triglyceride concentrations</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, 4 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>The concentration of plasma triglycerides before and after the high saturated fat meal challenge at both pre- and post-intervention visits (mg/dL)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in fasting and postprandial plasma non-esterified fatty acid (NEFA) concentrations</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, 4 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>The concentration of plasma NEFAs before and after the high saturated fat meal challenge at both pre- and post-intervention visits (mEq/L)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in fasting and postprandial plasma glucose concentrations</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, 4 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>The concentration of plasma glucose before and after the high saturated fat meal challenge at both pre- and post-intervention visits (mg/dL)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in fasting and postprandial plasma insulin concentrations</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, 4 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>The concentration of plasma insulin before and after the high saturated fat meal challenge at both pre- and post-intervention visits (uU/mL)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in fasting and postprandial plasma appetite control hormones concentrations</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, 4 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>The concentration of plasma appetite control hormones before and after the high saturated fat meal challenge at both pre- and post-intervention visits. Appetite control hormones include Cholecystokinin (CCK), Peptide YY (PYY), Ghrelin (pg/mL)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in fasting and postprandial subjective feelings related to appetite</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, 4 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Visual analog scale ratings of feelings related to appetite before and after the high saturated fat meal challenge at both pre- and post-intervention visits. Subjective feelings of hunger, fullness, desire to eat, prospective consumption, and a composite appetite score are measured by visual analog scales (mm).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in fasting and postprandial plasma Malondialdehyde (MDA)</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, 4 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>The concentration of MDA before and after the high saturated fat meal challenge at both pre- and post-intervention visits (nmol/mL).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in fasting and postprandial plasma total antioxidant capacity</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, 4 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Total antioxidant capacity before and after the high saturated fat meal challenge at both pre- and post-intervention visits (U/mL).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in fasting and postprandial plasma inflammatory cytokine concentrations</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, 4 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>The concentration of interleukin-1 beta, C reactive protein, tumor-necrosis factor-alpha, and interleukin-6 before and after the high saturated fat meal challenge at both pre- and post-intervention visits (pg/mL).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in fasting and postprandial plasma markers of coagulation potential</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, 4 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>The concentration of plasminogen activator inhibitor-1, and tissue factor before and after the high saturated fat meal challenge at both pre- and post-intervention visits (pg/mL).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in fasting and postprandial plasma angiopoietin-like (ANGPTL) proteins</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, 4 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>The concentration of ANGPTL 3, ANGPTL 4, and ANGPTL 8 before and after the high saturated fat meal challenge at both pre- and post-intervention visits (ng/mL).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in fasting insulin resistance metrics</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, 4 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Homeostatic Model Assessment for Insulin Resistance (HOMA-IR) and Homeostatic Model Assessment for β-cell function (HOMA-B) will be calculated from fasting insulin and glucose measures before and after the 28-day intervention.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in fasting serum hepatic enzymes</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 4 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Aspartate aminotransferase (AST), Alanine aminotransferase (ALT), Alkaline phosphatase (ALP), Gamma-Glutamyl Transferase (GGT) (U/L)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in fasting serum hepatic proteins</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 4 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Total protein and albumin (g/dL)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in fasting serum bilirubin</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 4 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Total total bilirubin, direct bilirubin, and indirect bilirubin (mg/dL)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in additional fasting and postprandial plasma appetite control hormones concentrations</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, 4 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>The concentration of additional plasma appetite control hormones before and after the high saturated fat meal challenge at both pre- and post-intervention visits. Additional appetite control hormones include Glucagon-like peptide-1 (GLP-1), Gastric inhibitory peptide (GIP), Pancreatic Polypeptide (PP) (pg/mL)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in fasting and postprandial plasma antioxidant parameters</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, 4 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Glutathione peroxidase activity, superoxide dismutase activity, glutathione-s-transferase activity before and after the high saturated fat meal challenge at both pre- and post-intervention visits (U/mL).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in additional fasting and postprandial plasma inflammatory cytokine concentrations</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, 4 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>The concentration of monocyte chemoattractant protein-1, and interleukin-10 before and after the high saturated fat meal challenge at both pre- and post-intervention visits (pg/mL).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in additional fasting and postprandial plasma markers of coagulation potential</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, 4 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>The concentration of Von Willebrand factor, tissue factor pathway inhibitor, fibrinogen and D-dimer before and after the high saturated fat meal challenge at both pre- and post-intervention visits (pg/mL).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in acute dietary intake</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, 4 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>One-day food logs will be used to record all foods and beverages consumed on testing days</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Change in blood pressure</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, 4 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Systolic and diastolic blood pressure (mmHg)</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Change in body weight</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, 4 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>body weight (kg)</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Change in body composition</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, 4 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>BodPod will be used to measure body fat percentage (body fat %)</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Change in diet composition</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, week 2, week 4</time_frame>
    <description>3-day food logs will be used to record foods and beverages consumed before and during the 28-day intervention period</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Change in fasting and postprandial fatty acid composition</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, 4 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Fatty acid composition of plasma before and after the high saturated fat meal challenge at pre- and post-intervention visits (% total triglycerides).</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Change in fasting tocopherol concentrations</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, 4 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Plasma tocopherol concentrations (ug/ml)</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Change in anthropometric circumferences</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, 4 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>hip and waist circumferences (cm)</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Change in resting metabolic rate</measure>
    <time_frame>Screening</time_frame>
    <description>Resting metabolic rate (RMR) will be measured for 30 minutes on the TrueOne 2400 (Parvo Medics, Sandy, UT)</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Change in perceived stress</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, 4 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Perceived Stress Scale will be administered and scored to determine stress levels</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Change in anxiety</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, 4 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>The State Trait Anxiety Inventory will be administered and scored to determine anxiety levels.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Change in self reported physical activity levels</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, 2 weeks, 4 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>The International Physical Activity Questionnaire will be used to collect self-reported average physical activity levels (met/min)</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Change in body Mass Index (BMI)</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, 4 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>BMI will be calculated based on height and weight measures (kg/m2)</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>4</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">80</enrollment>
  <condition>Dyslipidemias</condition>
  <condition>Overweight and Obesity</condition>
  <condition>Nutrition, Healthy</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>CSO LOW</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants are given foods enriched with cottonseed oil and instructed on how to substitute study foods into their diet to maintain caloric balance.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>CSO MID</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants are given foods enriched with cottonseed oil and instructed on how to substitute study foods into their diet to maintain caloric balance.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>CSO HIGH</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants are given foods enriched with cottonseed oil and instructed on how to substitute study foods into their diet to maintain caloric balance.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>CONTROL</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants are given foods enriched with a mixture of oils and instructed on how to substitute study foods into their diet to maintain caloric balance.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>CSO LOW</intervention_name>
    <description>Participants are provided a breakfast shake and a snack daily that delivers 10% of the participant's estimated energy needs as cottonseed oil for 28 days.</description>
    <arm_group_label>CSO LOW</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>CSO MID</intervention_name>
    <description>Participants are provided a breakfast shake and a snack daily that delivers 20% of the participant's estimated energy needs as cottonseed oil for 28 days.</description>
    <arm_group_label>CSO MID</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>CSO HIGH</intervention_name>
    <description>Participants are provided a breakfast shake and a snack daily that delivers 30% of the participant's estimated energy needs as cottonseed oil for 28 days.</description>
    <arm_group_label>CSO HIGH</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>CONTROL</intervention_name>
    <description>Participants are provided a breakfast shake and a snack daily that delivers 10% of the participant's estimated energy needs as a mixture of oils that match the average American fat intake for 28 days.</description>
    <arm_group_label>CONTROL</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  25-75-year-old men and women at increased risk for cardiovascular disease. Increased&#xD;
             risk for cardiovascular disease will be defined by either elevated cholesterol&#xD;
             profiles -or- overweight/obesity.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Elevated cholesterol profiles will be defined as:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  &quot;Borderline High&quot; and/or &quot;at risk&quot; in two or more of the following variables (total&#xD;
             cholesterol: 180-239 mg/dL, LDL cholesterol 110-159 mg/dL, triglycerides 130-199&#xD;
             mg/dL) --or---&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  &quot;High&quot; in total cholesterol (240 mg/dL and higher), LDL (160 mg/dL or higher), or&#xD;
             triglycerides (between 200 - 350 mg/dl).&#xD;
&#xD;
        Overweight/obesity will be defined by body mass index (overweight 25-29.9 kg/m2 or obesity&#xD;
        30 kg/m2 or greater).&#xD;
&#xD;
        Exclusion Criteria:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Probable familial hypercholesterolemia, defined by: total cholesterol greater than 290&#xD;
             mg/dL or LDL levels greater than 190 mg/dL plus a family history of myocardial&#xD;
             infarction (MI) before 50 years of age in a 2nd-degree relative or below age 60 in a&#xD;
             1st-degree relative.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  women on hormone replacement therapy for less than 2 years&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  women who are pregnant&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  individuals who regularly exercise more than 3 h/w&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  weight gain or loss of more than 5% of their body weight in the past 3 months&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  plans to begin a weight loss/exercise regimen during the trial&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  history of medical or surgical events that could affect digestion or swallowing&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  gastrointestinal surgeries, conditions or disorders,&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  any chronic diseases (including moderate to severe asthma, chronic lung disease, and&#xD;
             kidney disease),&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  metabolic diseases&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  atherosclerosis&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  previous MI or stroke&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  cancer&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  fasting blood glucose levels greater than 126 mg/dL&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  blood pressure greater than 180/120 mmHg&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  medication use affecting digestion and absorption, metabolism (e.g., thyroid meds),&#xD;
             lipid-lowering medications, medications for diabetes, steroid/hormone therapies, or&#xD;
             current antibiotic cycles&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  medically prescribed or special diets&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Food allergies (specific to the foods in the study, including wheat, dairy, and&#xD;
             cottonseed oil)&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  fish oil supplements,&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  excessive alcohol use (greater than 3 drinks/d for men; greater than 2 drinks/d for&#xD;
             women)&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  tobacco or nicotine use&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  underweight BMI (&lt;18.5 kg/m2)&#xD;
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>25 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>75 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Jamie A Cooper, Ph.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Georgia</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Jamie A Cooper, Ph.D.</last_name>
    <phone>706-542-4903</phone>
    <email>jamie.cooper@uga.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Georgia</name>
      <address>
        <city>Athens</city>
        <state>Georgia</state>
        <zip>30602</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Jamie A Cooper, Ph.D.</last_name>
      <phone>706-542-4903</phone>
      <email>jamie.cooper@uga.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Jamie A Cooper, Ph.D.</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>April 2023</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>January 5, 2023</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 13, 2023</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">January 17, 2023</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 23, 2023</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 23, 2023</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">April 25, 2023</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Georgia</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Jamie Cooper, PhD</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Professor, Director of UGA Obesity Initiative</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Overweight</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Dyslipidemias</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

