<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="9876">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 09, 2023</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT05688332</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>202112030076</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>IRB Number: 00011000</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>IORG Number: 0009227</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>FWA Number: 00026270</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT05688332</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Glycaemic &amp; Cardiovascular Treatment Outcomes of Voglibose Vs Glibenclamide Added to Metformin in T2DM Patients</brief_title>
  <acronym>VMGMProtocol</acronym>
  <official_title>Comparison of Glycaemic and Cardiovascular Treatment Outcomes of Voglibose Versus Glibenclamide Added to Metformin in T2DM Patients in Zambia: An Open-label Randomised Clinical Trial</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Zambia</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University Teaching Hospital, Lusaka, Zambia</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Zambia</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>No</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The goal of this clinical trial is to compare blood-sugar and blood circulatory system&#xD;
      risk-position in type 2 diabetes patients on voglibose versus those on glybenclamide when the&#xD;
      two drugs are added to metformin because metformin alone is not controlling the blood-sugar&#xD;
      well. The results of this trial will help in improving the health and treatment results of&#xD;
      the type 2 diabetic patients.&#xD;
&#xD;
      The main question the trial aims to answer is whether there is a difference in blood-sugar&#xD;
      and blood circulatory system treatment results between voglibose + metformin and&#xD;
      glibenclamide + metformin treatment combinations.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Participants that agree to participate in the trial will be asked to provide a sample of&#xD;
      blood so that the following measurable laboratory factors will be used to compare any&#xD;
      differences in treatment results between the two treatment groups from the beginning to the&#xD;
      end of the trial:&#xD;
&#xD;
        -  Total Cholesterol (TC),&#xD;
&#xD;
        -  Low Density Lipoproteins (LDL-c),&#xD;
&#xD;
        -  High Density Lipoproteins (HDL-c),&#xD;
&#xD;
        -  Fasting Triglycerides (FTG),&#xD;
&#xD;
        -  Fasting blood sugar (FBS),&#xD;
&#xD;
        -  Post prandial blood sugar (PPBG),&#xD;
&#xD;
        -  Glycated hemoglobin (HbA1c) correlated to hemoglobin level,&#xD;
&#xD;
        -  creatinine,&#xD;
&#xD;
        -  blood urea and&#xD;
&#xD;
        -  electrolytes (K+, Na+, Cl-).&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      BACKGROUND: Diabetes is an increasingly important risk factor for CVD, and individuals with&#xD;
      diabetes as compared to those without diabetes continue to have an increased risk of both&#xD;
      all-cause and cardiovascular mortality. It can be classified as type 1 diabetes mellitus&#xD;
      (T1DM), type 2 diabetes mellitus (T2DM), gestational diabetes mellitus (GDM) and others.&#xD;
      Metformin is a T2DM first line Oral Hypoglycaemic Agent (OHA). It usually requires a second&#xD;
      line add-on drug if blood glucose control is not on target. The add-on drug can either be&#xD;
      insulin, an injectable incretin mimetic, or an OHA. The choice of the OHA should be&#xD;
      considered with regard to improving the glycaemic control as well as reducing the&#xD;
      cardiovascular disease risk.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Glibenclamide, a Sulphonylurea, is a commonly used OHA in Zambia. Sulphonylureas are&#xD;
      associated with hypoglycaemia and arrhythmias. On the other hand Voglibose, an alpha&#xD;
      glucosidase inhibitor (AGI), is not associated with hypoglycaemia or with negative&#xD;
      cardiovascular events. The alpha-glucosidase inhibitors (AGIs), (acarbose, voglibose and&#xD;
      miglitol) reduce postprandial hyperglycaemia by reducing the absorption of glucose in the&#xD;
      gastrointestinal tract after a carbohydrate meal. AGIs are more effective at lowering&#xD;
      postprandial insulin levels than Sulphonylureas. Reduced postpradial glycaemia prevents&#xD;
      macrovascular complications. Since maize (a carbohydrate) is a staple food in Zambia, there&#xD;
      is need to investigate the glycaemic control in patients with T2DM using voglibose which is&#xD;
      as affordable as glibenclamide.&#xD;
&#xD;
      The main aim of this study will be to investigate the extent of glycaemic control and&#xD;
      cardiovascular risk parameter effects of voglibose versus glibenclamide add-on therapies in&#xD;
      Zambian patients with T2DM as we do not have published studies on these parameters in our&#xD;
      patients.&#xD;
&#xD;
      METHODOLOGY: This study will be a 12 weeks dual-center prospective interventional open-label&#xD;
      randomised controlled trial to comparatively evaluate the glycaemic and cardiovascular&#xD;
      treatment outcomes of voglibose versus glibenclamide add-on therapies in native Zambian&#xD;
      patients with type 2 diabetes inadequately controlled on 2g/day of metformin monotherapy. In&#xD;
      this study, glycaemic and cardiovascular parameters will be quantified and classified in the&#xD;
      laboratory to determine extent of glycaemic control and cardiovascular risk reduction as&#xD;
      patients report for their scheduled visits at the adult diabetes OPD clinics at University&#xD;
      Teaching Hospital and Matero General Hospital.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Participants to be included will be male and female native Zambian patients aged 22 to 59&#xD;
      years on metformin monotherapy for at least 12 weeks with HbA1c&gt; 7.0%. They will be randomly&#xD;
      allocated to two treatment arms i.e the voglibose-metformin or the glibenclamide-metformin&#xD;
      regimen in a 1:1 computer generated randomisation. The participants will then be followed up&#xD;
      to the 6th and 12th week for data collection. A comparative analysis of the expected outcome&#xD;
      of interest which is the change in the extent of glycaemic control and cardiovascular risk&#xD;
      reduction in the two groups will be done at the 12th week.&#xD;
&#xD;
      This study is significant as it will help to determine the glycaemic and cardiovascular risk&#xD;
      status of patients with type 2 diabetes mellitus on voglibose and glibenclamide, thereby&#xD;
      ascertain improvement in their healthcare and treatment outcomes.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">August 2023</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2024</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2023</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in mean Glycated Hemoglobin (HbA1c) levels</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline &amp; Week 6</time_frame>
    <description>The null hypothesis is that there is no significant difference between the voglibose and glibenclamide treatment groups in the change in mean HbA1c levels after 6 weeks of add-on therapy to metformin in the T2DM patients (i.e. H0: µ1 = µ2 where µ1 is the mean HbA1c change in the glibenclamide group and µ2 is the mean HbA1c change in the voglibose group). The alternative hypothesis is that there is a significant difference between the voglibose and glibenclamide groups in the change in mean HbA1c levels after 6 weeks of add-on therapy to metformin in the T2DM patients (i.e. H1: µ1 ≠ µ2).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in mean Glycated Hemoglobin (HbA1c) levels</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline &amp; Week 12</time_frame>
    <description>The null hypothesis is that there is no significant difference between the voglibose and glibenclamide treatment groups in the change in mean HbA1c levels after 12 weeks of add-on therapy to metformin in the T2DM patients (i.e. H0: µ1 = µ2 where µ1 is the mean HbA1c change in the glibenclamide group and µ2 is the mean HbA1c change in the voglibose group). The alternative hypothesis is that there is a significant difference between the voglibose and glibenclamide groups in the change in mean HbA1c levels after 12 weeks of add-on therapy to metformin in the T2DM patients (i.e. H1: µ1 ≠ µ2).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Glycemic control with regard to Fasting Plasma Glucose (FPG)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline &amp; week 6</time_frame>
    <description>Differences in change in glycemic control with regard to FPG: The null hypothesis is that there is no significant difference between the voglibose and glibenclamide treatment groups in the mean FPG change (i.e. H0: µ1 = µ2 where µ1 and µ2 represent the mean FPG change in the glibenclamide and voglibose groups respectively). The alternative hypothesis is that there is a difference between the voglibose and glibenclamide groups in the mean changes of FPG (i.e. H1: µ1 ≠ µ2).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in glycemic control with regard to Fasting Plasma Glucose (FPG)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline &amp; week 12</time_frame>
    <description>Differences in change in glycemic control with regard to FPG: The null hypothesis is that there is no significant difference between the voglibose and glibenclamide treatment groups in the mean FPG change (i.e. H0: µ1 = µ2 where µ1 and µ2 represent the mean FPG change in the glibenclamide and voglibose groups respectively). The alternative hypothesis is that there is a difference between the voglibose and glibenclamide groups in the mean changes of FPG (i.e. H1: µ1 ≠ µ2).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in glycemic control with regard to Post Prandial Blood Glucose (PPBG)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline &amp; week 6</time_frame>
    <description>Differences in Change in glycemic control with regard to PPBG: The null hypothesis is that there is no significant difference between the voglibose and glibenclamide treatment groups in the mean PPBG change (i.e. H0: µ1 = µ2 where µ1 and µ2 represent the mean PPBG change in the glibenclamide and voglibose groups respectively). The alternative hypothesis is that there is a difference between the voglibose and glibenclamide groups in the mean changes of PPBG (i.e. H1: µ1 ≠ µ2).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in glycemic control with regard to Post Prandial Blood Glucose (PPBG)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline &amp; week 12</time_frame>
    <description>Differences in change in glycemic control with regard to PPBG: The null hypothesis is that there is no significant difference between the voglibose and glibenclamide treatment groups in the mean PPBG change (i.e. H0: µ1 = µ2 where µ1 and µ2 represent the mean PPBG change in the glibenclamide and voglibose groups respectively). The alternative hypothesis is that there is a difference between the voglibose and glibenclamide groups in the mean changes of PPBG (i.e. H1: µ1 ≠ µ2).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Lipid profile (LDL-c, HDL-c, TC, TG) comparison</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline &amp; Week 6</time_frame>
    <description>Lipid profile (LDL-c, HDL-c, TC, TG) comparison: The null hypothesis is that there is no difference between the voglibose and glibenclamide groups in the mean changes in lipid profile (i.e. H0: µ1 = µ2 where µ1 and µ2 represent the mean changes in lipid profile in the glibenclamide and voglibose groups respectively). The alternative hypothesis is that there is a difference between voglibose and glibenclamide groups in the mean changes in lipid profile (i.e. H1: µ1 ≠ µ2).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Lipid profile (LDL-c, HDL-c, TC, TG) comparison</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline &amp; Week 12</time_frame>
    <description>Lipid profile (LDL-c, HDL-c, TC, TG) comparison: The null hypothesis is that there is no difference between the voglibose and glibenclamide groups in the mean changes in lipid profile (i.e. H0: µ1 = µ2 where µ1 and µ2 represent the mean changes in lipid profile in the glibenclamide and voglibose groups respectively). The alternative hypothesis is that there is a difference between voglibose and glibenclamide groups in the mean changes in lipid profile (i.e. H1: µ1 ≠ µ2).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Anthropometric parameter changes in BMI</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline &amp; Week 6</time_frame>
    <description>Anthropometric parameter changes in BMI: The null hypothesis is that there is no difference between the voglibose and glibenclamide groups in the mean anthropometric parameter changes (i.e. H0: µ1 = µ2 where µ1 and µ2 represent the mean anthropometric parameter changes in the glibenclamide and voglibose groups respectively). The alternative hypothesis is that there is a difference between voglibose and glibenclamide groups in the mean anthropometric parameter changes (i.e. H1: µ1 ≠ µ2).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Anthropometric parameter changes in BMI</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline &amp; Week 12</time_frame>
    <description>Anthropometric parameter changes in BMI: The null hypothesis is that there is no difference between the voglibose and glibenclamide groups in the mean anthropometric parameter changes (i.e. H0: µ1 = µ2 where µ1 and µ2 represent the mean anthropometric parameter changes in the glibenclamide and voglibose groups respectively). The alternative hypothesis is that there is a difference between voglibose and glibenclamide groups in the mean anthropometric parameter changes (i.e. H1: µ1 ≠ µ2).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Anthropometric parameter changes in Waist Circumference (WC)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline &amp; Week 6</time_frame>
    <description>Anthropometric parameter changes in WC: The null hypothesis is that there is no difference between the voglibose and glibenclamide groups in the mean anthropometric parameter changes (i.e. H0: µ1 = µ2 where µ1 and µ2 represent the mean anthropometric parameter changes in the glibenclamide and voglibose groups respectively). The alternative hypothesis is that there is a difference between voglibose and glibenclamide groups in the mean anthropometric parameter changes (i.e. H1: µ1 ≠ µ2).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Anthropometric parameter changes in Waist Circumference (WC)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline &amp; Week 12</time_frame>
    <description>Anthropometric parameter changes in WC: The null hypothesis is that there is no difference between the voglibose and glibenclamide groups in the mean anthropometric parameter changes (i.e. H0: µ1 = µ2 where µ1 and µ2 represent the mean anthropometric parameter changes in the glibenclamide and voglibose groups respectively). The alternative hypothesis is that there is a difference between voglibose and glibenclamide groups in the mean anthropometric parameter changes (i.e. H1: µ1 ≠ µ2).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Drug related AEs</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline &amp; Week 6</time_frame>
    <description>Drug related AEs: The null hypothesis is that there is no difference between the proportion of participants experiencing drug related AEs in the voglibose and glibenclamide groups (i.e. H0: p1 = p2 where p1 and p2 represent the proportion of participants experiencing a drug related AE in the glibenclamide and voglibose groups, respectively). The alternative hypothesis is that there is a difference between the proportion of participants experiencing drug related AEs in the voglibose and glibenclamide groups (i.e. H1: p1 ≠ p2).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Drug related AEs</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline &amp; Week 12</time_frame>
    <description>Drug related AEs: The null hypothesis is that there is no difference between the proportion of participants experiencing drug related AEs in the voglibose and glibenclamide groups (i.e. H0: p1 = p2 where p1 and p2 represent the proportion of participants experiencing a drug related AE in the glibenclamide and voglibose groups, respectively). The alternative hypothesis is that there is a difference between the proportion of participants experiencing drug related AEs in the voglibose and glibenclamide groups (i.e. H1: p1 ≠ p2).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">118</enrollment>
  <condition>Diabetes Mellitus Type 2 Without Complication</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Voglibose + Metformin (Group B)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>in treatment group B, 59 participants will randomly assigned to the voglibose 0.2 or 0.3mg + metformin 500 or 850mg treatment combination to be taken 3 times daily, during or after meals. After 6 to 12 days the dose will be individually titrated on the basis of blood glucose measurements. A slow increase of dose may improve gastrointestinal tolerability. In this study, 0.9mg voglibose and 2500 mg metformin will not be exceeded daily.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Glibenclamide + Metformin (Group A)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>In treatment group A, 59 participants will be randomly allocated to the glibenclamide 5mg O.D + metformin 500mg TDS regimen.&#xD;
In this study, 15mg glibenclamide and 2500 mg metformin will not be exceeded daily.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Voglibose + Metformin</intervention_name>
    <description>In treatment group B, 59 participants will also be randomly assigned to the voglibose 0.2/0.3mg + metformin 500mg treatment combination to be taken orally 3 times daily (TDS), during or after meals with dose titration at day 6 and 12 if the average fasting blood glucose (FBG) level is ≥7 mmol/L (126 mg/dL) and then dosage will be maintained for the remainder of the treatment period Participants in the intervention group initially receiving voglibose 0.2mg + metformin 500mg TDS will be dose-titrated to voglibose 0.3mg +metformin 850mg TDS.&#xD;
The duration of therapy for each participant will be 12 weeks, which is the minimum period for evaluating the primary endpoint.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Voglibose + Metformin (Group B)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Glibenclamide + Metformin</intervention_name>
    <description>The drugs (glibenclamide + metformin), in the control or comparator group will also be taken orally, glibenclamide once a day (OD) before meals, and metformin three times a day (TDS) also before meals. These drugs will also be taken with a dose-titration at days 6 and 12 if the average is FBG level will be ≥ 7 mmol/L and the dose will be maintained for the remainder of the study period.&#xD;
The duration of therapy for each participant will be 12 weeks, which is the minimum period for evaluating the primary endpoint. In this group, participants will initially receive glibenclamide 5mg once daily (OD) + metformin 500mg TDS then will be dose-titrated to glibenclamide 10mg OD + metformin 850 TDS.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Glibenclamide + Metformin (Group A)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  In order to be eligible to participate in this study, an individual must meet all of&#xD;
             the following criteria:&#xD;
&#xD;
               -  Provision of signed and dated informed consent form.&#xD;
&#xD;
               -  Stated willingness to comply with all study1 procedures and availability for the&#xD;
                  durtion of the study.&#xD;
&#xD;
               -  Male or female, aged 22-59 years.&#xD;
&#xD;
               -  In good general health as evidenced by medical history, diagnosed with T2DM and&#xD;
                  on tolerated dose of at least 2g/day of metformin monotherapy.&#xD;
&#xD;
               -  Ability to take oral medication and be willing to adhere to the medication&#xD;
                  regimen through out the study period.&#xD;
&#xD;
               -  For females of reproductive potential use of highly effective contraception.&#xD;
&#xD;
               -  Native-Zambian participants&#xD;
&#xD;
               -  Must be on metformin monotherapy for 12 weeks or longer.&#xD;
&#xD;
               -  Glycated haemoglobin (HbA1c) must be &gt;7.0% within 12 weeks before screening.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Exclusion Criteria:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  An individual who meets any of the following criteria will be excluded from&#xD;
             participation in this study:&#xD;
&#xD;
               -  Hypersensitivity or contraindication to AGIs&#xD;
&#xD;
               -  Hypersensitivity or contraindication to SUs&#xD;
&#xD;
               -  Type 2 diabetes patients with pregnancy or lactation&#xD;
&#xD;
               -  Patients with acute complications like diabetic ketoacidosis, or hyperosmolar&#xD;
                  hyperglycaemic state at the time of screening&#xD;
&#xD;
               -  Patients with established cardiovascular disease, e.g.; HF, coronary artery&#xD;
                  disease&#xD;
&#xD;
               -  Patients with altered haemoglobin levels, e.g.; in conditions like anaemias and&#xD;
                  haemoglobimopathies such as thalassemia&#xD;
&#xD;
               -  Patients on concomitant corticosteroid therapy.&#xD;
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>22 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>59 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Brown Kamanga, MMed</last_name>
    <phone>+260 97 2758137</phone>
    <email>brownkamanga@gmail.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <reference>
    <citation>American Diabetes Association Professional Practice Committee. 2. Classification and Diagnosis of Diabetes: Standards of Medical Care in Diabetes-2022. Diabetes Care. 2022 Jan 1;45(Suppl 1):S17-S38. doi: 10.2337/dc22-S002.</citation>
    <PMID>34964875</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Rosenquist KJ, Fox CS. Mortality Trends in Type 2 Diabetes. In: Cowie CC, Casagrande SS, Menke A, Cissell MA, Eberhardt MS, Meigs JB, Gregg EW, Knowler WC, Barrett-Connor E, Becker DJ, Brancati FL, Boyko EJ, Herman WH, Howard BV, Narayan KMV, Rewers M, Fradkin JE, editors. Diabetes in America. 3rd edition. Bethesda (MD): National Institute of Diabetes and Digestive and Kidney Diseases (US); 2018 Aug. CHAPTER 36. Available from http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/books/NBK568010/</citation>
    <PMID>33651566</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Coleman RL, Scott CAB, Lang Z, Bethel MA, Tuomilehto J, Holman RR. Meta-analysis of the impact of alpha-glucosidase inhibitors on incident diabetes and cardiovascular outcomes. Cardiovasc Diabetol. 2019 Oct 17;18(1):135. doi: 10.1186/s12933-019-0933-y.</citation>
    <PMID>31623625</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Akmal M, Wadhwa R. Alpha Glucosidase Inhibitors. 2022 Aug 12. In: StatPearls [Internet]. Treasure Island (FL): StatPearls Publishing; 2023 Jan-. Available from http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/books/NBK557848/</citation>
    <PMID>32496728</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>May 2023</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>December 27, 2022</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 14, 2023</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">January 18, 2023</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 10, 2023</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 10, 2023</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 11, 2023</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Zambia</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Lawrence Mukela</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Principal Investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>voglibose</keyword>
  <keyword>Metformin</keyword>
  <keyword>Glibenclamide</keyword>
  <keyword>Outcomes</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Diabetes Mellitus, Type 2</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Metformin</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Glyburide</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Voglibose</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Yes</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>Data obtained through this study may be provided to qualified researchers with academic interest in diabetes mellitus. Data or samples shared will be coded, with no PHI included. Approval of the request and execution of all applicable agreements (i.e. a material transfer agreement) are prerequisites to the sharing of data with the requesting parties.</ipd_description>
    <ipd_info_type>Study Protocol</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_info_type>Statistical Analysis Plan (SAP)</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_info_type>Informed Consent Form (ICF)</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_info_type>Clinical Study Report (CSR)</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_time_frame>Data requests can be submitted starting 9 months after article publication and the data will be made accessible for up to 24 months. Extensions will be considered on a case-by-case basis.</ipd_time_frame>
    <ipd_access_criteria>Access to trial IPD can be requested by qualified researchers engaging in independent scientific research, and will be provided following review and approval of a research proposal and Statistical Analysis Plan (SAP) and execution of a Data Sharing Agreement (DSA). For more information or to submit a request, please contact lawrencemukela@gmail.com</ipd_access_criteria>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

