<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="9516">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 09, 2023</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT05696262</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>N202207044</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT05696262</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>6 Minutes Walking Program for Terminally Ill Patients at Home or in an Institution</brief_title>
  <official_title>Effects of 6-minute Walking Exercise in Advanced Cancer and Non-cancer Patients: a Randomized Controlled Trial</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Taipei Medical University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Taipei Medical University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study was conducted with a single-blind, randomized control method for 120 participants,&#xD;
      60 in the regular care group and 60 in the exercise intervention group. Those who meet the&#xD;
      admission criteria will be contacted by phone and explained the purpose of the study. After&#xD;
      asking for and obtaining consent, those who are willing to sign the consent form will be&#xD;
      divided into groups and go to the home with the home care worker for the study. A suitable&#xD;
      space was arranged for a 6-minute explanation and demonstration of walking exercise and a&#xD;
      structured questionnaire to be filled out by the participant (the Barr's scale, Koch's scale&#xD;
      and cognitive function assessment in the basic data were filled out by the facilitator), and&#xD;
      the facilitator accompanied the participant during the process, giving explanations for&#xD;
      unclear points to facilitate the completion of the questionnaire and to achieve a valid&#xD;
      questionnaire. A trained research assistant was responsible for recruiting cases and&#xD;
      receiving a study number and corresponding group assignment. Stratified random assignment&#xD;
      (1:1) was used to divide the exercise intervention group and the usual care group. The study&#xD;
      was listed using a randomized use of replacement blocks (block size 4). The assignment&#xD;
      sequence was only available to the program facilitator and was not known to the other staff.&#xD;
      Interventional measures Routine care group: A primary care team of physicians and nurse&#xD;
      practitioners visited at least once a month for: (1) an initial intake visit (60-90 minutes)&#xD;
      to provide a holistic assessment of disease intensity and prognosis, psychological distress,&#xD;
      and social support; (2) at least one home care visit per month (30-60 minutes); (3) a&#xD;
      telephone (4) Provide caregivers with social software and telepresence to solve caregiving&#xD;
      problems (5) Provide exercise diaries to record daily activities of daily living (including&#xD;
      vital signs, mobility, and fatigue). Exercise intervention group: In addition to the regular&#xD;
      care group model, the intervention measure: 6 minute walk test (6MWT) is the simplest and&#xD;
      most cost effective way to assess exercise. Pre-intervention equipment: 6-minute walk&#xD;
      exercise video, yardstick, distance marker cone, measuring tape, exercise diary, smart&#xD;
      bracelet, all subjects were provided with 6-minute walk exercise video and related equipment&#xD;
      by the facilitator at intake. Before the test: explain the pre and post-test precautions,&#xD;
      demonstrate the correct way to perform the test, and inform the patient to perform the test&#xD;
      in a comfortable manner. In addition, the case was asked to wear the bracelet 24 hours a day&#xD;
      for 7 days a week to observe the sleep quality. During the intervention period, if a case has&#xD;
      the following conditions, the principle of implementation is as follows: (1) if the case has&#xD;
      good walking ability, the case will be reminded to comply with the intervention (or keep the&#xD;
      original physical activity) through telephone care and exercise diary; (2) if the case is&#xD;
      physically able to walk but has low willingness to perform the 6-minute walk due to various&#xD;
      conditions, the case will be reminded by family members or followed up by the researcher by&#xD;
      telephone to improve the implementation rate; (3) if the case has difficulty getting out of&#xD;
      bed due to the progress of the disease or treatment factors. (3) Cases with difficulty in&#xD;
      getting out of bed or at risk of falling due to the progress of the disease or treatment&#xD;
      factors; (4) Cases using oxygen to walk for 6 minutes in the area of the oxygen nasal cannula&#xD;
      and tubing; if there is a risk of falling or injury during the procedure, please stop all&#xD;
      activities immediately and ask the caregiver to monitor the vital signs and notify the&#xD;
      facilitator and home care provider. If the patient needs to be taken to the hospital for&#xD;
      treatment, assist in contacting the ambulance and send to the nearest hospital or the&#xD;
      hospital where the patient usually goes for treatment; the host will visit the hospital and&#xD;
      understand the situation and fill in the abnormal events. Outcome measurement: The family,&#xD;
      primary caregiver, and the case are instructed to correctly measure the number of laps,&#xD;
      distance, time, and number of times to walk, and to give instructions. Outcome measures were&#xD;
      collected by the co-facilitators at intake, month 1, month 2, month 3, and month 6, and all&#xD;
      data and assessment scales were tracked.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">January 16, 2023</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 31, 2025</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 31, 2025</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Supportive Care</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double (Participant, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Steps count</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from Baseline post exercise 5 min</time_frame>
    <description>exercise outcome using pedometer</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Steps count</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from Baseline at 6 month.</time_frame>
    <description>exercise outcome using pedometer</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Depression--Patient Health Questionnaire (PHQ-9)</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from Baseline post exercise 5 min</time_frame>
    <description>The PHQ-9 is the depression module, which scores each of the nine DSM-IV criteria as &quot;0&quot; (not at all) to &quot;3&quot; (nearly every day). It has been validated for use in primary care. It is not a screening tool for depression but it is used to monitor the severity of depression and response to treatment. high score mean higher emotion distress.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Depression--Patient Health Questionnaire (PHQ-9)</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from Baseline at 6 month.</time_frame>
    <description>The PHQ-9 is the depression module, which scores each of the nine DSM-IV criteria as &quot;0&quot; (not at all) to &quot;3&quot; (nearly every day). It has been validated for use in primary care. It is not a screening tool for depression but it is used to monitor the severity of depression and response to treatment. high score mean higher emotion distress.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>cancer fatigue--BFI</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from Baseline post exercise 5 min</time_frame>
    <description>severity of fatigue level; measurement tool: Brief Fatigue Index</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>cancer fatigue--BFI</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from Baseline at 6 month.</time_frame>
    <description>severity of fatigue level; measurement tool: Brief Fatigue Index</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Quality of Life--EQ5D-5L</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline and six month.</time_frame>
    <description>a 5-digit number that describes the patient's health state. The score increase means good quality of life.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Symptom Assessment---Chinese version of the Edmonton Symptom Assessment System，C-ESAS</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline</time_frame>
    <description>The ESAS includes 11 symptoms: pain, tiredness, nausea, depression, anxiety, drowsiness, appetite, sleep, well-being, shortness of breath, and other. It uses a 0-10 numerical scale: 0 shows the absence of a symptom, and 10 shows the worst experience of the symptom.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Symptom Assessment---Chinese version of the Edmonton Symptom Assessment System，C-ESAS</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from Baseline at 6 month.</time_frame>
    <description>The ESAS includes 11 symptoms: pain, tiredness, nausea, depression, anxiety, drowsiness, appetite, sleep, well-being, shortness of breath, and other. It uses a 0-10 numerical scale: 0 shows the absence of a symptom, and 10 shows the worst experience of the symptom.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Smart bracelet_Heart rate variability (HRV)</measure>
    <time_frame>Continue wear bracelet five days to record HRV data.</time_frame>
    <description>HRV is the physiological phenomenon of the variation in the time interval between consecutive heartbeats in milliseconds. A normal, healthy heart does not tick evenly like a metronome, but instead, when looking at the milliseconds between heartbeats, there is constant variation.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Trial Outcome Index (TOI)</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from Baseline post exercise 5 min</time_frame>
    <description>TOI is a useful tool to assess the physical and functional effects of treatment in patients. The higher score means higher outcome.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Trial Outcome Index (TOI)</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from Baseline at 6 month.</time_frame>
    <description>TOI is a useful tool to assess the physical and functional effects of treatment in patients. The higher score means higher outcome.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">120</enrollment>
  <condition>Walking Intervention</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>6-walking program</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Perform 6 minutes of walking exercise 3 times a day, 3 days a week, in a comfortable manner.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Usual care</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>Usual care</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>6-walking program</intervention_name>
    <description>Perform 6 minutes of walking exercise 3 times a day, 3 days a week, in a comfortable manner</description>
    <arm_group_label>6-walking program</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:&#xD;
&#xD;
          1. advanced cancer (cancer stage III or IV)&#xD;
&#xD;
          2. terminal ill disease&#xD;
&#xD;
          3. aged &gt;=20 years&#xD;
&#xD;
          4. ECOG stage 0-3&#xD;
&#xD;
          5. Life expectancy =&lt; 12 months&#xD;
&#xD;
        Exclusion Criteria:&#xD;
&#xD;
          1. unable to have normal conversation due to illness.&#xD;
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>20 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Tsai-Wei Huang, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>+886-2-27361661</phone>
    <phone_ext>6350</phone_ext>
    <email>tsaiwei@tmu.edu.tw</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <verification_date>January 2023</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>November 15, 2022</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 23, 2023</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">January 25, 2023</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 23, 2023</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 23, 2023</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">January 25, 2023</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Taipei Medical University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Tsai-Wei Huang</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

