<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="9011">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 09, 2023</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT05707169</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>R.22.09.1805 - 2022/09/06</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT05707169</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Comparison of Zero- and Two-centimeter Distance From Sapheno-femoral Junction in Laser Ablation of Varicose Vein</brief_title>
  <official_title>Comparison of Zero- and Two-centimeter Distance From Sapheno-femoral Junction in Laser Ablation of Long Saphenous Vein Incompetence: Evaluating the Kissing Technique</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Mansoura University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Mansoura University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      EVLA is used in in treating refluxing veins, commonly the GSV. The tip of catheter is usually&#xD;
      placed 2-2.5 cm distal to the sapheno-femoral junction. This technique theoretically provides&#xD;
      the lowest risk for endothermal heat-induced thrombosis (EHIT).&#xD;
&#xD;
      In the present study we aimed to evaluate the zero-distance technique (the kissing technique)&#xD;
      compared to 2-cm distance from SFJ valve in ablating incompetent GSV.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      INTRODUCTION Chronic venous disease (CVD) is one of the most common pathologies in the&#xD;
      general population of adults in both industrialized and developing countries. the most severe&#xD;
      form of CVD is venous ulceration with an overall prevalence of about 1 % in the adult&#xD;
      population, which increases with age and is more common in women and obese patients. Venous&#xD;
      ulcers significantly impair quality of life, and their treatment places a heavy financial&#xD;
      burden upon healthcare systems. Varicose veins (VVs) is a common disease in adults, and VVs&#xD;
      without skin changes are present in about 20% of the population, while active ulcers are&#xD;
      found in 0.5%.The traditional surgical treatment of VVs is high ligation of the great&#xD;
      saphenous vein (GSV), axial stripping and phlebotomy, but the postoperative clinical&#xD;
      recurrence is as high as 60%.4 Minimally invasive techniques, such as endovenous laser&#xD;
      ablation (EVLA) and radiofrequency ablation (RFA), have become widely used for the treatment&#xD;
      of VVS. Several reports have shown Several reports have shown that endovenous techniques are&#xD;
      as effective as traditional procedures.&#xD;
&#xD;
      EVLA is used in in treating refluxing veins, commonly the GSV. The tip of catheter is usually&#xD;
      placed 2-2.5 cm distal to the sapheno-femoral junction. This technique theoretically provides&#xD;
      the lowest risk for endothermal heat-induced thrombosis (EHIT).&#xD;
&#xD;
      In the present study we aimed to evaluate the zero-distance technique (the kissing technique)&#xD;
      compared to 2-cm distance from SFJ valve in ablating incompetent GSV. Postoperative quality&#xD;
      of life (QoL) analysis was assessed using the Aberdeen Varicose Vein Questionnaire (AVVQ) and&#xD;
      Venous Clinical Severity Score (VCSS).&#xD;
&#xD;
      Aim of the work: To compare laser therapy ablation of long saphenous vein reflux by&#xD;
      conventional and the kissing techniques on development of DVT, recurrence rate of VVs,&#xD;
      ulcer-free time, and health-related quality of life.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Patients and methods Study location: The study will be conducted at the department of&#xD;
      vascular surgery in Mansoura University, Faculty of Medicine, Mansoura, Egypt .&#xD;
&#xD;
      Type of study: Randomized Controlled Prospective study Study duration: 2 years: 2022-2024&#xD;
      Sample size: It will include all patients presented to our department fulfilling the&#xD;
      inclusion criteria.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Study population: The study will be conducted in patients with Incompetent long saphenous&#xD;
      vein with and without ulcer.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Inclusion criteria Primary symptomatic VVS (CEAP, C3-C6), sapheno-femoral junction (SFJ)&#xD;
      incompetence, and GSV reflux from the groin to below the knee Exclusion criteria included;&#xD;
      history of venous surgery, suspected or proven deep venous thrombosis, history of DVT, reflux&#xD;
      of deep veins to distal limb, duplication of GSV, and patients' refusal to participate in the&#xD;
      trial.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Data collection: The demographics, symptoms, and preoperative clinical data will be&#xD;
      collected.&#xD;
&#xD;
      History Data: including underlying medical conditions, any previous associated morbidity.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Examination: Venous examinations. Laboratory: Blood picture, Blood sugar level, Kidney&#xD;
      functions, Liver functions and Coagulation profile.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Imaging: Duplex US Method of Randomization: Computer-based Therapies Conventional Technique:&#xD;
      Endogenous Laser Ablation (EVLA) uses a laser fibre, which is inserted into the refluxing&#xD;
      vein via skin puncture. Using 1470 nm laser and a radial fibre for less discomfort. The&#xD;
      catheter is placed 2-2.5 cm distal to the sapheno-femoral junction. Tumescence with a mixture&#xD;
      of 20 mL 2% lidocaine, 1: 200,000 adrenaline and 20 mL 0.5% levobupivacaine in 1 L of 0.9%&#xD;
      saline.&#xD;
&#xD;
      The kissing technique: The catheter is positioned exactly at the terminal valve of the SFJ&#xD;
      (kissing the valve).&#xD;
&#xD;
      Follow up&#xD;
&#xD;
      Criteria for technical success will be:&#xD;
&#xD;
        1. Closed or absent GSV with absent reflux&#xD;
&#xD;
        2. A re-canalized GSV or treatment failure will be defined as an open segment of the&#xD;
           treated vein segment of &gt;10 cm in length.&#xD;
&#xD;
        3. All patients are followed in outpatient's settings at 1, 3, 6, 12, and 24 months after&#xD;
           surgery.&#xD;
&#xD;
        4. The operation time, number of punctures, intraoperative blood loss (determined by the&#xD;
           swabs weighed pre and postoperatively)&#xD;
&#xD;
        5. Recurrence of varicosities and any complications are recorded.&#xD;
&#xD;
      The criteria for assessment:&#xD;
&#xD;
        1. Assessment of Heat induced thrombosis&#xD;
&#xD;
        2. Ecchymosis was confirmed 72 h after operation when the lividity and congestion area was&#xD;
           &gt;1 cm2 in the affected limbs.&#xD;
&#xD;
        3. Skin burns were identified 72 h after operation when the skin was red and oedematous&#xD;
           according to the criteria for burns.&#xD;
&#xD;
        4. Recurrence was defined by both duplex ultrasound and the clinical examination. A&#xD;
           varicose vein that had not been observed before or previously been marked by the patient&#xD;
           on the AVVQ form was considered to be a recurrent varicose vein (owing to&#xD;
           neo-vascularization or dilation of pre-existing veins).7,11&#xD;
&#xD;
        5. Sensory impairment (numbness) that occurred around incisions was recorded based on the&#xD;
           patient's history and physical examination.&#xD;
&#xD;
      QoL assessment The diseased relation effect on QoL was determined using the AVVQ (Chinese&#xD;
      version), which assessed the specific effect on QoL and was scored from 0 (no effect of VVS&#xD;
      on QoL) to a theoretical maximum of 100.8 The VCSS (Chinese version) was also completed (for&#xD;
      the VCSS, 0 represents no significant venous disease and 30 is the maximum score), which is a&#xD;
      valid sensitive and responsive measure of the severity of VVs.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Statistical analysis&#xD;
&#xD;
      · The data will be analyzed using Statistical Package for the Social Sciences. The numerical&#xD;
      outcomes e.g. age is calculated as mean. Gender will be recorded as frequency and percentage.&#xD;
      Chi Square test is applied to assess the association of various parameters. The results will&#xD;
      be considered statistically significant if the p-value is found to be less than or equal to&#xD;
      0.05.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">January 4, 2023</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">May 4, 2024</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">February 4, 2024</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Laser Ablation of varicose veins</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Quadruple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Recurrence</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>both duplex ultrasound and the clinical examination. A varicose vein that had not been observed before or previously been marked by the patient on the AVVQ form was considered to be a recurrent varicose vein (owing to neo-vascularization or dilation of pre-existing veins).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Heat induced thrombosis</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Duplex Finding of thrombus near saphenofemoral junction</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">800</enrollment>
  <condition>Varicose Veins</condition>
  <condition>Venous Reflux</condition>
  <condition>Venous Insufficiency</condition>
  <condition>Venous Leg Ulcer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Two Centimeters from Saphenofemoral Junction</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Endogenous Laser Ablation (EVLA) uses a laser fibre, which is inserted into the refluxing vein via skin puncture. Using 1470 nm laser and a radial fibre for less discomfort. The catheter is placed 2-2.5 cm distal to the sapheno-femoral junction. Tumescence with a mixture of 20 mL 2% lidocaine, 1: 200,000 adrenaline and 20 mL 0.5% levobupivacaine in 1 L of 0.9% saline</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Zero point Ablation</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>The catheter is positioned exactly at the terminal valve of the SFJ (kissing the valve).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Saphenous Ablation</intervention_name>
    <description>Endogenous Laser Ablation (EVLA) uses a laser fibre, which is inserted into the refluxing vein via skin puncture.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Two Centimeters from Saphenofemoral Junction</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Zero point Ablation</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Endogenous Laser Ablation (EVLA)</intervention_name>
    <description>Endogenous Laser Ablation (EVLA)</description>
    <arm_group_label>Two Centimeters from Saphenofemoral Junction</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Zero point Ablation</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>mixture of 20 mL 2% lidocaine, 1: 200,000 adrenaline and 20 mL 0.5% levobupivacaine in 1 L of 0.9% saline</intervention_name>
    <description>mixture of 20 mL 2% lidocaine, 1: 200,000 adrenaline and 20 mL 0.5% levobupivacaine in 1 L of 0.9% saline</description>
    <arm_group_label>Two Centimeters from Saphenofemoral Junction</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Primary symptomatic VVS (CEAP, C3-C6), sapheno-femoral junction (SFJ) incompetence,&#xD;
             and GSV reflux from the groin to below the knee&#xD;
&#xD;
        Exclusion Criteria:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  history of venous surgery, suspected or proven deep venous thrombosis, history of DVT,&#xD;
             reflux of deep veins to distal limb, duplication of GSV, and patients' refusal to&#xD;
             participate in the trial.&#xD;
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>80 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Mansoura University Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Mansoura</city>
        <zip>35511</zip>
        <country>Egypt</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Egypt</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/21725957/</url>
    <description>Rasmussen LH, Bjoern L, Lawaerz M, Lawaetz B, Blemings A, Eklof B. Randomised clinical trial comparing endovenous laser ablation with stripping of the great saphenous vein: clinical outcome and recurrence after 2 years. Eur J Vasc Endovasc Surg 2010;39</description>
  </link>
  <link>
    <url>https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/19390287/</url>
    <description>Subwongcharoen S, Praditphol N, Chitwiset S. Endovenous microwave ablation of varicose veins: in vitro, live swine model, and clinical study. Surg Laparosc Endosc Percutan Tech 2009;19(2):170e4.</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>January 2023</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>September 11, 2022</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 30, 2023</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">January 31, 2023</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 30, 2023</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 30, 2023</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">January 31, 2023</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Varicose Ulcer</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Venous Insufficiency</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Varicose Veins</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Leg Ulcer</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Lidocaine</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Epinephrine</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Racepinephrine</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Levobupivacaine</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Epinephryl borate</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

