<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="9668">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 09, 2023</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT05693129</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>LE 3302</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT05693129</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Pediatric Patients Aged 1 to 6 Years With APDS</brief_title>
  <official_title>An Open-label, Single Arm Study of the Safety, Pharmacokinetics, Pharmacodynamics, and Efficacy of Leniolisib in Pediatric Patients (Aged 1 to 6 Years) With APDS (Activated Phosphoinositide 3-Kinase Delta Syndrome) Followed by an Open-label Long-term Extension</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Pharming Technologies B.V.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Cmed</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Labcorp Corporation of America Holdings, Inc</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>CMIC Co, Ltd. Japan</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Labcorp Central Laboratory</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Pharming Technologies B.V.</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is a 2-part, prospective, open-label, single arm, multicenter study to evaluate the&#xD;
      safety, tolerability, pharmacokinetics (PK), pharmacodynamics (PDx), and efficacy of&#xD;
      leniolisib in at least 15 pediatric patients (aged 1 to 6 years) with activated&#xD;
      phosphoinositide 3-kinase delta (PI3Kδ) syndrome (APDS)&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Part I will consist of a 12-week period to assess the safety and efficacy of treatment with&#xD;
      leniolisib. Part II will consist of a 1-year, long-term, safety follow-up extension with a&#xD;
      possible interim analysis.&#xD;
&#xD;
      The leniolisib doses to be used in study were selected based on safety, tolerability, PK, and&#xD;
      PDx data from the adult Phase 2/3 study, as well as PK modeling data. In both parts of the&#xD;
      study, leniolisib will be administered orally based on weight.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">June 30, 2023</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">February 25, 2025</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 30, 2024</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>N/A</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Part I &amp; II: Number of Participants with Treatment-emergent adverse events (TEAEs), Serious Adverse Events (SAEs) , and Adverse Events (AEs)</measure>
    <time_frame>From baseline to end of 12 weeks, &amp; From baseline to through study completion, an average of 1 year, plus 30 days</time_frame>
    <description>To assess number of Participants with TEAEs, SAEs, and AEs leading to discontinuation of study drug</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Part I &amp; II: Change from baseline in clinical laboratory test results</measure>
    <time_frame>From baseline to end of 12 weeks, &amp; From baseline to through study completion, an average of 1 year</time_frame>
    <description>Number of Participants with change in clinical laboratory test results (hematology, blood</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Part I &amp; II: Change from baseline in vital signs</measure>
    <time_frame>From baseline to end of 12 weeks, &amp; From baseline to through study completion, an average of 1 year</time_frame>
    <description>Number of Participants with change in vital signs</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Part I &amp; II: Change from baseline in physical examination findings</measure>
    <time_frame>From baseline to end of 12 weeks, &amp; From baseline to through study completion, an average of 1 year</time_frame>
    <description>Number of Participants with change in physical examination findings</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Part I &amp; II: Change from baseline in electrocardiograms (ECGs)</measure>
    <time_frame>From baseline to end of 12 weeks, &amp; From baseline to through study completion, an average of 1 year, plus 30 days</time_frame>
    <description>Number of Participants with change in electrocardiograms (ECGs)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Part I &amp; II: Change from baseline in growth and physical development</measure>
    <time_frame>From baseline to end of 12 weeks, &amp; From baseline to through study completion, an average of 1 year</time_frame>
    <description>Number of Participants with change in growth and physical development</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Part I &amp; II: Reduction in lymphadenopathy as measured by MRI or low-dose CT</measure>
    <time_frame>Part I: Baseline and Day 85 Part II: at Day 252, through study completion, an average of 1 year</time_frame>
    <description>To assess the impact of leniolisib on lymphadenopathy, patients will be scanned in an MRI or a CT scanner as based on clinical practice and local regulation. Index lesions will be selected from measurable nodal and extra nodal lesions as per the Cheson methodology. The same imaging modality will be used throughout the study for the same patient. Patients will be assessed by MRI, or in sites where local practice and local authorities/IECs/IRBs approve CT scans for research purposes using a low-dose CT scan.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Part I: A Percentage of Inhibition of Unstimulated and Stimulated pAkt Levels in B Cells</measure>
    <time_frame>Part I: Baseline, Days 29, 57 and 85</time_frame>
    <description>To assess change in the PDx effect of leniolisib will be assessed using ex vivo stimulated and unstimulated</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Part I: To evaluate changes in mTOR pathway through changes in pAkt</measure>
    <time_frame>From baseline to end of 12 weeks of treatment</time_frame>
    <description>To evaluate changes in mammalian target of rapamycin (mTOR) pathway pharmacodynamics (PDx) parameters</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Part I: To assess the total drug exposure (AUC) of leniolisib in pediatric patients (aged 4 to 11 years) with APDS</measure>
    <time_frame>From baseline to end of 12 weeks of treatment</time_frame>
    <description>Population pharmacokinetics (popPK) model that describes the appropriate covariates (eg, body weight and age) that influence leniolisib PK in pediatric patients.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Part I: To assess the maximum concentration (Cmax) of leniolisib in pediatric patients (aged 4 to 11 years) with APDS</measure>
    <time_frame>From baseline to end of 12 weeks of treatment</time_frame>
    <description>Population pharmacokinetics (popPK) model that describes the appropriate covariates (eg, body weight and age) that influence leniolisib PK in pediatric patients.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Part I: To assess the time to maximum concentration (Tmax) of leniolisib in pediatric patients (aged 4 to 11 years) with APDS</measure>
    <time_frame>From baseline to end of 12 weeks of treatment</time_frame>
    <description>Population pharmacokinetics (popPK) model that describes the appropriate covariates (eg, body weight and age) that influence leniolisib PK in pediatric patients.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Part II: Changes from baseline for Reduction in lymphadenopathy as measured by MRI or low-dose CT</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 85 to through study completion, an average of 1 year</time_frame>
    <description>Parameters for reduction in lymphadenopathy as a key secondary endpoint of Part II may include 3D volume of index and measurable non-index lesions selected as per the Cheson methodology. Summary statistics will be provided by visit. Arithmetic mean with SD of absolute values and change from baseline values may be plotted across time.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Part II: Changes from baseline for Reduction in lymphadenopathy as measured by MRI or low-dose CT</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 85 to through study completion, an average of 1 year</time_frame>
    <description>Parameters for reduction in 3D volume and bi-dimensional or 3D sizes of spleen, where appropriate. Summary statistics will be provided by visit. Arithmetic mean with SD of absolute values and change from baseline values may be plotted across time.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Part II: Changes from baseline for Reduction in lymphadenopathy as measured by MRI or low-dose CT</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 85 to through study completion, an average of 1 year</time_frame>
    <description>Parameters for reduction in 3D volume and bi-dimensional or 3D sizes of liver, where appropriate. Summary statistics will be provided by visit. Arithmetic mean with SD of absolute values and change from baseline values may be plotted across time.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Part I and II: Key secondary efficacy outcomes for Part I include incidence of infections and use of antibiotics.</measure>
    <time_frame>Part I: Baseline to Day 85 Part II: through study completion, an average of 1 year</time_frame>
    <description>The number and percentage of patients with infections, and the total number of infections will be summarized. The number and percentage of antibiotics taken will be presented along with number of patients for Part I. Use of immunoglobulin replacement therapy over time will be summarized.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Part I and II: Pediatric Quality of Life Inventory (PedsQLTM) Parent Report for Children Questionnaire 4.0 Generic Core Scales</measure>
    <time_frame>Part I: Baseline, Day 29, 57, &amp; 85 Part II: through study completion, an average of 1 year</time_frame>
    <description>To assess the ability of leniolisib to modify health related quality of life in pediatric patients with APDS</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">15</enrollment>
  <condition>APDS</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Leniolisib</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Leniolisib film-coated granules in 10, 15 and 20 mg strengths administered orally BID by body weight for 12 weeks for Part I and for 1 year for Part II.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Leniolisib</intervention_name>
    <description>The doses selected will range from 10 to 50 mg twice daily (BID) (resulting in total daily doses ranging from 20 to 100 mg per day).</description>
    <arm_group_label>Leniolisib</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:&#xD;
&#xD;
          1. Patient is male or female and between the age of 1 to 6 years old at time of the first&#xD;
             study procedure.&#xD;
&#xD;
          2. Patient weighs ≥8 and ≤37 kg at baseline.&#xD;
&#xD;
          3. Patient has a confirmed PI3Kδ genetic mutation of either the PIK3CD (APDS1) or PIK3R1&#xD;
             (APDS2) gene.&#xD;
&#xD;
          4. Patient has at least 1 measurable nodal lesion on MRI or low-dose CT within 6 months&#xD;
             of screening.&#xD;
&#xD;
          5. Patient has nodal or extranodal lymphoproliferation and clinical findings consistent&#xD;
             with APDS (eg, a history of repeated oto-sino-pulmonary infections or organ&#xD;
             dysfunction consistent with APDS).&#xD;
&#xD;
          6. Patient has the ability to ingest unaltered study-related medications without&#xD;
             difficulty in the investigator's opinion.&#xD;
&#xD;
          7. At screening, vital signs (body temperature, systolic BP, diastolic BP, and pulse rate&#xD;
             [PR]) will be assessed in the sitting position after the patient has been at rest for&#xD;
             at least 3 minutes. Patient's sitting vital signs should be within the following&#xD;
             ranges:&#xD;
&#xD;
               1. Systolic BP: Less than the 95th percentile adjusted for sex, age, and height&#xD;
                  percentile. See Section 10.5, Appendix 5 to determine BP percentiles adjusted for&#xD;
                  sex, age, and height percentile. (National High Blood Pressure Education Program&#xD;
                  Working Group on High Blood Pressure in Children and Adolescents, 2004). See&#xD;
                  Section 10.5, Appendix 5 to determine height percentiles.&#xD;
&#xD;
               2. Diastolic BP: Less than the 95th percentile adjusted for sex, age, and height&#xD;
                  percentile. See Section 10.5, Appendix 5 to determine BP percentiles adjusted for&#xD;
                  sex, age, and height percentile. See Section 10.6, Appendix 6 to determine height&#xD;
                  percentiles.&#xD;
&#xD;
               3. Pulse rate (Fleming 2011):&#xD;
&#xD;
             i. Age &lt;2 years: 100 to 190 bpm ii. Age 2 to 6 years: 60 to 140 bpm&#xD;
&#xD;
          8. Institutional review board- or IEC-approved written informed consent or assent and&#xD;
             privacy language as per national and local regulations must be obtained from the&#xD;
             patient and/or parent or legal guardian prior to any study-related procedures.&#xD;
&#xD;
          9. Patient parent or legal guardian is willing and able to complete the informed consent&#xD;
             or assent process and comply with study procedures and visit schedule.&#xD;
&#xD;
         10. Patient parent or legal guardian agrees patient will not participate in any other&#xD;
             interventional study while enrolled in this study.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Exclusion Criteria:&#xD;
&#xD;
          1. Patient has previous or concurrent use of immunosuppressive medication such as:&#xD;
&#xD;
               1. an mTOR inhibitor (eg, sirolimus, rapamycin, everolimus) or a PI3Kδ inhibitor&#xD;
                  (selective or non-selective PI3K inhibitors) within 6 weeks prior to first dose.&#xD;
&#xD;
                  o Short-term use for up to a total of 5 days is allowed but only up to 1 month&#xD;
                  prior to enrollment in the study.&#xD;
&#xD;
               2. B cell depleters (eg, rituximab) within 6 months prior to first dose of study&#xD;
                  medication.&#xD;
&#xD;
                  o If patient has received prior treatment with a B cell depleter, absolute B&#xD;
                  lymphocyte counts in the blood must have regained normal values.&#xD;
&#xD;
               3. Belimumab or cyclophosphamide within 6 months prior to first dose of study&#xD;
                  medication.&#xD;
&#xD;
               4. Cyclosporine A, mycophenolate, 6-mercaptopurine, azathioprine, or methotrexate&#xD;
                  within 3 months prior to first dose of study medication.&#xD;
&#xD;
               5. Glucocorticoids above a dose equivalent to either ≥2 mg/kg of body weight for&#xD;
                  weights less than 10 kg or ≥20 mg/day for weights ≥ 10 kg of prednisone or&#xD;
                  prednisolone or equivalent within 2 weeks prior to first dose of study&#xD;
                  medication.&#xD;
&#xD;
               6. Other immunosuppressive medication where effects are expected to persist at start&#xD;
                  of dosing of study medication.&#xD;
&#xD;
          2. Patient has a history or current diagnosis of ECG abnormalities indicating significant&#xD;
             risk of safety for patients participating in the study such as:&#xD;
&#xD;
               1. History of familial long QT syndrome or known family history of Torsades de&#xD;
                  Pointes.&#xD;
&#xD;
               2. Concomitant clinically significant cardiac arrhythmias, eg, sustained ventricular&#xD;
                  tachycardia, and clinically significant second or third degree atrioventricular&#xD;
                  block without a pacemaker.&#xD;
&#xD;
               3. Resting QTc (Fridericia preferred, but Bazett acceptable) &gt;460 msec if the&#xD;
                  measurement is confirmed with an additional ECG repeated as soon as possible.&#xD;
&#xD;
               4. Concomitant use of agents known to prolong the QT interval unless it can be&#xD;
                  permanently discontinued for the duration of the study.&#xD;
&#xD;
          3. Patient is currently using a medication known to be strong inhibitor or moderate or&#xD;
             strong inducer of isoenzyme CYP3A (see Table 2), if treatment cannot be discontinued&#xD;
             or switched to a different medication prior to starting study treatment.&#xD;
&#xD;
          4. Patient is currently using medications that are metabolized by isoenzyme CYP1A2 and&#xD;
             have a narrow therapeutic index (NTI) (drugs whose exposure response indicates that&#xD;
             increases in their exposure levels by the concomitant use of potent inhibitors may&#xD;
             lead to serious safety concerns [eg, Torsades de Pointes]).&#xD;
&#xD;
          5. Patient had been administered live vaccines (this includes any attenuated live&#xD;
             vaccines) starting from 6 weeks before the anticipated first study drug&#xD;
             administration, during the study, and up to 7 days after the last dose of leniolisib.&#xD;
&#xD;
          6. Patient has clinically significant abnormalities in hematology or clinical chemistry&#xD;
             (blood chemistry or urinalysis) parameters as determined by the investigator or&#xD;
             medical monitor.&#xD;
&#xD;
          7. Patient has liver disease or liver injury as indicated by clinically significant&#xD;
             abnormal liver function tests (LFTs) (alanine aminotransferase and aspartate&#xD;
             aminotransferase &gt;2.5 times upper limit of normal), history of renal injury or renal&#xD;
             disease (eg, renal trauma, glomerulonephritis, or one kidney only), or presence of&#xD;
             impaired renal function as indicated by a serum creatinine level &gt;1.5 mg/dL (133&#xD;
             μmol/L).&#xD;
&#xD;
          8. Patient has moderate or severe hepatic impairment (Child-Pugh Class B or C).&#xD;
&#xD;
          9. Patient is receiving concurrent treatment with another investigational therapy or use&#xD;
             of another investigational therapy less than 4 weeks from the first study procedure.&#xD;
&#xD;
         10. Patient has active hepatitis B (eg, hepatitis B surface antigen reactive) or active&#xD;
             hepatitis C (eg, hepatitis C virus RNA [qualitative] is detected) at screening.&#xD;
&#xD;
         11. Patient has human immunodeficiency virus (HIV) infection (HIV 1 or 2) at screening.&#xD;
&#xD;
         12. Patient has a positive COVID-19 result (polymerase chain reaction or antigen) within 1&#xD;
             week prior to first dose. The patient can be rescreened after a subsequent negative&#xD;
             result.&#xD;
&#xD;
         13. Patient has a history of malignancy (except lymphoma) within 3 years before the first&#xD;
             study procedure or has evidence of residual disease from a previously diagnosed&#xD;
             malignancy.&#xD;
&#xD;
         14. Patient has a previous diagnosis of lymphoma that has been treated with chemotherapy,&#xD;
             radiotherapy, or transplant within 1 year of the first study procedure or is&#xD;
             anticipated to require lymphoma treatment within 6 months of the first study&#xD;
             procedure.&#xD;
&#xD;
         15. Patient has a history of uncontrolled diabetes mellitus within 3 months of the first&#xD;
             study procedure.&#xD;
&#xD;
         16. Patient has had major surgery requiring hospitalization or radiotherapy within 4 weeks&#xD;
             prior to the first study procedure.&#xD;
&#xD;
         17. Patient has uncontrolled chronic or recurrent infectious disease (with the exception&#xD;
             of those that are considered to be characteristic of APDS) or evidence of tuberculosis&#xD;
             infection as defined by a positive QuantiFERON Gold test at screening. If presence of&#xD;
             latent tuberculosis is established, then treatment according to local country&#xD;
             guidelines must have been completed before patients can be considered for enrollment.&#xD;
&#xD;
         18. Patient has a known allergy or hypersensitivity to study defined medications or their&#xD;
             excipients.&#xD;
&#xD;
         19. Patient has a planned or expected major surgical procedure.&#xD;
&#xD;
         20. Patient or parent or legal guardian is unable or unwilling to comply with study&#xD;
             procedures or is unable to travel for repeat visits.&#xD;
&#xD;
         21. Patient or parent or legal guardian is unwilling to keep study results or observations&#xD;
             confidential or to refrain from posting confidential study results or observations on&#xD;
             social media sites.&#xD;
&#xD;
         22. Patient or parent or legal guardian refuses to sign consent or assent form.&#xD;
&#xD;
         23. Patient has other underlying medical condition that, in the opinion of the&#xD;
             investigator, would impair the ability of the patient to receive or tolerate the&#xD;
             planned procedures or follow-up.&#xD;
&#xD;
             -&#xD;
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>1 Year</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>6 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Anurag Relan, MD</last_name>
    <phone>+31 71 5247 400</phone>
    <email>medical-information@pharming.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Lesia Waynick, BSBA</last_name>
    <email>L.Waynick@pharming.com</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of California Los Angeles</name>
      <address>
        <city>Los Angeles</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>90095</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Manish L Butte, MD</last_name>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Alexis Stephens</last_name>
      <phone>310-210-8771</phone>
      <email>avstephens@mednet.ucla.ed</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Institutes of Health</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bethesda</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>20814</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Rao O Konenti, MD</last_name>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Alanvin Orpia</last_name>
      <email>alanvin.orpia@nih.gov</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>The University of North Carolina</name>
      <address>
        <city>Chapel Hill</city>
        <state>North Carolina</state>
        <zip>27599</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Eve Wu, MD</last_name>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Corinne Lawler</last_name>
      <email>corinne.lawler@unc.edu</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Rainbow Childrens Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Shaker Heights</city>
        <state>Ohio</state>
        <zip>44122</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Joao Lopes, MD</last_name>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Erica Denallo</last_name>
      <email>erica.denallo@UHHospitals.org</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Sophia Children's Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Rotterdam</city>
        <zip>3015 CN</zip>
        <country>Netherlands</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Clementien Vermont</last_name>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Jelka Van der Waal</last_name>
      <email>J.anderwaal@erasmusmc.nl</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Netherlands</country>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>June 2023</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>October 17, 2022</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 12, 2023</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">January 20, 2023</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 8, 2023</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 8, 2023</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">June 9, 2023</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

