<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="9523">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 09, 2023</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT05696132</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>RC21_0556</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT05696132</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Evaluation of the Decolonization Rate and Acceptance of a Complete Nasal Decolonization Kit With Povidone Iodine for MRSA Patients</brief_title>
  <acronym>MRSAD-PVP-I</acronym>
  <official_title>Evaluation of the Decolonization Rate and Acceptance of a Complete Nasal Decolonization Kit With Povidone Iodine for MRSA Patients</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Nantes University Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Nantes University Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Staphylococcus aureus (S. aureus) is a leading cause of healthcare-associated infections&#xD;
      worldwide. S. aureus colonizes several body sites, including the nose, throat, and perineum.&#xD;
      Colonization by methicillin-resistant S. aureus (MRSA) increases the risk of infection by up&#xD;
      to 27%, with infecting strains matching colonizing strains in up to 86% of cases.&#xD;
      Decolonization, the goal of which is to decrease or eliminate bacterial load on the body, is&#xD;
      an integral part of the strategies used to control and prevent the spread of MRSA. This&#xD;
      approach involves eradication of MRSA carriage from the nose through the intranasal&#xD;
      application of an antimicrobial agent and body washes with an antiseptic soap to eliminate&#xD;
      bacteria from other body sites. The most commonly used agents for MRSA decolonization are&#xD;
      intranasal mupirocin ointment applied to the anterior nares and chlorhexidine body wash.&#xD;
      Postdischarge MRSA decolonization with chlorhexidine and mupirocin led to a 30% lower risk of&#xD;
      MRSA infection. However, there are growing concerns about decolonization failures following&#xD;
      the emergence of mupirocin and chlorhexidine resistance. Povidone iodine (PVP-I) is an&#xD;
      alternative decolonization agent solutions and demonstrated rapid and superior bactericidal&#xD;
      activity against MRSA in in vitro and ex vivo studies available reports. Finally, the&#xD;
      induction of bacterial resistance or cross-resistance to antiseptics and antibiotics with&#xD;
      PVP-I was not observed. The present protocol aims to use a &quot;Decolonization kit&quot; into MRSA&#xD;
      patients to evaluate the efficacy of MRSA nasal decolonization with a topical PVP-I gel. This&#xD;
      kit will allow a complete transient decolonization with povidone-iodine (PVP-I)-based&#xD;
      products: nasal (gel), body (antiseptic soap) and oral (mouthwash).&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">February 2023</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">February 2025</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">February 2025</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>N/A</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>MRSA nasal decolonization: Negative nasal screening rate 6 hours after use of the kit.</measure>
    <time_frame>6 hours</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Acceptability by the patient and HCWs of the use of the complete kit by a satisfactory self- questionnaire.</measure>
    <time_frame>24 hours</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Characteristics of patients remained MRSA positive after PVP-I decolonization.</measure>
    <time_frame>24 hours</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>List of adverse events reported by patients.</measure>
    <time_frame>24 hours</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>MRSAD decolonization: negative nasal screening rate 24 hours after use of the kit</measure>
    <time_frame>24 hours</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">50</enrollment>
  <condition>MRSA</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Decolonization</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Nasal decolonization with betadin gel</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Betadine</intervention_name>
    <description>Nasal decolonization with betadine gel</description>
    <arm_group_label>Decolonization</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Patients readmitted at the Nantes University Hospital and detected to be already MRSA&#xD;
             positive by nasal systematic screening,&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  MRSA patients with length of hospital stay &gt; 4 days&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Patient older than 18 years and informed about the study,&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Patients who provide their written informed consent,&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Patient affiliated with French social security system or beneficiary from such system.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Women must meet one of the following criteria at the time of inclusion:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  use adequate contraceptive measures as recommended by the CTFG (Recommendations&#xD;
             related to contraception and pregnancy testing in clinical trials v1.1), and have a&#xD;
             negative pregnancy test (urine test) prior to receiving the first dose of study drug;&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  or be post-menopausal (over 50 years of age with amenorrhea for at least 12 months&#xD;
             after discontinuation of all exogenous hormonal therapy)&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  or (if under 50 years of age) have been amenorrheic for at least 12 months after&#xD;
             discontinuation of exogenous hormonal therapy and with luteinizing hormone (LH) and&#xD;
             follicle stimulating hormone (FSH) levels corresponding to post-menopausal levels&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  or have undergone irreversible surgical sterilization by hysterectomy, bilateral&#xD;
             oophorectomy or bilateral salpingectomy (this operation must be documented).&#xD;
&#xD;
        Exclusion Criteria:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Patient &lt; 18 years,&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Patient with known intolerance to PVD-I derivatives or excipients&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Known MRSA colonized patient managed in outpatient or inpatient care but with a&#xD;
             negative nasal screen,&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  New patient with MRSA infection (this patient can be included later in case of&#xD;
             hospital readmission),&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Pregnancy or breastfeeding, patient with childbearing potential that refused&#xD;
             acceptable contraceptive method&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Patients with a known risk of allergy to povidone iodine,&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Patients with damaged skin or mucous,&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Patients with a history of thyroid disorders,&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Adults under guardianship or trusteeship,&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Patients under juridical protection&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Use of mercurial antiseptic during the study.&#xD;
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Didier LEPELLETIER</last_name>
    <phone>024087069</phone>
    <phone_ext>+33</phone_ext>
    <email>didier.lepelletier@chu-nantes.fr</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>CHU de Nantes</name>
      <address>
        <city>Nantes</city>
        <zip>44093</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Didier LEPELLETIER, Pr</last_name>
      <phone>024087069</phone>
      <phone_ext>+33</phone_ext>
      <email>didier.lepelletier@chu-nantes.fr</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Didier LEPELLETIER, Pr</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>France</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>January 2023</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>January 13, 2023</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 13, 2023</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">January 25, 2023</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 13, 2023</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 13, 2023</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">January 25, 2023</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Povidone-Iodine</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

