<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="9179">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 09, 2023</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT05703633</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>GOT.2023.1</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT05703633</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Transplantation of Uncontrolled DCD Kidneys REconditioned by a Novel Ex-VIVo Perfusion MEthod</brief_title>
  <acronym>REVIVEME</acronym>
  <official_title>Single Center, First-In-Man, Proof-of-Concept Study: Transplantation of Uncontrolled DCD Kidneys REconditioned by a Novel Ex-VIVo Perfusion MEthod - The REVIVEME Trial</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Sahlgrenska University Hospital, Sweden</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Sahlgrenska University Hospital, Sweden</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Eight patient will be transplanted with kidneys from donors dying after uncontrolled&#xD;
      circulatory arrest (uDCD), with prolonged warm ischemia (up to 4,5 hours), preserved by a new&#xD;
      method based on removal of fibrinogen/fibrin in the capillary systems, leading to an&#xD;
      effective oxygenation of the tissue using an ex-vivo hospital manufactured perfusion device,&#xD;
      minimizing the risk for ischemia-reperfusion injury (I/R-I) after kidney transplantation.Each&#xD;
      patient will be studied for three months, with long-term follow-up data collected at 6 and 12&#xD;
      months&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      In a large animal model the investigators have shown that kidneys from uDCD donors, subjected&#xD;
      to 4½ hours of warm ischemia time (WIT) can be safely reconditioned to normal function,&#xD;
      without the use of advanced cardiopulmonary resuscitation (aCPR), extracorporeal circulation,&#xD;
      or use of anticoagulants given to the donor. Furthermore, kidneys from uDCD, treated&#xD;
      according to the new method, can safely be transplanted into pigs, having normal renal&#xD;
      function (measured with creatinine and iohexol-clearance) at the three-month follow-up.&#xD;
      Toxicity studies in pigs, conclude that minimal amounts of drugs are transferred at the&#xD;
      transplantation, most of the components being reduced during the ex-vivo process, showing&#xD;
      levels transferred to the recipient being very low. The renal histology was close to normal&#xD;
      in biopsies taken from the kidneys surviving three months, without signs of fibrosis or&#xD;
      glomerulosclerosis. Our research is supported by data from other labs. In short - our new&#xD;
      method means that the investigators prevent the I/R-I caused by obstruction of the arterial&#xD;
      flow, with hypoxia as result. Normally, at reperfusion, fibrin in abundance will result in&#xD;
      clot formation when activated platelets and red blood cells (RBCs) arrive. Consequently,&#xD;
      kidneys will tolerate a substantially longer WIT than if the capillaries would have been&#xD;
      occluded with hypoxia as result. Based on our large animal data, the investigators have&#xD;
      strong reasons to believe that the proposed new method significantly will reduce the&#xD;
      frequency of delayed graft function (DGF), increase the quality of the renal grafts, and&#xD;
      increase the donor pool for successful kidney transplantations.&#xD;
&#xD;
      The present study protocol describes a first-in-human trial, in which uDCD-kidneys are&#xD;
      reconditioned and preserved using this new perfusion method and then transplanted to patients&#xD;
      on the waiting list for diseased donors. The purpose of the present clinical proof-of-concept&#xD;
      (PoC) trial is to show that a novel method for preservation of donated kidneys with prolonged&#xD;
      warm ischemia time, developed in pigs, can be safely transferred to transplantations of&#xD;
      uDCD-kidneys in humans.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Injection time of Solution A is defined as the start of the reconditioning phase. Solution A&#xD;
      is injected into the renal arteries of the explanted kidneys after closing the renal veins&#xD;
      with a vascular clamp. A clamp is placed on the arteries after injection of Solution A. After&#xD;
      30 to 210 min, a second dose of Solution A is given, followed by Solution B 15 min later,&#xD;
      injected into the renal arteries. During the next 15 -30 minutes, vascular adapters for the&#xD;
      aorta patches/arteries and nipples for the ureters are mounted. The kidneys are moved to the&#xD;
      organ chamber in a hospital manufactured medical technical product (MTP) and connected to the&#xD;
      perfusion circuit. The oxygenated perfusion is started at 24 °C at a pressure of 30 mmHg. The&#xD;
      pressure is gradually increased with 5 mmHg every minutes up to a maximum of 80 mmHg, to&#xD;
      allow for the capillaries to be cleared of fibrin clots, after which temperature is decreased&#xD;
      to 15 °C and the pressure to 20mmHg. After three hours, washed RBCs (with low platelet&#xD;
      counts) are added, temperature is raised to 25 mmHg and temperature to 28-32 °C. Oxygenated&#xD;
      perfusion is continued, with the perfusate passing through adsorbers. Vascular resistance and&#xD;
      flow are monitored for during the whole medical device perfusion process. After final&#xD;
      evaluation and assessment of the kidneys by the user, temperature is decreased to 15 °C and&#xD;
      pressure to 20 mmHg, with perfusion continuing until kidney is disconnected and retrieved&#xD;
      from the organ chamber and assessed for viability for transplantation by the user prior to&#xD;
      being transplanted.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">August 21, 2023</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 31, 2024</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">August 31, 2024</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1/Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>N/A</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Single center, open label, proof-of-concept study, Phase 1-2a</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Safety - Serious Adverse Events</measure>
    <time_frame>Three months post transplantation</time_frame>
    <description>Occurrence of serious adverse events, Clavien-Dindo IV-V grade complications, including primary none function</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">8</enrollment>
  <condition>End-Stage Kidney Disease</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>uDCD arm</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients enroled in the study will receive a kidney from a uDCD donor, after the kidney has been subjected to a reconditioning procedure, preventing ischemia/reperfusion-injury, confirming large animal data using the same protocol.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>uDCD treatment</intervention_name>
    <description>Thrombolytic treatment/prevention ex-vivo to kidneys procured from patients after circulatory arrest</description>
    <arm_group_label>uDCD arm</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Both sexes&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Age 18 - 65&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  First-time transplant&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  ABO blood-group identical&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Living within 4 hours from transplant site&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Written consent&#xD;
&#xD;
        Exclusion Criteria:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Human Leukocyte Antigen (HLA) antibodies and/or preformed donor specific antibodies&#xD;
             (DSA)&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Total ischemia time of &gt; 16 hours&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Multi organ transplant recipients or previously transplanted&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  ABO-incompatible or positive complement-dependent crossmatch (CDC X-match)&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Contraindicating medical condition&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Contraindicating malignancy&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Recent drug abuse&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Non-adherent or difficulties understanding the protocol&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Known risk factors for technical surgical complications (i.e. serious arteriosclerosis&#xD;
             and or obesity)&#xD;
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>65 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Niclas Kvarnström, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>Västra Götalandsregionen - SU - Sahlgrenska</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Michael Olausson, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>+46705434360</phone>
    <email>michael.olausson@transplant.gu.se</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Markus Gäbel, MD</last_name>
    <phone>+46708643794</phone>
    <email>markus.gabel@vgregion.se</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <reference>
    <citation>Olausson M, Antony D, Travnikova G, Johansson M, Nayakawde NB, Banerjee D, Softeland JM, Premaratne GU. Novel Ex-Vivo Thrombolytic Reconditioning of Kidneys Retrieved 4 to 5 Hours After Circulatory Death. Transplantation. 2022 Aug 1;106(8):1577-1588. doi: 10.1097/TP.0000000000004037. Epub 2022 Jul 22.</citation>
    <PMID>34974455</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Olausson M, Antony D, Johansson M, Travnikova G, Nayakawde NB, Banerjee D, Mackay Softeland J, Ognissanti D, Andresen Bergstrom M, Hammarsten O, Premaratne GU. Long-term Transplant Function After Thrombolytic Treatment Ex Vivo of Donated Kidneys Retrieved 4 to 5 H After Circulatory Death. Transplantation. 2022 Dec 1;106(12):2348-2359. doi: 10.1097/TP.0000000000004235. Epub 2022 Nov 22.</citation>
    <PMID>35831928</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>January 2023</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>January 19, 2023</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 19, 2023</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">January 30, 2023</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 27, 2023</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 27, 2023</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">January 31, 2023</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Sahlgrenska University Hospital, Sweden</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Michael Olausson</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Kidney Transplantation</keyword>
  <keyword>uDCD</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Kidney Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Kidney Failure, Chronic</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

