<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="9063">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 09, 2023</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT05706025</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>22-0320</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>BIOE</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT05706025</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Pilot Study to Evaluate Utility of EnteroTracker® as a Minimally Invasive Sampling Method to Screen for Barrett's Esophagus and Esophageal Cancer</brief_title>
  <acronym>Enterotracker</acronym>
  <official_title>Pilot Study to Evaluate Utility of EnteroTracker® as a Minimally Invasive Sampling Method to Screen for Barrett's Esophagus and Esophageal Cancer</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Colorado, Denver</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Colorado, Denver</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>Yes</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to determine whether the EnteroTracker can obtain biomarkers&#xD;
      that have been studied to be significant in screening BE and EAC. The current standard of&#xD;
      care is endoscopic biopsy where the pathologist will visualize the tissue under a microscope&#xD;
      to interpret diagnosis. Another goal of this study is to understand tolerance of the&#xD;
      procedure so it might be used in an at-home setting.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This study seeks to determine the ability of a minimally invasive capsule-string device, the&#xD;
      EnteroTracker®, to capture biomarkers associated with Barrett's Esophagus (BE) and Esophageal&#xD;
      Adenocarcinoma (EAC). Identification of biomarkers in samples will support development of&#xD;
      this simple-to-use, scalable, method for early screening of EAC, a cancer that accounts for&#xD;
      the majority of esophageal cancers in the United States. In this study, the investigators&#xD;
      plan to capture esophageal luminal content using the EnteroTracker® from patients with&#xD;
      confirmed BE and/or EAC (test group) and healthy adults (control group). Samples will then be&#xD;
      analyzed for series of biomarkers associated with BE and/or EAC. The investigators will test&#xD;
      the hypothesis that the EnteroTracker® is able to capture biomarkers of interest in subjects&#xD;
      with BE and EAC compared to healthy controls. To address this hypothesis, the investigators&#xD;
      propose a pilot study with the following two specific aims. Evaluate the ability and&#xD;
      tolerability of the EnteroTracker® to capture esophageal mucosal samples in adults with BE&#xD;
      and/or EAC as well as controls and determine the ability of the EnteroTracker®-obtained&#xD;
      BE/EAC biomarkers to distinguish between BE and/or EAC from control subjects.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">March 1, 2023</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 1, 2025</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">March 1, 2025</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>N/A</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>The EnteroTracker® is a capsule device that includes an absorbent string.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Diagnostic</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Study Esophageal Mucosal Samples using Enterotracker Device</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <description>Capture esophageal mucosal samples in at least 50% of the test subjects using the EnteroTracker®.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Testing Tolerability via &quot;Post-Procedure Tolerability Survey&quot;</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <description>At least 50% of subjects describe the EnteroTracker® as &quot;Satisfactory&quot; from taking a &quot;Post-Procedure Tolerability Survey&quot;.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Testing difference in Biomarkers between Control and BE/EAC patients</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <description>At least one biomarker differentiated between BE/EAC patients and control subjects in at least 50% of test subjects. Samples will be analyzed for various biomarkers including proteins, DNA, RNA and/or methylation of DNA.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Studying DNA Collection using Enterotracker Device</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <description>Capture at least 1 µg of DNA from the EnteroTracker® obtained mucosal samples in at least 50% of the test subjects.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Testing Symptoms via Follow Up Adverse Event assessment call</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <description>No more than 50% of subjects experienced more than one of the following side effects: nausea, choking, sore throat, vomiting, or chest pain.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Testing difference in Multiple Biomarkers between Control and BE/EAC patients</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <description>More than one biomarker differentiated between BE/EAC patients and control subjects in at least 50% of test subjects. Samples will be analyzed for various biomarkers including proteins, DNA, RNA and/or methylation of DNA.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">60</enrollment>
  <condition>Barrett Esophagus</condition>
  <condition>Esophageal Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Enterotracker</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>The EnteroTracker® is a capsule device that includes an absorbent string. The trailing end of the string is taped to the cheek and the capsule is swallowed with 8-12 ounces of water. The capsule dislodges the string as it travels to the proximal small intestine. The capsule continues through the remainder of the GI tract, leaving a string in the esophagus, stomach, and duodenum. Following a 60-minute dwell time, the string is removed via the subjects' mouth and processed for analysis. Subjects will be coached to ease any potential anxieties and answer any questions. A preparatory video can be used for education if desired.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>EnteroTracker</intervention_name>
    <description>The EnteroTracker® is a capsule device that includes an absorbent string.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Enterotracker</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:&#xD;
&#xD;
          1. Provision to sign and date the consent form.&#xD;
&#xD;
          2. Stated willingness to comply with all study procedures and be available for the&#xD;
             duration of the study.&#xD;
&#xD;
          3. Be a male or female aged 45 years or older.&#xD;
&#xD;
          4. Fit in the below listed inclusion criteria&#xD;
&#xD;
        Inclusion Criteria for Test Population (BE and EAC subjects):&#xD;
&#xD;
          1. Previous diagnosis of indefinite Barrett's Esophagus (IND), non-dysplastic (ND), low&#xD;
             grade dysplasia (LGD), high grade dysplasia (HGD), and/or esophageal adenocarcinoma&#xD;
             (EAC)&#xD;
&#xD;
          2. Able to swallow a Tylenol sized capsule&#xD;
&#xD;
          3. Diagnostic endoscopy performed within past 3 months or able to arrive early to&#xD;
             endoscopy for EnteroTracker® to be swallowed before endoscopy&#xD;
&#xD;
        Inclusion Criteria for Control Population (otherwise healthy adults with no evidence of BE&#xD;
        or EAC or other esophageal cancer but with GERD) 4. Able to swallow a Tylenol sized capsule&#xD;
        5. 45 years of age or older&#xD;
&#xD;
        1. The majority of BE and EAC patients are age 50 years and older. Fewer than 15% of the&#xD;
        cases are found in people younger than age 55. However current literature has suggested&#xD;
        that there has been an increase in cases among 45-65 years old [47].&#xD;
&#xD;
        6. Apparently healthy or ≥5 years of:&#xD;
&#xD;
          1. Gastroesophageal Reflux Disease (GERD) symptoms, or&#xD;
&#xD;
          2. GERD treated with proton pump inhibitor (PPI) therapy (whether symptom control was&#xD;
             achieved or not), or&#xD;
&#xD;
          3. Any combination of treated and untreated periods if the cumulative total is at least 5&#xD;
             years&#xD;
&#xD;
        Exclusion Criteria:&#xD;
&#xD;
          1. History of difficulty swallowing (dysphagia) or painful swallowing (odynophagia),&#xD;
             including swallowing pills within 3 months of EnteroTracker® procedure&#xD;
&#xD;
          2. Inability to provide written informed consent&#xD;
&#xD;
          3. Pregnant women&#xD;
&#xD;
          4. Prior EGD during which a therapeutic procedure such as, but not limited to, ablation,&#xD;
             cryotherapy, or endoscopic mucosal resection, was performed for the treatment of BE&#xD;
             and/or EAC&#xD;
&#xD;
          5. Known history of esophageal varices or esophageal stricture&#xD;
&#xD;
          6. Any contraindication, as deemed in Investigator's medical judgment, to undergoing the&#xD;
             EnteroTracker® procedure&#xD;
&#xD;
          7. Oropharyngeal cancer&#xD;
&#xD;
          8. History of esophageal or gastric surgery, with exception of uncomplicated surgical&#xD;
             fundoplication&#xD;
&#xD;
          9. History of esophageal motility disorder&#xD;
&#xD;
         10. Currently implanted Linx device&#xD;
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>45 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Sachin Wani, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Colorado, Denver</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Jack R O'Hara, BA</last_name>
    <phone>2489258736</phone>
    <email>jack.ohara@cuanschutz.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Colorado</name>
      <address>
        <city>Aurora</city>
        <state>Colorado</state>
        <zip>80045</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Sachin Wani, MD</last_name>
      <phone>720-848-2746</phone>
      <email>sachin.wani@cuanschutz.edu</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>January 2023</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>October 5, 2022</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 20, 2023</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">January 31, 2023</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 20, 2023</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 20, 2023</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">January 31, 2023</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Esophageal Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Barrett Esophagus</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

