<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="9346">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 09, 2023</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT05699902</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>Pectoral nerve block in breast</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT05699902</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Pectoral Nerve Block During Mastectomy</brief_title>
  <acronym>PNB</acronym>
  <official_title>The Effect of Pectoral Nerve Block as a Part of Enhanced Recovery After Mastectomy</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Assiut University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Assiut University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Impact of pectoral nerve block on postoperative pain and quality of recovery in patients&#xD;
      undergoing breast cancer surgery: A prospective study&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Breast cancer is the most common malignancy in women; surgery is still the mainstay for the&#xD;
      treatment of breast cancer .&#xD;
&#xD;
      Postoperative pain can seriously reduce the quality of patient's life, and acute pain can&#xD;
      even trigger chronic pain syndrome. Thoracic paravertebral, thoracic epidural, intercostal&#xD;
      nerve, and interscalene brachial plexus blocks have been used for anesthesia and abirritation&#xD;
      during mastectomy, but their applications are limited by the complicated technique of the&#xD;
      procedures and several complications.&#xD;
&#xD;
      In recent years, there has been increasing interest on a novel, less invasive technique, the&#xD;
      pectoral nerve (PECS) block. Numerous clinical trials have focused on the analgesic potential&#xD;
      of the pectoral nerve block in breast augmentation surgery, small breast surgery, and breast&#xD;
      cancer surgery, and have shown positive results.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Several prospective observational studies in recent years demonstrated that postoperative&#xD;
      pain following breast surgery becomes chronic in up to 57% of women.&#xD;
&#xD;
      One of the most important risk factors is insufficiently treated postoperative acute pain.&#xD;
      The current gold standard for acute postoperative pain is a preventive procedure-specific&#xD;
      multimodal treatment including nonopioids, opioids and regional analgesia.&#xD;
&#xD;
      A recently published Cochran's meta-analysis demonstrated that regional analgesia [e.g.&#xD;
      paravertebral block (PVB), local infiltration] might even reduce the risk of chronic&#xD;
      postsurgical pain after breast surgery. According to a recently published guidelines,&#xD;
      pectoral nerves (PECS) blocks seem to be an effective alternative to PVB to manage&#xD;
      effectively postsurgical pain in major breast surgery.Anatomical studies revealed a different&#xD;
      local anaesthetic spread following injections between the pectoralis major and minor muscles&#xD;
      (PECS I) and a combination of the latter injection with a deeper injection between the&#xD;
      pectoralis minor and serratus anterior muscles (PECS II) but the results were not conclusive.&#xD;
      Many trials have been published and some meta-analyses revealed a high analgesic efficacy&#xD;
      following PECS II blocks compared with no block or PVB.&#xD;
&#xD;
      However, one of these meta-analyses was criticised because of methodological problems (e.g.&#xD;
      evidence assessment, missing sham block group), pain intensities not analysed separately for&#xD;
      resting pain and pain during movement and comparisons with other established or emerging&#xD;
      regional anaesthetic techniques (e.g. local infiltration, erector spinae block) were not&#xD;
      performed.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">April 1, 2023</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 30, 2024</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 1, 2024</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Interventional</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Quadruple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Post operative pain</measure>
    <time_frame>1year</time_frame>
    <description>Postoperative pain score at rest Pain score using a verbal numerical scale (0-10) in one breast (bupivacaine) compared to the other breast (placebo).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Patient's quality of life</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
    <description>Postoperative pain score on movement Pain score using a verbal numerical scale (0-10) in one breast (bupivacaine) compared to the other breast (placebo)&#xD;
Postoperative pain score at rest Pain score using a verbal numerical scale (0-10) in one breast (bupivacaine) compared to the other breast (placebo).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">40</enrollment>
  <condition>Breast Cancer Female</condition>
  <condition>Pain, Postoperative</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>PECs block group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Female undergone mastectomy and received pectoral nerve block</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Non PECs block group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Sham Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Female undergone mastectomy and not received pectoral nerve block but have received conventional analgesic methods</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>PECs block during mastectomy</intervention_name>
    <description>The patients were randomised to receive a PECS block consisting of 30 ml of levobupivacaine 0.25% after induction of anaesthesia (PECS group) or a saline mock block (control group). The patients answered a 40-item QoR questionnaire (QoR-40) before and 1 day after breast cancer surgery. MAIN OUTCOME MEASURES</description>
    <arm_group_label>PECs block group</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>PECs nerve injection</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Sham block</intervention_name>
    <description>Female undergone mastectomy and have received conventional analgesic methods</description>
    <arm_group_label>Non PECs block group</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Non PECs block</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:&#xD;
&#xD;
        1- all female planed for elective breast surgery&#xD;
&#xD;
        Exclusion Criteria:&#xD;
&#xD;
          1. Planned for bilateral axillary or bilateral reconstruction surgery.&#xD;
&#xD;
               -  Previous surgery on the surgical breast and/or axilla with the exception of&#xD;
                  partial mastectomy or sentinel lymph node biopsy Pre-existing pain in the axilla&#xD;
                  affecting the ability to use extremity for activities of daily living or&#xD;
                  requiring medication for treatment.&#xD;
&#xD;
          2. Current or past medical history of liver disease or cirrhosis with an elevated INR&#xD;
             &gt;1.4 or currently elevated transaminase levels.&#xD;
&#xD;
          3. known contraindications to peripheral nerve block placement.&#xD;
&#xD;
          4. Pregnant or breastfeeding.&#xD;
&#xD;
          5. History of allergic reactions attributed to compounds of similar chemical or biologic&#xD;
             composition&#xD;
&#xD;
          6. Planned additional surgery to the surgical breast or axilla in the next year&#xD;
             (exception would be minor surgery to breast but not axilla such as simple tissue&#xD;
             expander replacement or lumpectomy).&#xD;
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>75 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Mostafa Alaa eldin, Prof</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Assiut University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Khaled Salah, Resident Dr</last_name>
    <phone>+201030026633</phone>
    <phone_ext>+2</phone_ext>
    <email>ksa53516@gmail.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Mohamed Rizk, Lecturer</last_name>
    <phone>+201061988555</phone>
    <phone_ext>+2</phone_ext>
    <email>med.rizk٨٨@aun.edu.eg</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Assiut university</name>
      <address>
        <city>Assiut</city>
        <country>Egypt</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Egypt</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ueshima H, Otake H, Hara E, Blanco R. How to Use Pectoral Nerve Blocks Effectively-An Evidence-Based Update. Asian J Anesthesiol. 2019 Jun 1;57(2):28-36. doi: 10.6859/aja.201906_57(2).0002.</citation>
    <PMID>31382323</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Aarab Y, Ramin S, Odonnat T, Garnier O, Boissin A, Molinari N, Marin G, Perrigault PF, Cuvillon P, Chanques G. Pectoral Nerve Blocks for Breast Augmentation Surgery: A Randomized, Double-blind, Dual-centered Controlled Trial. Anesthesiology. 2021 Sep 1;135(3):442-453. doi: 10.1097/ALN.0000000000003855.</citation>
    <PMID>34195767</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Daniel Pereira D, Bleeker H, Malic C, Barrowman N, Shadrina A. Pectoral nerve block and acute pain management after breast reduction surgery in adolescent patients. Can J Anaesth. 2021 Oct;68(10):1574-1575. doi: 10.1007/s12630-021-02037-8. Epub 2021 Jun 3. No abstract available.</citation>
    <PMID>34081262</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>January 2023</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>December 11, 2022</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 24, 2023</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">January 26, 2023</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 24, 2023</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 24, 2023</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">January 26, 2023</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Assiut University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Khaled Salah Abd-Ellah</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Assistant lecturer</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Breast cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>Pain after mastectomy</keyword>
  <keyword>PECs block</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Pain, Postoperative</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Yes</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>The study will be available when the targeted number of cases reached</ipd_description>
    <ipd_info_type>Study Protocol</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_time_frame>1 year</ipd_time_frame>
    <ipd_access_criteria>Full access</ipd_access_criteria>
    <ipd_url>http://ksa53516@gmail.com</ipd_url>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

