<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="9892">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 09, 2023</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT05688020</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>0118-22-ASF</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT05688020</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Tranexamic Acid During Upper GI Endoscopic Resection Procedures</brief_title>
  <official_title>Comparison Between Epinephrine Versus Tranexamic Acid Usage During Upper Gastrointestinal Tract Endoscopic Resection Procedures for the Reduction of Intraprocedural and Postprocedural Bleeding</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Assaf-Harofeh Medical Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Assaf-Harofeh Medical Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>No</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Endoscopic resection of gastrointestinal lesions may prevent cancer. However, resection is&#xD;
      associated with adverse events such as bleeding. Tranexamic acid (TXA) is a synthetic&#xD;
      derivative of lysine that exerts antifibrinolytic effects and may prevent bleeding. The&#xD;
      investigators aim to evaluate the effect of local TXA on preventing intraprocedural and&#xD;
      postprocedural bleeding in patients undergoing endoscopic mucosal resection (EMR) of upper&#xD;
      gastrointestinal lesions.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Endoscopic resection (ER) is an endoscopic technique used for the removal of sessile or flat&#xD;
      neoplasms confined to the superficial layers (mucosa and submucosa) of the gastrointestinal&#xD;
      (GI) tract.&#xD;
&#xD;
      This technique is not without risk, and clinically significant intraprocedural bleeding and&#xD;
      post-ER bleeding remain the most frequently encountered serious adverse event.&#xD;
&#xD;
      The bleeding rate associated with ER varies for the different regions of the GI tract. This&#xD;
      is most probably due to differences in the vascularity within the wall of the GI tract in&#xD;
      each region.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Intraprocedural bleeding in the stomach and duodenum is more frequent and may be as high as&#xD;
      11.5% and 19.3%, respectively. Delayed bleeding has been reported at about 5% for these&#xD;
      sites.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Management of bleeding is often resource intensive and may necessitate hospitalization, blood&#xD;
      transfusion, and repeat intervention. Some techniques, such as soft coagulation with the tip&#xD;
      of a snare; epinephrine injection; hemoclip placement or proton-pump inhibitor treatment, are&#xD;
      used to decrease the risk of bleeding or treat active bleeding.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Diluted epinephrine, which causes vasoconstriction, is often added to the submucosal&#xD;
      injection fluid because of the theoretical benefit of decreasing bleeding. However,&#xD;
      epinephrine has a short time-of-action and for long procedures it requires multiple doses to&#xD;
      be injected. This can result in systemic effects such as severe hypertension, ventricular&#xD;
      tachycardia, and intestinal ischemia, and may also increase postprocedural pain and prolong&#xD;
      patient observation after the procedure.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Tranexamic acid (TXA) is a synthetic derivative of lysine that exerts antifibrinolytic&#xD;
      effects by inhibition of lysine binding sites on plasminogen molecules and therefore&#xD;
      stabilizes the fibrin meshwork produced by secondary hemostasis. TXA was patented by Dr. S.&#xD;
      Okamoto in 1957, and it was found to be significantly more potent than a precursor molecule&#xD;
      known as epsilon-amino-caproic acid.&#xD;
&#xD;
      During the past few years, TXA has been 'rediscovered' and is currently used in many&#xD;
      conditions that are associated with either overt or occult hemorrhage. It is one of the most&#xD;
      frequently cited drugs in recent surgical publications involving nearly all surgical&#xD;
      specialties.&#xD;
&#xD;
      After the CRASH-2 study which showed that administration of TXA to bleeding trauma patients&#xD;
      within 3 hours of injury significantly reduced the risk of death due to bleeding and&#xD;
      all-cause mortality without increasing the risk of vascular occlusive events, it has become&#xD;
      an important part of trauma management.&#xD;
&#xD;
      It is also widely used in gynecological practice. Early treatment with TXA reduces death due&#xD;
      to bleeding in women with post-partum hemorrhage, as well as total blood loss and transfusion&#xD;
      requirements in hemorrhage after caesarean delivery. Therefore, TXA has been recommended by&#xD;
      the WHO as part of postpartum hemorrhage management.&#xD;
&#xD;
      TXA is also commonly used in orthopedic surgery, either systemically or topically, to reduce&#xD;
      excessive bleeding and transfusion requirements.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Other hemorrhagic conditions in which TXA has been shown effective are epistaxis, hemoptysis&#xD;
      , endoscopic ear surgery , mastectomy, and hereditary hemorrhagic telangiectasia with&#xD;
      bleeding.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Topical use of TXA may be more beneficial than systemic use as it may provide a higher drug&#xD;
      concentration on the wound surface with negligible systemic concentrations. Most publications&#xD;
      concerning topically administered TXA come from orthopedic literature where instilling TXA as&#xD;
      a bolus into the joint reduces bleeding. Recently, a study revealed that intradermal&#xD;
      injections of TXA in dermatological surgery reduces bleeding, especially in those on&#xD;
      anticoagulant medications.&#xD;
&#xD;
      While TXA is an inhibitor of fibrinolysis, and therefore might theoretically increase the&#xD;
      risk of thrombotic vascular events, most studies show no increased risk of thromboembolism.&#xD;
      This finding has been consistent with all routes of TXA administration including IV,&#xD;
      topical/intra-articular, and other routes.&#xD;
&#xD;
      The most frequently described contraindications to TXA administration include patients with&#xD;
      histories of allergic reactions to TXA, seizures, and patients with acute renal failure or&#xD;
      chronic kidney disease.&#xD;
&#xD;
      We propose that the use of TXA in the injection gel during ER procedures will be as effective&#xD;
      as epinephrine usage in reducing intraprocedural and postprocedural bleeding, while also&#xD;
      decreasing the incidence of side effects including abdominal pain.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">February 2023</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">February 2026</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">February 2025</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 4</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>This study is designed as a prospective, double-blinded, controlled, non-inferiority pilot study.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Quadruple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Intraprocedural bleeding</measure>
    <time_frame>During procedure</time_frame>
    <description>To evaluate the effect of TXA in the submucosal injectate during upper GI endoscopic resection, compared to epinephrine use, for reduction intraprocedural bleeding.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Postprocedural bleeding</measure>
    <time_frame>2 weeks post-procedure</time_frame>
    <description>Primary aim: To evaluate the effect of TXA in the submucosal injectate during upper GI endoscopic resection, compared to epinephrine use, for reduction postprocedural bleeding.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Side effects</measure>
    <time_frame>2 weeks post-procedure</time_frame>
    <description>To evaluate the effect of TXA versus epinephrine in reducing side effects including abdominal pain, tachycardia, and hypertension.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">200</enrollment>
  <condition>Gastric Polyp</condition>
  <condition>Gastric Neoplasm</condition>
  <condition>Duodenal Neoplasms</condition>
  <condition>Esophageal Neoplasms</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Tranexamic acid</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>During the ER procedure, de-identified injectate solution will be introduced. Study group: 9 ml of standart solution for injection [Consisit of: 6 ml indigo carmine + 500 ml succinylated gelatin 4% (Gelofusine; B. Braun, Crissier, Switzerland)] + 1 ml (100mg) of TXA (tranexamic acid).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Epinephrine</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>During the ER procedure, de-identified injectate solution will be introduced. 9 ml of standart solution for injection [Consisit of: 6 ml indigo carmine + 500 ml succinylated gelatin 4% (Gelofusine; B. Braun, Crissier, Switzerland)] + 1 ml epinephrine 1:100,000 + 1 ml saline 0.9%.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Tranexamic acid</intervention_name>
    <description>Tranexamic acid will be injected as part of the injectate during endoscopic resection.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Tranexamic acid</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Hexakapron</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Epinephrine injection</intervention_name>
    <description>Epinephrine will be injected as part of the standard injectate used during endoscopic resection.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Epinephrine</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Adrenaline</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Patients referred for endoscopic resection of a non-neoplastic and neoplastic lesions&#xD;
             in the upper GI presenting to our tertiary academic center.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Age &gt; 18 years&#xD;
&#xD;
        Exclusion Criteria:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  patients with histories of allergic reactions to TXA&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  history of seizures&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  pregnancy&#xD;
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Anton Bermont, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Shamir Medical Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Anton Bermont, MD</last_name>
    <phone>972-52-6944145</phone>
    <email>bermont@doctor.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Sergei Vosko, MD</last_name>
    <email>sergeivosko@gmail.com</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Shamir Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Be'er Ya'aqov</city>
        <zip>70300</zip>
        <country>Israel</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Israel</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>ASGE Technology Committee; Hwang JH, Konda V, Abu Dayyeh BK, Chauhan SS, Enestvedt BK, Fujii-Lau LL, Komanduri S, Maple JT, Murad FM, Pannala R, Thosani NC, Banerjee S. Endoscopic mucosal resection. Gastrointest Endosc. 2015 Aug;82(2):215-26. doi: 10.1016/j.gie.2015.05.001. Epub 2015 Jun 12.</citation>
    <PMID>26077453</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Park CH, Lee SK. Preventing and controlling bleeding in gastric endoscopic submucosal dissection. Clin Endosc. 2013 Sep;46(5):456-62. doi: 10.5946/ce.2013.46.5.456. Epub 2013 Sep 30.</citation>
    <PMID>24143302</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Libanio D, Pimentel-Nunes P, Dinis-Ribeiro M. Complications of endoscopic resection techniques for upper GI tract lesions. Best Pract Res Clin Gastroenterol. 2016 Oct;30(5):735-748. doi: 10.1016/j.bpg.2016.09.010. Epub 2016 Sep 14.</citation>
    <PMID>27931633</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Yang Z, Wu Q, Liu Z, Wu K, Fan D. Proton pump inhibitors versus histamine-2-receptor antagonists for the management of iatrogenic gastric ulcer after endoscopic mucosal resection or endoscopic submucosal dissection: a meta-analysis of randomized trials. Digestion. 2011;84(4):315-20. doi: 10.1159/000331138. Epub 2011 Nov 9.</citation>
    <PMID>22075541</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Castro R, Libanio D, Pita I, Dinis-Ribeiro M. Solutions for submucosal injection: What to choose and how to do it. World J Gastroenterol. 2019 Feb 21;25(7):777-788. doi: 10.3748/wjg.v25.i7.777.</citation>
    <PMID>30809079</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Watts G. Utako Okamoto. Lancet. 2016 Jun 4;387(10035):2286. doi: 10.1016/s0140-6736(16)30697-3. No abstract available.</citation>
    <PMID>27308678</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Montroy J, Hutton B, Moodley P, Fergusson NA, Cheng W, Tinmouth A, Lavallee LT, Fergusson DA, Breau RH. The efficacy and safety of topical tranexamic acid: A systematic review and meta-analysis. Transfus Med Rev. 2018 Feb 19:S0887-7963(17)30151-7. doi: 10.1016/j.tmrv.2018.02.003. Online ahead of print.</citation>
    <PMID>29567052</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>January 2023</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>January 5, 2023</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 8, 2023</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">January 18, 2023</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 8, 2023</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 8, 2023</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">January 18, 2023</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Esophageal Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Stomach Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Duodenal Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Epinephrine</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Tranexamic Acid</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

