<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="9313">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 09, 2023</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT05700669</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>OX2022-203-01</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT05700669</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Study To Assess Safety And Efficacy Of AsiDNA In Combination With Olaparib In Participants With Recurrent Solid Tumors</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase 1b/2 Basket Study To Assess The Safety And Efficacy Of AsiDNA™ In Combination With Olaparib In Participants With Recurrent Solid Tumors</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Onxeo</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Onxeo</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is a phase 1b/2 open-label, multicenter, basket study to determine the safety,&#xD;
      anti-tumor activity, tolerability, and pharmacokinetics /pharmacodynamics of AsiDNA in&#xD;
      combination with olaparib in participants with recurrent epithelial ovarian cancer, breast&#xD;
      cancer and metastatic castration-resistant prostate cancer who have progressed on previous&#xD;
      Poly (ADP-ribose) polymerase (PARP) inhibitor therapy. The study will be conducted in two&#xD;
      phases. The Phase 1b dose escalation study designed to establish the safety, tolerability,&#xD;
      pharmacologically active doses/ maximum tolerated dose and/or recommended phase 2 dose of&#xD;
      AsiDNA in combination with olaparib.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This is a phase 1b/2 open-label, multicenter, basket study to determine the safety,&#xD;
      anti-tumor activity, tolerability, and pharmacokinetics /pharmacodynamics of AsiDNA in&#xD;
      combination with olaparib in participants with recurrent epithelial ovarian cancer, breast&#xD;
      cancer and metastatic castration-resistant prostate cancer who have progressed on previous&#xD;
      PARP inhibitor therapy. The study will be conducted in two phases. The Phase 1b dose&#xD;
      escalation study designed to establish the safety, tolerability, pharmacologically active&#xD;
      doses/ maximum tolerated dose and/or recommended phase 2 dose of AsiDNA in combination with&#xD;
      olaparib.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Once the RP2D has been determined the Phase 2 study will proceed evaluating AsiDNA in&#xD;
      combination with olaparib in participants with recurrent ovarian cancer, recurrent breast&#xD;
      cancer and recurrent CRPC that failed or progressed on PARP inhibitors (PARPi) therapy. The&#xD;
      objective of Phase 2 study is to evaluate the preliminary efficacy as measured by ORR of&#xD;
      AsiDNA in combination with olaparib in each of the three cohorts. Eligible participants will&#xD;
      be included to receive AsiDNA by IV infusion in addition to olaparib.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">February 20, 2023</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">April 2027</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2026</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1/Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Sequential Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Dose Escalation followed by dose expansion</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Phase 1b: Evaluate the safety and tolerability and determine the recommended Phase 2 dose (RP2D) of AsiDNA administered in combination with olaparib in participants with advanced and/or metastatic ovarian, breast, or prostate cancer.</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline to Week 26</time_frame>
    <description>• Dose-limiting toxicities (DLTs) as determined by adverse events (AEs) according to Common Terminology Criteria for Adverse Events (CTCAE 5.0)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Phase 1b: Evaluate the safety and tolerability and determine the recommended Phase 2 dose (RP2D) of AsiDNA administered in combination with olaparib in participants with advanced and/or metastatic ovarian, breast, or prostate cancer.</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline to Week 26</time_frame>
    <description>• Dose-limiting toxicities (DLTs) as determined by physical examination</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Phase 1b: Evaluate the safety and tolerability and determine the recommended Phase 2 dose (RP2D) of AsiDNA administered in combination with olaparib in participants with advanced and/or metastatic ovarian, breast, or prostate cancer.</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline to Week 26</time_frame>
    <description>• Dose-limiting toxicities (DLTs) as determined vital signs</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Phase 1b: Evaluate the safety and tolerability and determine the recommended Phase 2 dose (RP2D) of AsiDNA administered in combination with olaparib in participants with advanced and/or metastatic ovarian, breast, or prostate cancer.</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline to Week 26</time_frame>
    <description>• Dose-limiting toxicities (DLTs) as determined by ECG</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Phase 1b: Evaluate the safety and tolerability and determine the recommended Phase 2 dose (RP2D) of AsiDNA administered in combination with olaparib in participants with advanced and/or metastatic ovarian, breast, or prostate cancer.</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline to Week 26</time_frame>
    <description>• Dose-limiting toxicities (DLTs) as determined by clinical laboratory tests</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Phase 1b: Evaluate the safety and tolerability and determine the recommended Phase 2 dose (RP2D) of AsiDNA administered in combination with olaparib in participants with advanced and/or metastatic ovarian, breast, or prostate cancer.</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline to Week 26</time_frame>
    <description>• Dose-limiting toxicities (DLTs) as determined by Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG) performance status</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Phase 1b: Evaluate the safety and tolerability and determine the recommended Phase 2 dose (RP2D) of AsiDNA administered in combination with olaparib in participants with advanced and/or metastatic ovarian, breast, or prostate cancer.</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline to Week 26</time_frame>
    <description>Pharmacologically active dose (PAD) and/or Maximum Tolerated Dose (MTD).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Phase 2: Evaluate the anti-tumor activity of AsiDNA in combination with olaparib.</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline to Week 52</time_frame>
    <description>Objective Response Rate (ORR) defined as the percentage of participants achieving a confirmed complete response (CR) or partial response (PR) based on Investigator assessment per Response Evaluation Criteria in Solid Tumors (RECIST) v1.1 criteria guidelines.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Phase 1b: Assess the pharmacokinetics (PK) of AsiDNA when administered in combination with olaparib in participants with advanced and/or metastatic ovarian, breast, or prostate cancer.</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline to Week 26</time_frame>
    <description>• Safety PK parameters: total exposure including Area under the plasma concentration-time curve (AUC)0-24.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Phase 1b: Assess the pharmacokinetics (PK) of AsiDNA when administered in combination with olaparib in participants with advanced and/or metastatic ovarian, breast, or prostate cancer.</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline to Week 26</time_frame>
    <description>• Safety PK parameters: total exposure including AUC0-last.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Phase 1b: Assess the pharmacokinetics (PK) of AsiDNA when administered in combination with olaparib in participants with advanced and/or metastatic ovarian, breast, or prostate cancer.</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline to Week 26</time_frame>
    <description>• Safety PK parameters: total exposure including Cmax.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Phase 2: Evaluate additional parameters of efficacy of AsiDNA in combination with olaparib.</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline to Week 52</time_frame>
    <description>• Duration of Response: time from earliest date of disease response (CR or PR) until earliest date of disease progression, or death, whichever occurs first.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Phase 2: Evaluate additional parameters of efficacy of AsiDNA in combination with olaparib.</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline to Week 52</time_frame>
    <description>• Disease Control Rate: the proportion of participants in whom a CR or PR or stable disease is observed as best overall response.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Phase 2: Evaluate additional parameters of efficacy of AsiDNA in combination with olaparib.</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline to Week 52</time_frame>
    <description>• Progression Free Survival: time from start of treatment until the first documented radiographic progressive disease or death, whichever occurs first.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>4</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">115</enrollment>
  <condition>Metastatic Castration-resistant Prostate Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Recurrent Epithelial Ovarian Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Breast Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Dose Escalation</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Three dose levels of AsiDNA delivered intravenously weekly in combination with Olaparib</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Dose Expansion: Recurrent Epithelial Ovarian Cancer Cohort</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Recommended Phase 2 dose of AsiDNA delivered intravenously weekly in combination with Olaparib</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Dose Expansion: Metastatic Castration-resistant Prostate Cancer Cohort</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Recommended Phase 2 dose of AsiDNA delivered intravenously weekly in combination with Olaparib</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Dose Expansion: Recurrent Breast Cancer Cohort</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Recommended Phase 2 dose of AsiDNA delivered intravenously weekly in combination with Olaparib</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>AsiDNA</intervention_name>
    <description>All patients will receive a loading dose of AsiDNA intravenously (D1, D2, D3) followed by weekly intravenous administrations in combination with Olaparib.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Dose Escalation</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Dose Expansion: Metastatic Castration-resistant Prostate Cancer Cohort</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Dose Expansion: Recurrent Breast Cancer Cohort</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Dose Expansion: Recurrent Epithelial Ovarian Cancer Cohort</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Olaparib</intervention_name>
    <description>Olaparib is given orally in combination with AsiDNA</description>
    <arm_group_label>Dose Escalation</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Dose Expansion: Metastatic Castration-resistant Prostate Cancer Cohort</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Dose Expansion: Recurrent Breast Cancer Cohort</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Dose Expansion: Recurrent Epithelial Ovarian Cancer Cohort</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:&#xD;
&#xD;
          1. Male or female participants aged ≥18 years (no upper limit of age) at the time of&#xD;
             consent signature.&#xD;
&#xD;
          2. Voluntarily signed written informed consent form (ICF) before performance of any study&#xD;
             related screening procedures.&#xD;
&#xD;
          3. Phase 1b: Participants with advanced or metastatic ovarian, breast, or prostate cancer&#xD;
             that have had disease progression after treatment with available therapies that are&#xD;
             known to confer clinical benefit or are intolerant to or ineligible for standard&#xD;
             treatment.&#xD;
&#xD;
          4. Phase 2: Participants with:&#xD;
&#xD;
             A. Ovarian Cancer:&#xD;
&#xD;
             i. Female participants with histologically diagnosed relapsed high-grade serous or&#xD;
             endometrioid ovarian, fallopian tube, or primary peritoneal cancer. ii. Participants&#xD;
             must have ≥6 months elapsed since last platinum-based chemotherapy regimen.&#xD;
&#xD;
             B. Breast Cancer:&#xD;
&#xD;
             i. Histologically or cytologically confirmed recurrent breast cancer. ii. Advanced&#xD;
             stage, metastatic disease as documented by imaging. iii. Participants must have&#xD;
             documented status of ER, PR, and Human epidermal growth factor receptor 2 (HER2)&#xD;
             according to ASCOCAP criteria prior to study entry. Participants must have had a&#xD;
             biopsy to confirm hormone receptor status in the metastatic setting prior to study&#xD;
             entry. Note: Participants with hormone receptor-positive (estrogen and/or progesterone&#xD;
             receptor-positive) disease must have received and progressed on at least one endocrine&#xD;
             therapy (adjuvant or metastatic), or have disease that the treating physician believes&#xD;
             to be inappropriate for endocrine therapy. Endocrine therapy must have been completed&#xD;
             at least 7 days before study treatment. iv. Participants with HER2 positive disease&#xD;
             are not eligible for enrollment. v. Participants with ER+ tumors should have&#xD;
             progressed on prior CDK4/6 inhibitors (in addition to hormonal therapy) to be&#xD;
             eligible. vi. Participants with TNBC should have received sacituzumab prior to study&#xD;
             enrollment.&#xD;
&#xD;
             C. Prostate Cancer:&#xD;
&#xD;
             i. Histologically or cytologically confirmed adenocarcinoma of the prostate, CRPC.&#xD;
&#xD;
             ii. Advanced-stage, metastatic prostate cancer disease documented by soft tissue&#xD;
             disease (per RECIST 1.1) by computerized tomography (CT)/ magnetic resonance imaging&#xD;
             (MRI) imaging. iii. Progressive disease in the setting of medical or surgical&#xD;
             castration (ie, CRPC) by&#xD;
&#xD;
             PCWG3 criteria for study entry:&#xD;
&#xD;
               -  Evidence of disease progression by rising Prostate-specific antigen (PSA), or&#xD;
&#xD;
               -  Soft tissue progression per RECIST 1.1, or&#xD;
&#xD;
               -  Evidence of disease progression by observation of ≥2 new bone lesions since the&#xD;
                  initiation of last systemic therapy. iv. Surgically (bilateral orchiectomy) or&#xD;
                  medically castrated, with serum testosterone&#xD;
&#xD;
                    -  50 ng/dL (≤1.73 nmol/L) at screening. v. Medically castrated participants&#xD;
                       must be willing to continue gonadotropin- releasing hormone (GnRH) analog or&#xD;
                       antagonist for the duration of study treatment.&#xD;
&#xD;
          5. All participants in Phase 2 must have documented progression (clinical or&#xD;
             radiographic) on PARPi.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Exclusion Criteria:&#xD;
&#xD;
          1. Any systemic anti-tumor-directed drug therapy within 28 days or 5 times the&#xD;
             elimination half life (whichever is shorter) before study treatment, except for PARPi.&#xD;
&#xD;
          2. Treatment with investigational drugs within 28 days before first study drug&#xD;
             administration.&#xD;
&#xD;
          3. Radical radiation therapy within four weeks prior to the first dose of study treatment&#xD;
             or received local palliative radiation therapy for bone metastases within two weeks of&#xD;
             the first dose of study treatment.&#xD;
&#xD;
          4. Concomitant use of known strong cytochrome P450 (CYP) 3A inhibitors (eg, itraconazole,&#xD;
             telithromycin, clarithromycin, protease inhibitors boosted with ritonavir or&#xD;
             cobicistat, indinavir, saquinavir, nelfinavir, boceprevir, telaprevir) or moderate&#xD;
             CYP3A inhibitors (eg, ciprofloxacin, erythromycin, diltiazem, fluconazole, verapamil).&#xD;
             The required washout period prior to starting olaparib is two weeks.&#xD;
&#xD;
          5. Concomitant use of known strong (eg, phenobarbital, enzalutamide, phenytoin,&#xD;
             rifampicin, rifabutin, rifapentine, carbamazepine, nevirapine and St John's Wort) or&#xD;
             moderate CYP3A inducers (eg, bosentan, efavirenz, modafinil). The required washout&#xD;
             period prior to starting olaparib is five weeks for enzalutamide or phenobarbital and&#xD;
             three weeks for other agents.&#xD;
&#xD;
          6. Other malignancy within the last 5 years except curatively treated non-melanoma skin&#xD;
             cancer or in situ carcinoma of the cervix, and in situ breast cancer.&#xD;
&#xD;
          7. Participant has a condition which precludes the swallowing or absorption of an oral&#xD;
             medication.&#xD;
&#xD;
          8. Participants with symptomatic uncontrolled brain metastases. Participants with&#xD;
             previously treated brain metastases may participate provided they are stable and are&#xD;
             on stable or tapering doses of steroids for at least 7 days prior to first dose of&#xD;
             study treatment.&#xD;
&#xD;
          9. Participant with persistent toxicities (≥ CTCAE grade 2) caused by previous cancer&#xD;
             therapy, excluding alopecia.&#xD;
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Ashish Gulati, M.D.</last_name>
    <phone>(617) 932-7572</phone>
    <email>a.gulati@onxeo.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Next Oncology</name>
      <address>
        <city>San Antonio</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>78229</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Kari Cortez</last_name>
      <phone>210-580-9500</phone>
      <email>NXTSA_Coordinators@nextoncology.com</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>March 2023</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>December 22, 2022</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 17, 2023</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">January 26, 2023</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 28, 2023</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 28, 2023</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 31, 2023</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Carcinoma, Ovarian Epithelial</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Recurrence</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Olaparib</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

