<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="9031">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 09, 2023</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT05706727</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>KISTMTH 01</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT05706727</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Comparative Analytical Study of Intravenous Bolus Dose of Mephentermine and Phenylephrine for Hemodynamic Stability During Elective Cesarean Section Under Spinal Anesthesia at KIST Medical College and Teaching Hospital</brief_title>
  <official_title>Comparative Analytical Study of Intravenous Bolus Dose of Mephentermine and Phenylephrine for Hemodynamic Stability During Elective Cesarean Section Under Spinal Anesthesia at KIST Medical College and Teaching Hospital</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>KIST Medical and Teaching Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>KIST Medical and Teaching Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>No</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Hemodynamics changes with spinal anesthesia is mainly due to sympathetic block which causes&#xD;
      mainly hypotension &amp; bradycardia. Post spinal hypotension usually leads to various adverse&#xD;
      maternal and fetal outcomes. Hence, effective prevention and treatment of maternal&#xD;
      hypotension is of great clinical significance. Various studies have been done for the&#xD;
      prevention of subarachnoid block induced hypotension but the optimal choice of vasopressors&#xD;
      for the maintenance of hemodynamic stability during cesarean under spinal anesthesia is still&#xD;
      unclear. The ideal vasopressor would be the one which is reliable and easy to use , has rapid&#xD;
      onset, short duration of action, easily tritatable, can potentially be used prophylactically&#xD;
      and lack any adverse maternal and fetal impact. Thus, aim of study is to compare the&#xD;
      hemodynamic stability of mephenterime and phenylephrine during elective cesarean section&#xD;
      under spinal anesthesia. The methodology of the study will be prospective, randomized double&#xD;
      blinded study where patient meeting inclusion criteria for the study is divided into two&#xD;
      groups ( Group M n=21) and ( Group P n= 21) i.e. Group M receives intravenous bolus of&#xD;
      mephentermine 6mg and intravenous bolus of 50mcg. Hemodynamics changes in blood pressure and&#xD;
      heart rate will monitored and compared among the study groups receiving intravenous boluses&#xD;
      of study drugs. Data will be collected in proforma and saved by entering in the MS- EXCEL as&#xD;
      well. Data will be analyzed using the statistical package for the social sciences (SPSS)&#xD;
      version 27. The categorical data will be analyzed with Chi-square test and numerical&#xD;
      variables of hemodynamic parameters between the study groups will be analyzed using student&#xD;
      t- test. P-value &lt; 0.05 will be considered statistically significant.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Hence, mephenterime and phenylephrine effectiveness will be studied for hemodynamic stability&#xD;
      during cesarean section under spinal anesthesia&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Spinal anesthesia is the most common administered neuraxial anesthetic technique for patient&#xD;
      undergoing cesarean section due to its rapid and reliable onset and remains preferred choice&#xD;
      for cesarean deliveries. The advantage of spinal anesthesia includes no airway manipulation,&#xD;
      profound analgesia and anesthesia, minimal maternal and fetal drug exposure stable&#xD;
      hemodynamic parameters (based on level of anesthesia), decrease intraoperative blood loss and&#xD;
      provide postoperative pain control. Hemodynamics changes is due to sympathetic block which&#xD;
      causes reduction in venous return which further reduces the cardiac output and blood pressure&#xD;
      by activation of Bezold Jarisch reflex In addition, the vasodilatory effect due to&#xD;
      prostaglandins, progesterone relaxin and nitric oxide during pregnancy and loss of intrinsic&#xD;
      sympathetic vascular tone further exaggerated fall of blood pressure with prevalence of&#xD;
      50-90% despite of fluid preload and uterine displacement Various preventive measures like&#xD;
      fluid preload , left lateral tilt , left uterine displacement and along with vasopressors&#xD;
      such as mephentermine , phenylephrine have been tried to prevent hypotension Phenylephrine is&#xD;
      currently recommended as 1st line of vasopressor which acts as alpha 1 agonist with&#xD;
      negligible beta action increasing blood pressure due to vasoconstriction whereas it causes&#xD;
      dose dependent bradycardia and decrease cardiac output Mephentermine non catecholamine&#xD;
      nondirectly acts on both adrenergic alpha and beta receptors and indirectly by releasing&#xD;
      norepinephrine and epinephrine that increases blood pressure and augments cardiac output&#xD;
      whereas tachyphylaxis may occur rapidly.&#xD;
&#xD;
      This study would help to compare the effectiveness of phenylephrine and mephentermine for&#xD;
      maintenance of hemodynamic parameters in patient undergoing cesarean section under spinal&#xD;
      anesthesia.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">March 23, 2023</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">May 15, 2024</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">April 29, 2023</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Comparative Interventional</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Quadruple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
    <masking_description>The patients will be randomly allocated to the two groups of study by sealed envelope method. Group M patients who will receive intravenous bolus dose of mephentermine 6mg and Group P who will receive intravenous bolus dose of phenylephrine 50 mcg The drug preparations phenylephrine 50mcg/ml and mephenterime 6mg/ml will be done and labelled with code numbers by anesthesia assistant for all the patient and it is provided to anesthesiologist for administration who is not involved in the study as they will not be actively involved in the study nor in the patient care. The other anesthesia assistant or intern will be monitoring and recording information on proformas. Therefore investigator and participant of the study were blinded to the study drugs.</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>To compare the intravenous bolus dose of mephentermine and phenylephrine for hemodynamic stability during elective cesarean section under spinal anesthesia</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>To measure systolic blood pressure ( SBP) and diastolic blood pressure ( DBP) of the study groups</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>To measure Mean Arterial Pressure ( MAP ) of study groups</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Mean Arterial Pressure will be measured and compared between study groups</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>To measure heart rate ( HR) of study group</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Heart rate will be measured and compared between study groups</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">42</enrollment>
  <condition>Hemodynamic Stability</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Mephentermine ( M group)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Group M</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Phenylephrine ( P group )</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Group P</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Intravenous bolus dose of Mephentermine and mephentermine</intervention_name>
    <description>intravenous bolus dose of mephenteramine 6mg</description>
    <arm_group_label>Mephentermine ( M group)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Mephentermine</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>intravenous bolus dose of phenylephrine 50 mcg</intervention_name>
    <description>intravenous bolus dose of phenylephrine 50 mcg</description>
    <arm_group_label>Phenylephrine ( P group )</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Phenylephrine</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Patient undergoing elective cesarean section under spinal anesthesia&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Age between 18-48 years&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  ASA class II ( all pregnant are categorized as ASA II)&#xD;
&#xD;
        Exclusion Criteria:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Patient refusal&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Contraindication to spinal anesthesia like coagulation disorder , localized infection&#xD;
             , sepsis, raised intracranial pressure etc&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Patchy spinal block , failed spinal block converting to GA&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Hypersensitivity to any drugs&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  High Risk Pregnancy ( preeclampsia, eclampsia, preterm, Gestational Diabetes , etc )&#xD;
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <gender_based>Yes</gender_based>
    <gender_description>All parturient meeting the study inclusion criteria and receiving sub-arachnoid block for undergoing elective cesarean section at KIST MEDICAL COLLEGE AND TEACHING HOSPITAL</gender_description>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>48 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Dr. Smriti Koirala, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>KIST Medical College and Teaching Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Dr RAJU Basnet, MBBS</last_name>
    <phone>9861729729</phone>
    <email>ramanrj483@gmail.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Dr. Ram Bhakta Koju, MD,</last_name>
    <phone>9841113271</phone>
    <email>dr.koju@gmail.com</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>KIST Medical and Teaching Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Lalitpur</city>
        <zip>56900</zip>
        <country>Nepal</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Dr. Raju Bikram Basnet, MBBS</last_name>
      <phone>9861729729</phone>
      <email>ramanrj483@gmail.com</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Dr. Ram Bhakta Koju, MBBS</last_name>
      <phone>9841113271</phone>
      <email>dr.koju@gmail.com</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Dr. Smriti Koirala, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Nepal</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Habib AS. A review of the impact of phenylephrine administration on maternal hemodynamics and maternal and neonatal outcomes in women undergoing cesarean delivery under spinal anesthesia. Anesth Analg. 2012 Feb;114(2):377-90. doi: 10.1213/ANE.0b013e3182373a3e. Epub 2011 Nov 21.</citation>
    <PMID>22104076</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Klohr S, Roth R, Hofmann T, Rossaint R, Heesen M. Definitions of hypotension after spinal anaesthesia for caesarean section: literature search and application to parturients. Acta Anaesthesiol Scand. 2010 Sep;54(8):909-21. doi: 10.1111/j.1399-6576.2010.02239.x. Epub 2010 Apr 23.</citation>
    <PMID>20455872</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Corke BC, Datta S, Ostheimer GW, Weiss JB, Alper MH. Spinal anaesthesia for Caesarean section. The influence of hypotension on neonatal outcome. Anaesthesia. 1982 Jun;37(6):658-62. doi: 10.1111/j.1365-2044.1982.tb01278.x.</citation>
    <PMID>7091625</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ohpasanon P, Chinachoti T, Sriswasdi P, Srichu S. Prospective study of hypotension after spinal anesthesia for cesarean section at Siriraj Hospital: incidence and risk factors, Part 2. J Med Assoc Thai. 2008 May;91(5):675-80.</citation>
    <PMID>18672631</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Campagna JA, Carter C. Clinical relevance of the Bezold-Jarisch reflex. Anesthesiology. 2003 May;98(5):1250-60. doi: 10.1097/00000542-200305000-00030. No abstract available.</citation>
    <PMID>12717149</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Mohta M, Janani SS, Sethi AK, Agarwal D, Tyagi A. Comparison of phenylephrine hydrochloride and mephentermine sulphate for prevention of post spinal hypotension. Anaesthesia. 2010 Dec;65(12):1200-5. doi: 10.1111/j.1365-2044.2010.06559.x.</citation>
    <PMID>21182601</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Mahajan L, Anand LK, Gombar KK. A randomized double-blinded comparison of ephedrine, phenylephrine and mephentermine infusions to maintain blood pressure during spinal anaesthesia for cesarean delivery: The effects on fetal acid-base status and haemodynamic control. J Anaesthesiol Clin Pharmacol. 2009;25(4):427-32.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Chandak A V., Bhuyan D, Singam AP, Patil B. Comparison of bolus phenylephrine, ephedrine and mephentermine for maintenance of arterial pressure during spinal anaesthesia in caesarean section. Res J Pharm Technol. 2021;14(3):1349-52.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Nag DS, Samaddar DP, Chatterjee A, Kumar H, Dembla A. Vasopressors in obstetric anesthesia: A current perspective. World J Clin Cases. 2015 Jan 16;3(1):58-64. doi: 10.12998/wjcc.v3.i1.58.</citation>
    <PMID>25610851</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>March 2023</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>January 23, 2023</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 23, 2023</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">January 31, 2023</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 12, 2023</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 12, 2023</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 15, 2023</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>KIST Medical and Teaching Hospital</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Dr. Raju Bikram Basnet</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Post Graduate</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Phenylephrine</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Oxymetazoline</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Mephentermine</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

