<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="9545">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 09, 2023</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT05695703</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>REC/01402 Siraj ul Haq</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT05695703</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Point Prevalence of Side Strain in Fast Bowlers and Effectiveness of Core Strength Training.</brief_title>
  <official_title>Point Prevalence of Side Strain in Fast Bowlers and Effectiveness of Core Strength Training</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Riphah International University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Riphah International University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      To find out the prevalence of side strain in fast bowlers and determine the effectiveness of&#xD;
      core strength training in treating side strain&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      A fast bowler needs to have strong core muscles in order to prevent side strain, which can&#xD;
      hider the performance. Variation in deliveries , bowling speed and bowling action can be&#xD;
      compromised due to side strain injuries specifically in fast bowlers.&#xD;
&#xD;
      A strong and stable core helps to maintain balance and provide strength while performing&#xD;
      repetitive movements such as bowling. Core strengthening program should include exercises&#xD;
      that are sports specific, conditioning exercises that focus on anterior and posterior&#xD;
      musculature of the trunk and hip.&#xD;
&#xD;
      The aim of this study is to find out the prevalence of side strain in fast bowlers and to&#xD;
      incorporate strengthening exercises for core muscles to evaluate its effectiveness for side&#xD;
      strain.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">April 1, 2023</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">September 1, 2023</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">July 1, 2023</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Core Muscle Strength Test</measure>
    <time_frame>6 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>The objective of this evaluation is to monitor the development and improvement of an athlete's core strength and endurance over time.&#xD;
We will start in the plank exercise position. This is parallel to the ground with your torso straight and rigid, resting your weight on your toes and forearms.&#xD;
Start in the modified press up position elbows and feet on the ground, hold this position for 60 seconds, lift your right arm off the ground, hold this position for 15 seconds.&#xD;
Return your right arm to the ground and lift the left arm off the ground, hold this position for 15 seconds, return your left arm to the ground and lift the right leg off the ground, hold this position for 15 seconds, return your right leg to the ground and lift the left leg off the ground, hold this position for 15 seconds, lift your left leg and right arm off the ground.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Sahrmann Core Stability Test</measure>
    <time_frame>6 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>The Sahrmann core stability test is a 5-level test used to evaluate the ability of the core muscles to stabilize the spine.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Ultrasonographical assessment of side strain</measure>
    <time_frame>6 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>The integration of ultrasound imaging with musculoskeletal modelling has the potential to create new opportunities in the study of human movement science.&#xD;
Ultrasound will be performed by scanning in a location immediately inferior to the tender rib in the longitudinal and transverse directions for iden-tification of a muscle tear. The fibers of the internal oblique muscle lie deep in relation to the external oblique muscle fibres and run in a direction different from the external oblique muscle fibres by passing in a superior and medial direction. The internal oblique muscle appears as a sheet of linear fibril-lar echotexture. Tears were defined as loss of the normal fibrillar echotexture pattern with a hypoechoic gap at the rib or costal cartilage attachment of the internal oblique muscle.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Cornell Musculoskeletal Discomfort Questionnaire</measure>
    <time_frame>6 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>The Cornell Musculoskeletal Discomfort Questionnaire (CMDQ) was used to assess discomfort. Professor Alan Hedge and Ergonomics students at the Cornell University developed a well-designed data collection tool named CMDQ. The CMDQ is a 54-item questionnaire that includes a body chart and questions about musculoskeletal ache, pain, or discomfort occurrence in 20 parts of the body over the past week.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">36</enrollment>
  <condition>Sport Injury</condition>
  <condition>Sports Physical Therapy</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Core Strength Training Group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>The participants of core strength training group will perform core strength training for 6 weeks (3 days per week).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Conventional Training Group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>The participants of conventional training group will perform conventional exercises for 6 weeks (3 days per week).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Core Strength Training Group</intervention_name>
    <description>The participants of experimental group will perform core strength training regime for 6 weeks (3 days per week). Each exercise session will last for a period of 45 mins, the exercises would be performed in 3 sets of 5 repetitions with 5 seconds hold time and 10 seconds rest between each repetition and a minutes rest in between each set.&#xD;
Following exercises would be performed :&#xD;
Bridge, Crunch, Plank, Side Plank, Mountain Climb.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Core Strength Training Group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Conventional Training Group</intervention_name>
    <description>The participants of conventional group will perform following exercises :&#xD;
Running (10 repetitions X 3 sets), Jogging (10 repetitions X 3 sets), Stretching (10 repetitions X 3 sets)&#xD;
Rest between Exercises : 10-15 Seconds Rest between Set of Exercises : 30-60 Seconds Cricketers will receive exercises for 8 weeks. There will be 3 sessions per week.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Conventional Training Group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Male fast bowlers&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Age 14 to 40 years&#xD;
&#xD;
        Exclusion Criteria:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Athletes who have undergone any surgery&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Anyone with history of chest pain due to cardiopulmonary disorders&#xD;
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Male</gender>
    <minimum_age>14 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>40 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Saad Rauf, Ph.D*</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Riphah University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Saad Rauf, Ph.D*</last_name>
    <phone>+92332 5957732</phone>
    <email>saad.rauf@riphah.edu.pk</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Sawar Muhammad Hussain Shaheed Sports Stadium, Gujar Khan</name>
      <address>
        <city>Gujar Khan</city>
        <state>Punjab</state>
        <zip>47850</zip>
        <country>Pakistan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Usman Shareef</last_name>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Siraj Ul Haq, MS-SPT</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Pakistan</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2023</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>January 13, 2023</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 23, 2023</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">January 25, 2023</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 3, 2023</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 3, 2023</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 6, 2023</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Athletic Injuries</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

