<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="9873">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 09, 2023</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT05688384</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>EUDRACT: 2021-003821-31</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT05688384</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Patient-Controlled Sedation in Port Implantation (PACSPI-2)</brief_title>
  <acronym>PACSPI-2</acronym>
  <official_title>Patient-Controlled Sedation in Port Implantation (PACSPI-2) -a Randomized Controlled Trial</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Region Jönköping County</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Region Östergötland</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Region Jönköping County</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>No</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The goal of the study is to determine if patient-controlled sedation (PCS) with propofol and&#xD;
      alfentanil reduces patient-reported pain perception during implantation of subcutaneous&#xD;
      venous port (SVP).&#xD;
&#xD;
      The main question it aims to answer: How much pain did you (patient) experience during&#xD;
      SVP-implantation Several other questions will be answered regarding: patient´s perception of&#xD;
      the procedure, complication rate, procedure data.&#xD;
&#xD;
      The study contains two groups which will be compared. Control group: will do SVP implantation&#xD;
      under local anaesthesia Study group: will do SVP implantation under local anaesthesia and&#xD;
      patient-controlled sedation.&#xD;
&#xD;
      The patients are asked to complete a questionnaire postoperatively which contains questions&#xD;
      on pain perception and satisfaction.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The study is an open multicentre randomized controlled trial with a study and a control arm&#xD;
      in a 1:1 ratio. Patients will be randomized to either a control arm of LA for&#xD;
      SVP-implantation or a study arm of PCS with propofol and alfentanil as adjunct to LA for&#xD;
      SVP-implantation. The aim is to randomize 340 patients with an estimated patient recruitment&#xD;
      over 18 months with a following 6 months of data cleaning and analysis. The trial will be&#xD;
      performed at two centres; County Hospital Ryhov, Jönköping, Sweden and University Hospital&#xD;
      Linköping, Sweden. SVP implantation procedure and perioperative time period is estimated to&#xD;
      2-4 hours. The primary endpoint is assessment of patients´ self-reported pain perception.&#xD;
      Secondary outcomes include patient satisfaction, implantation conditions, sedation level,&#xD;
      sedative and analgesic medication consumption, procedural time consumption as well as safety&#xD;
      aspects, adverse events and estimation of perioperative experience. Participation in the&#xD;
      trial ends after telephone inquiry one day postoperatively.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Control arm:&#xD;
&#xD;
      SVP-implantation in LA:&#xD;
&#xD;
      Subcutanous venous ports were introduced in 1981. A SVP is a small device around 3cm in&#xD;
      diameter with an injectable membrane buried just under the skin. It is connected to a thin&#xD;
      tube with its tip in a large bore vein. Access to the SVP is achieved by puncturing the skin&#xD;
      with a needle.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Local anaesthetic causes the absence of pain sensation in the location where applied by&#xD;
      decreasing the rate of depolarization and repolarization of excitable membranes such as&#xD;
      nociceptors and nerves. The most commonly used solutions are from the amide group differing&#xD;
      in pharmacokinetics. In order to reduce a burning sensation on infiltration substances can be&#xD;
      combined with sodium bicarbonate. There will be no restrictions in the choice of LA-solution&#xD;
      being left up to local practice at participating sites. With the beginning of the procedure&#xD;
      LA is subcutaneously applied to patients in both groups. LA used at participating centres are&#xD;
      Mepivacaine 10mg/ml, 20-40ml subcutaneously or Lidnocaine 10mg/ml, 20-40 ml subcutaneously.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Study arm:&#xD;
&#xD;
      SVP-implantation in LA and PCS:&#xD;
&#xD;
      In addition to LA, patients in the study group are able to self-administer a combination of&#xD;
      propofol and alfentanil using a patient-controlled sedation pump. The pump enables the&#xD;
      patient via a hand-held button to trigger the release of a single bolus of 0.5ml containing&#xD;
      4.5mg propofol and 25µg alfentanil under an 10 second period. This results in a maximal&#xD;
      possible amount of 6 bolus doses per minute.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Propofol is a short-acting anaesthetic agent commonly used for general anaesthesia and&#xD;
      procedural sedation. Several mechanisms of action have been proposed both through&#xD;
      potentiation of GABAA receptor activity and in higher doses behaving as GABAA receptor&#xD;
      agonist. When used for intravenous sedation a single dose wears off within minutes demanding&#xD;
      for continuous or intermittent application.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Alfentanil is a short-acting synthetic opioid analgesic agent with rapid onset of effects at&#xD;
      µ-opioid receptors. These properties make it suitable to provide analgesia for brief&#xD;
      procedures and to infuse for longer procedures and yet provide relatively rapid recovery.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Rescue sedation will be available to patients in both groups on the patient´s or operator´s&#xD;
      demand. Rescue sedation consists of propofol and alfentanil administered by the clinician and&#xD;
      is documented in the e-CRF.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Setting:&#xD;
&#xD;
      This trial will be carried out in the following anaesthesia departments:&#xD;
&#xD;
      OP/IVA clinic, County Hospital Ryhov, Sweden AnOpIVA clinic, University Hospital Linköping,&#xD;
      Sweden&#xD;
&#xD;
      Participants will be instructed on use of the PCS pump (Syramed µSP6000, Arcomed AG,&#xD;
      Switzerland) by a nurse anesthetist. The syringe is loaded with 36 ml propofol (10 mg/ml) and&#xD;
      4 ml alfentanil (0.5 mg/ml). Each time the patient presses the handheld button, an aliquot of&#xD;
      0.5 ml is injected (4.5 mg propofol/0.025 mg alfentanil). The injection time is set to 10 s,&#xD;
      restricting self-administration to a maximum of 6 bolus doses per minute corresponding to 27&#xD;
      mg propofol and 0.15 mg alfentanil per minute. No lockout period is applied. Local&#xD;
      anaesthesia is injected in the operating site. Vital parameters prior to the procedure are&#xD;
      recorded. Patients are monitored using electrocardiography for heartrate (HR), non-invasive&#xD;
      blood pressure (BP), oxygen saturation (SpO2), and respiratory rate (RR) at 5-min intervals&#xD;
      during the procedure. Bradycardia is defined as HR &lt;40 beats/min, tachycardia as HR &gt;100&#xD;
      beats/min, hypotension as systolic BP &lt; 90 mmHg or a decrease of &gt;30% from baseline, hypoxia&#xD;
      as SpO2 &lt;90% or a decrease of &gt;5% from baseline, and bradypnea as RR of &lt;8 breaths per&#xD;
      minute. Supplemental oxygen via a capnograph-fitted nasal cannula is administered to all&#xD;
      patients at 2 L/min during the procedure. The Observer's Assessment of Alertness/Sedation&#xD;
      score (OAA/S) [9] is used to determine the sedation level during the four procedural steps:&#xD;
      1) sterile swabbing, 2) injection of LA, 3) catheter tunneling, and 4) sterile drape removal.&#xD;
      The operating anesthesiologist assesses the operating conditions on a 4 point scale with 1&#xD;
      enabling the operator to perform the procedure without time delay and 4 having to abort the&#xD;
      procedure. Puncture attempt is defined as continuous needle advancement to establish vein&#xD;
      puncture. An unvalidated patient perception assessment tool with seven dimensions applying&#xD;
      the NRS is used to evaluate patient perception. QoR-15 will be measured att 3 timepoints.&#xD;
      Preoperatively, postoperatively before patient discharge and one day postoperatively.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">January 19, 2023</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">July 31, 2024</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">July 31, 2024</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 4</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Maximal intraprocedural pain level on numeric rating scale</measure>
    <time_frame>after completion of procedure 10 minutes before discharge</time_frame>
    <description>NRS Participants assessment of maximal pain level experienced during the procedure using a numeric rating scale from 0-10 (0=no pain, 10=worst pain I know) on patient questionnaire.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Participants overall satisfaction, Participants satisfaction with staff</measure>
    <time_frame>after completion of procedure 10 minutes before discharge</time_frame>
    <description>NRS Participants assessment of overall satisfaction experienced during the procedure using a numeric rating scale from 0-10 (0=not satisfied at all, 10=very satisfied) on patient questionnaire</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of participants with arterial puncture, pneumothorax, bradycardia, hypoxia, airway intervention, bradypnea</measure>
    <time_frame>during the procedure</time_frame>
    <description>Respiratory and circulatory complications as well as mechanical complications during the procedure bradycardia: defined as heart &lt; 40/minutes during the procedure Hypoxia: defined as Oxygen saturation &lt;90% or significant drop from baseline (&gt;5% SaO2 drop) during the procedure Airway intervention: defined as intervention by staff with chin lift during the procedure bradypnea: defined as respiratory rate &lt;8/minute during the procedure</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Sedation score on Observers Assessment of Alertness/Sedation scale (OAA/S)</measure>
    <time_frame>during procedure at time point T1: sterile skin prepping; T2: local anaesthetic injection; T3: tunneling procedure; T4: draping removal</time_frame>
    <description>Sedation levels according to Observers Assessment of Alertness/Sedation scale 5: responds readily to naame spoken in normal tone 4: responds lethargically to name spoken in normal tone 3: responds only after name is called loudly, repeatedly, or both 2: responds only after mild prodding or shaking&#xD;
1: responds only after painful trapezius squeeze 0: does not respond to painful trapezius squeeze</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>type of catheter</measure>
    <time_frame>during the procedure</time_frame>
    <description>Procedural measures</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>amount and type of local anaesthesia</measure>
    <time_frame>during the procedure</time_frame>
    <description>Procedural measures</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>amount of sedative medication given</measure>
    <time_frame>during the procedure</time_frame>
    <description>Procedural measures</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>time consumption of the procedure</measure>
    <time_frame>during the procedure</time_frame>
    <description>Procedural measures</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>number of puncture attempts</measure>
    <time_frame>during the procedure</time_frame>
    <description>Procedural measures</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>use of ultrasound</measure>
    <time_frame>during the procedure</time_frame>
    <description>Procedural measures</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>positioning of catheter tip</measure>
    <time_frame>during the procedure</time_frame>
    <description>Procedural measures</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>vessel choice</measure>
    <time_frame>during the procedure</time_frame>
    <description>Procedural measures</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Quality of Recovery QoR-15 questionnaire</measure>
    <time_frame>by telephone the day after the procedure</time_frame>
    <description>Quality of Recovery according to QoR-15 Have you had any of the following in the last 24 hours? 10 to 0, where: 10 = none of the time [excellent] and 0 = all of the time [poor])&#xD;
Able to breathe easily&#xD;
Been able to enjoy food&#xD;
Feeling rested&#xD;
Have had a good sleep&#xD;
Able to look after personal&#xD;
Able to communicate with family or friends&#xD;
Getting support from hospital doctors and nurses&#xD;
Able to return to work or usual home activities&#xD;
Feeling comfortable and in control&#xD;
Having a feeling of general well-being&#xD;
Moderate pain&#xD;
Severe pain&#xD;
Nausea or vomiting&#xD;
Feeling worried or anxious&#xD;
Feeling sad or depressed</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Quality of Recovery QoR-15 questionnaire</measure>
    <time_frame>before the procedure at arrival to preoperative unit</time_frame>
    <description>Quality of Recovery according to QoR-15</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Quality of Recovery QoR-15 questionnaire</measure>
    <time_frame>within 1 hour after completion of procedure</time_frame>
    <description>Quality of Recovery according to QoR-15</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Participants evaluation of the importance of receiving sedatives during the procedure Participants evaluation of the importance of being in control of sedation administration</measure>
    <time_frame>within 1 hour after completion of procedure</time_frame>
    <description>Participants assessment of the importance of receiving sedatives and being in control of sedation on a numeric rating scale from 0-10 (0=not important, 10=very important) on patient questionnaire</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">340</enrollment>
  <condition>Pain</condition>
  <condition>Patient Satisfaction</condition>
  <condition>Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Venous Puncture</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control arm (LA)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients in this arm will undergo SVP insertion in local anesthesia (LA)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Study arm (LA+PCS)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients in this arm will undergo SVP insertion in local anesthesia and PCS (LA+PCS)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Propofol + Alfentanil</intervention_name>
    <description>In addition to LA, patients in the study group are able to self-administer a combination of propofol and alfentanil using a patient-controlled sedation pump. The pump enables the patient via a hand-held button to trigger the release of a single bolus of 0.5ml containing 4.5mg propofol and 25µg alfentanil under an 10second period. This results in a maximal possible amount of 6 bolus doses per minute.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Study arm (LA+PCS)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Patients ≥18 years with cancer in need of SVP.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Exclusion Criteria:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Inability to operate the PCS apparatus.&#xD;
&#xD;
               -  Inability to communicate in Scandinavian languages.&#xD;
&#xD;
               -  Patients who require general anaesthesia or patients eligible for LA only on&#xD;
                  anesthesiologist´s assessment (i.e. severe sleep apnea).&#xD;
&#xD;
               -  Propofol or alfentanil allergy.&#xD;
&#xD;
               -  Non-fasting according to guidelines of the Swedish Society for Anaesthesia and&#xD;
                  Intensive Care (SFAI).&#xD;
&#xD;
               -  Failure to achieve peripheral vascular access.&#xD;
&#xD;
               -  Pregnancy&#xD;
&#xD;
               -  Previous participation in study&#xD;
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>110 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Stefanie Seifert</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Region Jönköping</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Stefanie Seifert</last_name>
    <phone>+46102422939</phone>
    <email>stefanie.seifert@rjl.se</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Knut Taxbro</last_name>
    <phone>+46102429345</phone>
    <email>knut.taxbro@rjl.se</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Länssjukhuset Ryhov</name>
      <address>
        <city>Jönköping</city>
        <zip>555185</zip>
        <country>Sweden</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Stefanie Seifert</last_name>
      <phone>+46102422939</phone>
      <email>stefanie.seifert@rjl.se</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Knut Taxbro</last_name>
      <phone>+46102429345</phone>
      <email>knut.taxbro@rjl.se</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Sweden</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Taxbro K, Hammarskjold F, Thelin B, Lewin F, Hagman H, Hanberger H, Berg S. Clinical impact of peripherally inserted central catheters vs implanted port catheters in patients with cancer: an open-label, randomised, two-centre trial. Br J Anaesth. 2019 Jun;122(6):734-741. doi: 10.1016/j.bja.2019.01.038. Epub 2019 Apr 17.</citation>
    <PMID>31005243</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Grossmann B, Nilsson A, Sjoberg F, Bernfort L, Nilsson L. Patient-controlled sedation with propofol for endoscopic procedures-A cost analysis. Acta Anaesthesiol Scand. 2020 Jan;64(1):53-62. doi: 10.1111/aas.13463. Epub 2019 Oct 10.</citation>
    <PMID>31436310</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kreienbuhl L, Elia N, Pfeil-Beun E, Walder B, Tramer MR. Patient-Controlled Versus Clinician-Controlled Sedation With Propofol: Systematic Review and Meta-analysis With Trial Sequential Analyses. Anesth Analg. 2018 Oct;127(4):873-880. doi: 10.1213/ANE.0000000000003361.</citation>
    <PMID>29750696</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Clements W, Sneddon D, Kavnoudias H, Joseph T, Goh GS, Koukounaras J, Snow T. Randomized and controlled study comparing patient controlled and radiologist controlled intra-procedural conscious sedation, using midazolam and fentanyl, for patients undergoing insertion of a central venous line. J Med Imaging Radiat Oncol. 2018 Dec;62(6):781-788. doi: 10.1111/1754-9485.12817. Epub 2018 Oct 8.</citation>
    <PMID>30295410</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Burlacu CL, McKeating K, McShane AJ. Remifentanil for the insertion and removal of long-term central venous access during monitored anesthesia care. J Clin Anesth. 2011 Jun;23(4):286-91. doi: 10.1016/j.jclinane.2010.12.007.</citation>
    <PMID>21663812</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>December 2022</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>December 16, 2022</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 16, 2023</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">January 18, 2023</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 19, 2023</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 19, 2023</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">January 23, 2023</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>patient-controlled sedation</keyword>
  <keyword>totally implantable venous access device</keyword>
  <keyword>subcutaneous implanted venous port</keyword>
  <keyword>local anesthesia</keyword>
  <keyword>propofol</keyword>
  <keyword>alfentanil</keyword>
  <keyword>indwelling catheter</keyword>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Alfentanil</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Propofol</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Yes</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>All IPD that underlie results in a publication will be available for sharing on request</ipd_description>
    <ipd_info_type>Study Protocol</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_info_type>Statistical Analysis Plan (SAP)</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_info_type>Informed Consent Form (ICF)</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_time_frame>The supporting information will be available from november 2022.</ipd_time_frame>
    <ipd_access_criteria>Requests for sharing IPD that underlie results in a publication can be made to the principal investigator.&#xD;
The supporting information will be available on researchgate.com.</ipd_access_criteria>
  </patient_data>
  <provided_document_section>
    <provided_document>
      <document_type>Statistical Analysis Plan</document_type>
      <document_has_protocol>No</document_has_protocol>
      <document_has_icf>No</document_has_icf>
      <document_has_sap>Yes</document_has_sap>
      <document_date>March 17, 2022</document_date>
      <document_url>https://ClinicalTrials.gov/ProvidedDocs/84/NCT05688384/SAP_000.pdf</document_url>
    </provided_document>
  </provided_document_section>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

