<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="9393">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 09, 2023</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT05698706</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>HIFU-BCC-2023-1</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT05698706</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>High Intensity Focused Ultrasound (HIFU) Treatment of Basal Cell Carcinoma</brief_title>
  <acronym>HIFU-BCC</acronym>
  <official_title>High Intensity Focused Ultrasound (HIFU) Treatment of Basal Cell Carcinoma: Efficacy and Safety</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Jacek Calik</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Old Town Clinic, Poland</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The overall objective of the study is to evaluate the safety and efficacy of treatment of&#xD;
      Basal Cell Carcinoma (BCC) using a new modality based on high-intensity focused ultrasound&#xD;
      (HIFU). BCC is the most common type of skin cancer in Europe, Australia and the US. It&#xD;
      accounts for more than 75% of all skin cancer cases in those regions. There are currently&#xD;
      more the 14000 BCC cases registrations in Poland every year, and occurrences on a global&#xD;
      scale are counted in several millions per year. Given the trend of aging population those&#xD;
      numbers will only increase with time. Finding new and more effective treatment methods are&#xD;
      therefore highly relevant from both a clinical and socioeconomic perspective. The&#xD;
      investigational device used in the study is a system capable of making controlled and&#xD;
      targeted thermo-mechanical treatment of small intradermal volumes containing e.g. BCC cells,&#xD;
      but without inflicting damage to the surrounding tissue.&#xD;
&#xD;
      The investigation involves an evaluation of the safety and efficacy profile 3 months after a&#xD;
      single few-minute treatment. Subsequent follow-up of secondary endpoints is done every third&#xD;
      month until the end of the study one year after the treatment.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">December 14, 2022</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">May 14, 2025</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">May 14, 2025</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>N/A</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Cure rate</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months</time_frame>
    <description>Frequency of complete clearance of BCC after HIFU treatment. Binary output: yes/no</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Severity of short term adverse events</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months</time_frame>
    <description>Safety profile after treatment of basal cell carcinoma measured on a 4-point severity score ranging from No side effects (score 0) to Severe side effects (score 3)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Severity of adverse events</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Any objective adverse effect or event, local or systemic, related to the treatment and the investigational device (wound and course of wound healing, scar formation, instrumental hazards) measured at 6, 9 and 12 months. Measured on a 4-point severity score ranging from No side effects (score 0) to Severe side effects (score 3)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Cure rate</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Frequency of complete clearance of BCC after HIFU treatment measured at 6, 9, 12 months after HIFU treatment. Binary output: yes/no</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">27</enrollment>
  <condition>Basal Cell Carcinoma</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>De-novo BCC with thickness not more than 2.0 mm</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Areas with de-novo BCC of thickness not more than 2.0 mm (as confirmed by ultrasound imaging or histopathological examination) will be treated by high intensity focused ultrasound</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>TOOsonix System ONE-M</intervention_name>
    <description>Selected BCC sites will be treated using high intensity focused ultrasound</description>
    <arm_group_label>De-novo BCC with thickness not more than 2.0 mm</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Subjects of each gender aged 18 years or older at the time of informed consent. There&#xD;
             is no upper limit of age.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Subjects who have received oral and written study information, accepted participation&#xD;
             and signed the informed consent document.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Subjects who are willing and mentally and physically capable to understand and follow&#xD;
             the treatment and follow-up schedule including post-treatment care instructions.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Subjects who are willing to have photographs and images taken of the treated lesions&#xD;
             to be used anonymously or coded in evaluations and publications.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Subjects, who have histologically and clinically verified basal cell carcinoma cancer&#xD;
             of thickness not more 2.0 mm measured by ultrasound imaging or histopathological&#xD;
             examination.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Exclusion Criteria:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Subjects who are less than 18 years at the time of informed consent.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Subject is pregnant or lactating at time of first treatment&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Subjects with extensive, invasive or advanced skin cancer when another method in use&#xD;
             such as radiotherapy or Mohs' surgery has priority and offers the patient better&#xD;
             opportunity of cure.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Cancers on anatomical sites where the ultrasound probe cannot be adapted for&#xD;
             anatomical reasons&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Any systemic disease that according to investigator's assessment may interfere with&#xD;
             the spontaneous course of a skin cancer.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Any condition predisposing to treatment-related adverse effects or complications from&#xD;
             the ultrasound treatment.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Subjects with abnormal scar formation&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Subjects with impaired wound healing&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Subjects with any other acute or chronic condition which, in the opinion of the&#xD;
             investigator, could interfere with the conduct of the study&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Subjects undergoing immunosuppressive treatment&#xD;
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Jacek Calik, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Old Town Clinic</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Jacek Calik, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>+48 516 222 516</phone>
    <email>jacek.calik@oldtownclinic.pl</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Bartosz Wozniak, MD</last_name>
    <phone>+48 516 222 516</phone>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Old Town Clinic</name>
      <address>
        <city>Wrocław</city>
        <zip>50-127</zip>
        <country>Poland</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Jacek Calik, MD, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>+48 516 222 516</phone>
      <email>jacek.calik@oldtownclinic.pl</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Poland</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>https://oldtownclinic.pl/en/</url>
    <description>Website of Old Town Clinic</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bove T, Zawada T, Serup J, Jessen A, Poli M. High-frequency (20-MHz) high-intensity focused ultrasound (HIFU) system for dermal intervention: Preclinical evaluation in skin equivalents. Skin Res Technol. 2019 Mar;25(2):217-228. doi: 10.1111/srt.12661. Epub 2019 Jan 8.</citation>
    <PMID>30620418</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Soegaard S, Aarup V, Serup J, Bove T, Zawada T, Jessen A, Poli M. High-frequency (20 MHz) high-intensity focused ultrasound system for dermal intervention: A 12-week local tolerance study in minipigs. Skin Res Technol. 2020 Mar;26(2):241-254. doi: 10.1111/srt.12786. Epub 2019 Sep 20.</citation>
    <PMID>31541524</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Serup J, Bove T, Zawada T, Jessen A, Poli M. High-frequency (20 MHz) high-intensity focused ultrasound: New Treatment of actinic keratosis, basal cell carcinoma, and Kaposi sarcoma. An open-label exploratory study. Skin Res Technol. 2020 Nov;26(6):824-831. doi: 10.1111/srt.12883. Epub 2020 Jun 17.</citation>
    <PMID>32557832</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Calik J, Zawada T, Bove T. Treatment of superficial benign vascular tumors by high intensity focused ultrasound: Observations in two illustrative cases. J Cosmet Dermatol. 2022 Aug;21(8):3371-3379. doi: 10.1111/jocd.14682. Epub 2021 Dec 17.</citation>
    <PMID>34921489</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Calik J, Migdal M, Zawada T, Bove T. Treatment of Seborrheic Keratosis by High Frequency Focused Ultrasound - An Early Experience with 11 Consecutive Cases. Clin Cosmet Investig Dermatol. 2022 Jan 28;15:145-156. doi: 10.2147/CCID.S348106. eCollection 2022.</citation>
    <PMID>35125879</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>January 2023</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>January 16, 2023</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 16, 2023</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">January 26, 2023</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 31, 2023</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 31, 2023</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">February 2, 2023</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor-Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Old Town Clinic, Poland</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Jacek Calik</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Managing Director</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Skin cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>HIFU</keyword>
  <keyword>BCC</keyword>
  <keyword>Dermatology</keyword>
  <keyword>High Intensity Focused Ultrasound</keyword>
  <keyword>Dermoscopy</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Carcinoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Carcinoma, Basal Cell</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

