<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="9743">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 09, 2023</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT05691218</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>EOLE</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT05691218</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Early High-flow Oxygen Therapy With nebuLized Beta-2-agonist Using a Vibrating Mesh for the Management of Moderate to Severe Asthma Exacerbation in the Emergency Department</brief_title>
  <acronym>EOLE</acronym>
  <official_title>Early High-flow Oxygen Therapy With nebuLized Beta-2-agonist Using a Vibrating Mesh for the Management of Moderate to Severe Asthma Exacerbation in the Emergency Department</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Poitiers University Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Poitiers University Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Acute exacerbation of asthma represents an acute or sub-acute worsening in symptoms and lung&#xD;
      function in patients with asthma. It is characterized by a progressive increase in symptoms&#xD;
      of shortness of breath, cough, wheezing, or chest tightness. It is a common diagnosis in&#xD;
      patients admitted in an Emergency Department for dyspnoea. Near 10 to 15% of respiratory&#xD;
      symptoms in an ED are related to acute exacerbation of asthma.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Treatment of acute exacerbation of asthma associates nebulized beta-2 agonist adrenergic with&#xD;
      or without ipratropium bromide, oral corticosteroids and controlled oxygen therapy to&#xD;
      maintain SpO2 between 93 and 95%. Treatment in the ED did not vary during last years,&#xD;
      including for patients with a lack of efficacy after first line treatment, and exacerbation&#xD;
      are always associated with a hospitalisation in 40% of adult patients and with mortality in&#xD;
      1% of hospitalized patients.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Vibrating mesh nebulizers are devices using vibration to push drug through the mesh,&#xD;
      resulting in the drug nebulization. Vibrating mesh nebulizers have been associated with&#xD;
      better pulmonary drug delivery than jet-nebulizers, provide faster improvement in peak&#xD;
      expiratory flow and have been associated in retrospective studies with patient prognosis,&#xD;
      particularly in terms of throughput time and need for hospitalisation. However, no studies&#xD;
      have prospectively compared nebulisation with a vibrating membrane device with standard&#xD;
      nebulisation in patients with asthma exacerbation on clinically relevant criteria.&#xD;
      Nebulisation with a vibrating membrane device may potentiate the clinical efficacy of&#xD;
      short-acting bronchodilators, result in faster and more effective clinical improvement, and&#xD;
      be associated with improved short- and medium-term patient outcomes.&#xD;
&#xD;
      High-flow nasal cannula heated, and humidified oxygen (HNFO) is a ventilatory support which&#xD;
      is commonly used for the management of acute respiratory failure for acute respiratory&#xD;
      failure in intensive care units and in emergency departments. HFNO delivers high fraction of&#xD;
      inspired oxygen (FiO2), generates a low level of positive pressure and provides washout of&#xD;
      dead space in the upper airways, thereby improving mechanical pulmonary properties and&#xD;
      unloading inspiratory muscles during ARF. Consequently, HFNO is associated with a decrease in&#xD;
      the work of breathing. During asthma exacerbation, HFNO was associated with an improvement in&#xD;
      the dyspnea level and in the respiratory rate compared with conventional oxygen therapy.&#xD;
      However, HFNO has never been assessed in association with nebulized beta-2 adrenergic&#xD;
      agonist.&#xD;
&#xD;
      To resume, beta-2 adrenergic agonist nebulization with a vibrating mesh nebulizer seems&#xD;
      effective, especially compared to standard jet nebulization. In addition, HFNO is a technique&#xD;
      that appears to be suitable for the pathophysiological conditions of chronic reversible&#xD;
      respiratory failure, and can be used during exacerbations of asthmatic disease. The high flow&#xD;
      rate of gas makes it possible to control the FiO2 in order to avoid hyperoxia, to generate a&#xD;
      PEEP effect, to reduce the patient's work of breathing and the respiratory resistance, and to&#xD;
      avoid the re-inhalation of CO2 by a dead space wash-out.&#xD;
&#xD;
      In the EOLE study, the investigators propose to compare three therapeutic management&#xD;
      strategies. One standard strategy (nebulisation with a jet-nebulizer), and two experimental&#xD;
      strategies (nebulisation with a vibrating mesh device, and nebulisation with a vibrating mesh&#xD;
      device in association with HFNO).&#xD;
&#xD;
      The investigators hypothesise that bronchodilator nebulization with a vibrating mesh&#xD;
      nebulizer is more effective than jet-nebulizers for the management of patients admitted for&#xD;
      asthma exacerbation and non-responders or with lack to efficacy to initial treatment.&#xD;
      Furthermore, the investigators also hypothesise that the addition of the physiological&#xD;
      effects of HFNO may enhance the efficacy of the treatment.&#xD;
&#xD;
      The therapeutic effects of nebulisation with a vibrating membrane device alone or with the&#xD;
      addition of the physiological effects of HFNO could constitute a new approach to the&#xD;
      management of asthma patients, particularly in patients who are insufficiently responsive or&#xD;
      non-respondent to initial treatment.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">May 15, 2023</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 15, 2025</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">May 15, 2025</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of responding patients one hour after inclusion</measure>
    <time_frame>1 hour</time_frame>
    <description>A responding patient is defined by a patient responding to all the following criteria :&#xD;
Respiratory rate ≤ 22 ventilations /minutes&#xD;
Peak flow &gt; 60% of theorics&#xD;
SpO2 ≥ 95% in room air&#xD;
Absence of clinical signs related with severe exacerbation of asthma</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">60</enrollment>
  <condition>Moderate Asthma Exacerbation</condition>
  <condition>Severe Asthma Exacerbation</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control - Standard Nebulization</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>A-Vibrating mesh Nebulization</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>B-Vibrating mesh Nebulization and High-flow nasal cannula heated and humidified oxygen</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Standard Nebulization</intervention_name>
    <description>Beta-2 adrenergic agonist administred by standrad nebulization</description>
    <arm_group_label>Control - Standard Nebulization</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>A - Vibrating mesh nebulization</intervention_name>
    <description>Beta-2 adrenergic agonist nebulisation using a vibrating mesh nebuliser device (Aerogen, Galway, Ireland). Nebulisation will take place under medical air at 6L/min or medical O2 at 6L/min depending on the patient's needs and for a SpO2 target between 94-96%</description>
    <arm_group_label>A-Vibrating mesh Nebulization</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>B - Vibrating mesh nebulisation and high-flow nasal cannula heated and humidified oxygen</intervention_name>
    <description>High-flow nasal cannula heated and humidified oxygen (HFNO) and nebulisation of beta-adrenergic agonist using a vibrating mesh device.&#xD;
HFNO will be administered using an Airvo2 device and beta-2 adrenergic agonist nebulisation enabled by the use of a dedicated heated humidifier and an adaptable vibrating mesh nebuliser device</description>
    <arm_group_label>B-Vibrating mesh Nebulization and High-flow nasal cannula heated and humidified oxygen</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Age equal or over 18 years&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  admitted in an Emergency Department with a clinical suspicion of acute exacerbation of&#xD;
             asthma according to the Global Initiative for Asthma (GINA) criteria.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  with at least one of the following criteria 60mn after a first treatment by beta-2&#xD;
             agonist adrenergic nebulization with 3 x 5 mg of terbutaline:&#xD;
&#xD;
               -  Respiratory rate over 22 breaths/min&#xD;
&#xD;
               -  Peak flow &lt; 50% of predictive normal value&#xD;
&#xD;
               -  SpO2 &lt; 95% in room air&#xD;
&#xD;
               -  Signs of severe asthma exacerbation (at least one criteria):&#xD;
&#xD;
        Talks in word, Agitation, Sits hunched forwards, Accessory muscles in use&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Free subject, without guardianship or curatorship or subordination&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Patients benefiting from a Social Security scheme or benefiting from it through a&#xD;
             third party&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Informed consent signed by the patient after clear and honest information about the&#xD;
             study&#xD;
&#xD;
        Exclusion Criteria:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Acute exacerbation of asthma during the last 30 days&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Clinical suspicion of acute exacerbation of asthma due to anaphylaxis, pneumothorax,&#xD;
             pneumomediastinum, pneumonia or atelectasis.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  At least ONE of the following serious signs: drowsiness, confusion, auscultatory&#xD;
             silence&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Clinical suspicion of another pathology that could explain the respiratory failure&#xD;
             such as heart failure, laryngeal obstruction, pulmonary embolism, etc&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Patients with neurological (Glasgow &lt; 13) or hemodynamical failure (Mean Arterial&#xD;
             Pressure &lt; 65 mmHg)&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  contraindication to treatment with a beta-2-adrenergic agonist&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  History of hypersensitivity (allergy) to terbutaline or any of the constituents&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Contraindication to OHD&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Persons benefiting from enhanced protection, namely minors, persons deprived of their&#xD;
             liberty by a judicial or administrative decision, people assessed GIR1 or GIR 2 (AGGIR&#xD;
             grid), adults under legal protection&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Pregnant or breastfeeding women, Women at age to procreate and not using effective&#xD;
             contraception&#xD;
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Nicolas MARJANOVIC, MD PHD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>CHU Poitiers</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Nicolas MARJANOVIC, MD PHD</last_name>
    <phone>0549441873</phone>
    <phone_ext>+33</phone_ext>
    <email>nicolas.marjanovic@chu-poitiers.fr</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Sabrina SEGUIN, CRA</last_name>
    <phone>0549443229</phone>
    <phone_ext>+33</phone_ext>
    <email>sabrina.seguin@chu-poitiers.fr</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University Hospital of Poitiers</name>
      <address>
        <city>Poitiers</city>
        <zip>86021</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Nicolas MARJANOVIC, MD PHD</last_name>
      <phone>0549441873</phone>
      <phone_ext>+33</phone_ext>
      <email>nicolas.marjanovic@chu-poitiers.fr</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Sabrina SEGUIN, CRA</last_name>
      <phone>0549443229</phone>
      <phone_ext>+33</phone_ext>
      <email>sabrina.seguin@chu-poitiers.fr</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>France</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>January 2023</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>January 11, 2023</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 11, 2023</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">January 19, 2023</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 5, 2023</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 5, 2023</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">April 7, 2023</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Asthma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Emergencies</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

