<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="9325">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 09, 2023</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT05700435</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>UNM HRRC 22-317</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT05700435</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Resiliency in U.S. Air Force Personnel</brief_title>
  <official_title>Increasing Resiliency in U.S. Air Force Personnel: A Multi-Site Trial</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of New Mexico</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University of Nevada, Las Vegas</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Wright-Patterson Air Force Base</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Joint Base San Antonio-Lackland</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Johns Hopkins University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Nellis Air Force Base</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Joint Base Andrews</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>TriService Nursing Research Program (Funder)</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of New Mexico</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The goal of this clinical trial is to examine the effectiveness of the Stress Management and&#xD;
      Resilience Training (SMART) in increasing resilience in a population of U.S. Air Force&#xD;
      personnel at Joint Base Andrews, Joint Base San Antonio-Lackland, Nellis Air Force Base, and&#xD;
      Wright-Patterson Air Force Base.&#xD;
&#xD;
      The main questions it aims to answer are:&#xD;
&#xD;
        1. When delivered in real-world conditions, to what extent does SMART increase levels of&#xD;
           resiliency and decrease levels of stress in a sample of active component U.S. Air Force&#xD;
           personnel?&#xD;
&#xD;
        2. Does SMART have a sustained effectiveness from baseline to 12, 24 and 36-weeks after&#xD;
           training completion in a sample of active component U.S. Air Force personnel?&#xD;
&#xD;
        3. Does SMART provided via an in-person/video-teleconference (VTC) or Computer-Based&#xD;
           Training (CBT) modality demonstrate equivalent effectiveness in increasing resilience&#xD;
           and decreasing stress in active component Air Force personnel?&#xD;
&#xD;
      Participants will be asked to complete a pre-intervention survey, complete the assigned&#xD;
      modality of SMART ( in-person/VTC or CBT), and complete follow-up measurements at 12-, 24-,&#xD;
      and 36-weeks post-intervention completion.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Researchers will compare in-person/VTC and CBT groups' measurements to see if a difference in&#xD;
      self-reported resilience, stress, anxiety, or quality of life is present pre-intervention.&#xD;
      Researchers will compare in-person/VTC and CBT groups' measurements to see if a difference in&#xD;
      self-reported resilience, stress, anxiety, or quality of life is present post-intervention.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      A cluster randomized, pragmatic-explorative two-arm multi-site study is proposed to examine&#xD;
      the effectiveness of the Stress Management and Resilience Training (SMART) in increasing the&#xD;
      levels of resiliency in active component personnel serving in the U.S. Air Force. The SMART&#xD;
      training will be provided through either video-teleconference (VTC), in-person or&#xD;
      computer-based training (CBT).The VTC/in-person trainings will be provided to a maximum of 10&#xD;
      individuals per session. Participants in the CBT group will be provided a code to access the&#xD;
      training website. A cluster randomization of sites will take place first to place two sites&#xD;
      into the self-selection arm, a pragmatic trial where study participants will choose&#xD;
      intervention arm and place the other two sites into a randomization-arm in which participants&#xD;
      will be randomized into either the VTC or CBT arms. SMART is focused on improving the&#xD;
      practices of gratitude, mindful presence, kindness, and developing a resilient mindset.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Four study sites have been identified for the study (Joint Base Andrews, Joint Base San&#xD;
      Antonio-Lackland, Nellis Air Force Base, and Wright-Patterson Air Force Base). Simple&#xD;
      randomization will be used to assign 2 sites to the randomization arm (Arm 1) and 2 sites to&#xD;
      the self-selection arm (Arm 2). Arm randomization will be accomplished in Year1, Month 1.&#xD;
      Initial recruitment and randomization will be completed during Month 2 of Year 1 through&#xD;
      Month 5 of year 2 of the study.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Arm 1: Randomization: At two study site locations, the investigators will use a ratio of 2:1&#xD;
      to randomly assign participants to the VTC/in-person or CBT training modalities. Therefore,&#xD;
      the investigators anticipate 84 participants (42 per site) will be assigned to the CBT&#xD;
      modality and 168 (84 per site) will be assigned to the VTC/in-person modality. Randomization&#xD;
      will be stratified with respect to military grade and sex to reduce potential confounding due&#xD;
      to baseline differences. There may be important differences based upon military grade between&#xD;
      the 5 categories of military grade or two categories of participants may select. Under&#xD;
      stratification, 1 in every 3 participants will be assigned to complete CBT and the other two&#xD;
      participants will be assigned to VTC/in-person training to maintain a balanced distribution&#xD;
      between groups.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Arm 2: Self-selection: At two study site locations, the investigators aim to recruit 250&#xD;
      participants in the self-selection arm. Participants will be able to self-select their&#xD;
      preferred method of SMART completion (VTC/in-person or CBT training modality).&#xD;
&#xD;
      In order to assure consistent delivery of the intervention, the study PI and the Site AIs&#xD;
      will meet to discuss course delivery, make notations, and jointly agree to incorporate&#xD;
      recommendations for improving training delivery. At the end of the course, participants will&#xD;
      be offered a copy of a Resilience Journal. This book will serve as a review of the resiliency&#xD;
      practices and allow participants to track their use of these practices for improving&#xD;
      gratitude, mindful presence, kindness, and developing a resilient mindset.&#xD;
&#xD;
      The Site PIs and PI will work with identified local points of contact to develop a schedule&#xD;
      to assure the maximum number of participants can receive SMART during a variety of times.&#xD;
      After informed consent is obtained and prior to the delivery of the intervention, a survey&#xD;
      will be administered to collect demographic information and baseline measurements of&#xD;
      resilience, stress, anxiety, and quality of life. Participants will be provided a link to&#xD;
      access the initial survey via the research data capture survey system (REDCap; DHHS/NIH/NCRR&#xD;
      #8UL1TR000041) to provide demographic data, e-mail contact information, and responses to&#xD;
      survey instruments.&#xD;
&#xD;
      REDCap is a secure and encrypted, web-based platform licensed to and managed by the&#xD;
      University of New Mexico Health Sciences Center Clinical and Translational Science Center&#xD;
      (UNM HSC CTSC). REDCap includes research tools for project management, survey administration,&#xD;
      encrypted database storage and retrieval, and reporting. REDCap will be utilized to&#xD;
      administer follow-up surveys at week 12, 24, and 36 (if applicable) after participants&#xD;
      complete SMART. The investigators propose to collect the 36-week follow-up survey responses&#xD;
      in order to conduct an analysis to assess the longevity of the effect of SMART on resilience&#xD;
      and stress.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Participants' e-mail contact information will be used be utilized to send follow-up surveys&#xD;
      through REDCap. Each survey will take approximately 10 to 15 minutes for participants to&#xD;
      complete. If the participant does not respond to the initial REDCap invitation, a maximum of&#xD;
      three e-mail reminders (one reminder per week after the initial e-mail is sent) will be sent&#xD;
      to complete the survey. If the participant still has not responded, no further attempt to&#xD;
      contact the participant will be made until the next scheduled interval (e.g. at 24 and 36&#xD;
      weeks). Because participants' demographic information will be associated with an individual's&#xD;
      contact information in REDCap™, demographic information will not be requested as part of the&#xD;
      surveys at weeks 12, 24, or 36. All data will be de-identified when it is exported from&#xD;
      REDCap for the data analysis.&#xD;
&#xD;
      IBM SPSS Statistics (version 28 or later) and R (survey package, version 4.1.2) will be used&#xD;
      for the statistical analysis. Initial analysis will include descriptive statistics, including&#xD;
      means or medians, frequencies and percentages, as appropriate, to characterize demographic&#xD;
      status, military grade, duty location, military occupation, and previous deployment status.&#xD;
      Cronbach's α will be calculated for each multi-item scale.&#xD;
&#xD;
      The objectives of our analysis include testing and estimating the effectiveness of the&#xD;
      intervention by comparing pre-post intervention changes (improvements) in the outcome&#xD;
      measurements of interest at each follow-up. Analyses will be reported as point estimates with&#xD;
      95% confidence intervals and appropriate estimates of effect size. In this analysis, both the&#xD;
      VTC and CBT groups will be analyzed separately and scores will also be pooled together to&#xD;
      test for overall intervention effects as well as difference between the modalities.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Post-intervention improvements in resilience, stress, anxiety, and quality of life will be&#xD;
      assessed by separately analyzing changes from baseline to each follow-up time (e.g. week 12,&#xD;
      week 24, and week 36). A joint analysis of the longitudinal trend over the study period will&#xD;
      be conducted as well. The investigators will also consider a joint analysis of resilience,&#xD;
      stress, anxiety, or QOL, as well as, analysis for subscales of any specific domain of&#xD;
      interest. To better understand factors that can impact the intervention effects, our&#xD;
      regression models on the post intervention improvements over time incorporate changing&#xD;
      time-slopes and between-subject random effects. The investigators will control for&#xD;
      demographic characteristics, AFSC, and previous deployment. The investigators will also use&#xD;
      random effects to take into consideration potential clustering effects among the participants&#xD;
      from the same organizational unit.&#xD;
&#xD;
      With the two-arm randomization scheme, the results of the &quot;self-selection&quot; group provide a&#xD;
      window into &quot;potential&quot; outcomes in real-world settings.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Comparison of the outcomes from the &quot;self-selection&quot; arm with the results from the&#xD;
      &quot;randomized assignment&quot; (per-protocol) will enable us to conduct causal inference and use the&#xD;
      real difference between VTC and CBT to inform scale-up implementation of SMART.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">July 1, 2023</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">September 30, 2024</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">September 30, 2024</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Cluster randomized, pragmatic-explorative two-arm multi-site study. Arm 1: Randomization Arm 2: Self-selection</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Supportive Care</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in Connor-Davidson 10-Item Scale (CD-10)</measure>
    <time_frame>Changes in self-reported CD-10 from Baseline at 12, 24, and 36 weeks post-SMART completion</time_frame>
    <description>Resilience will be measured using the CD-10, a 10-item scale derived from the original, 25-item Connor Davidson Resilience Scale. Respondents can answer each item using a five-point rating ranging from not true at all (0) to true nearly all the time (4). A total CD-RISC score is calculated by summing the score of all 10 items for a total possible score of 40, with a higher score reflecting a greater level of resilience. The CD-10 has a reported Cronbach's alpha of .85 and has demonstrated construct validity.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in Perceived Stress Scale (PSS)</measure>
    <time_frame>Changes in self-reported PSS from Baseline at 12, 24, and 36 weeks post-SMART completion</time_frame>
    <description>The PSS was developed to provide both a global measure and a measure for current levels of perceived stress. The PSS is a 14-item instrument, and respondents answer each item on a four-point scale ranging from never (0) to very often (4). An individual's score is calculated by reverse scoring seven items and then summing all item scores, resulting in a score range of 0-56.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in Generalized Anxiety Disorder Scale (GAD-7)</measure>
    <time_frame>Changes in self-reported GAD-7 from Baseline at 12, 24, and 36 weeks post-SMART completion</time_frame>
    <description>Anxiety was measured with the GAD-7. Respondents can answer each item using a four-point scale ranging from not at all (0) nearly every day (3). A total score is calculated by summing the scores of the seven items with possible scores ranging from 0-21. Scores between 5-9 are indicative of mild anxiety, and score between 15-21 are indicative of severe anxiety.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in Quality of Life (QOL)</measure>
    <time_frame>Changes in self-reported QOL scores from Baseline at 12, 24, and 36 weeks post-SMART completion</time_frame>
    <description>A Linear Analogue Self-Assessment (LASA) QoL measure was used to measure overall quality of life for this study. Participants responded to each item using an 11-pointLikert scale ranging from as bad as it can be (0) to as good as it can be (10).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">500</enrollment>
  <condition>Stress</condition>
  <condition>Quality</condition>
  <condition>Anxiety</condition>
  <condition>Resilience</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Randomization</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>At two study sites, we will randomly assign participants to the VTC/in-person group or CBT group using a ratio of 2:1 to assign participants to the VTC/in-person or CBT training modalities. We anticipate 84 participants (42 per site) will be assigned to the CBT modality and 168 (84 per site) will be assigned to the VTC/in-person modality.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Self-selection</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>At two study sites, participants will be able to self-select which SMART training modality they will complete (VTC/in-person or CBT).We aim to recruit 250 participants in the self-selection arm.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Stress Management and Resilience Training</intervention_name>
    <description>The Stress Management and Resilience Training (SMART) program focuses on improving the practices of gratitude, mindful presence, kindness, and developing a resilient mindset. In this proposed study, SMART will be provided via either a two-hour, video teleconference (VTC) or in-person training or by completion of a self-paced, on-line version completed over a period of four to eight weeks. The modalities VTC and in-person are the two intervention conditions.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Randomization</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Self-selection</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Active Component Air Force personnel assigned or attached to the:&#xD;
&#xD;
               -  59th Medical Wing, including the 59th Medical Operations Group, 59th Medical&#xD;
                  Support Group, 559th MDG, 959th MDG, 59th Training Group, and 59th Dental Group&#xD;
                  (Joint Base San Antonio-Lackland, TX [JBSA-L])&#xD;
&#xD;
               -  316th Medical Group (Joint Base Andrews, MD [JBA])&#xD;
&#xD;
               -  99th Medical Group (Nellis AFB, NV)&#xD;
&#xD;
               -  711th Human Performance Wing (HPW), including the U.S. Air Force School of&#xD;
                  Aerospace Medicine (USAFSAM), and the 88th Medical Group (MDG) at&#xD;
                  Wright-Patterson Air Force Base, OH (WPAFB)&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Able to provide informed consent&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  ≥ 18 years of age&#xD;
&#xD;
        Exclusion Criteria:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Personnel at the above locations who are not Active Component Air Force personnel&#xD;
             (e.g. individuals on temporary duty [TDY] at the location or civilian personnel):&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Unable to provide informed consent&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Basic Military Trainees (BMTs)&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  &lt; 18 years of age&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Prisoners&#xD;
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Stephen Hernandez, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of New Mexico</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Stephen Hernandez, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>505-272-0756</phone>
    <email>shhernandez@salud.unm.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Yiliang Zhu, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>505-272-7578</phone>
    <email>YiZhu@salud.unm.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Johns Hopkins University, School of Nursing (Joint Base Andrews)</name>
      <address>
        <city>Baltimore</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>21205</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Vickie Hughes, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>443-287-1981</phone>
      <email>vhughes@jhu.edu</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Nevada Las Vegas, School of Nursing (Nellis Air Force Base)</name>
      <address>
        <city>Las Vegas</city>
        <state>Nevada</state>
        <zip>89154</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Wright-Patterson Air Force Base</name>
      <address>
        <city>Dayton</city>
        <state>Ohio</state>
        <zip>45433</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Theresa Bedford, PhD, FNP-BC</last_name>
      <phone>678-360-4725</phone>
      <email>theresa.bedford@us.af.mil</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Joint Base San Antonio-Lackland</name>
      <address>
        <city>San Antonio</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>78236</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Laurie Migliore, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>210-292-5931</phone>
      <email>laurie.a.migliore.mil@health.mil</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>https://www.resilientoption.com/online-program</url>
    <description>Resilient Option. (n.d.). Resilient option on-line program.</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Meredith LS, Sherbourne CD, Gaillot SJ, Hansell L, Ritschard HV, Parker AM, Wrenn G. Promoting Psychological Resilience in the U.S. Military. Rand Health Q. 2011 Jun 1;1(2):2. eCollection 2011 Summer.</citation>
    <PMID>28083176</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Thompson SR, Dobbins S. The Applicability of Resilience Training to the Mitigation of Trauma-Related Mental Illness in Military Personnel [Formula: see text]. J Am Psychiatr Nurses Assoc. 2018 Jan/Feb;24(1):23-34. doi: 10.1177/1078390317739957. Epub 2017 Nov 15.</citation>
    <PMID>29139325</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Rocklein Kemplin K, Paun O, Godbee DC, Brandon JW. Resilience and Suicide in Special Operations Forces: State of the Science via Integrative Review. J Spec Oper Med. 2019 Summer;19(2):57-66. doi: 10.55460/BQES-AM8H.</citation>
    <PMID>31201752</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Committee on the Assessment of Resiliency and Prevention Programs for Mental and Behavioral Health in Service Members and Their Families; Board on the Health of Select Populations; Institute of Medicine; Denning LA, Meisnere M, Warner KE, editors. Preventing Psychological Disorders in Service Members and Their Families: An Assessment of Programs. Washington (DC): National Academies Press (US); 2014 Feb 11. Available from http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/books/NBK222170/</citation>
    <PMID>25057692</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Connor KM, Davidson JR. Development of a new resilience scale: the Connor-Davidson Resilience Scale (CD-RISC). Depress Anxiety. 2003;18(2):76-82. doi: 10.1002/da.10113.</citation>
    <PMID>12964174</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sood A, Prasad K, Schroeder D, Varkey P. Stress management and resilience training among Department of Medicine faculty: a pilot randomized clinical trial. J Gen Intern Med. 2011 Aug;26(8):858-61. doi: 10.1007/s11606-011-1640-x. Epub 2011 Jan 29.</citation>
    <PMID>21279454</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Chesak SS, Bhagra A, Schroeder DR, Foy DA, Cutshall SM, Sood A. Enhancing resilience among new nurses: feasibility and efficacy of a pilot intervention. Ochsner J. 2015 Spring;15(1):38-44.</citation>
    <PMID>25829879</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Campbell-Sills L, Stein MB. Psychometric analysis and refinement of the Connor-davidson Resilience Scale (CD-RISC): Validation of a 10-item measure of resilience. J Trauma Stress. 2007 Dec;20(6):1019-28. doi: 10.1002/jts.20271.</citation>
    <PMID>18157881</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Harris PA, Taylor R, Thielke R, Payne J, Gonzalez N, Conde JG. Research electronic data capture (REDCap)--a metadata-driven methodology and workflow process for providing translational research informatics support. J Biomed Inform. 2009 Apr;42(2):377-81. doi: 10.1016/j.jbi.2008.08.010. Epub 2008 Sep 30.</citation>
    <PMID>18929686</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Cohen, S., &amp; Williamson, G. (1988). Perecived stress in a probablility sample of the United States. In S. Spacapan &amp; S. Oskamp (Eds.), The social psychology of health (pp. 31-67). Newbury Park, CA: Sage.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Cohen S, Kamarck T, Mermelstein R. A global measure of perceived stress. J Health Soc Behav. 1983 Dec;24(4):385-96. No abstract available.</citation>
    <PMID>6668417</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Spitzer RL, Kroenke K, Williams JB, Lowe B. A brief measure for assessing generalized anxiety disorder: the GAD-7. Arch Intern Med. 2006 May 22;166(10):1092-7. doi: 10.1001/archinte.166.10.1092.</citation>
    <PMID>16717171</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Locke DE, Decker PA, Sloan JA, Brown PD, Malec JF, Clark MM, Rummans TA, Ballman KV, Schaefer PL, Buckner JC. Validation of single-item linear analog scale assessment of quality of life in neuro-oncology patients. J Pain Symptom Manage. 2007 Dec;34(6):628-38. doi: 10.1016/j.jpainsymman.2007.01.016. Epub 2007 Aug 20.</citation>
    <PMID>17703910</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Campbell-Sills L, Flynn PJ, Choi KW, Ng THH, Aliaga PA, Broshek C, Jain S, Kessler RC, Stein MB, Ursano RJ, Bliese PD. Unit cohesion during deployment and post-deployment mental health: is cohesion an individual- or unit-level buffer for combat-exposed soldiers? Psychol Med. 2022 Jan;52(1):121-131. doi: 10.1017/S0033291720001786. Epub 2020 Jun 10.</citation>
    <PMID>32517825</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Rubin, D.B., Causal inference using potential outcomes. Journal of the American Statistical Association, 2005. 100(469): p. 322-331.</citation>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>May 2023</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>January 12, 2023</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 25, 2023</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">January 26, 2023</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 10, 2023</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 10, 2023</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 12, 2023</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>military</keyword>
  <keyword>Air Force</keyword>
  <keyword>resilience</keyword>
  <keyword>stress</keyword>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>There is not a plan to make IPD available.</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

