<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="9373">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 09, 2023</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT05699226</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>R33MH125126</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>5R61MH125126</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT05699226</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Amplitude Titration to Improve ECT Clinical Outcomes</brief_title>
  <official_title>Amplitude Titration to Improve ECT Clinical Outcomes Randomized Clinical Trial</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of New Mexico</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Institute of Mental Health (NIMH)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of New Mexico</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>Yes</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      A randomized controlled trial will compare hippocampal neuroplasticity, antidepressant, and&#xD;
      cognitive outcomes between individualized amplitude and fixed 800 mA amplitude ECT in older&#xD;
      depressed subjects (n = 25 per group, n = 50 total). Relative to fixed 800 mA ECT:&#xD;
&#xD;
      H1: Individualized amplitude arm will have improved RUL antidepressant outcome (IDS-C30&#xD;
      response rates and reduced BT electrode placement switch at V2).&#xD;
&#xD;
      H2: Individualized amplitude arm will have improved cognitive outcomes (DKEFS-Verbal Fluency&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      ECT dosing can be divided into three categories for the ECT responder: insufficient (no&#xD;
      antidepressant response, no cognitive impairment), optimal (antidepressant response, no&#xD;
      cognitive impairment), or excessive (antidepressant response, cognitive impairment).&#xD;
      Traditional fixed amplitude ECT dosing with 800 mA adjusts pulse train duration and frequency&#xD;
      based on seizure titration or demographic factors (age, sex). Fixed amplitude produces&#xD;
      variable electric fields and ECT dosing secondary to individual neuroanatomic differences.&#xD;
      Adjustments to pulse width, pulse train duration, and frequency do not improve the efficacy&#xD;
      of insufficient dosing or mitigate the cognitive risk of excessive dosing. In contrast,&#xD;
      individualized amplitude based on electric field modeling or amplitude seizure titration&#xD;
      produces consistent electric fields and ECT dosing. Based on our results from the R61&#xD;
      investigation, individualized amplitude with right unilateral electrode placement has the&#xD;
      potential to reliably achieve optimal dosing and will be tested with the R33 phase of the&#xD;
      investigation.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Subjects will receive baseline imaging, clinical (primary outcome: clinician rated Inventory&#xD;
      of Depressive Symptomatology, IDS-C30), and neuropsychological assessment (primary outcome:&#xD;
      Delis Kaplan Executive Function System Verbal Fluency, DKEFS) 24 to 48 hours prior to the&#xD;
      first ECT session (V1). Subjects will receive their second assessment (V2) one day after the&#xD;
      sixth ECT treatment and the final assessment (V3) one day after the ECT series. If the&#xD;
      subject fails to demonstrate improvement at V2 (&lt; 25% reduction from baseline IDS-C30 total&#xD;
      score, the primary antidepressant outcome), the subject will then receive bitemporal (BT)&#xD;
      electrode placement for the remainder of the ECT series. The transition to BT will be a&#xD;
      secondary antidepressant outcome. Subjects will be randomized to receive right unilateral&#xD;
      (RUL) electrode placement with an individualized amplitude (n = 25) or traditional fixed 800&#xD;
      mA amplitude (n = 25, 1:1 ratio). Subjects and Raters will be blinded to subject assignment.&#xD;
      Subjects in both arms will receive fixed pulse width (1.0 milliseconds), frequency (20&#xD;
      hertz), and pulse train duration (8 seconds).&#xD;
&#xD;
      For the individualized amplitude arm, subjects will receive RUL amplitude determined seizure&#xD;
      titration during the first treatment like the R61 phase of the investigation (IDE for Soterix&#xD;
      adapter: G200123). Subsequent RUL treatments will be completed with an individualized&#xD;
      amplitude. To determine the individualized amplitude, we will use Ebrain. The individualized&#xD;
      amplitude can be determined from the optimal E-field (V/m) / baseline E-field (V/m per mA).&#xD;
      If a discrepancy exists between the amplitude seizure and E-field modeling methods that&#xD;
      results in amplitude difference &gt; 100 mA, we will use the E-field modeling method to&#xD;
      determine the individualized amplitude. We will round the amplitude to the nearest 100 mA&#xD;
      from 500 to 900 mA (the current dosing range of the FDA approved ECT device).&#xD;
&#xD;
      For the fixed 800 mA amplitude arm, subjects will receive RUL amplitude determined seizure&#xD;
      titration during the first treatment. The rationale for amplitude titration with the fixed&#xD;
      amplitude arm is to 1) improve the goodness of fit of the amplitude-seizure and Ebrain&#xD;
      relationship; and 2) control for a sub-therapeutic stimulation associated with the first&#xD;
      treatment for both arms. RUL amplitude seizure titration will be conducted during the first&#xD;
      treatment like the individualized amplitude arm. Subsequent RUL treatments will be completed&#xD;
      with 800 mA amplitude. The only difference between the arms will be individualized versus&#xD;
      fixed 800 mA amplitude after amplitude titration.&#xD;
&#xD;
      A randomized controlled trial will compare hippocampal neuroplasticity, antidepressant, and&#xD;
      cognitive outcomes between individualized amplitude and fixed 800 mA amplitude ECT in older&#xD;
      depressed subjects (n = 25 per group, n = 50 total). Relative to fixed 800 mA ECT:&#xD;
&#xD;
      H1: Individualized amplitude arm will have improved RUL antidepressant outcome (IDS-C30&#xD;
      response rates and reduced BT electrode placement switch at V2).&#xD;
&#xD;
      H2: Individualized amplitude arm will have improved cognitive outcomes (DKEFS-Verbal Fluency&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">July 1, 2023</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">January 30, 2026</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">January 30, 2026</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Randomized clinical trial with two arms: experimental (variable amplitude) and control (fixed amplitude). Participant and outcomes assessor will be masked to assignment.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double (Participant, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
    <masking_description>This investigation will use allocation concealment and masking for subject assignment.</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Inventory of Depressive Symptomatology - Clinician Rated</measure>
    <time_frame>4 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Depression severity, scores from 0 to 84, higher scores indicate more depression severity</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Delis Kaplan Executive Function System Letter Fluency</measure>
    <time_frame>4 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Cognitive measure, scale scores range from 0 to 20, higher scores indicate better cognitive performance</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">50</enrollment>
  <condition>Depression</condition>
  <condition>ECT</condition>
  <condition>Cognitive Change</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Variable amplitude</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Individualized amplitude</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Fixed amplitude</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Fixed (800 milliamperes) amplitude</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Soterix Medical Incorporated 4x1 adapter</intervention_name>
    <description>Device permits individualized amplitudes</description>
    <arm_group_label>Variable amplitude</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Traditional ECT device</intervention_name>
    <description>FDA approved ECT device with fixed amplitude.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Fixed amplitude</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Diagnosis of major depressive disorder or bipolar II&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Clinical indications for ECT with right unilateral electrode placement&#xD;
&#xD;
        Exclusion Criteria:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Defined neurological or neurodegenerative disorder (e.g., traumatic brain injury,&#xD;
             epilepsy, Alzheimer's disease)&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Other psychiatric conditions (e.g., schizophrenia, bipolar I disorder)&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Current drug or alcohol use disorder (except for nicotine)&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Contraindications to MRI.&#xD;
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>50 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Chris Abbott, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of New Mexico</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Chris Abbott, MD</last_name>
    <phone>5052720406</phone>
    <email>cabbott@salud.unm.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Megan Lloyd, MS</last_name>
    <phone>‭(505) 272-3507‬</phone>
    <email>meglloyd@salud.unm.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <verification_date>January 2023</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>January 13, 2023</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 13, 2023</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">January 26, 2023</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 22, 2023</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 22, 2023</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 23, 2023</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Depression</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Yes</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>Data will be uploaded to National Data Archive.</ipd_description>
    <ipd_info_type>Study Protocol</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_info_type>Statistical Analysis Plan (SAP)</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_info_type>Analytic Code</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_time_frame>Data will become available after study completion.</ipd_time_frame>
    <ipd_access_criteria>National Data Archive guidelines.</ipd_access_criteria>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

