<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="9213">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 09, 2023</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT05702840</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>EXerCise wEight Loss Study</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT05702840</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>EXerCise wEight Loss</brief_title>
  <acronym>EXCEL</acronym>
  <official_title>The Effects of a Home-based Resistance Training Programme on Body Composition and Muscle Function During Weight Loss in People With Overweight or Obesity: a Randomised Controlled Pilot Trial</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Glasgow</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Glasgow</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The overall aim of this study is to investigate the effects of home-based resistance exercise&#xD;
      programme on changes in body composition and strength during weight loss, in people living&#xD;
      with obesity or overweight.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">February 1, 2023</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">February 1, 2024</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">February 1, 2024</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Randomised controlled pilot trial with two groups, resistance exercise + weight loss group and weight loss only group.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Basic Science</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
    <masking_description>Members of the research team that perform measurements are blinded to group allocation.</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in whole body lean mass</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from baseline to 12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>whole body lean mass measured via bio-electrical impedance</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in whole body fat mass</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from baseline to 12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>whole body fat mass measured via bio-electrical impedance</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in body mass</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from baseline to 12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>body mass measured on scales</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in vastus lateralis muscle thickness</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from baseline to 12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Muscle thickness of the vastus lateralis muscle measured via ultrasound</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in knee extensor maximal isometric torque</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from baseline to 12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Knee extensor maximal isometric torque measured during a maximal voluntary contraction</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in grip strength</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from baseline to 12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Grip strength measured with a hand held dynamometer</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in functional physical abilities</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from baseline to 12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>A 30-second sit-to-stand test measured functional abilities</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">50</enrollment>
  <condition>Overweight and Obesity</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Resistance exercise training + weight loss group (RT+WL)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants (WL-RT) will be provided with a resistance exercise booklet containing instructions for exercises and links to demonstration videos. A demonstration and explanation of the exercises will be given at the beginning of the intervention, alongside a discussion of the principles of the programme such as starting level and progression. We will ask participants to perform the resistance exercises for 12-week period. Participants will be asked to perform exercises 3 times a week (3 sets reaching the RPE scale between 8 - 10 out of 10 (4-6 out of 10 in the first week)) for the intervention period. The exercises will include press-ups, band lateral raises, band seated low row, squat, lunge and calf raise.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Weight loss only group (WL)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>All participants (WL and WL-RT) will be provided with vouchers to access the weight watchers weight loss programme for a 12-week period. Weight Watchers is a commercially available programme and participants will set an initial goal to lose 5kg of body mass. If 5kg weight loss is achieved then the participant can chose further weight loss goals, as long as it would result in a body mass in the weight watchers healthy weight range (https://www.weightwatchers.com/uk/weight-loss/programme/tools/healthy-weight-chart).This plan works on the basis of an individualised points plan that can then be used by the participant to select foods/meals to consume throughout the day.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Resistance exercise training + weight loss group</intervention_name>
    <description>Doing resistance exercises as well as following the weight watchers weight loss programme for a 12-week period</description>
    <arm_group_label>Resistance exercise training + weight loss group (RT+WL)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Weight loss only group (WL)</intervention_name>
    <description>Only following the weight watchers weight loss programme for a 12-week period</description>
    <arm_group_label>Weight loss only group (WL)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Obesity or overweight (BMI ≥ 25kg/m2).&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Passing the Physical Activity Readiness Questionnaire (PAR-q+)&#xD;
&#xD;
        Exclusion Criteria:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Currently take part in more than 1.5 hours of structured exercise per week.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Having recently (&lt;6 months) taken part in any resistance exercise training, taking any&#xD;
             medications known to affect weight loss.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Actively engaged in a weight loss programme, having lost more than 2kg weight in the&#xD;
             last 6 months.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Any other reason which would limit ability to perform the exercises and outcome&#xD;
             measurements safely.&#xD;
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>65 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Stuart R Gray, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>01413302569</phone>
    <phone_ext>Gray</phone_ext>
    <email>stuart.gray@glasgow.ac.uk</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Ahmad S Binmahfoz, MSc</last_name>
    <email>a.binmahfoz.1@research.gla.ac.uk</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Stuart Robert Gray</name>
      <address>
        <city>Glasgow</city>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Stuart R Gray</last_name>
      <phone>01413302569</phone>
      <email>stuart.gray@glasgow.ac.uk</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <phone>01413302569</phone>
      <phone_ext>Gray</phone_ext>
      <email>stuart.gray@glasgow.ac.uk</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Stuart R Gray, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United Kingdom</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Upadhyay J, Farr O, Perakakis N, Ghaly W, Mantzoros C. Obesity as a Disease. Med Clin North Am. 2018 Jan;102(1):13-33. doi: 10.1016/j.mcna.2017.08.004. Epub 2017 Oct 21.</citation>
    <PMID>29156181</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>An R, Ji M, Zhang S. Global warming and obesity: a systematic review. Obes Rev. 2018 Feb;19(2):150-163. doi: 10.1111/obr.12624. Epub 2017 Oct 4.</citation>
    <PMID>28977817</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>James PT, Leach R, Kalamara E, Shayeghi M. The worldwide obesity epidemic. Obes Res. 2001 Nov;9 Suppl 4:228S-233S. doi: 10.1038/oby.2001.123.</citation>
    <PMID>11707546</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Siervo M, Montagnese C, Mathers JC, Soroka KR, Stephan BC, Wells JC. Sugar consumption and global prevalence of obesity and hypertension: an ecological analysis. Public Health Nutr. 2014 Mar;17(3):587-96. doi: 10.1017/S1368980013000141. Epub 2013 Feb 18.</citation>
    <PMID>23414749</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ge L, Sadeghirad B, Ball GDC, da Costa BR, Hitchcock CL, Svendrovski A, Kiflen R, Quadri K, Kwon HY, Karamouzian M, Adams-Webber T, Ahmed W, Damanhoury S, Zeraatkar D, Nikolakopoulou A, Tsuyuki RT, Tian J, Yang K, Guyatt GH, Johnston BC. Comparison of dietary macronutrient patterns of 14 popular named dietary programmes for weight and cardiovascular risk factor reduction in adults: systematic review and network meta-analysis of randomised trials. BMJ. 2020 Apr 1;369:m696. doi: 10.1136/bmj.m696. Erratum In: BMJ. 2020 Aug 5;370:m3095.</citation>
    <PMID>32238384</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lean ME, Leslie WS, Barnes AC, Brosnahan N, Thom G, McCombie L, Peters C, Zhyzhneuskaya S, Al-Mrabeh A, Hollingsworth KG, Rodrigues AM, Rehackova L, Adamson AJ, Sniehotta FF, Mathers JC, Ross HM, McIlvenna Y, Stefanetti R, Trenell M, Welsh P, Kean S, Ford I, McConnachie A, Sattar N, Taylor R. Primary care-led weight management for remission of type 2 diabetes (DiRECT): an open-label, cluster-randomised trial. Lancet. 2018 Feb 10;391(10120):541-551. doi: 10.1016/S0140-6736(17)33102-1. Epub 2017 Dec 5.</citation>
    <PMID>29221645</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Cava E, Yeat NC, Mittendorfer B. Preserving Healthy Muscle during Weight Loss. Adv Nutr. 2017 May 15;8(3):511-519. doi: 10.3945/an.116.014506. Print 2017 May.</citation>
    <PMID>28507015</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Enriquez Guerrero A, San Mauro Martin I, Garicano Vilar E, Camina Martin MA. Effectiveness of an intermittent fasting diet versus continuous energy restriction on anthropometric measurements, body composition and lipid profile in overweight and obese adults: a meta-analysis. Eur J Clin Nutr. 2021 Jul;75(7):1024-1039. doi: 10.1038/s41430-020-00821-1. Epub 2020 Dec 9.</citation>
    <PMID>33293678</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Pellegrini M, Cioffi I, Evangelista A, Ponzo V, Goitre I, Ciccone G, Ghigo E, Bo S. Effects of time-restricted feeding on body weight and metabolism. A systematic review and meta-analysis. Rev Endocr Metab Disord. 2020 Mar;21(1):17-33. doi: 10.1007/s11154-019-09524-w. Erratum In: Rev Endocr Metab Disord. 2020 Feb 18;:</citation>
    <PMID>31808043</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Wolfe RR. The underappreciated role of muscle in health and disease. Am J Clin Nutr. 2006 Sep;84(3):475-82. doi: 10.1093/ajcn/84.3.475.</citation>
    <PMID>16960159</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sajoux I, Lorenzo PM, Gomez-Arbelaez D, Zulet MA, Abete I, Castro AI, Baltar J, Portillo MP, Tinahones FJ, Martinez JA, Crujeiras AB, Casanueva FF. Effect of a Very-Low-Calorie Ketogenic Diet on Circulating Myokine Levels Compared with the Effect of Bariatric Surgery or a Low-Calorie Diet in Patients with Obesity. Nutrients. 2019 Oct 4;11(10):2368. doi: 10.3390/nu11102368.</citation>
    <PMID>31590286</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ashton RE, Tew GA, Aning JJ, Gilbert SE, Lewis L, Saxton JM. Effects of short-term, medium-term and long-term resistance exercise training on cardiometabolic health outcomes in adults: systematic review with meta-analysis. Br J Sports Med. 2020 Mar;54(6):341-348. doi: 10.1136/bjsports-2017-098970. Epub 2018 Jun 22.</citation>
    <PMID>29934430</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Cornelissen VA, Fagard RH, Coeckelberghs E, Vanhees L. Impact of resistance training on blood pressure and other cardiovascular risk factors: a meta-analysis of randomized, controlled trials. Hypertension. 2011 Nov;58(5):950-8. doi: 10.1161/HYPERTENSIONAHA.111.177071. Epub 2011 Sep 6.</citation>
    <PMID>21896934</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Plotnikoff RC, Eves N, Jung M, Sigal RJ, Padwal R, Karunamuni N. Multicomponent, home-based resistance training for obese adults with type 2 diabetes: a randomized controlled trial. Int J Obes (Lond). 2010 Dec;34(12):1733-41. doi: 10.1038/ijo.2010.109. Epub 2010 Jun 8.</citation>
    <PMID>20531348</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Mikesky AE, Topp R, Wigglesworth JK, Harsha DM, Edwards JE. Efficacy of a home-based training program for older adults using elastic tubing. Eur J Appl Physiol Occup Physiol. 1994;69(4):316-20. doi: 10.1007/BF00392037.</citation>
    <PMID>7851367</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Zion AS, De Meersman R, Diamond BE, Bloomfield DM. A home-based resistance-training program using elastic bands for elderly patients with orthostatic hypotension. Clin Auton Res. 2003 Aug;13(4):286-92. doi: 10.1007/s10286-003-0117-3.</citation>
    <PMID>12955554</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>NIH Consensus statement. Bioelectrical impedance analysis in body composition measurement. National Institutes of Health Technology Assessment Conference Statement. December 12-14, 1994. Nutrition. 1996 Nov-Dec;12(11-12):749-62.</citation>
    <PMID>8974099</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>May 2023</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>January 18, 2023</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 18, 2023</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">January 27, 2023</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 8, 2023</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 8, 2023</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 10, 2023</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Glasgow</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Stuart Gray</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Obesity</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Overweight</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Weight Loss</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

