<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="9326">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 09, 2023</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT05700422</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>851655</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT05700422</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Nasal Spray Study in Sjogren's Dry Eye Disease</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Single-arm Investigator Initiated Study to Evaluate the Efficacy of OC-01 (Varenicline Solution) Nasal Spray on Signs and Symptoms of Dry Eye Disease in Subjects With Sjogren's Syndrome</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Pennsylvania</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Oyster Point Pharma, Inc.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Pennsylvania</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>Yes</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study will investigate how well OC-01 (varenicline) nasal spray can treat the signs and&#xD;
      symptoms of dry eye disease in those Sjogren's Syndrome. Patients at least 18 years old with&#xD;
      moderate-to-severe Sjogren's dry eye disease may be eligible for this study. If you are&#xD;
      eligible to participate in the study and you decide to join, there will be 3 study visits&#xD;
      over approximately 1 month. You will also self-administer the nasal spray at home every day,&#xD;
      2 times a day during this month.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">May 1, 2023</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">February 2025</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">February 2024</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 4</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>N/A</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Mean change in cornea staining</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline to Day 28</time_frame>
    <description>The NEI scale is the method that will be used to measure corneal staining using fluorescein strips with a higher score indicating a higher level of staining. It divides the corneal and conjunctival surfaces to help measure fluorescein uptake.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Mean change in eye dryness score as measured by the Visual Analogue Scale (VAS)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline to Day 28</time_frame>
    <description>VAS is a validated, subjective measure for acute and chronic pain. Patients rate eye dryness on a scale of 1-10 with higher scores indicating high levels of pain.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Mean change in conjunctival staining</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline to Day 28</time_frame>
    <description>The Van Bijsterveld and Utrecht scale is the method that will be used to measure conjunctival staining while using lissamine green dye with higher vaules indicating higher levels of staining.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mean change in best corrected visual acuity</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline to Day 28</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mean change in dry mouth scale</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline to Day 28</time_frame>
    <description>VAS is a validated, subjective measure for acute and chronic pain. Patients rate mouth dryness on a scale of 1-10 with higher scores indicating high levels of pain.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence and severity of adverse events</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline to Day 28</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mean change in nose dryness scale</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline to Day 28</time_frame>
    <description>VAS is a validated, subjective measure for acute and chronic pain. Patients rate nose dryness on a scale of 1-10 with higher scores indicating high levels of pain.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">40</enrollment>
  <condition>Sjogren's Syndrome</condition>
  <condition>Dry Eye</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>OC-01 (varenicline solution) 0.03 mg nasal spray</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Varenicline Nasal Spray</intervention_name>
    <description>OC-01 (varenicline solution) 0.03 mg nasal spray</description>
    <arm_group_label>OC-01 (varenicline solution) 0.03 mg nasal spray</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Provide signed written consent prior to study-related procedures&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Be at least 22 years of age at the screening visit&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Have diagnosed moderate to severe Sjogrens Syndrome via blood work or biopsy Category&#xD;
             2 staining score for Conjunctiva based on the Van Bjisterveld and Utrect scale and 3&#xD;
             staining score for cornea based on the NEI scale&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Have been using Cyclosporine or Lifitegrast 3 months&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Be literate and able to complete questionnaires independently&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Be able and willing to use the study drug and participate in all study assessments and&#xD;
             visits&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Have sufficient hand strength, in the opinion of the Investigator, to be able to&#xD;
             independently administer the study drug&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Have provided verbal and written informed consent&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  If a female is of childbearing potential, they must: use an acceptable means of birth&#xD;
             control (acceptable methods of contraception include: hormonal oral, implantable,&#xD;
             injectable, or transdermal contraceptives, mechanical spermicide in conjunction with a&#xD;
             barrier such as a diaphragm or condom, IUD, or surgical sterilization of partner), and&#xD;
             have a negative urine pregnancy test on Day 1&#xD;
&#xD;
        Exclusion Criteria:&#xD;
&#xD;
        Have undergone previous ocular surgery (e.g., intraocular, oculoplastic, corneal or&#xD;
        refractive surgical procedure)&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Have had thermal pulsation or IPL in prior 3 months&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Have used topical ophthalmic corticosteroid therapy in prior 4 weeks&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Have had cataract surgery in the last 6 months&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Have clinically significant ocular trauma.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Have active ocular Herpes simplex or Herpes Zoster infection&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Have ocular inflammation (uveitis, iritis, scleritis, episcleritis, keratitis,&#xD;
             conjunctivitis) at the discretion of the investigator.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Have ocular infection (e.g., viral, bacterial, mycobacterial, protozoan or fungal&#xD;
             infection or the cornea, conjunctiva, lacrimal gland, lacrimal sac or eyelids&#xD;
             including hordeolum/stye).&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Have retinal pathology that can limit visual potential and refractive outcomes in the&#xD;
             opinion of the investigator&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Have severe (Grade 3 or 4) inflammation of the eyelid (e.g., blepharochalasis,&#xD;
             staphylococcal blepharitis or seborrheic blepharitis)&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Have eyelid abnormalities that significantly affect the lid function (e.g., entropion,&#xD;
             ectropion, tumor, edema, blepharospasm, lagophthalmos, severe trichiasis, severe&#xD;
             ptosis).&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Have ocular surface abnormality that may compromise the corneal integrity (e.g., prior&#xD;
             chemical burn, recurrent corneal erosion, corneal epithelial defect, Grade 3 corneal&#xD;
             fluorescein staining, map dot fingerprint dystrophy, or the effect of any other&#xD;
             ophthalmic medication that might in the opinion of the investigator compromise the&#xD;
             ocular surface integrity).&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Have a systemic condition or disease not stabilized or judged by the Investigator to&#xD;
             be incompatible with participation in the study or with the lengthier assessments&#xD;
             required by the study (e.g., current systemic infection, uncontrolled autoimmune&#xD;
             disease, uncontrolled immunodeficiency disease, history of myocardial infarction or&#xD;
             heart disease, etc.)&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Have chronic or recurrent epistaxis, coagulation disorders or other conditions that,&#xD;
             in the opinion of the Investigator, may lead to clinically significant risk of&#xD;
             increased bleeding.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Have had nasal or sinus surgery (including history of application of nasal cautery) or&#xD;
             significant trauma to these areas&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Be currently treated with nasal continuous positive airway pressure&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Have any untreated nasal infection at Visit 1&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Have a vascularized polyp, severely deviated septum, chronic recurrent nosebleeds, or&#xD;
             severe nasal obstruction as confirmed by intranasal examination performed at Visit 1.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Have a known hypersensitivity to any of the procedural agents or study drug components&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Be currently enrolled in an investigational drug or device study or have used an&#xD;
             investigational drug or device within 30 days prior to Visit 1 and during the&#xD;
             treatment period.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Be a female who is pregnant, nursing, or planning a pregnancy at Visit 1. Be a woman&#xD;
             of childbearing potential who is not using an acceptable means of birth control;&#xD;
             acceptable methods of contraception include: hormonal oral, implantable, injectable,&#xD;
             or transdermal contraceptives; mechanical spermicide in conjunction with a barrier&#xD;
             such as a diaphragm or condom; IUD; or surgical sterilization of partner. The risks of&#xD;
             OC-01 among pregnant patients are not known.&#xD;
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Giacomina Massaro-Giordano, MD</last_name>
    <phone>215-662-8038</phone>
    <email>ophth.clinicalresearch@pennmedicine.upenn.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Scheie Eye Institute at the University of Pennsylvania</name>
      <address>
        <city>Philadelphia</city>
        <state>Pennsylvania</state>
        <zip>19104</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Emma Iacobucci</last_name>
      <phone>215-662-9393</phone>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2023</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>January 14, 2023</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 25, 2023</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">January 26, 2023</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 10, 2023</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 10, 2023</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 12, 2023</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Pennsylvania</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Giacomina Massaro-Giordano</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Clinician, Co-Director, Penn Dry Eye &amp; Ocular Surface Center, and Professor of Clinical Ophthalmology</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Sjogren's Syndrome</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Dry Eye Syndromes</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Keratoconjunctivitis Sicca</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Eye Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Syndrome</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Varenicline</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

