<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="9333">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 09, 2023</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT05700279</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>21092002</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT05700279</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Preventing the Development of Chronic Pain: Treating PTSD at Acute Pain Onset</brief_title>
  <official_title>Preventing the Development of Chronic Pain: Treating PTSD at Acute Pain Onset</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Rush University Medical Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>United States Department of Defense</agency>
      <agency_class>U.S. Fed</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Rush University Medical Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Although most people recover from acute pain (such as pain caused by injury, surgery,&#xD;
      repetitive motion, or unknown causes), many people do not fully recover and will experience&#xD;
      chronic pain. Untreated posttraumatic stress disorder (PTSD) appears to be a key risk factor&#xD;
      for the transition from acute pain to chronic pain. However, few published studies have&#xD;
      addressed the issue of preventing the transition from acute to chronic pain via PTSD&#xD;
      reduction. This project will aim to test whether trauma-related PTSD symptoms can be reduced&#xD;
      using either Stellate Ganglion Block (SGB) treatment or Cognitive Processing Therapy (CPT),&#xD;
      and whether reducing PTSD symptoms can prevent the transition from non-injury based acute&#xD;
      pain to chronic pain.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Untreated PTSD appears to be a key risk factor for the transition from acute pain to chronic&#xD;
      pain. Thus, reducing PTSD symptoms during an acute pain episode may potentially decrease the&#xD;
      likelihood of transitioning to chronic pain. CPT is an evidence-based trauma-focused&#xD;
      cognitive behavioral treatment that is hypothesized to reduce PTSD symptoms via reducing&#xD;
      negative trauma-related cognitions about oneself, others, and the world. SGB treatment is an&#xD;
      injection of a local anesthetic into the stellate ganglion, which is a bundle of nerves&#xD;
      located at the base of the neck that is part of the sympathetic nervous system. Previous&#xD;
      studies suggest that 1-week massed CPT and SGB treatment can both reduce the severity of PTSD&#xD;
      symptoms in short periods of time via two distinct psychological and biological mechanisms.&#xD;
&#xD;
      This 4 year project will test study hypotheses in a sample of 345 individuals with PTSD&#xD;
      symptoms who present to the Emergency Department (ED) with non-injury based acute pain.&#xD;
      Participants will be randomly assigned to receive 1-week massed CPT, 2 SGB treatments, or&#xD;
      usual care. All participants will complete identical self-report and/or clinician&#xD;
      administered assessments at baseline (prior to randomization) and on study days 1, 7, 14, 21,&#xD;
      28, 56 (approximately 3 months after the initial ED presentation), and 112 (approximately 6&#xD;
      months after ED presentation).&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">June 1, 2023</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">February 1, 2027</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">February 1, 2027</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Patient-Reported Outcomes Measurement Information System (PROMIS) Pain Intensity</measure>
    <time_frame>Through study completion, for an average of 6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Intensity of chronic pain reported by subject. The PROMIS Pain Intensity scale consists of 3 questions with a 5-point response scale ranging from &quot;Had no pain&quot; -to &quot;Very severe. &quot; Participants are asked how intense their pain has been in the past 7 days. Higher scores indicate more intense pain.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in PTSD Checklist for Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders, 5th Edition (PCL-5) Self-Reported PTSD Symptoms</measure>
    <time_frame>Through study completion, for an average of 6 months</time_frame>
    <description>PCL-5 will be used to measure self-reported PTSD symptoms. The PCL-5 consists of 20 questions that ask how much a given symptom has bothered the participant within a specified time period. Each question has a 5 point response scale ranging from &quot;not at all&quot; (0) to &quot;extremely&quot; (4). Higher scores indicate greater PTSD symptom severity.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in CAPS-5 PTSD Diagnosis</measure>
    <time_frame>Through study completion, for an average of 6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Clinician Administered PTSD Scale for DSM-5 (CAPS-5) will be administered by a trained interviewer for formal assessment for PTSD diagnosis. The CAPS-5 is a semi-structured interview measure consisting of 30 items. Interviewers assess the frequency and intensity of PTSD symptoms; These frequency and severity scores for each item are then combined into one symptom severity score for each item that ranges from &quot;absent&quot; (0) to &quot;extreme/incapacitating&quot; (4). Higher scores indicate greater PTSD symptom severity.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in SCID-5 mood and anxiety disorder diagnoses</measure>
    <time_frame>Through study completion, for an average of 6 months</time_frame>
    <description>The Structured Clinical Interview for the DSM-5 (SCID-5) is a semi-structured interview measure for making DSM-5 diagnoses. The SCID-5 will be administered by a trained interviewer for assessment of mood and anxiety disorders.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in AUDIT-C Self-Reported Substance Use</measure>
    <time_frame>Through study completion, for an average of 6 months</time_frame>
    <description>The Alcohol Use Disorder Identification Test (AUDIT-C) is a self-report questionnaire consisting of 12 items that ask participants about the frequency of their alcohol and substance use both generally and within the past 2 weeks (14 calendar days).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Patient-Reported Outcomes Measurement Information System (PROMIS) Pain Interference</measure>
    <time_frame>Through study completion, for an average of 6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Interference in daily activities attributed to chronic pain as reported by subjects. The PROMIS Pain Interference scale consists of 8 questions with a 5-point response scale ranging from &quot;Not at all&quot; to &quot;Very much.&quot; Participants are asked how much in the past 7 days everyday activities were affected by their pain. Higher scores indicate more pain interference in daily activities.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Patient-Reported Outcomes Measurement Information System (PROMIS) Depression (Short Form)</measure>
    <time_frame>Through study completion, for an average of 6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Degree of depressive symptoms reported by subject. The PROMIS Depression scale consists of 8 questions with a 5-point response scale ranging from &quot;Never&quot; to &quot;Always.&quot; Participants are asked how often they felt depressive emotions in the past 7 days. Higher scores indicate more depressive emotions.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Patient-Reported Outcomes Measurement Information System (PROMIS) Physical Function (Short Form)</measure>
    <time_frame>Through study completion, for an average of 6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Amount of physical activity reported by subject. The PROMIS Physical Function scale consists of 10 questions with a 5-point response scale ranging from &quot;Without any difficulty&quot; to &quot;Unable to do.&quot; Participants are asked how much their pain affects their physical functioning. Higher scores indicate more inability to perform specific physical activities due to pain.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Patient-Reported Outcomes Measurement Information System (PROMIS) sleep disturbance (short form)</measure>
    <time_frame>Through study completion, for an average of 6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Degree of sleep disturbance reported by subject. The PROMIS Sleep Disturbance scale consists of 8 questions with a 5-point response scale ranging from &quot;Not at all&quot; to &quot;Very much.&quot; Participants are asked how much in the past 7 days their symptoms interfered with their sleep. Higher scores indicate more sleep disruptions.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Patient-Reported Outcomes Measurement Information System (PROMIS) anxiety (short form)</measure>
    <time_frame>Through study completion, for an average of 6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Degree of anxiety symptoms reported by subject. The PROMIS Anxiety scale consists of 7 questions with a 5-point response scale ranging from &quot;Never&quot; to &quot;Always.&quot; Participants are asked how often they experienced anxiety symptoms in the past 7 days. Higher scores indicate more anxiety symptoms.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Patient-Reported Outcomes Measurement Information System (PROMIS) anger (short form)</measure>
    <time_frame>Through study completion, for an average of 6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Degree of anger reported by subject. The PROMIS Anger scale consists of 5 questions with a 5-point response scale ranging from &quot;Never&quot; to &quot;Always.&quot; Participants are asked how often they experienced anger in the past 7 days. Higher scores indicate more frequent anger.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Patient-Reported Outcomes Measurement Information System (PROMIS) Satisfaction with Social Roles</measure>
    <time_frame>Through study completion, for an average of 6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Satisfaction with social roles reported by subject. The PROMIS Satisfaction with Social Roles scale consists of 7 questions with a 5-point response scale ranging from &quot;Not at all&quot; to &quot;Very Much.&quot; Participants are asked how satisfied they have felt with their performance in various social roles in the past 7 days. Higher scores indicate greater satisfaction.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">345</enrollment>
  <condition>PTSD</condition>
  <condition>Chronic Pain</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Stellate Ganglion Block Treatment</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants randomly assigned to the Stellate Ganglion Block (SGB) condition will receive 2 SGB treatments separated by 2 weeks.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Cognitive Processing Therapy</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants randomly assigned to the Cognitive Processing Therapy (CPT) condition will receive 1-week massed CPT treatment consisting of 10 CPT sessions given within a single 5-day period via telehealth.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Usual Care</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants randomly assigned to the Usual Care condition will not receive any active intervention.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Stellate Ganglion Block</intervention_name>
    <description>Stellate Ganglion Block (SGB) procedure involves an injection of a local anesthetic (0.5% ropivacaine) around the stellate ganglion (a bundle of nerves located at the base of the neck) to block the transmission of pain signals. The SGB injection is administered by an anesthesiologist.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Stellate Ganglion Block Treatment</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Cognitive Processing Therapy</intervention_name>
    <description>Cognitive Processing Therapy (CPT) is a form of trauma-based talk therapy that will be conducted by clinical therapists. CPT can help people identify and challenge unhelpful trauma-related beliefs about themselves, others, and the world.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Cognitive Processing Therapy</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:&#xD;
&#xD;
          1. Age 18 to 70 years&#xD;
&#xD;
          2. Ability to read and write English sufficiently to understand and complete study&#xD;
             questionnaires and participate in interviews&#xD;
&#xD;
          3. Presenting to the Rush Emergency Department (ED) with a medical problem and&#xD;
             experiencing non-injury based acute pain&#xD;
&#xD;
          4. A primary acute pain site of chest, back, shoulder, abdomen, or pelvis&#xD;
&#xD;
          5. Self-reported symptoms consistent with a diagnosis of PTSD&#xD;
&#xD;
        Exclusion Criteria:&#xD;
&#xD;
          1. Pain intensity great enough to impair concentration or capacity to understand&#xD;
             instructions or nature of being invited into a study, as assessed by a member of&#xD;
             medical staff&#xD;
&#xD;
          2. Any illness or injury that precludes the ability to understand or follow instructions,&#xD;
             as assessed by a member of the medical staff&#xD;
&#xD;
          3. Current illness that involves constant or frequent pain&#xD;
&#xD;
          4. Self-reported history of chronic pain on presentation to the ED or documented in the&#xD;
             electronic medical record&#xD;
&#xD;
          5. Pain from the traumatic event that is the source of their PTSD&#xD;
&#xD;
          6. Neurological disorder&#xD;
&#xD;
          7. Cancer diagnosis&#xD;
&#xD;
          8. Blood pressure greater than 160/100 mmHg&#xD;
&#xD;
          9. Taking anticoagulants or antiplatelet drugs other than aspirin&#xD;
&#xD;
         10. Pregnancy&#xD;
&#xD;
         11. Current or lifetime psychotic or bipolar disorders&#xD;
&#xD;
         12. Current alcohol or substance dependence&#xD;
&#xD;
         13. Receiving treatment for chronic or significant disease such rheumatoid disease,&#xD;
             current influenza that may manifest temporary flu-related pain, and heart disease.&#xD;
             People with well-controlled diabetes or HIV/AIDS will be included only if there is no&#xD;
             self-reported history of chronic or neuropathic pain on presentation to the ED or&#xD;
             documented in the electronic medical record.&#xD;
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>70 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>John W Burns, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Rush University Medical Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>John W Burns, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>312-942-0379</phone>
    <email>john_burns@rush.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Rush University Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Chicago</city>
        <state>Illinois</state>
        <zip>60612</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <contact>
      <last_name>John W Burns, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>312-942-0379</phone>
      <email>john_burns@rush.edu</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>April 2023</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>January 17, 2023</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 17, 2023</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">January 26, 2023</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 17, 2023</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 17, 2023</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">April 18, 2023</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>PTSD</keyword>
  <keyword>Chronic Pain</keyword>
  <keyword>Acute Pain</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Chronic Pain</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Acute Pain</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

