<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="9014">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 09, 2023</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT05707078</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>H-22067459</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT05707078</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>PET/CT Follow up for Head and Neck Squamous Cell Carcinoma</brief_title>
  <acronym>PET Follow</acronym>
  <official_title>PET/CT Follow up for Head and Neck Squamous Cell Carcinoma</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Rigshospitalet, Denmark</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Rigshospitalet, Denmark</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      PET/CT follow up for Head and Neck Squamous Cell Carcinoma The following is a presentation of&#xD;
      a prospective protocol, named PET/CT follow up for Head and Neck Squamous Cell Carcinoma (PET&#xD;
      Follow), including patients who have completed radiotherapy treatment for squamous cell&#xD;
      carcinoma of the head and neck (HNSCC).&#xD;
&#xD;
      The purpose of this study is to investigate the diagnostic performance of&#xD;
      18F-fluorodeoxy-D-glucose (FDG) Positron Emission Tomography/ Computed Tomography (PET/CT) in&#xD;
      patients with HNSCC after curative intended treatment.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      PET/CT follow up for Head and Neck Squamous Cell Carcinoma The following is a presentation of&#xD;
      a prospective protocol, named PET/CT follow up for Head and Neck Squamous Cell Carcinoma (PET&#xD;
      Follow), including patients who have completed radiotherapy treatment for squamous cell&#xD;
      carcinoma of the head and neck (HNSCC).&#xD;
&#xD;
      Purpose The purpose of this study is to investigate the diagnostic performance of&#xD;
      18F-fluorodeoxy-D-glucose (FDG) Positron Emission Tomography/ Computed Tomography (PET/CT) in&#xD;
      patients with HNSCC after curative intended treatment.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Background Head and neck cancer HNSCC is the most frequent malignancy in the head and neck&#xD;
      area and arises from the mucosal lining in the oral cavity, naso-, oro-, hypo-pharynx and&#xD;
      larynx. HNSCC is a heterogeneous disease in regard to involved anatomical subsite and&#xD;
      prognosis. Patients with human papilloma virus (HPV) related tumors in oropharynx have a good&#xD;
      prognosis, whereas patients with tobacco and alcohol related tumors have a relatively poor&#xD;
      prognosis. Treatment involves surgery and or radiotherapy (RT) with or without concomitant&#xD;
      chemotherapy depending on disease stage and anatomical sublocation. Even with optimal&#xD;
      treatment approximately 40-50% of the patients experience recurrence after treatment and the&#xD;
      majority of recurrences occurs within 2 years after treatment. Early detection of possible&#xD;
      recurrence is important to enable possible salvage treatment early. In Denmark patients are&#xD;
      followed up, according to DAHANCA guidelines (www.dahanca.dk), with clinical examination 2,&#xD;
      6, 12, 18, 24 months after ended treatment and then yearly until five years after end of&#xD;
      treatment. Although clinical examination of HNSCC patients can be difficult, routine follow&#xD;
      up with imaging is not recommended in Denmark but may be used on clinical suspicion of&#xD;
      relapse. Especially the neck is difficult to assess clinically, and some centers have&#xD;
      implemented routine imaging 2-3 months after ended treatment. However, there are no consensus&#xD;
      guidelines regarding imaging modality, timing nor how to interpretate the results. This lack&#xD;
      of consensus challenges the management of the patients following imaging procedures with&#xD;
      uncertain and varying specificity and sensitivity. Figure 1 below depicts the current follow&#xD;
      up management in Denmark.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Imaging Both surgical and radiotherapeutic treatment alter the anatomy in HNSCC patients&#xD;
      which challenge both clinical examination and conventional anatomical imaging with CT and&#xD;
      Magnetic Resonance Imaging (MRI). Imaging with FDG-PET is based on assessment of cellular&#xD;
      metabolism and thus less influenced by changes in anatomical structures and could be of value&#xD;
      to distinguish between treatment related changes and recurrence. On the other hand, increased&#xD;
      FDG can be seen in residual/recurrent tumour as well as in inflammation caused by&#xD;
      radiotherapy or recent surgery. Previously, planned neck dissection after RT has been routine&#xD;
      in some countries. But in a recent clinical randomized trial (PET-NECK), surveillance with&#xD;
      PET/CT proved non-inferior compared to routine planned neck dissection after RT treatment. In&#xD;
      the PET-NECK study patients were classified in three categories based on the PET/CT&#xD;
      assessment as follows: 1) incomplete response (ICR); 2.) equivocal response (EQR) and 3.)&#xD;
      complete response (CR). Both patients with ICR and EQR underwent neck dissection and only&#xD;
      patients with CR continued with conventional follow up in the PET-NECK study. Based on the&#xD;
      PET-NECK study, several institutions have changed the management of patients from planned&#xD;
      neck dissection to surveillance with PET/CT and preserved neck dissection only for patients&#xD;
      with ICR or EQR. However, the follow up management has in some institutes changed beyond the&#xD;
      PET-NECK study using further surveillance for patients with ICR or EQR, despite lack of&#xD;
      direct evidence to validate the safety of this approach. These institutes have gradually&#xD;
      adopted a more conservative, watch and wait, approach using PET/CT surveillance for patients&#xD;
      with EQR and in some cases patients with ICR on the evaluation PET/CT after treatment. These&#xD;
      patients have a repeated PET/CT scan 1-6 months later instead of immediate neck dissection.&#xD;
      This change in day to day practice is based on institutional experience and a few&#xD;
      retrospective studies reporting, that some patients may be spared from unnecessary neck&#xD;
      dissection. The watch and wait approach are driven mainly by two reasons. 1) The high&#xD;
      negative predictive value of the evaluation PET/CT scan can identify patients who can be&#xD;
      spared of neck dissection; And 2) The lower positive predictive value reported in&#xD;
      meta-analyses raise a concern of unnecessary neck dissection in patients whom on the repeated&#xD;
      PET/CT are converted from EQR or ICR to CR. Especially in patients with HPV related disease&#xD;
      who have a fairly good prognosis and tumors that seems to take longer to respond to RT.&#xD;
      Planned neck dissection after RT has never been the standard of care in Denmark and post&#xD;
      treatment evaluation with imaging has been preserved for patients with clinical suspicion of&#xD;
      recurrence. As such, the PET-NECK study has in principal not changed the routine follow up&#xD;
      guidelines for HNSCC patients in Denmark. However, also in Denmark a growing concern for&#xD;
      overtreating patients has led to a more conservative approach using PET/CT scans for&#xD;
      surveillance and gradually adopting a watch and wait approach without clear consensus&#xD;
      recommendations nor evidence supporting this approach.&#xD;
&#xD;
      There are two main concerns with the watch and wait strategy both with several potential&#xD;
      issues and pitfalls. The first concern relates to the lack of clinical guidelines on whom,&#xD;
      how and when to scan. There is no agreement nor consensus on the timing of the subsequently&#xD;
      PET/CT scans, and no well-established standardization on how to interpretate the PET/CT&#xD;
      scans. And there is no direct evidence recommending a watch and wait approach, which has led&#xD;
      to some ambiguity in different recommendations for follow up management for HNSCC patients.&#xD;
      The second concern relates to the uncertainties in the diagnostic performance in PET/CT.&#xD;
      There is a high physiological FDG uptake in head and neck area challenging the&#xD;
      interpretation, especially after surgery or radiotherapy, and the potential correlation&#xD;
      between FDG uptake and vital tumor cells is low and not well understood.&#xD;
&#xD;
      In this study both concerns will be addressed by investigating the diagnostic performance of&#xD;
      PET/CT scans in the follow up management of patients treated for HNSCC.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Aim&#xD;
&#xD;
      To achieve the purpose of the study the following specific aim (SA) will be addressed:&#xD;
&#xD;
      -SA1: Investigate the diagnostic performance of PET/CT scan in a post treatment setting and&#xD;
      calculate positive and negative predictive values.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Methods This is a prospective two stage single arm study where patients undergoing&#xD;
      surveillance after treatment for HNSCC will be offered inclusion in the study to quantify the&#xD;
      sensitivity, specificity, positive and negative predictive values of PET/CT 3 months after&#xD;
      radiotherapy treatment. Patients who have completed curative intended radiotherapy for HNSCC&#xD;
      in the oral cavity, pharynx or larynx and meet the inclusion criteria will be asked to&#xD;
      participate in the study.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Study plan Approximately 600 hundred patients were treated for HNSCC in eastern Denmark in&#xD;
      2020 (DAHANCA annual report; available in danish only www.DAHANCA.dk). We therefore expect&#xD;
      300-400 patients would be relevant candidates for this study and 200-300 to be accrued yearly&#xD;
      after initiation of the protocol. The enrollment in the study will not delay any treatment in&#xD;
      case of recurrence. Figure 1 depicts the current conventional follow up and figure 2&#xD;
      illustrates the follow up for the patients included in the study. Changes from conventional&#xD;
      follow up are marked in red.&#xD;
&#xD;
      All included patients will have a PET/CT performed three months after ended treatment.&#xD;
      Patients with EQR or ICR will undergo neck dissection.&#xD;
&#xD;
      PET/CT The PET/CT scans will be performed in accordance with EANM guidelines. The&#xD;
      interpretation of the PET/CT scans regarding N-site will be performed according to the&#xD;
      Deauville scoring system. Deauville relies on visual inspection of the relative difference in&#xD;
      tumor metabolism compared to surrounding normal tissue and/or background uptake in the&#xD;
      mediastinal blood pool and liver. The Deauville criteria use 5-point scales, where scores 1&#xD;
      and 2 effectively represent a complete metabolic response. The Deauville scoring system is&#xD;
      already known and used in lymphoma patients and proved to minimize indeterminate scan results&#xD;
      in the study by Zhong et al.&#xD;
&#xD;
      A central review board will be established between the three participating departments of&#xD;
      Clinical Physiology and Nuclear Medicine at Rigshospitalet, Herlev and Køge. The PET/CT scans&#xD;
      will be assessed by consultants at two of the involved departments and in case of lack of&#xD;
      consensus, the third department will be involved to ensure consensus by at least two&#xD;
      departments. Beside above the PET/CT scans will be assessed and described as done in clinical&#xD;
      routine.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Surgery The neck dissection will be performed according to institutional guideline and the&#xD;
      preoperative workup is done as in normal routine as are the postoperative follow up.&#xD;
      Suspicious lymph nodes will be marked separately according to anatomical orientation&#xD;
      per-operatively. The remaining specimen will be assessed and marked according to specified&#xD;
      involved neck levels.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Pathology During the histologic processing all identified lymph nodes will be removed and&#xD;
      examined with HE-staining, complemented if needed with other immunohistochemical stains as&#xD;
      done in routine diagnostic setting. The per-operatively marked lymph nodes will be sectioned&#xD;
      continuously and all slices embedded in paraffin. A pathological positive lymph node is&#xD;
      defined by presence of vital tumor cells.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Statistical considerations In the PET NECK study 47 of the 270 (17%) patients in the&#xD;
      surveillance group had CR at primary site but ICR or EQR at N-site, and 19 patients (7%) had&#xD;
      ICR in both T and N site. In the retrospective studies in literature the numbers of patients&#xD;
      with EQR or ICR are higher and reported from 37-40% in patients with HPV related HNSCC to 55%&#xD;
      in patients with HPV unrelated HNSCC and 51% in a cohort including patients with both HPV&#xD;
      related and unrelated HNSCC. In other words, the numbers of patients with CR, EQR and ICR&#xD;
      varies considerably between the different studies.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Stage one Based on the ambiguous results presented above, the first step in this two-stage&#xD;
      study is 1) to investigate how many patients will achieve CR, EQR and ICR on PET/CT performed&#xD;
      three months after treatment and 2) to identify a group of EQR patients on imaging with low&#xD;
      risk of pathologically viable tumor (&lt;5%).&#xD;
&#xD;
      In terms of statistical power assessment, a sample size of 160 achieves 80% power to detect a&#xD;
      difference (P1-P0) of 0.0550 using a one-sided exact test with a target significance level of&#xD;
      &lt; 0.0500 (The actual significance level achieved by this test is 0.0305). These results&#xD;
      assume that the population proportion under the null hypothesis (P0) is 0.0500.&#xD;
&#xD;
      In other words, a sample of 160 patients is required to determine that the patients in that&#xD;
      group has less than 10.5% risk of viable tumor cells assuming the underlying true risk is 5%.&#xD;
      Assuming 20% attrition or dropout, we should design for 200 patients undergoing NECK&#xD;
      dissection. With 200-300 patients included yearly and 20-50% with EQR or ICR based on the&#xD;
      literature, we expect 40-100 patients will have a NECK dissection performed yearly. Based on&#xD;
      this assumption we expect to complete the first stage within two to three years.&#xD;
&#xD;
      This is a realistic level for training a risk model in the first stage of the study. However,&#xD;
      given that the model will be data generated in this first stage, there is a need for a&#xD;
      confirmatory stage where the treatment is unchanged, but the risk model is fixed for&#xD;
      validation.&#xD;
&#xD;
      The included variables will include patient information such as smoking history and age and&#xD;
      clinical examination including ultrasound and clinical assessment of remission at T- and N-&#xD;
      site (complete remission or incomplete remission), p16 status, UICC stage, subsite and PET&#xD;
      results (CR, EQR and IR). Please see below subheading &quot;Respect for the subjects' physical and&#xD;
      mental integrity and privacy&quot;.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Annual interim analyses During both stage one and stage two an annual interim analysis will&#xD;
      be conducted and presented for the steering committee.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Stage two In the confirmatory stage we will proceed with a corresponding sample and sample&#xD;
      size as in stage one for model building and validate the model for predicting a low risk&#xD;
      (&lt;5%) of pathological viable tumor cells of stage one. The combined dataset of stage one and&#xD;
      stage two will be used to determine the diagnostic properties of imaging (positive predictive&#xD;
      value and negative predictive value) using best expert judgement.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Further stages Further stages will be considered adapted to the findings from stage one and&#xD;
      two and the most important clinical questions remaining and will be conducted as shared&#xD;
      decision making with the patients based on the predictive values established from stage one&#xD;
      and two. The future stages will aid in avoiding unnecessary operations in patients with low&#xD;
      risk and avoid delaying salvage treatment with extra control scans in patients with high&#xD;
      risk. Separate protocols for further stages will be sent to the scientific ethics committee&#xD;
      for approval and will not be initiated before approval.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Steering committee A steering committee will be established to assess the annual interim&#xD;
      analyses. Beside the already involved investigators, we propose one person from each of the&#xD;
      participating institutions and departments.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Inclusion criteria for the project patients&#xD;
&#xD;
        -  Informed consent&#xD;
&#xD;
        -  Age above 18&#xD;
&#xD;
        -  Completed curative treatment for HNSCC of the oral cavity, nasopharynx, oropharynx,&#xD;
           hypopharynx or larynx Exclusion criteria&#xD;
&#xD;
        -  Patient refusal&#xD;
&#xD;
        -  Patients with clinical N0 neck&#xD;
&#xD;
        -  Patients who had neck dissections prior to radiotherapy&#xD;
&#xD;
        -  Patients who are clinical inoperable for any reason&#xD;
&#xD;
      Investigators Capitol Region Department of Otorhinolaryngology, Head &amp; Neck Surgery and&#xD;
      Audiology, Rigshospitalet Signe B Gram, Jacob H Rasmussen, Irene Wessel and Christian von&#xD;
      Buchwald. Department of Oncology, Section of Radiotherapy, Rigshospitalet Ivan R Vogelius and&#xD;
      Jeppe Friborg Department of Oncology, Herlev Hospital Elo Verner Andersen Department of&#xD;
      Clinical Physiology and Nuclear Medicine, Rigshospitalet Barbara M Fischer and Danijela&#xD;
      Dejanovic Department of Clinical Physiology and Nuclear Medicine, Herlev Charlotte Birk&#xD;
      Christensen Department of Pathology, Rigshospitalet Giedrius Lelkaitis Region Zealand&#xD;
      Department of Otorhinolaryngology, Head &amp; Neck Surgery, Køge Hospital Gitte Hvilsom&#xD;
      Department of Oncology, Næstved Hospital Mohammad Farhadi Department of Clinical Physiology&#xD;
      and Nuclear Medicine, Køge Hospital Oriol Puig Calvo Dissemination of results The results&#xD;
      whether positive, negative or inconclusive will be published in international peer-reviewed&#xD;
      journals and submitted to national and international conferences.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">March 7, 2023</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 30, 2030</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 30, 2028</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>N/A</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of patients with malignant lymph nodes</measure>
    <time_frame>2 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Number of lymph nodes with vital tumor cells</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">600</enrollment>
  <condition>Head and Neck Squamous Cell Carcinoma</condition>
  <condition>PET/CT</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Surgery</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>Based on PET/CT scan patients will undergo neck dissection.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Neck dissection</intervention_name>
    <description>Based on PET/CT scan patients will undergo neck dissection.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Surgery</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Informed consent&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Age above 18&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Completed curative treatment for HNSCC of the oral cavity, nasopharynx, oropharynx,&#xD;
             hypopharynx or larynx&#xD;
&#xD;
        Exclusion Criteria:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Patient refusal&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Patients with clinical N0 neck&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Patients who had neck dissections prior to radiotherapy&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Patients who are clinical inoperable for any reason&#xD;
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Jacob H Rasmussen, MD; PhD</last_name>
    <phone>+4535453251</phone>
    <email>jacob.hoeygaard.rasmussen.01@regionh.dk</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <verification_date>March 2023</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>January 20, 2023</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 20, 2023</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">January 31, 2023</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 7, 2023</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 7, 2023</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 8, 2023</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Rigshospitalet, Denmark</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Jacob H Rasmussen</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>MD, PhD</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>PET/CT</keyword>
  <keyword>HNSCC</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Carcinoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Carcinoma, Squamous Cell</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Squamous Cell Carcinoma of Head and Neck</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

