<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="9992">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 09, 2023</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT05685732</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>KP415.P01</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT05685732</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>An Efficacy and Safety Study w/ Azstarys® in Children With ADHD</brief_title>
  <acronym>KP415P01</acronym>
  <official_title>A Multicenter, Dose-Optimized, Randomized, Double Blind, Efficacy and Safety Study With Azstarys® in Children 4 to 12 Years of Age With Attention Deficit/Hyperactivity Disorder</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Corium, Inc.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Premier Research Group plc</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Prometrika, LLC</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Almac</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Corium, Inc.</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is a multicenter, dose-optimized, randomized, double-blind, efficacy and safety study&#xD;
      with Azstarys® in children 4 to 12 years of age with attention-deficit/hyperactivity disorder&#xD;
      (ADHD). Azstarys® contains dexmethylphenidate (d-MPH) and serdexmethylphenidate (SDX), a&#xD;
      prodrug of d-MPH and is orally adminstered. The primary objective is to determine the&#xD;
      efficacy of Azstarys® compared to placebo in treating children ages 4 to 12 years old with&#xD;
      ADHD. The study will consist of two randomized and blinded treatment cohorts ages 4 to 5&#xD;
      years of age and 6 to 12 years of age. 130 and 100 subjects will be enrolled respectively.&#xD;
      Approximately 20 sites will participate.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      -  Screening Period (Visit 1) Subjects will undergo a screening period up to 30 days prior&#xD;
           to entering the Treatment Period.&#xD;
&#xD;
        -  Double-Blind Treatment Period (Visit 2 through Visit 6) Eligible subjects will be&#xD;
           randomized in a blinded fashion to Azstarys® or placebo at the start of the Treatment&#xD;
           Period. Randomization will be applied separately in each cohort and stratified by&#xD;
           gender.&#xD;
&#xD;
             -  Cohort 1: Subjects 4 and 5 years (&lt;6 years) will start at 13.1 mg/2.6 mg or&#xD;
                matching placebo and may be titrated up or down to doses of 13.1 mg/2.6 mg, 26.1&#xD;
                mg/5.2 mg, or 39.2 mg/7.8 mg Azstarys® or matching placebo approximately each week&#xD;
                through Visit 5&#xD;
&#xD;
             -  Cohort 2: Subjects 6-12 years (&lt;13 years) will start at 39.2 mg/7.8 mg or matching&#xD;
                placebo and may be titrated up or down to doses of 26.1 mg/5.2 mg, 39.2 mg/7.8 mg,&#xD;
                or 52.3 mg/10.4 mg Azstarys® or matching placebo approximately each week through&#xD;
                Visit 5&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">March 22, 2023</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">August 2024</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2024</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 4</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>The primary endpoint is defined as the change in a subject's ADHD Rating Scale total score in the Efficacy Population at Visit 6 compared to baseline (ADHD-RS total score at Visit 2). The Visit 2 baseline will be obtained prior to the first administration of study drug. The same analysis will be performed at other post-baseline visits. Visit 6 is the last visit of the Treatment Period (after the last dose of study drug).</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Quadruple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
    <masking_description>Study drug will be blinded during the Treatment Period. Neither the subject, the Investigator, nor the Sponsor will know the subject's treatment assignment.</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>A comparison of the change in mean ADHD Rating Scale (ADHD-RS) results from baseline to end of treatment between active and placebo treatments.</measure>
    <time_frame>4 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>The ADHD-RS is an 18-item scale based on Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders criteria of ADHD that rates symptoms on a 4-point scale. Each item is scored using a combination of severity and frequency ratings from a range of 0 (reflecting no symptoms or a frequency of never or rarely) to 3 (reflecting severe symptoms or a frequency of very often), so that the total ADHD-RS scores range from 0 to 54. Scores will be obtained during a clinician-directed interview with the parent/guardian/caregiver at each visit.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>A comparison of the change in mean Clinical Global Impressions-Severity (CGI-S) results from baseline to end of treatment between active and placebo treatments.</measure>
    <time_frame>4 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>The CGI-S is a clinician-rated scale that evaluates the severity of psychopathology (ADHD symptoms in the study) on a scale from 1 (not at all ill) to 7 (among the most severely ill).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>A comparison of the change in mean Clinical Global Impressions-Improvement (CGI-I) results from Visit 3 to end of treatment between active and placebo treatments.</measure>
    <time_frame>3 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>The CGI-I is a clinician-rated scale that evaluates the improvement of psychopathology (ADHD symptoms in the study) on a scale from 1 (very much improved) to 7 (very much worse).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>4</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">230</enrollment>
  <condition>Attention Deficit/Hyperactivity Disorder</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 1: SDX/d-MPH in 4-5 year old</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>13.1 mg/2.6 mg SDX/d-MPH, 26.1 mg/5.2 mg SDX/d-MPH, 39.2 mg/7.8 mg SDX/d-MPH</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 1: Placebo in 4-5 year old</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>matching placebo</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 2: SDX/d-MPH in 6-12 year old</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>26.1 mg/5.2 mg SDX/d-MPH, 39.2 mg/7.8 mg SDX/d-MPH, 52.3 mg/10.4 mg SDX/d-MPH</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 2: Placebo in 6-12 year old</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>matching placebo</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Serdexmethylphenidate (SDX) and dexmethylphenidate (d-MPH)</intervention_name>
    <description>Serdexmethylphenidate (SDX) and dexmethylphenidate (d-MPH)</description>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 1: SDX/d-MPH in 4-5 year old</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 2: SDX/d-MPH in 6-12 year old</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>placebo</intervention_name>
    <description>matching placebo</description>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 1: Placebo in 4-5 year old</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 2: Placebo in 6-12 year old</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:&#xD;
&#xD;
          1. In Cohort 1, subjects must be at least 4 years old and less than 5 years and 10 months&#xD;
             at Screening; in Cohort 2, subjects must be at least 6 years old and less than 12&#xD;
             years and 10 months at Screening.&#xD;
&#xD;
          2. Subjects must have a body weight within the 5th and 95th percentile according to the&#xD;
             gender-specific weight-for-age percentile charts from the Centers for Disease Control&#xD;
             and Prevention (CDC). See calculator at https://www.infantchart.com/child/.&#xD;
&#xD;
          3. Female subjects must agree, if they are of childbearing potential at Screening or when&#xD;
             they become of childbearing potential during the study, to remain abstinent or agree&#xD;
             to use an effective and medically acceptable form of birth control from the time of&#xD;
             written or verbal assent to at least 14 days after the last dose of study drug.&#xD;
             Childbearing potential is defined as follows: Girls under the age of 12 who have not&#xD;
             had their first period will be considered &quot;not of child-bearing potential.&quot; Girls 12&#xD;
             years of age (including girls who will become 13 years during the study) will be&#xD;
             considered &quot;of child-bearing potential,&quot; even if they have not yet had their first&#xD;
             period. Irrespective of age, girls who have had their first period, will be considered&#xD;
             &quot;of child-bearing potential.&quot;&#xD;
&#xD;
          4. Subjects must be in general good health defined as the absence of any clinically&#xD;
             relevant abnormalities as determined by the Investigator based on physical&#xD;
             examinations, vital signs, electrocardiograms (ECGs), medical history, and clinical&#xD;
             laboratory values (chemistry, hematology, urinalysis) at Screening. If any of the&#xD;
             chemistry or hematology tests are not within the laboratory's reference range, then&#xD;
             the subject can be included only if the Investigator determines the deviations to be&#xD;
             not clinically relevant.&#xD;
&#xD;
          5. At least one parent/legal guardian of the subject must voluntarily give written&#xD;
             permission for him/her to participate in the study.&#xD;
&#xD;
          6. Subjects in Cohort 2 must give written or verbal assent prior to study participation.&#xD;
             For verbal assent, the procedure will be documented and signed by a witness. A parent&#xD;
             or guardian may not be the witness for a child's verbal assent document.&#xD;
&#xD;
          7. Subject must meet Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders - Fifth&#xD;
             Edition (DSM-5) criteria for a primary diagnosis of ADHD (combined, inattentive, or&#xD;
             hyperactive/impulsive presentation) per clinical evaluation and confirmed by&#xD;
             Mini-International Neuropsychiatric Interview for Children and Adolescents (MINI Kid).&#xD;
&#xD;
          8. Subject has had ADHD symptoms present for at least 6 months prior to the Screening&#xD;
             Visit.&#xD;
&#xD;
          9. Subject must be able and willing to wash out current stimulant ADHD medications,&#xD;
             including herbal medications, from 5 days prior to the start of the Treatment Period,&#xD;
             and abstain from taking these to the end of Visit 6 or ET; and wash out non-stimulant&#xD;
             ADHD medications from 14 days prior to the start of the Treatment Period, and abstain&#xD;
             from taking these to the end of Visit 6.&#xD;
&#xD;
         10. Subject must have a score of ≥4 (Moderately Ill) on the clinician-administered&#xD;
             Clinical Global Impressions-Severity (CGI-S) scale. For subjects requiring washout of&#xD;
             ADHD medications, this criterion refers to a score following washout.&#xD;
&#xD;
         11. Subjects must have age and sex adjusted ratings of ≥90th percentile Total Score on the&#xD;
             ADHD-Rating Scale (ADHD-RS) rated over the past 6 months (for 4- and 5-year old&#xD;
             children, use Preschool Version of ADHD-RS-IV; for 6-12 years old children, use&#xD;
             ADHD-RS-5).&#xD;
&#xD;
         12. Subject functions at an age-appropriate level intellectually, as determined by the&#xD;
             Investigator.&#xD;
&#xD;
         13. Subject must have a systolic and diastolic blood pressure below the 95th percentile&#xD;
             for age and gender according to the 2017 AAP guidelines (Flynn 2017) based on the&#xD;
             average of 3 measurements 2-5 minutes apart.&#xD;
&#xD;
         14. Subject, subject's parent/legal guardian, and caregiver (if applicable) must&#xD;
             understand and be willing and able to comply with all study procedures and visit&#xD;
             schedule.&#xD;
&#xD;
         15. Subject, parent/legal guardian, and caregiver (if applicable) must be able to speak&#xD;
             and understand English or Spanish and be able to communicate satisfactorily with the&#xD;
             Investigator and study coordinator.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Exclusion Criteria:&#xD;
&#xD;
          1. If female, must not be pregnant or breastfeeding, and if of childbearing potential,&#xD;
             must have a negative urine pregnancy test at the start of the Screening Period. In&#xD;
             addition, a positive pregnancy test before the last dose of study drug will result in&#xD;
             early termination from the study.&#xD;
&#xD;
          2. Subject with any clinically significant chronic medical condition that, in the&#xD;
             judgment of the Investigator, may interfere with the participant's ability to&#xD;
             participate in the study.&#xD;
&#xD;
          3. Subject has any diagnosis of bipolar I or II disorder, major depressive disorder,&#xD;
             conduct disorder, obsessive-compulsive disorder, any history of psychosis, autism&#xD;
             spectrum disorder, disruptive mood dysregulation disorder (DMDD), intellectual&#xD;
             disability, Tourette's Syndrome, confirmed genetic disorder with cognitive and/or&#xD;
             behavioral disturbances. Subjects with oppositional defiant disorder (ODD) are&#xD;
             permitted to enroll in the study as long as ODD is not the primary focus of treatment,&#xD;
             and, in the opinion of the Investigator, the ODD is mild to moderate, and eligible&#xD;
             subjects with ODD are appropriate and cooperative during Screening.&#xD;
&#xD;
          4. Subject has generalized anxiety disorder or panic disorder that has been the primary&#xD;
             focus of treatment at any time during the 12 months prior to Screening or that has&#xD;
             required pharmacotherapy any time during the 6 months prior to Screening.&#xD;
&#xD;
          5. Subject has evidence of any chronic disease of the central nervous system (CNS) such&#xD;
             as tumors, inflammation, seizure disorder, depression, vascular disorder, potential&#xD;
             CNS-related disorders that might occur in childhood (e.g., Duchenne Muscular&#xD;
             dystrophy, myasthenia gravis, or other neurologic or serious neuromuscular disorders),&#xD;
             or history of persistent neurological symptoms attributable to serious head injury.&#xD;
&#xD;
          6. Subject taking anticonvulsants for seizure control or antidepressants currently or&#xD;
             within the past 2 years before Screening are not eligible for study participation. A&#xD;
             past history of febrile seizure or drug-induced seizure is allowed.&#xD;
&#xD;
          7. Subject has a current (last month) psychiatric diagnosis other than specific phobia,&#xD;
             motor skills disorders, ODD, sleep disorders, elimination disorders, adjustment&#xD;
             disorders, learning disorders, or communication disorders. Subjects allowed to enroll&#xD;
             with any of these DSM disorders will require written justification from the&#xD;
             Investigator documenting why the conditions will not interfere with participation and&#xD;
             to emphasize that ADHD is the primary indication.&#xD;
&#xD;
          8. In the opinion of the Investigator, subject has clinically significant suicidal&#xD;
             ideation/behavior, based on history of attempted suicide and the Columbia-Suicide&#xD;
             Severity Rating Scale (C-SSRS) assessment at Screening.&#xD;
&#xD;
          9. Subject has any clinically significant unstable medical abnormality, chronic disease&#xD;
             (including asthma or diabetes), or a history of a clinically significant abnormality&#xD;
             of the cardiovascular (including cardiomyopathy, serious arrhythmias, structural&#xD;
             cardiac disorders, or severe hypertension), gastrointestinal, respiratory, hepatic, or&#xD;
             renal systems, or a disorder or history of a condition (e.g., malabsorption,&#xD;
             gastrointestinal surgery) that may interfere with absorption, distribution,&#xD;
             metabolism, or excretion of study drug. In cases in which the impact of the condition&#xD;
             upon risk to the subject or study results is unclear, the medical monitor should be&#xD;
             consulted. Any subject with a known cardiovascular disease or condition (even if&#xD;
             controlled) must be discussed with the Medical Monitor during Screening.&#xD;
&#xD;
         10. Subject has a history or presence of abnormal ECGs, which in the Investigator's&#xD;
             opinion is clinically significant.&#xD;
&#xD;
         11. Subject has a history of, or currently has, a malignancy.&#xD;
&#xD;
         12. Subject has uncontrolled thyroid disorder as evidenced by thyroid stimulating hormone&#xD;
             (TSH) ≤0.8 x the lower limit of normal (LLN) or ≥1.25 x the upper limit of normal&#xD;
             (ULN) for the reference laboratory at Screening.&#xD;
&#xD;
         13. Subject has greater than trace proteinuria in the urinalysis at Screening. Subjects&#xD;
             with greater than trace proteinuria in the urinalysis at Screening but with a urine&#xD;
             protein to creatinine (UP/C) ratio &lt;0.2 in a first morning void urine sample will not&#xD;
             be excluded from enrollment.&#xD;
&#xD;
         14. Subjects has a current or recent (past 12 months) history of drug abuse; or current or&#xD;
             recent history of drug abuse in someone living in the subject's home, or are using or&#xD;
             planning to use prohibited drugs during the trial as specified in the protocol.&#xD;
&#xD;
         15. Subject has a positive urine drug screen at Screening. Subjects with a positive&#xD;
             methylphenidate (MPH) urine drug screen may be allowed to continue in the study,&#xD;
             provided that the Investigator determines that the positive test is a result of taking&#xD;
             prescribed medications and subject is willing to wash out the current medication as&#xD;
             required.&#xD;
&#xD;
         16. Subject has participated in any other clinical study with an investigational&#xD;
             drug/product within 30 days or at least 5 half-lives, whichever is longer, prior to&#xD;
             Screening.&#xD;
&#xD;
         17. Subject has taken ADHD medications from more than one class within 30 days prior to&#xD;
             Screening. Subjects on a stable dose of one ADHD medication with occasional use of&#xD;
             ADHD medications from another class are eligible at the discretion of the&#xD;
             Investigator.&#xD;
&#xD;
         18. Subjects with demonstrated lack of response or intolerability to adequate dose and&#xD;
             duration of treatment with MPH products. Judgment of adequate dose and duration is at&#xD;
             the discretion of the Investigator.&#xD;
&#xD;
         19. Subject has a positive urine MPH screen by dipstick (e.g., NarcoCheck®) at Visit 2.&#xD;
&#xD;
         20. Subject is planning to initiate psychotherapy during the study (subjects participating&#xD;
             in psychotherapy beginning at least 4 weeks before study initiation are permitted to&#xD;
             continue).&#xD;
&#xD;
         21. Subject has a history of severe allergies or adverse drug reactions to more than one&#xD;
             class of medications.&#xD;
&#xD;
         22. Subject has a history of allergic reaction or a known or suspected sensitivity to MPH&#xD;
             or any substance that is contained in the study drug.&#xD;
&#xD;
         23. Subject, parent/legal guardian, and caregiver (if applicable, at the Investigator's&#xD;
             discretion) has commitments during the study that would interfere with attending study&#xD;
             visits.&#xD;
&#xD;
         24. Subject or subject's family anticipates a move outside the geographic range of the&#xD;
             investigative site during the study period, or plans extended travel inconsistent with&#xD;
             the recommended visit interval during study duration.&#xD;
&#xD;
         25. Subject has one or more siblings living in the same household who are enrolled in this&#xD;
             or another clinical drug trial.&#xD;
&#xD;
         26. Subject shows evidence of current physical, sexual, or emotional abuse.&#xD;
&#xD;
         27. Subject is, in the opinion of the Investigator, unsuitable in any other way to&#xD;
             participate in this study.&#xD;
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>4 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>12 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Ann Childress, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Center for Psychiatry And Behavioral Medicine Inc.</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Ron Tashjian</last_name>
    <phone>6172337474</phone>
    <email>rtashjian@coriumintl.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Charles Oh, MD</last_name>
    <phone>857-331-7950</phone>
    <email>coh@coriumintl.com</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Preferred Research Partners (PRP)</name>
      <address>
        <city>Little Rock</city>
        <state>Arkansas</state>
        <zip>72211</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Amy Kelley</last_name>
      <phone>501-553-9987</phone>
      <email>akelley@preferredresearchpartners.com</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Renea Henderson, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>IMMUNOe International Research center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Centennial</city>
        <state>Colorado</state>
        <zip>80112</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Maureen Collins</last_name>
      <phone>303-771-9000</phone>
      <email>mcollins@immunoe.com</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Joe Williams, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Vertex Research Group inc</name>
      <address>
        <city>Clermont</city>
        <state>Florida</state>
        <zip>34711</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Austin Wing</last_name>
      <phone>352-261-0901</phone>
      <email>austin.wing@vtxresearch.com</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Ayesha Lall, M.A</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Clinical Neuroscience Solutions- Orlando</name>
      <address>
        <city>Jacksonville</city>
        <state>Florida</state>
        <zip>32256</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Susan Angel</last_name>
      <phone>904-281-5757</phone>
      <email>sangel@cnshealthcare.com</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Nandita Jones, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Accel Research Sites</name>
      <address>
        <city>Lakeland</city>
        <state>Florida</state>
        <zip>33803</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Colleen Figueroa</last_name>
      <phone>863-940-2087</phone>
      <email>cfigueroa@accelclinical.com</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Rosa Negron, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Accel Research Sites</name>
      <address>
        <city>Maitland</city>
        <state>Florida</state>
        <zip>32751</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Ashley McCaffrey</last_name>
      <phone>407-644-1165</phone>
      <email>amccaffrey@accelclinical.com</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Andrea Marraffino, Ph.D</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>South Florida Research Phase I-IV INC</name>
      <address>
        <city>Miami Springs</city>
        <state>Florida</state>
        <zip>33166</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Lisbelle Revoredo</last_name>
      <phone>305-418-0847</phone>
      <email>lrevoredo@southfloridatrials.com</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Silvia S Duluc, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>CNS Healthcare</name>
      <address>
        <city>Orlando</city>
        <state>Florida</state>
        <zip>32801</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Eric McCaffrey</last_name>
      <phone>407-425-5100</phone>
      <email>emccaffrey@cnshealthcare.com</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Robert Molpus, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Sky Clinical Research Network Group P.C</name>
      <address>
        <city>Atlanta</city>
        <state>Georgia</state>
        <zip>30339</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Quinci Kennedy</last_name>
      <phone>470-317-3604</phone>
      <email>quinci.kennedy@skycrng.com</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Yvonne Smith, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>iResearch Atlanta</name>
      <address>
        <city>Decatur</city>
        <state>Georgia</state>
        <zip>30030</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Morgan Hecker</last_name>
      <phone>404-537-1281</phone>
      <email>Morgan.Hecker@iresearchatlanta.com</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Kimball Johnson, MS</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>CenExel iResearch, LLC</name>
      <address>
        <city>Savannah</city>
        <state>Georgia</state>
        <zip>31405</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Jennifer Clifton</last_name>
      <phone>912-722-0800</phone>
      <email>jennifer.clifton@iresearchsavannah.com</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Yael Elfassy, M.S</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>DelRicht Research- Touro Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>New Orleans</city>
        <state>Louisiana</state>
        <zip>70115</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Lesley A Saketkoo</last_name>
      <phone>504-336-2667</phone>
      <email>lsaketk@tulane.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Caroline Campion, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>St. Charles Psychiatric Associates &amp; Midwest Research Group</name>
      <address>
        <city>Saint Charles</city>
        <state>Missouri</state>
        <zip>80112</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Joshua Wilson</last_name>
      <phone>636-946-8032</phone>
      <email>drwilson2017@yahoo.com</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Gregory Mattingly, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Boeson research</name>
      <address>
        <city>Missoula</city>
        <state>Montana</state>
        <zip>75093</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Heather Marshall</last_name>
      <phone>406-763-8833</phone>
      <email>heatherm@bluemoose.me</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Merlin Fausett, Ph.D</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Alivation Research, LLC</name>
      <address>
        <city>Lincoln</city>
        <state>Nebraska</state>
        <zip>68526</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Katy Boman</last_name>
      <phone>402-817-2235</phone>
      <email>kboman@alivation.com</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Walter Duffy, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Center for Psychiatry and Behavioral Medicine Inc</name>
      <address>
        <city>Las Vegas</city>
        <state>Nevada</state>
        <zip>89128</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Randi Lampert</last_name>
      <phone>702-838-0742</phone>
      <email>randi.lampert@gmail.com</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Ann C Childress, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Dayton Clinical Research</name>
      <address>
        <city>Dayton</city>
        <state>Ohio</state>
        <zip>45409</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Missy Chapman</last_name>
      <phone>937-276-4311</phone>
      <email>daytonclinical@aol.com</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Martin Schear, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>IPS Research Company, Inc.</name>
      <address>
        <city>Oklahoma City</city>
        <state>Oklahoma</state>
        <zip>73106</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Matthew Korstjens</last_name>
      <phone>405-235-8188</phone>
      <email>mkorstjens@ipsresearch.com</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Louise Thurman</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Clinical Nueroscience Solution, Inc</name>
      <address>
        <city>Memphis</city>
        <state>Tennessee</state>
        <zip>38119</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Anthony Codi</last_name>
      <phone>901-843-1045</phone>
      <email>canthony@cnhealthcare.com</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Valerie Arnold, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Houston Clinical Trials</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bellaire</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>77401</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Johnny Timmons</last_name>
      <phone>713-527-8993</phone>
      <email>jtimmons@houstonclintrials.com</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Alain Katic, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>AIM Trials</name>
      <address>
        <city>Plano</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>75093</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Sonia Prashar</last_name>
      <phone>972-267-1988</phone>
      <email>sonia.prashar@aimtrials.com</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Sejal Mehta, Ph.D</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Flourish Research</name>
      <address>
        <city>San Antonio</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>78229</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Nathan Cortez</last_name>
      <phone>210-949-0122</phone>
      <email>ncortez@flourishresearch.com</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Kerry D Jesus, MS</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>January 2023</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>December 13, 2022</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 5, 2023</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">January 17, 2023</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 24, 2023</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 24, 2023</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 25, 2023</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Hyperkinesis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Attention Deficit Disorder with Hyperactivity</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Dexmethylphenidate Hydrochloride</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

