<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="9908">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 09, 2023</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT05687708</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>MedipolDKT</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT05687708</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Effect of Non-nutritive Sucking on Transition to Oral Feeding in Infants With Asphyxia</brief_title>
  <official_title>Effect of Non-nutritive Sucking Stimulation on Oral Intake and Early Feeding Skills in Newborns With Perinatal Asphyxia: A Randomized Controlled Trial</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Medipol University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Medipol University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The transition period to full oral feeding in infants with perinatal asphyxia is important in&#xD;
      predicting long-term outcomes. The transition to independent oral feeding is accepted as a&#xD;
      discharge criterion by the American Academy of Pediatrics, and the long transition from tube&#xD;
      feeding to oral feeding prolongs the discharge process. Prolonged transition to oral feeding&#xD;
      increases maternal stress as it delays gastrointestinal problems, mother-infant interaction&#xD;
      and attachment, as well as increasing health expenditures. Due to long-term feeding tube use;&#xD;
      Infection, leakage, delay in wound healing, trauma caused by repeated placement, as well as&#xD;
      oral reluctance are observed. In asphyxia infants, in whom oral-motor dysfunction is common,&#xD;
      the transition to oral feeding takes a long time and tube feeding support is required. The&#xD;
      effect of hypothermia, which is a general therapeutic intervention that reduces the risk of&#xD;
      mortality and morbidity in infants with asphyxia, on oral feeding has been previously studied&#xD;
      and shown to have a positive effect. They also found that MR imaging in infants with asphyxia&#xD;
      and the need for gastrostomy and tube feeding in those with brainstem involvement were&#xD;
      associated.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Various interventions that affect the transition to oral nutrition positively and shorten the&#xD;
      discharge time are included in the literature. Stimulation of non-nutritive sucking (NNS) is&#xD;
      the most frequently preferred method among these interventions. It has been shown in studies&#xD;
      that there are no short-term negative effects of NNS stimulation with the help of a pacifier&#xD;
      or gloved finger, and some clinical benefits such as better bottle feeding performance,&#xD;
      acceleration of discharge and transition to oral feeding.&#xD;
&#xD;
      The effect of the NNS stimulation method, which has been shown to be effective in preterm&#xD;
      infants with large-scale randomized controlled studies, is not known exactly.&#xD;
&#xD;
      The aim of this study is to examine the effect of NNS stimulation applied to oral feeding,&#xD;
      feeding skills, weight gain and discharge in asphyxia infants receiving hypothermia&#xD;
      treatment.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Perinatal asphyxia is the interruption of fetal blood flow or gas exchange during the&#xD;
      perinatal period. Injury to the brain as a result of systemic hypoxia caused by disruption of&#xD;
      gas exchange and slowing of cerebral blood flow is called hypoxic ischemic encephalopathy&#xD;
      (HIE). Perinatal asphyxia may be maternally related or may occur as a result of conditions&#xD;
      related to the placenta and the newborn itself. It may have etiologies such as maternal&#xD;
      diseases such as diabetes, hypertension or preeclampsia, uterine rupture, cord compression,&#xD;
      congenital airway anomalies of the newborn, neurological disorder, and severe cardiopulmonary&#xD;
      disease. According to the World Health Organization (WHO) report, perinatal asphyxia causes 4&#xD;
      million newborn deaths every year and constitutes 23% of total neonatal deaths. Asphyxia,&#xD;
      which has effects such as death, seizures and HIE in the short term, has effects such as&#xD;
      motor disorders such as cerebral palsy, sensory disorders such as vision and hearing loss,&#xD;
      cognitive, neurodevelopmental, behavioral and emotional disorders in the long term.&#xD;
      Malnutrition is a problem that can occur both in the short and long term. In the short term,&#xD;
      it may have consequences such as orogastric or nasogastric tube feeding due to sucking and/or&#xD;
      swallowing dysfunction, prolonged feeding times in the long term, frequent coughing,&#xD;
      aspiration pneumonia and gastrostomy. The transition period to full oral feeding in infants&#xD;
      with perinatal asphyxia is important in predicting long-term outcomes. The transition to&#xD;
      independent oral feeding is accepted as a discharge criterion by the American Academy of&#xD;
      Pediatrics, and the long transition from tube feeding to oral feeding prolongs the discharge&#xD;
      process. Prolonged transition to oral feeding increases maternal stress as it delays&#xD;
      gastrointestinal problems, mother-infant interaction and attachment, as well as increasing&#xD;
      health expenditures. Due to long-term feeding tube use; Infection, leakage, delay in wound&#xD;
      healing, trauma caused by repeated placement, as well as oral reluctance are observed. In&#xD;
      asphyxia infants, in whom oral-motor dysfunction is common, the transition to oral feeding&#xD;
      takes a long time and tube feeding support is required. The effect of hypothermia, which is a&#xD;
      general therapeutic intervention that reduces the risk of mortality and morbidity in infants&#xD;
      with asphyxia, on oral feeding has been previously studied and shown to have a positive&#xD;
      effect. They also found that MR imaging in infants with asphyxia and the need for gastrostomy&#xD;
      and tube feeding in those with brainstem involvement were associated.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Various interventions that affect the transition to oral nutrition positively and shorten the&#xD;
      discharge time are included in the literature. Stimulation of non-nutritive sucking (NNS) is&#xD;
      the most frequently preferred method among these interventions. It has been shown in studies&#xD;
      that there are no short-term negative effects of NNS stimulation with the help of a pacifier&#xD;
      or gloved finger, and some clinical benefits such as better bottle feeding performance,&#xD;
      acceleration of discharge and transition to oral feeding.&#xD;
&#xD;
      The effect of the NNS stimulation method, which has been shown to be effective in preterm&#xD;
      infants with large-scale randomized controlled studies, is not known exactly. The NNS&#xD;
      stimulation method applied in a newborn with severe asphyxia with medical complications was&#xD;
      investigated in a case study and it was pointed out that it could have positive results, but&#xD;
      more research should be done in this patient group.&#xD;
&#xD;
      The aim of this study is to examine the effect of NNS stimulation applied to oral feeding,&#xD;
      feeding skills, weight gain and discharge in asphyxia infants receiving hypothermia&#xD;
      treatment.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">November 1, 2021</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2023</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">May 2023</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Triple (Participant, Care Provider, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Early Feeding Skills Assessment Tool</measure>
    <time_frame>1 month</time_frame>
    <description>are the scores obtained by the clinician from the early feeding assessment tool. The minimum score that can be obtained from the scale is 19, and the maximum score is 57. A higher score indicates better feeding skills.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Time from tube feeding to oral intake</measure>
    <time_frame>20 days</time_frame>
    <description>how many days the baby transitions from tube feeding to oral intake</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>discharge time</measure>
    <time_frame>1 month</time_frame>
    <description>how many days the baby is discharged from the neonatal intensive care unit</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>weight gain</measure>
    <time_frame>1 month</time_frame>
    <description>is the weight information of the baby at certain intervals</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">100</enrollment>
  <condition>Swallowing Disorder</condition>
  <condition>Perinatal Asphyxia</condition>
  <condition>Feeding; Difficult, Newborn</condition>
  <condition>Feeding Disorder of Infancy or Early Childhood</condition>
  <condition>Hypoxic-Ischemic Encephalopathy</condition>
  <condition>Speech Therapy</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Non-Nutritive Sucking</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Non-Nutritive Sucking</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>routine treatment</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Non-Nutritive Sucking</intervention_name>
    <description>NNS is stimulated by giving stimulus into the baby's mouth with the help of a finger wearing gloves.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Non-Nutritive Sucking</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  to be diagnosed with asphyxia,&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  to have received hypothermia treatment,&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  to have started enteral nutrition,&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  to have physiological stability to tolerate NNS stimulation.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Exclusion Criteria:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Having a craniofacial anomaly,&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  having a congenital anomaly,&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  being referred to another center/hospital during treatment.&#xD;
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>34 Months</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>41 Months</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Seyhun Topbas</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>Medipol University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Hilal Berber Çiftci, Lecturer</last_name>
    <phone>00905447604184</phone>
    <email>hilalberber1@gmail.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Seyhun Topbas, Professor</last_name>
    <phone>00905327324684</phone>
    <email>sstopbas@medipol.edu.tr</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Medipol University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Istanbul</city>
        <country>Turkey</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Seyhun sstopbas@medipol.edu.tr</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Turkey</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Harding C, Frank L, Dungu C, Colton N. The use of nonnutritive sucking to facilitate oral feeding in a term infant: a single case study. J Pediatr Nurs. 2012 Dec;27(6):700-6. doi: 10.1016/j.pedn.2012.01.006. Epub 2012 Feb 22.</citation>
    <PMID>22366642</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>April 2023</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>January 8, 2023</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 8, 2023</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">January 18, 2023</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 7, 2023</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 7, 2023</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">April 10, 2023</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Medipol University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Hilal Berber Çiftci</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Doctoral Student, Speech and Language Therapist</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>perinatal asphyxia</keyword>
  <keyword>non-nutritive sucking</keyword>
  <keyword>oral feeding</keyword>
  <keyword>oral stimulation</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Deglutition Disorders</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Brain Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Brain Ischemia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hypoxia-Ischemia, Brain</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Communication Disorders</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Asphyxia Neonatorum</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Disease</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Asphyxia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Feeding and Eating Disorders</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

