<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="9413">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 09, 2023</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT05698355</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>Akdeniz</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT05698355</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Telerehabilitation in Chronic Pelvic Pain</brief_title>
  <acronym>CPP</acronym>
  <official_title>Telerehabilitation in Chronic Pelvic Pain</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Akdeniz University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Akdeniz University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Objective: Physical therapists utilize telerehabilitation as the common term for telehealth&#xD;
      applications. Many physiotherapists worked as telehealth providers during the coronavirus&#xD;
      pandemic. The objective of the study will show the efficacy of Telerehabilitation-Based&#xD;
      Physical Therapy (TBPT) on pain intensity and treatment satisfaction in patients with chronic&#xD;
      pelvic pain.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Method: This study is a prospective study of patients with chronic pelvic pain.42&#xD;
      participants will include the study. Patients who have any other distribution pattern of&#xD;
      pelvic pain were equally considered for therapy. Women age between 18-50 years will be&#xD;
      include. Their symptoms should be one of these follows such as chronic pain in pelvic region,&#xD;
      hyperalgesia in vulva, and pain during sitting or intercourse. They will get diagnosed by a&#xD;
      gynecologist who is a multidisciplinary team comprising and referred to a pelvic health&#xD;
      physiotherapist. Prior to treatment patients will complete questionnaires and interview a&#xD;
      pelvic health physiotherapist. Pain symptoms will be assessed with the Visual Analog Scale&#xD;
      (VAS) and The Pelvic Pain Impact Questionnaire (PPIQ) before and after treatment. Patient&#xD;
      Global Impression of Improvement (PGI-I) for evaluating patient satisfaction after treatment.&#xD;
      Women with chronic pelvic pain will be treated for 16 sessions (an hour for each session) in&#xD;
      8 weeks with the TBPT technique by the same pelvic health physiotherapist (AB). Patients will&#xD;
      apply internal and external trigger point release therapy and self-massage techniques by&#xD;
      themselves with Telerehabilitation-Based Physical Therapy.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Telerehabilitation is described as the remote conveyance of healthcare services and clinical&#xD;
      information using information and telecommunication technologies involving the internet,&#xD;
      wireless satellite, and telephone media to provide a series of rehabilitation services by&#xD;
      eliminating the barriers of distance, time, and travel to receive care. There is an abundance&#xD;
      of commercially available applications (such as Zoom) offered for health care monitoring and&#xD;
      management. Most of the studies have employed telerehabilitation methods with patients who&#xD;
      have pain, mainly for assessment or exercise programs. There is not any study on the&#xD;
      telerehabilitation application of physical therapy in patients with chronic pelvic pain&#xD;
      during the coronavirus pandemic.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Our conceptual framework is based on two arguments. First, physiotherapists need physical&#xD;
      access to their patients only for a limited number of interventions. Most of the methods used&#xD;
      by physiotherapists to treat their patients can be conducted at a distance without having&#xD;
      direct access to the patient. Previous studies have shown that telerehabilitation can be used&#xD;
      in many cases and provide results on par with face-to-face treatment. In fact,&#xD;
      self-administered treatment was found to be effective even in the case of postal treatment&#xD;
      where the participants received instruction through postal systems.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Second, the pelvic floor area is relatively well-suited for self-treatment. Most, if not all,&#xD;
      of the exercises and procedures, can be safely conducted by the patients themselves. The&#xD;
      patients can even use pelvic wands and dilators for harder-to-reach inner release points.&#xD;
      Therefore, training the patient and supervising and guiding self-administered procedures&#xD;
      should be sufficiently effective to reduce pelvic pain and reach patient satisfaction in most&#xD;
      cases.&#xD;
&#xD;
      The aim of the study will show the efficacy of Telerehabilitation-Based Physical Therapy&#xD;
      (TBPT) on pain intensity and treatment satisfaction in patients with chronic pelvic pain.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">January 16, 2023</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">May 10, 2023</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">January 16, 2023</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Randomized control trial</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Pelvic Pain Impact Questionnaire</measure>
    <time_frame>1-3 monts</time_frame>
    <description>The Pelvic Pain Impact Questionnaire is a questionnaire composed of eight (8) questions. The patient is asked to grade how pelvic pain has affected various activities on a 5-point Likert scale. The total score is obtained by adding the scores given for each item, a high score is directly proportional to the severity of pain.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>VAS</measure>
    <time_frame>1-3 months</time_frame>
    <description>The VAS is frequently used in cases where rapid measurement of pain intensity is required in clinical and laboratory conditions. It consists of drawing a line from zero (0) to ten (10) and ask the patient to mark the pain intensity on the line where zero (0) means &quot;I have no pain&quot; and ten (10) means &quot;the most severe pain possible&quot;.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>The Female Sexual Function Index</measure>
    <time_frame>1-3 months</time_frame>
    <description>The Female Sexual Function Index is a brief multidimensional scale for assessing sexual function in women. The scale has received initial psychometric evaluation, including studies of reliability, convergent validity, and discriminant validity</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>The Female Sexual Distress Scale-Revised</measure>
    <time_frame>1-3 months</time_frame>
    <description>The Female Sexual Distress Scale-Revised was used to assess sexual distress, with higher scores relating to more sexual distress</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Vaginal Penetration Cognition Questionnaire</measure>
    <time_frame>1-3 months</time_frame>
    <description>To assess cognition regarding vaginal penetration in women with vaginismus or dyspareunia</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The Patient Global Impression of Change</measure>
    <time_frame>1-3 motnhs</time_frame>
    <description>The Patient Global Impression of Change allowed the participants to self-report their perceived improvement (categories ranging from very much improved to very much worse). The PGI-I requires the patient to grade on a seven (7) point likert scale how the condition has evolved compared to how it was prior to the treatment. All questionnaires have validity and reliability in Turkish language .</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">43</enrollment>
  <condition>Pelvic Pain</condition>
  <condition>Telerehabilitation</condition>
  <condition>Pelvic Floor; Relaxation</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Telerehabilitation group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Multimodal self-treatment-based telerehabilitation will be implemented with a video conference method. For telerehabilitation, at each session, manual therapy techniques, (i.e., stretching, myofascial release, and tissue desensitization), sex education, and pelvic floor muscle relaxation massages with a pelvic wand (i.e., relaxation, stretching) using small intra-vaginal wand were used. Women were also asked to perform home exercises resembling those performed under supervision five times per week as well as auto-insertion exercises with a pelvic wand in addition to desensitization techniques three times per week.&#xD;
Sessions consist of 60 minutes. Telerehabilitation will take place 2 days a week for 12 weeks.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Education group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>60 minutes of video recording training will be given about pelvic pain relaxation exercises.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Telerehabilitation Treatment</intervention_name>
    <description>Telerehabilitation includes self-massages for pelvic floor muscle, sex education, breathing, myofascial releasing with wand, and pelvic floor relaxing exercises.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Telerehabilitation group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  experienced pelvic pain (dyspareunia) for over six (6) months prior to the study&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  to be able to use the internet and their willingness to participate.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  no pelvic floor surgeries&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  no C-section and birth history&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  to have a diagnoses by dyspareunia&#xD;
&#xD;
        Exclusion Criteria:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  to have endometriosis&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  to have a pelvic health physiotherapy history&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  pelvic organ prolapse, or a previous pelvic organ surgery.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  the use of analgesics in the previous three (3) months,&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  to have a pregnancy,&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  to have an active vaginal or urinary tract infection, or suffering from other&#xD;
             comorbidities that affect the lower urinary tract such as diabetes mellitus&#xD;
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>20 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>45 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Alime Buyuk</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Akdeniz University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Alime Buyuk, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>+905543239836</phone>
    <email>alimebuyuk@gmail.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Selen Dogan, Assos. Prof.</last_name>
    <email>selendogan@akdeniz.edu.tr</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Alime Buyuk</name>
      <address>
        <city>Antalya</city>
        <state>Select State / Province...a</state>
        <zip>07070</zip>
        <country>Turkey</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Alime Buyuk</last_name>
      <phone>05543239836</phone>
      <email>alimebuyuk@gmail.com</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Turkey</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Padoa A, McLean L, Morin M, Vandyken C. The Overactive Pelvic Floor (OPF) and Sexual Dysfunction. Part 2: Evaluation and Treatment of Sexual Dysfunction in OPF Patients. Sex Med Rev. 2021 Jan;9(1):76-92. doi: 10.1016/j.sxmr.2020.04.002. Epub 2020 Jul 4.</citation>
    <PMID>32631813</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Morin M, Dumoulin C, Bergeron S, Mayrand MH, Khalife S, Waddell G, Dubois MF; PVD Study Group. Multimodal physical therapy versus topical lidocaine for provoked vestibulodynia: a multicenter, randomized trial. Am J Obstet Gynecol. 2021 Feb;224(2):189.e1-189.e12. doi: 10.1016/j.ajog.2020.08.038. Epub 2020 Aug 18.</citation>
    <PMID>32818475</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Cyr MP, Dostie R, Camden C, Dumoulin C, Bessette P, Pina A, Gotlieb WH, Lapointe-Milot K, Mayrand MH, Morin M. Improvements following multimodal pelvic floor physical therapy in gynecological cancer survivors suffering from pain during sexual intercourse: Results from a one-year follow-up mixed-method study. PLoS One. 2022 Jan 25;17(1):e0262844. doi: 10.1371/journal.pone.0262844. eCollection 2022.</citation>
    <PMID>35077479</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Cyr MP, Dumoulin C, Bessette P, Pina A, Gotlieb WH, Lapointe-Milot K, Mayrand MH, Morin M. Feasibility, acceptability and effects of multimodal pelvic floor physical therapy for gynecological cancer survivors suffering from painful sexual intercourse: A multicenter prospective interventional study. Gynecol Oncol. 2020 Dec;159(3):778-784. doi: 10.1016/j.ygyno.2020.09.001. Epub 2020 Oct 1.</citation>
    <PMID>33010968</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>January 2023</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>January 16, 2023</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 25, 2023</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">January 26, 2023</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 25, 2023</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 25, 2023</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">January 26, 2023</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Akdeniz University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Alime Buyuk</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Principal Investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Pelvic Pain</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

