<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="9100">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 09, 2023</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT05705284</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>ERGO ID 71720</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT05705284</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>MODIFY or Medication Review in Primary Care Study</brief_title>
  <acronym>MODIFY</acronym>
  <official_title>The Development and iMplementation Of a Multidisciplinary Medication Review and Deprescribing Intervention Among Frail Older People in primarY Care (MODIFY Study)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Southampton</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University of Portsmouth</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Southampton</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      A third of older people take five or more regular medications (polypharmacy) potentially&#xD;
      increasing the risk of side-effects, hospital admission and death, with higher risk among&#xD;
      people living with frailty. National recommendations suggest that medications taken by frail&#xD;
      older people should be reviewed annually by GPs to identify and reduce/ stop inappropriate&#xD;
      medications (deprescribing). Yet this does not happen routinely due to GPs' lack of time,&#xD;
      increased workloads and worries about stopping medicines. Recent recommendations suggest&#xD;
      involving other non-medical prescribers such as practice-pharmacists and advanced nurse&#xD;
      practitioners (ANPs) in reviewing medications. However, it is unknown how staff could work&#xD;
      together most effectively and whether they have any training needs.&#xD;
&#xD;
      This research will investigate how practice-pharmacists, ANPs and GPs could best work&#xD;
      together with patients living with frailty to perform regular medication reviews. There are&#xD;
      four work packages (WPs).&#xD;
&#xD;
        1. Review literature to identify what makes a successful medication review and how to&#xD;
           safely deprescribe.&#xD;
&#xD;
        2. Interviews with GPs, practice-pharmacists, ANPs, frail older patients and carers will&#xD;
           investigate where medication review should take place, the role of involved parties,&#xD;
           type of medications that could be deprescribed, staff training needs, barriers and&#xD;
           facilitators for implementation, and strategies to address them.&#xD;
&#xD;
        3. Information from WP1&amp;2 will be used to develop the intervention: a structured medication&#xD;
           review process using pharmacists, ANPs and GPs and involving frail patients and their&#xD;
           families in decisions about medications. This will be refined through workshops with&#xD;
           service users, clinicians and commissioners. A training programme to implement the&#xD;
           intervention and increase staff confidence in deprescribing will be developed alongside&#xD;
           the intervention.&#xD;
&#xD;
        4. Feasibility study for staff in four GP practices to be trained and to implement the&#xD;
           intervention.(this will be subject to further amendment).&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Background A third of older people take five or more regular medications (polypharmacy)&#xD;
      potentially increasing the risk of side-effects, hospital admission and death. These effects&#xD;
      are higher among people living with frailty who lose their in-built reserves and become&#xD;
      vulnerable to changes triggered by small events such as a change in medication. National&#xD;
      recommendations suggest that medications taken by frail older people should be reviewed&#xD;
      annually by their GPs to identify and reduce/ stop inappropriate medications (deprescribing).&#xD;
      Yet this does not happen routinely due to GPs' lack of time, increased workloads and worries&#xD;
      about stopping medicines.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Recent recommendations suggest involving other non-medical prescribers such as&#xD;
      practice-pharmacists and advanced nurse practitioners (ANPs) in reviewing medications.&#xD;
      However, it is unknown how staff could work together most effectively and whether they have&#xD;
      any training needs.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Aim This research will investigate how practice-pharmacists, ANPs and GPs could best work&#xD;
      together with patients living with frailty to perform regular medication review.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Methods The study involves four work packages (WPs). The research team will review previous&#xD;
      literature to identify what makes a successful medication review and how to safely reduce/&#xD;
      stop inappropriate medications (WP1).&#xD;
&#xD;
      Interviews with GPs, practice-pharmacists, ANPs, frail older patients and carers will be&#xD;
      conducted (WP2). These will discover views about where medication review should take place,&#xD;
      the role of each of the involved parties in the process, type of medications that could be&#xD;
      deprescribed, staff development and training needs, barriers and facilitators for&#xD;
      implementation, and strategies to address these barriers.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Information gathered from WP1&amp;2 will be used to develop the intervention: a structured&#xD;
      medication review process using pharmacists, ANPs and GPs most effectively and involving&#xD;
      frail patients and their families in decisions about medications (WP3). The intervention will&#xD;
      be refined further through a series of workshops with service users, clinicians and&#xD;
      commissioners. A training programme to implement the intervention and increase staff&#xD;
      confidence in reducing/ stopping medications safely will be developed and delivered to GPs,&#xD;
      practice-pharmacists and ANPs based on the Polypharmacy Action Learning Sets approach adopted&#xD;
      by the Wessex Academic Health Science Network (AHSN) .&#xD;
&#xD;
      Finally, the feasibility and acceptability of the intervention to staff and patients in four&#xD;
      GP practices will be assessed (WP4).&#xD;
&#xD;
      Patient and Public Involvement (PPI) Three PPI members have been involved in protocol&#xD;
      development and refinement and will continue to contribute to the research study by for&#xD;
      example being involved in developing research instruments and monitoring recruitment.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Dissemination and impact Working with colleagues in the Wessex AHSN and local clinical&#xD;
      commissioners, the research team will be able to share our findings and training programme to&#xD;
      the wider research and clinical community in Wessex and potentially influence practices and&#xD;
      policies both locally and nationally.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">January 1, 2022</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 30, 2024</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">April 30, 2024</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>N/A</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Multidisciplinary process for medication review/deprescribing: The intervention will be a structured process for performing a shared-decision, person-centred medication review among those living with frailty involving GPs, PCN-pharmacist and ANPs.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Other</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Feasibility of recruitment</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline</time_frame>
    <description>proportion of staff recruited and trained in each GP practice</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of medications</measure>
    <time_frame>change in scores between baseline and 3 months follow up</time_frame>
    <description>Total number of medications taken by each patient</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Rates of adverse events</measure>
    <time_frame>at 3 months</time_frame>
    <description>rates of adverse drug events due to deprescribing (including self-reported dizziness, falls, drowsiness, confusion, hallucinations, blurred vision, constipation, diarrhoea, dry mouth or other) during 3 months follow up.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Rates of hospitalisation</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months</time_frame>
    <description>rates of hospitalisation 3 months post intervention</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Mortality rates</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months</time_frame>
    <description>mortality rates 3 months post intervention</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>frailty status</measure>
    <time_frame>changes between baseline and 3 months</time_frame>
    <description>Frailty score using the electronic frailty index (e-FI)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>rates of falls</measure>
    <time_frame>changes between baseline and 3 months</time_frame>
    <description>number of falls reported and proportion of fallers (self-reported)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Rates of fractures</measure>
    <time_frame>changes between baseline and 3 months</time_frame>
    <description>number of fractures and proportion of people sustained fractures (self-reported)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>function</measure>
    <time_frame>changes between baseline and 3 months</time_frame>
    <description>Activity of daily living using Barthel</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>cognition</measure>
    <time_frame>changes between baseline and 3 months</time_frame>
    <description>- cognition using the abbreviated mental test (AMT)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>depression</measure>
    <time_frame>changes between baseline and 3 months</time_frame>
    <description>- depression using the geriatric depression scale (GDS)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>healthcare utilisation</measure>
    <time_frame>at 3 months follow up</time_frame>
    <description>number of visits to GP/specialists and number of unplanned hospitalisations</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Acceptability</measure>
    <time_frame>at 3 months follow up</time_frame>
    <description>Interviews or focus groups will be conducted at the end of the feasibility study with a purposive sample of (n=6-8) GPs, pharmacists, ANPs in the four GP practices who received the training and implemented the intervention, and 8-10 patients and carers who received the intervention</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Feasibility of deprescribing</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months follow up</time_frame>
    <description>number of recommendations in the medication reviews made to each patient (stop, reduce, switch or start).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>number of potentially inappropriate medications</measure>
    <time_frame>Change between baseline and 3 months follow up</time_frame>
    <description>total number of potentially inappropriate medications months using the STOPP/START criteria.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">90</enrollment>
  <condition>Aging</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Patients participating in structured multidisciplinary medication review</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients participating in structured multidisciplinary medication review</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Structured multidisciplinary medication review</intervention_name>
    <description>Multidisciplinary process for medication review/deprescribing: The intervention will be a structured process for performing a shared-decision, person-centred medication review among those living with frailty involving GPs, PCN-pharmacist and ANPs.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Patients participating in structured multidisciplinary medication review</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Eligibility criteria for WP2&#xD;
&#xD;
        Patients:&#xD;
&#xD;
        Inclusion criteria&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Aged 65 and over&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Frail, (as judged by their health care professional, if applicable)&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Prescribed multiple medications (10+), as determined by their health care professional&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Able to give informed consent&#xD;
&#xD;
        Exclusion criteria&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Aged under 65&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Severe cognitive impairment, as judged by their health care professional&#xD;
&#xD;
        Informal carers/ relatives eligibility criteria&#xD;
&#xD;
        Inclusion criteria&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  An informal carer/ relative of a frail patient (aged 65 and over) who is taking&#xD;
             multiple medications, as identified by a health care professional&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  An informal carer/ relative of a patient (aged 65 and over) living with severe&#xD;
             dementia who is taking multiple medications, as identified by a health care&#xD;
             professional&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Able to consent&#xD;
&#xD;
        Health care professional eligibility criteria&#xD;
&#xD;
        • A health care professional based in GP surgeries in Wessex (eg. GPs,&#xD;
        practice-pharmacists, advanced nurse prescriber (ANPs) who works with older people living&#xD;
        with frailty, who are prescribed multiple medications.&#xD;
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>65 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Kinda Ibrahim, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Southampton</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Eloise Radcliffe, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>(023) 8120 4656</phone>
    <email>e.radcliffe@soton.ac.uk</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Kinda Ibrahim, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>(023) 8120 4656</phone>
    <email>k.ibrahim@soton.ac.uk</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Clinical Research Network in Primary Care</name>
      <address>
        <city>Southampton</city>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Eloise Radcliff, PhD</last_name>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Kinda Ibrahim, PhD</last_name>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United Kingdom</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>January 2023</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>March 22, 2022</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 26, 2023</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">January 30, 2023</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 26, 2023</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 26, 2023</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">January 30, 2023</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>polypharmacy</keyword>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

