<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="9869">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 09, 2023</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT05688449</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>20220609</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT05688449</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Effect of Epidural Analgesia on Burst Suppression</brief_title>
  <official_title>Investigation of the Effect of Epidural Analgesia Combined With General Anesthesia on Burst Suppression Rate in Electroencephalogram Based Anesthesia Management</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Bezmialem Vakif University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Bezmialem Vakif University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      It has been shown in previous studies that burst suppression has an effect on the development&#xD;
      of postoperative delirium (POD) and postoperative cognitive dysfunction (POCD). With the&#xD;
      development of technology, EEG-based anesthesia management is getting more and more&#xD;
      attention. In particular, methods that reduce anesthetic drug consumption are expected to&#xD;
      prevent POD and POCD by reducing burst suppression. There are studies that show that epidural&#xD;
      analgesia applications reduce general anesthesia drug consumption in patients receiving&#xD;
      general anesthesia. In this study, investigators want to investigate the effect of epidural&#xD;
      analgesia combined with general anesthesia on burst suppression. POD and POCD development in&#xD;
      these patients will be examined as secondary objectives.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Postoperative delirium (POD) is an acute cognitive disorder characterized by inattention,&#xD;
      disorganized thinking, and a fluctuating course that develops over hours or days. Although&#xD;
      delirium depends on the type of surgery, it is a common postoperative complication with an&#xD;
      incidence of 10%-70%. POD causes an increase in mortality, morbidity and health care costs.&#xD;
      Risk factors for POD; age, type and duration of surgery, inadequate pain control, type of&#xD;
      anesthesia, anemia, transfusion, and preoperative cognitive impairment. In recent years, it&#xD;
      has been emphasized that POD can be reduced with the widespread use of electroencephalogram&#xD;
      (EEG) based anesthesia management and optimization of anesthetic drugs according to EEG&#xD;
      patterns. EEG consists of 6 waveforms: slow, delta, theta, alpha, beta and gamma. Behavioral&#xD;
      and neurophysiological patterns caused by anesthetic drugs are associated with different&#xD;
      electroencephalogram waveforms. Recent developments in the introduction of EEG-based monitors&#xD;
      have made significant contributions to the understanding of the fundamental changes in brain&#xD;
      activity caused by anesthetic agents. Today, there are EEG-based anesthesia depth monitors&#xD;
      such as bispectral index (BIS) (Medtronic, USA) or Sedline (Masimo Irvine CA). These monitors&#xD;
      make it easier to optimize the depth of anesthesia with the numerical data obtained as a&#xD;
      result of some calculations as well as the raw EEG. The burst suppression (BS) pattern on the&#xD;
      EEG shows a decrease in brain neuronal activity and metabolic activity. Burst suppression can&#xD;
      be induced by anesthetic drugs that modulate γ-aminobutyric acid type A receptors. Although&#xD;
      sometimes deliberately induced for therapeutic purposes to treat refractory status&#xD;
      epilepticus or increased intracranial pressure, burst suppression is generally considered&#xD;
      potentially harmful and should be avoided.Studies conducted in recent years have shown the&#xD;
      relationship between intraoperative burst suppression (BS) and POD. POD; It can be reduced by&#xD;
      continuous EEG monitoring, reducing the dose of propofol, preferring regional anesthesia,&#xD;
      effective postoperative pain control, early mobilization, and early postoperative discharge.&#xD;
      Interventions that can reduce the development of postoperative delirium will be important for&#xD;
      public health. Epidural analgesia can be used effectively in perioperative analgesia. It has&#xD;
      been reported in the literature that epidural analgesia combined with general anesthesia&#xD;
      reduces the amount of hypnotic drug required to achieve similar depth of anesthesia compared&#xD;
      to general anesthesia alone. There is no study in the literature on whether the combination&#xD;
      of epidural analgesia and general anesthesia reduces BS in EEG-based anesthesia applications.&#xD;
      Our primary aim in this study is to evaluate whether the combination of general anesthesia&#xD;
      and epidural analgesia reduces BS in EEG-based anesthesia in patients undergoing total hip&#xD;
      and knee arthroplasty.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">July 30, 2022</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">April 2023</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">April 2023</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 4</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Triple (Participant, Care Provider, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>burst suppression</measure>
    <time_frame>Form beginning of anesthesia induction to the end of anesthesia(During perioperative period)</time_frame>
    <description>burst suppression rate</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>postoperative two days delirium rate</measure>
    <time_frame>Within the first two postoperative days</time_frame>
    <description>Screening of the patients regarding a postoperative delirum by Confusion Assessment Method for the ICU.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Postoperative cognitive dysfunction rate</measure>
    <time_frame>Participants will be called for control in the postoperative 1st and 3rd months.</time_frame>
    <description>Screening of the patients regarding a postoperative cognitive dysfunction by the telephone Montreal Cognitive Assessment(t-MoCA)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">64</enrollment>
  <condition>Post-operative Delirium</condition>
  <condition>Cognitive Dysfunction</condition>
  <condition>Electroencephalography</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Epidural analgesia</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Eeg monitoring will be implemented with Sedline monitor(Masimo Irvine CA) 5 minutes before epidural catheter insertion, 30 minutes after epidural catheter insertion, during surgery and 5 minutes after extubation.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Eeg monitoring will be implemented with Sedline monitor (Masimo Irvine CA) 5 minutes before epidural catheter insertion, 30 minutes after epidural catheter insertion, during surgery and 5 minutes after extubation.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Bupivacaine-fentanyl</intervention_name>
    <description>A 20 ml bolus of 2 mcg/ml fentanyl + 0.125% bupivacaine solution will be administered to the bupivacaine group via the epidural catheter, and 5ml/hour infusion will be started.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Epidural analgesia</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Saline</intervention_name>
    <description>A 20 ml bolus of saline will be administered to the saline group via the epidural catheter, and 5ml/hour infusion will be started.</description>
    <arm_group_label>placebo</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  American Society of Anesthesiologists (ASA) Physical Status 1-3&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Hip or knee arthroplasty surgery&#xD;
&#xD;
        Exclusion Criteria:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  severe renal failure (need for renal replacement therapy)&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  severe liver failure (child-pudg grade c)&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  body mass index &gt;40&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  long-term use of some drugs (sedatives, tricyclic antidepressants, narcotic&#xD;
             painkillers)&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  having a disease related to the nervous system&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  having a psychiatric disease&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  having a history of substance abuse&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  having consumed 2 or more glasses of alcohol per day in the last 1 year&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  contraindications for neuraxial block&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  allergy to drugs to be used&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  emergency surgeries&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  patient's refusal to accept the procedure&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  hearing and visual impairment&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  anesthesia awareness history&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  preoperative delirium&#xD;
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>60 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>mustafa gunay</last_name>
    <phone>+905363146236</phone>
    <email>dr.mustafagunay@gmail.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Bezmialem Vakif University Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Istanbul</city>
        <state>Fatih</state>
        <zip>34500</zip>
        <country>Turkey</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>mustafa gunay</last_name>
      <phone>+905363146236</phone>
      <email>dr.mustafagunay@gmail.com</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>ayla turkoz</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>serdar yesiltas</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Turkey</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>January 2023</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>November 7, 2022</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 15, 2023</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">January 18, 2023</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 15, 2023</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 15, 2023</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">January 18, 2023</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>burst suppression</keyword>
  <keyword>delirium</keyword>
  <keyword>electroencephalography</keyword>
  <keyword>anesthesia</keyword>
  <keyword>regional anesthesia</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Delirium</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Emergence Delirium</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Cognitive Dysfunction</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Fentanyl</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Bupivacaine</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

