<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="9528">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 09, 2023</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT05696015</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>61722122.8.0000.0071</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT05696015</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Impact of Telehealth Education in Diabetes Patients</brief_title>
  <official_title>Impact of Telehealth Education After Hospital Discharge on the Self-care of Patients With Diabetes</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Hospital Israelita Albert Einstein</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Hospital Israelita Albert Einstein</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The goal of this clinical trial is to to evaluate the effectiveness of continuity of&#xD;
      in-hospital care with the application of a structured telemonitoring protocol in self-care&#xD;
      activities in patients with type 1 or type 2 Diabetes Mellitus or those who have an HbA1C&#xD;
      level greater than or equal to 6.5% during hospitalization, regardless of the reason for&#xD;
      hospitalization. The main question[s] it aims to answer are:&#xD;
&#xD;
      • Is telehealth education effective for improving self-care for type 1 or type 2 Diabetes&#xD;
      Mellitus or those with an HbA1C level greater than or equal to 6.5% during hospitalization&#xD;
      will be included, regardless of the reason for hospitalization? Participants will answer the&#xD;
      Diabetes Self-Care Activity Questionnaire Researchers will compare patients in the&#xD;
      intervention group, in addition to the hospital's standard hospital guidance, will receive an&#xD;
      educational approach through structured telemonitoring, reinforcing and validating the points&#xD;
      addressed in the face-to-face guidance, which are considered the foundations of self-care.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This study have two groups of patients. Group 1 will be carried out at discharge, discharge&#xD;
      orientation of the patient with diabetes and application of the Diabetes Self-Care Activity&#xD;
      Questionnaire (QAD). For this group, a new contact will be made within 30 days after&#xD;
      discharge, where the QAD will be applied again.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Group 2 will be performed at the time of discharge, guidance for discharge of patients with&#xD;
      diabetes. This group will receive 3 contacts, the first will be carried out within 72 hours&#xD;
      after discharge, the second contact within 10 days after the first contact and the third&#xD;
      within 30 days after discharge, where diabetes education guidelines will be given to the&#xD;
      patient in all contacts. At the time of discharge, and in the third contact, 30 days, the QAD&#xD;
      will also be applied.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">March 2, 2023</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 30, 2025</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 30, 2024</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>The randomized clinical trial.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Other</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
    <masking_description>Patients will be randomized using the Randomizer software into a group that will receive the telemonitoring intervention and a control group (which will only receive the hospital's standard hospital discharge instructions).</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline discharge orientation of the patient with diabetes and application of the Diabetes Self-Care Activity Questionnaire (QAD) at 30 days follow-up. (Standard education)</measure>
    <time_frame>immediately pre and within 4 weeks post intervention</time_frame>
    <description>The QAD instrument has six dimensions and 15 items for evaluating self-care with diabetes: &quot;general diet&quot; (two items), &quot;specific diet&quot; (three items), &quot;physical activity&quot; (two items) , &quot;blood glucose monitoring&quot; (two items), &quot;foot care&quot; (three items) and &quot;medication use&quot; (three items, used according to the medication regimen), in addition to three other items for the assessment of smoking . Patients answer how often (answers from 0 to 7) they performed the activities or behaviors in the seven days prior to completing the form.&#xD;
For the calculation of scores, the items of the specific food dimension that ask about the consumption of foods high in fat and sweets, the values must be inverted (7=0, 6=1, 5=2, 4=3, 3=4 , 2=5, 1=6 and 0=7). Scores are calculated by averaging the items that make up each dimension, with zero being the least desirable situation and seven being the most favorable.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline discharge telehealth orientation and application of the Diabetes Self-Care Activity Questionnaire (QAD) at within 72 hours after discharge, 10 days after and within 30 days after discharge</measure>
    <time_frame>immediately pre and within 72 hours after discharge, the second contact within 10 days after the first contact and the third within 30 days after discharge</time_frame>
    <description>Patients in the intervention group, in addition to the hospital's standard hospital guidance, will receive an educational approach through structured telemonitoring, reinforcing and validating the points addressed in the face-to-face guidance, which are considered the foundations of self-care. Contacts will be made via video call by trained health professionals, who will provide care based on a script structured by the authors, assessing adherence to self-care. The American Association of Diabetes Educators ( 7 Self-Care Behaviors ™) ) is a structured evidence-based tool that allows, in addition to self-care assessment, educational intervention in the seven topics covered, which include: 1) healthy eating, 2) physical activity, 3) glycemic monitoring , 4) medication use, 5) problem solving, 6) healthy coping, and 7) risk reduction.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">200</enrollment>
  <condition>Diabetes Mellitus, Type 1</condition>
  <condition>Diabetes Mellitus, Type 2</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Standard education</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Standard education group will be carried out at discharge, discharge orientation of the patient with diabetes and application of the Diabetes Self-Care Activity Questionnaire (QAD). For this group, a new contact will be made within 30 days after discharge, where the QAD will be applied again.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Amplied education</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Amplied education group will be performed at the time of discharge, guidance for discharge of patients with diabetes. This group will receive 3 contacts, the first will be carried out within 72 hours after discharge, the second contact within 10 days after the first contact and the third within 30 days after discharge, where diabetes education guidelines will be given to the patient in all contacts. At the time of discharge, and in the third contact, 30 days, the QAD will also be applied.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Standard education</intervention_name>
    <description>Without telehealth education, this group has only postdischarge education.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Standard education</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Ampiled Education</intervention_name>
    <description>With telehealth education, in addition of discharge education.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Amplied education</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  patients who were hospitalized at Hospital Israelita Albert Einstein and included in&#xD;
             the subcutaneous insulin protocol to control hyperglycemia&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  patients monitored by the Diabetes Program, an institutional program that manages&#xD;
             glycemic changes that occur within the institution.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  patients with type 1 or type 2 Diabetes Mellitus or those with an HbA1C level greater&#xD;
             than or equal to 6.5% during hospitalization.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Exclusion Criteria:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Patients not submitted to the first face-to-face educational approach required by&#xD;
             protocol&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Patients discharged on the weekend or holidays&#xD;
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Simone Brandi, MS</last_name>
    <phone>5511971505024</phone>
    <email>simone.brandi@einstein.br</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Tatianna Pinheiro Rozzino, MD</last_name>
    <phone>5511981425691</phone>
    <email>tatianna.rozzino@einstein.br</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <reference>
    <citation>Chrvala CA, Sherr D, Lipman RD. Diabetes self-management education for adults with type 2 diabetes mellitus: A systematic review of the effect on glycemic control. Patient Educ Couns. 2016 Jun;99(6):926-43. doi: 10.1016/j.pec.2015.11.003. Epub 2015 Nov 22.</citation>
    <PMID>26658704</PMID>
  </reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Toobert DJ, Hampson SE, Glasgow RE. The summary of diabetes self-care activities measure: results from 7 studies and a revised scale. Diabetes Care. 2000 Jul;23(7):943-50. doi: 10.2337/diacare.23.7.943.</citation>
    <PMID>10895844</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Dong Y, Wang P, Dai Z, Liu K, Jin Y, Li A, Wang S, Zheng J. Increased self-care activities and glycemic control rate in relation to health education via Wechat among diabetes patients: A randomized clinical trial. Medicine (Baltimore). 2018 Dec;97(50):e13632. doi: 10.1097/MD.0000000000013632.</citation>
    <PMID>30558051</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Ansari RM, Harris MF, Hosseinzadeh H, Zwar N. The Summary of an Urdu Version of Diabetes Self-Care Activities Measure: Psychometric Evaluation and Validation. J Prim Care Community Health. 2020 Jan-Dec;11:2150132720935292. doi: 10.1177/2150132720935292.</citation>
    <PMID>32538255</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Frosch DL, Uy V, Ochoa S, Mangione CM. Evaluation of a behavior support intervention for patients with poorly controlled diabetes. Arch Intern Med. 2011 Dec 12;171(22):2011-7. doi: 10.1001/archinternmed.2011.497. Epub 2011 Oct 10.</citation>
    <PMID>21986347</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Weinger K, Beverly EA, Smaldone A. Diabetes self-care and the older adult. West J Nurs Res. 2014 Oct;36(9):1272-98. doi: 10.1177/0193945914521696. Epub 2014 Feb 7.</citation>
    <PMID>24510969</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Whitehouse CR, Long JA, Maloney LM, Daniels K, Horowitz DA, Bowles KH. Feasibility of Diabetes Self-Management Telehealth Education for Older Adults During Transitions in Care. Res Gerontol Nurs. 2020 May 1;13(3):138-145. doi: 10.3928/19404921-20191210-03. Epub 2019 Dec 13.</citation>
    <PMID>31834415</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Ose D, Kamradt M, Kiel M, Freund T, Besier W, Mayer M, Krisam J, Wensing M, Salize HJ, Szecsenyi J. Care management intervention to strengthen self-care of multimorbid patients with type 2 diabetes in a German primary care network: A randomized controlled trial. PLoS One. 2019 Jun 12;14(6):e0214056. doi: 10.1371/journal.pone.0214056. eCollection 2019. Erratum In: PLoS One. 2019 Aug 9;14(8):e0221229.</citation>
    <PMID>31188825</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>So CF, Chung JW. Telehealth for diabetes self-management in primary healthcare: A systematic review and meta-analysis. J Telemed Telecare. 2018 Jun;24(5):356-364. doi: 10.1177/1357633X17700552. Epub 2017 May 2.</citation>
    <PMID>28463033</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <verification_date>January 2023</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>January 13, 2023</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 13, 2023</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">January 25, 2023</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 26, 2023</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 26, 2023</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">January 30, 2023</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Hospital Israelita Albert Einstein</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Simone Brandi</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Principal investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>self care</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Diabetes Mellitus</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Diabetes Mellitus, Type 2</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Diabetes Mellitus, Type 1</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

