<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="9893">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 09, 2023</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT05687994</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2020-386</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>R21DC018893</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT05687994</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Speech Entrainment Treatment for People With Aphasia</brief_title>
  <official_title>Efficacy and Optimization of Speech Entrainment Practice for People With Aphasia</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Albert Einstein Healthcare Network</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Institute on Deafness and Other Communication Disorders (NIDCD)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Albert Einstein Healthcare Network</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The objective of this research is to experimentally delineate the direct effect of speech&#xD;
      entrainment practice on independent speech production and identify practice conditions that&#xD;
      enhance treatment benefits. The primary outcome measure (Correct Information Units per&#xD;
      minute) tallies informativeness and efficiency of independent speech in treated stories.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Speech entrainment refers to speaking in unison with a model speaker by imitating the model&#xD;
      in real time. The objective of the study is to (1) experimentally establish the direct effect&#xD;
      of speech entrainment practice on independent speech production post-treatment, and (2)&#xD;
      identify conditions that enhance treatment benefits. These aims are addressed in a&#xD;
      within-subject efficacy study, where 40 people with aphasia produce different stories with&#xD;
      entrainment support. Speaking without entrainment is evaluated one day before and one day&#xD;
      after speech entrainment practice. Different practice stories will be randomized within&#xD;
      participants to three experimental conditions to assess the effect of treatment (trained vs.&#xD;
      untrained), training schedule (massed vs. distributed presentation of stories), and&#xD;
      entrainment modality (practice with auditory-only or audiovisual model). Correct information&#xD;
      units per minute for each story will be tallied to evaluate the differences between&#xD;
      conditions and the associations with patient characteristics. For consistency with prior&#xD;
      research, number of different words per minute will serve as a secondary outcome. The&#xD;
      proposed research addresses a clinical need by testing and optimizing a promising treatment&#xD;
      technique for enhancing aphasia rehabilitation.&#xD;
&#xD;
      This proof-of-concept study is the first to evaluate the direct effect of speech entrainment&#xD;
      practice on independent speech. Thus, the effect size for accurate power estimation is not&#xD;
      known. The strategy for this study is to optimize experimental sensitivity by maximizing the&#xD;
      number of observations per participants per condition within the constraints of feasibility.&#xD;
      The results from this study will provide critical information for evaluating the effect size&#xD;
      for a subsequent phase. Nevertheless, to estimate an optimal sample size, the investigators&#xD;
      leveraged the data from our Pilot Study, which examines the speech entrainment effect on&#xD;
      immediate performance rather than learning. With 13 participants, the investigators estimated&#xD;
      80% power to detect the effect of 0.8 (mean difference between groups divided by the pooled&#xD;
      standard deviation) observed in our pilot study for speaking with audiovisual speech&#xD;
      entrainment vs. independent speech (Aim 1). The calculation is based on a paired t-test with&#xD;
      an alpha of .05 (two-tailed) and a correlation of 0.5 between groups. With 24 participants,&#xD;
      there is 80% power to detect the observed effect of 0.6 for speaking with audiovisual speech&#xD;
      entrainment vs. auditory-only speech entrainment (alpha is set to .05, two-tailed,&#xD;
      correlation between groups is .57; Aim 2b). The investigators have substantially increased&#xD;
      the sample size (N=40) with the consideration that learning effects (the focus of the present&#xD;
      study) are expected to be smaller than performance effects (the focus of the Pilot Study).&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">January 25, 2023</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2025</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2024</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Crossover Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Correct Information Units per Minute</measure>
    <time_frame>one day post treatment</time_frame>
    <description>Correct Information Units per Minute will be tallied by blinded coders to measure the informativeness and efficacy of speech</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of Different Words per Minute</measure>
    <time_frame>one day post treatment</time_frame>
    <description>Number of Different Words per Minute will be tallied by blinded coders to measure the amount and variability of speech</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">40</enrollment>
  <condition>Aphasia, Acquired</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Audiovisual Speech Entrainment Practice</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Audiovisual Speech Entrainment includes repeated practice of speaking synchronously with a recorded model, which provides contextual, temporal, and audiovisual cues for speaking.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Auditory Speech Entrainment Practice</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Auditory Speech Entrainment includes repeated practice of speaking synchronously with a recorded model, which provides contextual, temporal, and auditory cues for speaking.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Audiovisual Speech Entrainment Practice</intervention_name>
    <description>Speech Entrainment Practice is an aphasia rehabilitation treatment based on imitation of recorded speech in real time. Treatment includes repeated practice of speaking along with a recorded model, which provides contextual, temporal, auditory, and visual cues for speaking</description>
    <arm_group_label>Audiovisual Speech Entrainment Practice</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Auditory Speech Entrainment Practice</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Auditory Speech Entrainment Practice</intervention_name>
    <description>Speech Entrainment Practice is an aphasia rehabilitation treatment based on imitation of recorded speech in real time. Treatment includes repeated practice of speaking along with a recorded model, which provides contextual, temporal, and auditory cues for speaking</description>
    <arm_group_label>Audiovisual Speech Entrainment Practice</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Auditory Speech Entrainment Practice</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Between 18-80 years at the time of enrollment&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  English as native language&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  greater than six months post onset&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Diagnosis of aphasia based on Western Aphasia Battery - Revised (WAB-R)&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Score of 7 or less on the Fluency subsection of the WAB-R&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Demonstrate having the willingness and stamina to participate in the multiple-session&#xD;
             protocol, either by traveling to the MRRI testing site or being tested at home&#xD;
&#xD;
        Exclusion Criteria:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  History of learning disabilities&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  History of other comorbid neurological impairments&#xD;
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>80 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Marja-Liisa Mailend, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Albert Einstein Healthcare Network</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Shauna Zodrow, BA</last_name>
    <phone>215-663-6107</phone>
    <email>shauna.zodrow@jefferson.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Moss Rehabilitation Research Institute</name>
      <address>
        <city>Elkins Park</city>
        <state>Pennsylvania</state>
        <zip>19027</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Shauna Zodrow</last_name>
      <phone>215-663-6107</phone>
      <email>shauna.zodrow@jefferson.edu</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>March 2023</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>January 9, 2023</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 9, 2023</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">January 18, 2023</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 27, 2023</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 27, 2023</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 28, 2023</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Albert Einstein Healthcare Network</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Marja-Liisa Mailend, PhD</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Institute Scientist</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Aphasia</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

