<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="9198">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on June 09, 2023</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT05703152</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>Folio No. 06-2022</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT05703152</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Effect of a Combined Exercise Program on Neuropathic Pain and Perceived Quality of Life in Type 2 Diabetes</brief_title>
  <official_title>Effect of a Combined Therapeutic Exercise Program on Neuropathic Pain and Perceived Quality of Life in Patients With Type 2 Diabetes</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Universidad Autónoma de Yucatán</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Universidad Autónoma de Yucatán</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Therapeutic exercise is one of the therapies used as a treatment for diabetic neuropathy,&#xD;
      which is a complication of diabetes. In order to reduce pain and improve the perception of&#xD;
      quality of life, a combined therapeutic exercise program will be implemented as an adjuvant&#xD;
      and non-pharmacological treatment for diabetic neuropathy.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This is a prospective, longitudinal, quasi-experimental study of repeated measures&#xD;
      (pretest-posttest), has been approved by the research and ethics committee of the Faculty of&#xD;
      Medicine of the Autonomous University of Yucatan, issuing a report on October 26, 2022. An&#xD;
      identification form will be filled out that will include socio-demographic and clinical data:&#xD;
      presence of type II diabetes, presence of neuropathy, sex, age, marital status, schooling,&#xD;
      occupation, BMI, time of diagnosis, HbA1C, insulin use, medical treatment and a neurological&#xD;
      examination of the extremities. The DN4 questionnaire will be used to evaluate neuropathic&#xD;
      pain and its characteristics, the VAS will be used to evaluate the degree of intensity or&#xD;
      severity of pain, and the SF-36 questionnaire will be used to evaluate perception before and&#xD;
      after the combined exercise program. During the intervention stage, a therapeutic exercise&#xD;
      program will be applied that will include two modalities: aerobic and resistance exercise in&#xD;
      the facilities of the Unidad Universitaria de Inserción social de San José Tecoh. The&#xD;
      duration will be 8 weeks with a frequency of 3 sessions per week, with a duration per session&#xD;
      of 60 minutes each, to achieve the minimum total time suggested by the guidelines of 150&#xD;
      minutes per week. These exercises will be prescribed in three phases to increase times,&#xD;
      series, repetitions and resistances in a progressive manner according to the Borg scale. For&#xD;
      the analysis of the variables, the parametric Student's t-test for related samples or the&#xD;
      nonparametric Wilcoxon test with significance at 95% reliability will be used. The&#xD;
      implementation of the study can demonstrate significant improvements in the symptomatology of&#xD;
      diabetic neuropathy, directly impacting on the perception of the quality of life of patients&#xD;
      with type II diabetes.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">October 31, 2022</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">July 31, 2023</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 30, 2023</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>N/A</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>A prospective, longitudinal, quasi-experimental study of repeated measures (pretest-posttest)</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline in neuropathic pain on Douleur Neuropathique-4 (DN4) at 8 weeks</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and week 8</time_frame>
    <description>The DN4 questionnaire will be used to evaluate neuropathic pain and its characteristics. DN4 for neuropathic pain consists of interview questions and physical tests. It has 10 items grouped into four questions: seven items relating to the pain description (burning, painful cold, electric shocks) and to its associated abnormal sensations (tingling, pins and needles, numbness, itching), and the other three items relating to a brief bedside neurological examination in the painful area (touch hypoaesthesia, pinprick hypoaesthesia and tactile dynamic allodynia). For scoring, 1 is given to each positive and 0 to each negative item (total score range 0-10). The cut-off value for diagnosis of neuropathic pain is a total score of 4.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline in pain intensity on Visual Analogue Scale (VAS) at 8 weeks</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and week 8</time_frame>
    <description>Pain severity will be assessed using VAS. Each patient will be asked to choose in a perpendicular line on the VAS at the point that signifies the pain severity. The score is ranged 0-10, 0 suggests no pain and 10 suggest severe pain.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline in quality of life on the short form-36 questionnaire (SF-36) at 8 weeks</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and week 8</time_frame>
    <description>The 36-item questionnaire consists of eight domains (general health, mental health, role emotion, role physical, body pain, social function, physical function and vitality), which can be further aggregated into a physical component score (PCS) and mental component score (MCS). Total score ranges from 0 to 100, 0 indicates the poor quality of life and 100 indicates the best quality of life.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Socio-demographic data</measure>
    <time_frame>Before intervention</time_frame>
    <description>An identification form will be filled out at the beginning of the study that will include socio-demographic information: sex (woman/man), age (years), marital status (single/married/widowed/divorced), educational stage (Primary education/High School/University/Master) and occupation (yes/no). All data will be presented in frequency and percentage.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Clinical data</measure>
    <time_frame>Before intervention</time_frame>
    <description>An identification form will be filled out at the beginning of the study that will include clinical information: presence of type II diabetes, presence of neuropathy, time of diagnosis (years), Glycemic status (A1C percentage), insulin use (yes/no) and medical treatment. All data will be presented in frequency and percentage.&#xD;
For the neurological examination of the extremities, three instruments will be used: the 10g or Semmes-Weinstein monofilament, 128 hertz tuning fork and Taylor reflex hammer.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Weight measurement</measure>
    <time_frame>Before intervention</time_frame>
    <description>Body weight will be measured in kilograms (kg) using the body weight scale &quot;Omron HBF-514C&quot;.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Height measurement</measure>
    <time_frame>Before intervention</time_frame>
    <description>Height will be measured in meters (m) using a stadiometer.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Body Mass Index (BMI) measurement</measure>
    <time_frame>Before intervention</time_frame>
    <description>BMI will be calculated by dividing the weight in kilograms by the height in metres squared (kg/m^2).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">12</enrollment>
  <condition>Diabetes Mellitus, Type 2</condition>
  <condition>Neuropathic Pain</condition>
  <condition>Neuropathy, Diabetic</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Combined Exercise</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Therapeutic exercise program</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Combined Exercise</intervention_name>
    <description>Therapeutic exercise program will be applied that will include two modalities: aerobic and resistance exercise. The duration will be 8 weeks with a frequency of 3 sessions per week, with a duration per session of 60 minutes.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Combined Exercise</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Patients with diabetes type 2&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Patients with neuropathy&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Patients with medical treatment&#xD;
&#xD;
        Exclusion Criteria:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Patients with several limit function&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Patients with foot ulcer or amputation&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Patients who are involved in a exercise program already&#xD;
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>35 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>80 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Maria Gabriela Aké Palomo</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Facultad de Medicina</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Damaris Francis Estrella Castillo, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Falcultad de Medicina</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Gloria de los Ángeles Uicab Pool, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Facultad de Enfermeria</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Hector Armado Rubio Zapata</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Facultad de Medicina</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Unidad Universitaria de Inserción Social San José Tecoh</name>
      <address>
        <city>Mérida</city>
        <state>Yucatán</state>
        <zip>97299</zip>
        <country>Mexico</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Mexico</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Pop-Busui R, Boulton AJ, Feldman EL, Bril V, Freeman R, Malik RA, Sosenko JM, Ziegler D. Diabetic Neuropathy: A Position Statement by the American Diabetes Association. Diabetes Care. 2017 Jan;40(1):136-154. doi: 10.2337/dc16-2042. No abstract available.</citation>
    <PMID>27999003</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Scholz J, Finnerup NB, Attal N, Aziz Q, Baron R, Bennett MI, Benoliel R, Cohen M, Cruccu G, Davis KD, Evers S, First M, Giamberardino MA, Hansson P, Kaasa S, Korwisi B, Kosek E, Lavand'homme P, Nicholas M, Nurmikko T, Perrot S, Raja SN, Rice ASC, Rowbotham MC, Schug S, Simpson DM, Smith BH, Svensson P, Vlaeyen JWS, Wang SJ, Barke A, Rief W, Treede RD; Classification Committee of the Neuropathic Pain Special Interest Group (NeuPSIG). The IASP classification of chronic pain for ICD-11: chronic neuropathic pain. Pain. 2019 Jan;160(1):53-59. doi: 10.1097/j.pain.0000000000001365.</citation>
    <PMID>30586071</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Perez C, Galvez R, Huelbes S, Insausti J, Bouhassira D, Diaz S, Rejas J. Validity and reliability of the Spanish version of the DN4 (Douleur Neuropathique 4 questions) questionnaire for differential diagnosis of pain syndromes associated to a neuropathic or somatic component. Health Qual Life Outcomes. 2007 Dec 4;5:66. doi: 10.1186/1477-7525-5-66.</citation>
    <PMID>18053212</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Pereira EV, Tonin FS, Carneiro J, Pontarolo R, Wiens A. Evaluation of the application of the Diabetes Quality of Life Questionnaire in patients with diabetes mellitus. Arch Endocrinol Metab. 2020 Feb;64(1):59-65. doi: 10.20945/2359-3997000000196. Epub 2020 Mar 13.</citation>
    <PMID>32187271</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kanaley JA, Colberg SR, Corcoran MH, Malin SK, Rodriguez NR, Crespo CJ, Kirwan JP, Zierath JR. Exercise/Physical Activity in Individuals with Type 2 Diabetes: A Consensus Statement from the American College of Sports Medicine. Med Sci Sports Exerc. 2022 Feb 1;54(2):353-368. doi: 10.1249/MSS.0000000000002800.</citation>
    <PMID>35029593</PMID>
  </reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Pan B, Ge L, Xun YQ, Chen YJ, Gao CY, Han X, Zuo LQ, Shan HQ, Yang KH, Ding GW, Tian JH. Exercise training modalities in patients with type 2 diabetes mellitus: a systematic review and network meta-analysis. Int J Behav Nutr Phys Act. 2018 Jul 25;15(1):72. doi: 10.1186/s12966-018-0703-3.</citation>
    <PMID>30045740</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <verification_date>January 2023</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>December 5, 2022</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 26, 2023</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">January 27, 2023</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 26, 2023</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 26, 2023</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">January 27, 2023</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Diabetes Mellitus type 2</keyword>
  <keyword>Neuropathic pain</keyword>
  <keyword>combined exercise</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Neuralgia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Diabetic Neuropathies</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Diabetes Mellitus</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Diabetes Mellitus, Type 2</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

